￼PENGUIN MODERN POETS IIHera's Spring‘Nothing -will be left of Jeserac but a galaxy of electrons frozen in the heart of a crystal. I shall sleep, and without dreams. Then one day, perhaps a hundred thousand years from now, I shall find myself in a new body, meeting those who have been chosen to be my guardians.... At first I will know nothing of Diaspar and will have no memories of what I was before. Those memories will slowly return, at the end of my infancy, and I will build upon them as I move forward into mynewcycleofexistence.’Arthur C. Clarke :TheCityandtheStarsMissing his noisyplay around thehouse, and remembering the time was nodoubt near, she hurried out, unkempt asshe was, andfound him at last, pale-facedand tearstained, hunched on the weir bank - nofishing-rod in sight - plunged in himself, hispain. With a motherly tendernessshe wiped his eyes with her skirt-hem; she knew; she gently questioned him; and said:Believe me, dear, though it will seem strange to you, I have wept too for all thesethings you mention - and others that may­ be have not yet started to haunt youagain. Do you recall, for instance,the dark coppery flowers on the lowtrees ? the waterfalls, or methane-falls- call them what you like - leaping off cliffs ? the strong, live winds, and violet sky flashing with great clouds ? And I expect you have walked many a time with your husband on those mountain-slopes as bright- 114-
￼D. M. THOMASas metal, with thunder laughing inthe ground, and clear red flame exploding above you? I know I have - though with, as it happens, a wife beside me- a dear woman. ... I too have been there, Jeserac; a terribly long timeago, but it’s still precious to me.Today isn’t the time to convinceyou that these eroded hills, blue sky, green woods, not to mention the speckled fish you like catching, are themselves not unbeautiful. . . this first day, you’ve a right to feel desperate. I recallmyself (though how many others in between 1) writhing in the ammonia-snow I’d always thought of as home, and was to again - tormented by theglobe your mind is filled with, shrieking at my sisters to leave me in peace 1Poor mites, they ran off and told everyonethat ayarn was inside me 1- This,darling, was near Procyon, the lightyour father taught you to find last night.- Oh, don’t think I don’t understand; it’s the beings you gave yourself in loveto - not moons or cliffsIAnd the dull ache of this you must expect never towholly leave you. How often one finds oneself wondering - and the worst of it’s being completely unable toshare your dark thoughts with anyone else - where is, say, Kersti ? - a granddaughter-115-r
￼PENGUIN MODERN POETS III once had somewhere in Bootes;in which of the far-flung micro-filesof our cosmic city Diasparis that beloved pattern crystallized;and where will she - or he - emerge again ? Yet one knows there can be no answer. Only the dumb Selector knows that.Still, it’s the way of Hera’s Spring; we have to count our blessings. - I see that too hasn’t come back yet, dearl It would soon, so I may as well remind you.Ages and ages ago, on thisvery planet (in re-emerginghere, we’ve come home, in the deepest sense), men, who had previously ‘died’, asthough they were cattle or sheep, found outthe secret of immortality.. . . Still doesn’t bring it back? - Just vaguely\ Well, anyway, after they’d finishedrejoicing, they found that, after all,the threatening shears were things they couldn’t do without. It’s said the daffodilswithered in the poets’ verses; nothingseemed beautiful when nothing would pass away I - in fact, they found the prospectsso deadly they clamoured for death tobe restored. Instead, their scientiststhought up a middle way, called Hera’sSpring, (I don’t know who gave it that name). But it came from the way Hera, ‘queenof the heavens ’ (you’ve heard of her inthis world) renewed her virginity,- 116-
￼BBSSD. M. THOMASthat is her purity, each year, by bathing in the spring of Canathos.It fits. The spring we step into isthe frozen heart of a crystal, from which we emerge, having just held our breaths, maybe a million years later.This first time is the worst, Jeseracdear - your homesickness, if you like, is focused, not radiated. When youhave had, like me, almost as manyparents alone as there are stars outon these sharp, moonless nights - in fact, when I look up, to whatever point inthe sky, I know I’ll face a dozenable to pierce through me, hazy orbright, each with a dozen bereavements - you’ll find the ache is a thing you can’tdo without either, in some queer way. ...But here I am, talking as if I’mantique, instead of being quite ayoungster in the city, not all thatmuch older or wiser than your smallbrother Helderr, whose first world this isI- and who, if I know anything,has woken up howling for my milkby this time! You stay here, Jeserac; come home to us when you feel ready, or hungry!-117-
￼POMEGRANATEEach year more clearly you can see her dark flowers wither to the sick light, or crush to our tighter embrace,as she picks up her bag and her coat, drifts out to facethe statutory six-months with her mother.She turns to my heart’s cog; rounded, no longer the child the courts shared between us, as a pomegranate cleft: small need any more for the fury who would have left me nothing . . . though god knows I have never reviledher. ‘Be good to her,’ I say, this morning; ‘give hermy — ’ (I cannot finish). ‘And — forget me while you’re there.’ ‘You both say that!’ She flicks her eyes . . . ‘Father, must I go?’My green shoot, Kore, dawdles now at the brightening river’s ferry — waves once — head bent, March uncabling her hair — then shoulders her bag, full of books I’ll expect her to know.
￼r
￼CYGNUS ARemoving hairgrips, nail-varnish, pensively brushing Black hair down to the blackBra, scattering a thick perfume on the night,You've time to read me pointed textsFrom the Gideons’ Bible propped by the red-stained kleenexTill I must shut my eyes tight While you slipOff (still that ludicrous reserve) Your diaphanous half-slip.But I prefer to gaze over the dark rooftopsAnd talk to you over my shoulder.Somewhere out there, love, near-neighbour Rigel Winks its white Chaucerian lightFrom Orion’s heel; taking its petty flight From the peaks of the EagleBurning through
￼Hitler, by Deneb and Altair, Falls Vega’s vulturous blue;Cambering Perseus covers half the sky,His spring from the weeping, huddled sisters, To see if he can reach AndromedaBefore the formless monster lands— Cassiopeia stretches out her hands;And out there too’s the glareOf yellow CapellaAnd red, bull-eyed Aldebaran.Yet since, sweet, all my stellarFriends are in fact outshone and liquidatedBy the sun streaming from the green shade Suspended on this window over flickers of you, I let myself go on and onPast Deneb, into the dark breast of the Swan Where only the radio-Telescope,Picking up its grating noisesHas any real hopeOf finding out that such a thing exists—- To a celestial catastropheGreater than most at various times enacted In this Trust House — a cataclysm Unforeseeable by their worst pessimism— To two galaxies attractedInto each otherAt a slow thousand miles a second Transformed to a smotherWhich astronomers cannot untangle; Cygnus A. . . . So girlish, now that your hollow mouthhas shed its lipstick flavour, you hold my hand. Preventively, I kiss black hair,Your eyes shui tight in pseudo-tragic prayer, Your weekend penates andMy cupidonClutter the bedside-table besideThe white text of St. John.What must it be to have been bom inside Such a fantastic complication —To pull aside a Cygnian tryst-house curtain And watch the overwhelming merge
￼As whistling suns and planets all converge! For a moment to feel uncertainIf one’s discreteGalaxy will ever emergeW ith all its stars complete,But only for a moment — the chances are That not two single stars will getToo entangled, as the run-through takes its course In the next millenium; no glacialFate is ready, sweet, to quench an outer-spatial Swan-light, though scoresOf spheres sail byEach second — blues, golds and reds In a greased, fabulous sky.We’re sure to see two ‘silver plates’ unpair Round the Year of our Lord 90,000— Though really, five hundred million years ago These ‘lovers’ fled away, despiteCuriosity at Jodrell Bank tonight; No doubt by this time snowHas covered overMany a planet, and Judgment-Day Has heard the excuse of lovers:“But that was in another galaxy,And besides, the star is dead!”While on live red-dwarfs, other will see St. John Shine in your eyes, an aeon hence,Recording, with their brilliant instruments, That the red-shift heaven’s undergoneSo shyly, doesn’t veilCompletely the Magellanic Cloud,Though all space-trips fail.
￼On October 21, I960, in the Welsh coal-mining village of Aberfan, Tip number 7, containing waste or slurry from the mine, slipped and overwhelmed Pantglas Junior School. Twenty eight adults and 116 children were killed: a generation.The marginal prose-passages are from ‘Aberfan'. a book by Tony Austin, and from a B.B.C. television documentary.REQUIEM FOR ABERFAN
￼‘The scenery tothe south . . . became surprisingly beautiful. . . noble mountains metthe view, greenIMagnates whose sweated legions crucifiedThe valleys, washed their soft white hands, although The children died before they died.Brethren who rode their God in on the tideOf weeping, hawk this good comfort, that we owe Our deaths to One on green hill crucified.The child whose dream, the child whose drawing tried To tell somebody that the hill would flow,Knew that they died before they died.Workmen who chose and staked this mountainside, Their ankles lush with streams, a school below, Learn on what green hill they were crucified.Sleepers who from their sheets saw the coal slide And bury, seven nights before it happened, know The children died before they died.Mothers, whose olf-to-death sharp voices denied Fevers and fancies, following at each cock-crow The road they drove them to be crucified,Die on the ninth-hour before they died.fields andmajestic woods.'— George Borrow.‘I dreamt I went to school andthere was no school there. Something black had come all overit.’-— A victim, the day before Aberfan.‘Mountains of coal and water were rushing down upon the valley, burying the building. The screams of those children were so vivid I screamed myself— -4Kent woman’s dream.
￼CouncillorJim Williams remembering how he said just before October 21 thathe hoped Bethania Chapel wouldsoon befull.Bethania(the chapel used as a mortuary)‘Soon, Lord, soon may I see it full.’A child to each pew, to work His will, And the gallery opened as an overspill.When Christ rode in to Bethany.The man He killed as God aboveHe chose to raise, in human love. Comeforth, He said, and the linens moved.When Christ rode in to Bethany.F for Female, M for Male,‘Not to be opened’, like Christmas mail:Had these women, searching, anointed Him with oil,Would Christ have come to Bethania?Would He have raced, with police-escort,Up the jammed trunk-road, to avertThe stink of death that had four hours’ start,Two thousand years after Bethany?Cramped in a valley, Aberfan. Manmade black hills roadblock the sun. Only embalmers, in Capel Aberfan,Make miracles out of Bethania.In two’s, they queue at the door through the night, Dazed, unspeaking. A crude flashlightGets smashed by a stone as its stare insults,No light like His at Bethany.He spoke; and the corpse resumed its ghost. Only churning lorries, piled with waste, And ambulances, processing without haste,Have cracked and emptied Bethania.Letters toindicate the barest details were chalked at the ends ofthe pews . . .The ‘Not to be opened’ notes were ignored because cause of death had to be confirmed and identity established.Once there had been identification coffins were taken to Capel Aberfan. Here a team of embalmers worked.The old building was not to be used again in the coming months; itsfoundations were too shaken bythe traffic.
￼There was no keeping out, that day, or keeping in Either. They set up roadblocks, but you couldn’t stop All Britain pitching in and trying to help.Or gawp. I stopped one car myself, a whole family, From the Midlands, ‘Is this the place where all thosekids Are buried?’he said. But mostly they wanted to help,Anything they could do. Which wasn’t much. They didn’t have a chance, you see, didn’t have achance.. . Yet, you couldn’t seem to keep them in. The children.Not all that lot could. My missus and me, we saw David A score of times, I suppose, that Friday. He waseverywhere! Running up to the front-door, about to bang it shut,About to turn the corner. Always about to,always three of us,In the road, in the crowd. Once, I still swear I didsee him,In Moy Road, then he vanished. There were the rumours, you see,Of some being found alive. The whole terrace was like that, Full of them. No, you couldn’t shut them in. It was likeHoles in the slurry you couldn’t see. There were More kids about the place than normal, I’d say. Funny, it was the same even when I’d found David In Betliania. Not a mark on him, there wasn’t.Like a doll. We still hoped. It hadn’t happened, do you know?
￼ifThe FatherThe day you came, I felt her turn from me. Absence, fullbreasted, coasting at my side, Straining for different hungers — rightfully.With no regrets, my pit-black spirit died And rose like waste through galleries of you. Cast like a tip, I saw and sang my pride,The first-born, inexhaustible, the newSeam, richer, deeper than all Rhondda. A man Gets bora again out of his wife, I knew,What did it matter that the more you ranInto your mother’s heart, the closer I feltTo an eighth spewed cone outtopping Aberfan?With no regrets. And yet have I not knelt Begging God that His curse should overwhelm Me also, so confirmed was I in guiltAt having willed this on you, in some dreamI had forgotten maybe. When, as the arc-Lights flickered on the ant-hill, I heard your screamRise faintly from a desk, miles deep, the black Slurry was in myself. Why did we pause?Now, when the shuddering cage transports us backTo that rise up to hell — untold, we knew — Always I hear, faintly, unreachably,You cry where my own evil fell on you.Breaths held in, earsstrained for a faint murmur thatwould lead to alife saved. Silence. . . the whistle again, digging resumed.Deputies and over­men kept the few details tothemselves. They did not want panic.There was none, but no man came to the surface without knowing why. There are no secrets underground.IV
p￼He dreams of his elder brother having parties in the grave.“ Robert, Robert, play with me. You can win.”Last night, in my sleep, I heard it.I was in disgrace for telling on them, but I didn’t. Robert called me, Sissy.The BrotherI steal into his room, with my pack of cards, And plays patience under his photo,Hoping to tempt him.I get tired of it. It never comes out.So I go to the mountain, quite a lot.I remember we had a story onceAbout how somebody led these children into theVAnd there was a lame boy who couldn’t go. mountain, Mummy doesn’t know, but they have parties in thegrave.The terrace is empty. All summer it’s Sunday.If I showed him my cards, offered to let him win Only so he would play with me, play,Would he let me in?
￼Diane could move her head now; she turned, saw the child who sat next to her. She screamed: “That’s my sister.” “No, dear, it’s aI should have seen her. I might accept it, resign Myself to having lost her. Not now. You can’t Send your child off to school at nineO’clock and never see her again. You can’t!They wouldn’t let me into Bethania, whereThey had taken her. I should have fought my way in. They seemed to think I wouldn’t be able to bearIt. The condition she was in.dolly." Dr Oliver threw a blanket over the dolly. Diane went quiet.Because of that, she lives. I put flowers On her grave like the rest, every day,but she’s not there, Not to me she isn’t. It has blue eyes like hers —Look how they open. To me, she’s there,Shut inside the doll. It was her best doll.I say Try, darling, try to moveYour arms and legs for me, try. But it’s allThat stuff, surrounding, binding. She never moves.But I can see her struggling. It’s such a shame,All that blackness round them . . . Sometimes her eyes Flinch open up at me as though I’ll blameHer for not escaping. As though her eyesCan see me, either! But there is always hopeThat one day . . . And so I keep the roomExactly as she left it — her books, her skipping-rope, Her nightclothes. Suppose she woke to a strange room?People don’t like it. Callers say I should free Myself from the past, that I must forget.My freedom’s here in this room. She grew from me: Who would remember her if I forgot?
￼Settle? Ah no! a butterfly, a cabbage-white.Earth trapped our shadows also as we leant Over the sllt-trench.Bodies saw them die.Yet when we drifted down the pathVIIThe TreeJune. A pallid cloud-drift of sun.Tree, where a year ago she swung,Branch and ropes holding the deepening brunt, Tree, where seven years ago we forked the afterbirthForked it under, watched it grow. We tried to please, But there’s little enough you could give, to child or tree, In Aberfan. Watch how coaldust blackens and defeats In two days the cherry blossom, too late for Easter.By what trick of its branches’ shadow and lightDo I look from the window and see thin limbs flashhigh? By what trick of time do I glimpse a torn leaf rise,V IIICommittal— Buoyed up breathless, half-conscious, by communalloss, Our bodies stayed behind, our shadows went.As if lifted off our feet by a great crowd Out of Cardiff Arms Park —under.
￼The third, week of October 1966 was notablefor high winds and heavy rain.Parents neededto have children near. Mothersslept with daughters and fathers with sons. Normal marital relations were interrupted.The QuickeningThe year turns, to the eve. She lies awake.Once more the storm comes slanting out of the west. The younger girl is breathing by her side.Even so, that night, black drops had slashed the pane. She flinches; at this hour her child had criedOut in her sleep, but she has calmed her fears.She hears the tip upbristling, stormed awake.Silently, she rises. There are fearsOf rain the spirit in the doll cannotExpress. She crosses the dim passageway,To comfort it. But it is cold! so trapped!She bears it downstairs, opens the door, to lay Her burden in the fury of the storm.Crying, the storm lacerates her tears.She mounts. And goes this time into his room. She melts into his dream of wind and rain.She hears the loud drops guttering from the eaves Upon the lonely doll, running the stiff wax, Releasing limbs beflagged with torn wet leaves, And as the rain drums on, the quickening breach, She feels her child’s return within her womb.IX
￼■ima,'!*!j«iii'rfiii>MiM'i'iftnilimittT*.*'XThe red lights of Tip number 7 gleam through the dusk, Shutting the stable. It is Christmas. Except in Aberfan. I stand in the mountainside cemetery, handblowing,The school is here,Pantglas School eternally in session.The master arrived, the names called, and theDyfrig, David, Janette, Kelvyn . . . Incorrigible, they are now corrected, Wilful, in line.register collected.Not requiem, not rest, —Unrest, mischievousness!Have them break ranks,Somewhere, somewhere, a boy set rebellion going! Dissolve this petrifaction of scriptureInto games, into movement;Release them to a playground’s anarchy.They have won well their omegas, their black stars, their death’s word-perfect:They are impatient to say it over, and go.I would sayLearn, you too-rigid, you too-silencing teacher, That children can’t concentrateOn any subject, can’t concentratePast bell and alarum, can’t concentrate,As these are doing,For long./cold.