￼TETE-A-TETEAfter supper (ratatouille, heated on his gas ring) she remarked on a moth which circled the lamp throwing wild shadows round the room.When it quivered to rest on the rubber plant they leafed through his book of lepidoptera their knees almost touching,they leaned over its furry, palpitating body, their heads almost touching, and at last, after an awkward pause,he read aloud: TheMonarch butterfly knocks the female to the groundand copulates with her wherever she falls1.Almost at once, she looked at her watch and, murmuring politely, slipped from the doorand flew down the steps to the street.4CW
￼IN THE EMPORIUMIn the emporium a man is always sittinq waiting for his wifeto come out of the eternal chanqinq-rooms.Greyly he sits, brushed by cobwebs of lace, swirled at by chiffon. The satin leqs of the assistant scissor past his face.He takes his rod to a quiet, riparian stretch. There is nothinq in the world but a point of liqht.When it moves, everythinq will break up and his creature will come to him, sinuous in the spindrift -qlintinq in all colours of the rainbow - electric under his hand,beatinq at his slippery wrists.His breath comes short:his fingers itch to pick the wicked barb from the pink mouth; but on the banka matronly fiqure materialisesrevolving slowly, stiff with taffeta.
￼THE SLIPPING GLIMPSEI am into the business of uninvention.My desk is loaded with applications: I am quite private behind my in-tray.The procedures, you can imagineare tortuous: thepaperwork, the manual work,the research, the lasering out of information from human brain cells.Often there are misunderstandings about my scope and capability:(Famine? Disease?I do not set myself up against God.)My prime achievements would mean nothing to you success conceals success.You may hear a phrase, perhaps, cut off frcm its context -muffled sounds on the radio of a passing car; words heard through a door as it closes.
￼CHACUN"That weekend, she lay on the bedas usual, smooth and distant in my arms.We seemed set for our normal parts -I, noisy, active, verging on the hysterical she marmoreal, abstractedamong the rucked and musky sheets.And then, this day, she moved:her body moved to me.Her teeth clenched, a tremor broke in her like power through a fault in the earth.I swung over, hot as fur, and fought herto conclusion. We did not speak.If I laughed, it was only briefly:but when I left, she slammed the door on me lock, hook and bolt."
￼THE WINNERAs a rival he was unassailable eating from her fingers, lounging on her bed, canvassing attentionwith his upturned, obscene, bald stomach.When at last I despatched him he lay, mingling his pelt with the hearthrug,unmoving but complacent,knowing that his last gaspA. was the coup de grace.