￼D. M. THOMASDear Mrs Thatcher,Truro, Cornwall.I imagine this book of letters will be full of abuse from deck-chair Socialists, and I have no intention of adding to it. Instead I would like to congratulate you on your premiership. Although your touch seems to have deserted you of late - temporarily, I hope - I think you have been an excellent Prime Minister.You taught us the hard lesson that a country, like a family, has to live within its means. As you read thcMulent attacks, I suggest you-try -to imagine the state Britain wotdd be in, within- a couple-^ m onths, if those who attack-you were in N o. 10; banlc-r-upt, cuts, in. the health service and education.You have brought a more human, feminine touch to our politics. Oh, of course, your royal We is irritating, and I wish you’d learn to say I; but at crucial moments, like the Falklands and the Brighton bombing, you haven’t been afraid to show your feelings in a way somehow impossible for male politicians.You have been a great friend to democracy, both at home and abroad. At home, you curbed the undemocratic Union barons; and you have forced the Labour Party to democratise itself: one of your finest achievements may turn out to have been the creation of a decent alternative to your own party'. Abroad, you helped —with understandable reluctance - to bring to birth an African kind of democracy in Rhodesia. Without your firmness over the Falklands, Argentina would today still be a military dictatorship. And through your friendship with, and encouragement of, Mr Gorbachev you have contributed greatly to the liberation from Communism ofpastern Europe. Few statesmen or women - I think you would shudder, as I do, at statesperson - have helped democracy so well. Speaking of democracy, I am not aware that anyone has ever asked me if I wish to be a citizen of a federal Europe. Indeed, when the referendum took place, I was assured this would never occur. As it happens, I hate the idea of European federation. If Britain votes for it, I would have to accept it, but I object to the present bullying and browbeating (of you) when the electorate has had no chance to express its wishes. So all power to you in your cautionp-H. Of-\Lv ° o » . v o i c e SoH * i»»- ° ^ vo(c. Eu t "r ” a1
￼144 D. M. T H O M A Sand “stubbornness”.By the way, I write as someone who is not a Conservative, nor aSocialist, nor a Liberal Democrat - but a floating voter; that is to say, I am quite proud of having a free mind. I certainly don’t agree with everything you have done. I wish you were more sceptical about big business and military power. With the privatisation of water and electricity, and with the Poll Tax, I think you have let ideology overcome common sense and pragmatism. My hope for the nineties is that you will re-discover your popular touch, give ideology a rest, help Russia all you can, and fight to preserve our independence within a Europe of friendly nations - from Ireland to the Urals. I hope you will find it possible to reduce military' expenditure considerably, and with the money saved improve the health sendee and the environment. And on a personal level I’d like you to develop a more relaxed style, and reveal the warm human being that I am sure you really are.Thank you, finally, for giving me the enormous pleasure of seeing most of my literary friends and acquaintances grow apoplectic with fury at the mere sound of your name. I know you have had a pseudo-Freudian anr^sis written about you; I think the unconscious of your attackers is more worthy of serious Freudian study. I doubt if they would feel as virulent towards a male Prime Minister who had fought his way up from a corner grocer’s shop and Grammar School. (I am tempted to leave my mistyping there: ‘fought his wife up’ —a good Freudian joke, no?)Of course, the hostility of the intelligentsia is almost a guarantee that you have been doing okay; since they are mostly the kind of people who would have turned Communist and lauded Stalin in the thirties, and clamoured for negotiations with Hider. Nevertheless, their attacks must sometimes hurt, and I think your stamina under fire has been admirable.One consolation must be the sure knowledge that in 20 years’t i m e , l o n g o u t o f p o w e r , vo fi w M b e c o m e a n a f f e c t i o n a t e l y - r e g a r d e d ^ —“’tution, like the Queen Mother or some ageing Wimbledon^,ennis champion. I hope you will write a stunninglylionestA autqbiographyf including your real feelings for your parents and/^ your love-life. T look forward to reading it - but not for a few years \ yet.Yours sincerely,D. M. THOMAS.D. M. Thomas is a novelist, poet and translator. His novels include The White Hotel (shortlisted for the Booker Prize), Summit, and most recently, Lying Together (Gollancz, 1990). He divides his time between writing and tutoring poetry and fiction courses at his house in Cornwall.IOCL UVdDCXZ-t J