￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm Roaje 42 Crepusculo - IbizaAnd he was famousfor the way he handled girls.He was like a butcher with a knife. I followed him.My little knock -so high-pitched, so final. Remembering what? Somebody saying O f course, if it’s your first gala,you will be nervous.He smiled, and singed my hair with his gold-plated cigarette-lighter.The doctor came too late.It was snowing.He put a box of chocolateson my bed, and kissed my cheek. You’re a good girl, he said.CuHis long white skirts,his polished shoes,his soft pink handsthat never touched my lips.He sent me photographs of naked menon diving boardsand decks of yachts. Crepusculo - Ibiza.Shell Bay. Torquay.La carte postale de Vamitie.Jean Genet’s Liverpool.42-e-I-
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm43We used to do thisin the war, he said,marching all night in our sleep, then hiding in a bluebell wood, crying out loud for girls.He carries apples in his coat.His mother thinks he’s dying.He hears white cows that move about when he’s alone at night.Cme-O43-o-
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 p m E a j e 4 4The Ptarmigan HunterII’m being kept awake by too many kissesand the new central-heating system of a high-rise Carousel hotel.The hot pipes go tick tick and this man I hardly knowkeeps turning me over and over like the hunter on the radiowho came across a mummy while on holiday in Greenland.IILady of Qilakitsoq, sleeping on ice,your face tattooed by the old womanwith the seal-bone needle, your body wrappedin cormorant skinsand polar willow leaves,sleepwhile you can.^44
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm ^ 45IIIAn off-duty rangerdrove over in his Dodge from Umanakto shoot ptarmigan,and found a young woman, freeze-dried,like coffee, under a rock.He cut off her black underclothesand took them home to his father who, being afraid of ghosts,fed them into the Garbage Guzzler he had just bought.
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm Page 46The BathHe presses an oval of soapinto the palm of his handand twirls the bristles in the violet foamuntil it quilts his fingers like the snow where trappers crawl to pull the hairs from little Russian weasels.I lie under the greying water; drape my flannel on my curlslike palls, or like the coloured coatsthat poodles wear; or muslin lain on cheese in dingy larders to protect it from the flies.Not that he’s likely to look:his only joy’s his - twizzle twizzle twizzle - obsessive pirouettes. Then I rememberHe’s been deadfor weeks.I roll over in the water thoughtfully, feeling - not lonely exactly -more like a floating pear-halfhaving warm chocolate sauce poured over me.46-0 -
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm Rase 48Mother StoneMy father was a tall man who approved of beating, but my mother, like a mother stone,preferred us to be sitting in a small roomlined with damson-coloured velvetthinking quietly to ourselves, undisturbed; everything was slow and beautifulwhen we were being punished: all we had to do was watch the dark-red petals’ rosespress against each other in a slight breeze on the window pane, and blossoms fallin silence from the cherry tree;and now my son is lying in a long white shirtacross our eiderdown, trying to stay awake,and fingering my spine’s shell pink as if I were a beach and he were blades of marram grass in drifts of sand.I dab my face with cream that smells of cucumberand whisper in a distant milky voiceO f course I ’ll wake you up when he comes',and then his eyelids close,and in his self-created darkness he is followinga big car on a motorway at night,it turns into the driveway to the house,and presently the driver gets out:it is only a bear in the moonlight,walking on the lavender beds.480--0
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm Raje 47Eating Chocolates in the DarkAnd after that, the diaries stop.We think he went to his grandmother’s, whom he adored apparently.They sat on her bedwith the lights turned off,and ate chocolates,and listened to the sea.It was a kind of ritualthey both found very comforting.Her other love was hyacinths.He said he didn’t like them,and asked her to take them away.And then he started telling her about a lost eskimowho paddled up the Don in a kayak. He was dressed in sealskin,and very tired. After a few days,he caught a cold and died.The dip dip dip of the little boat, and his sad story-telling voice,were like a lullaby,and she was asleep, or nearly asleep, when suddenly he asked herif she believed in God.(She told me all this quite openly - the old Russian grandmother,half lying back on her cushions.Perhaps I shouldn’t say this, she said, but listen to me for a moment -if you wake up,and feel something fat like a puppy wriggling between your legs,you’re not going to say it’s God,or the answer to all your questions, or Love, are you? It’s sex!It was the same for him.)-e-47
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:06 pm ROage 49 No oneNo one is to touch me but the Lord.His fingertips caress me like a knife.Everywhere I go I am adored.I want to be a monk but I’m a wife.49©