￼Thehad eaten nothing for da^s , andNbhe yolk was yellow ana warm,but l\*ras still far frpm well,and all wantedand I thoti than dribblerider dribble it oyfto me'for me;so I lay ck down on'kny sackand con- ued to dream OxXthe Master,as out/in the rain the horses drifted away like fish.or let the myleer,rather^a-ie o my^cfTgue,
￼SipsThey come from certain over-heated quarries that ooerate illicitly,in relays,for those who are attracted to the flowers that grow gigantic in the noonday sun.And then they come on here and pester me - sort of oester,sort of guide my lirsuntil,like them,! learn to sir the flowers that grow so big they block the daylight out,and people are condemned to live in darkness; and,such is their confusion,every daymen with yellow dogs oatrol the rocks,and kill and Quarter anything that moves.
￼I'm here to be their keener for a while.Have a break.Think a few things over.I need the space.My only friends will bethe ghosts of skaters and a pack of dogs.The.y range across the concrete wastes like liners,avoiding human contact,crop-eared,lean; retiring,when night falls, to giant ninesthat echo to the crunch of broken lambs.And Massey's man will come,and bring me orchids; we'll lie together like two hired snakes,our brains as soft as sugar,or the skater whose lovely agile bones were ground to nowderand scattered on the sites of his desnair.
￼How To Be HappyIn the crowded hold of someone's boat,chocolate sauce is being poured on nearsthat shudder as the chocolate coats their should and snreads its lip across each tilted plate, across the Ians of guests,the rubber floor,till everything is sunk in utter darkness,and noone sneaks,and noone even moves.Years go by;then someone's eyes maice outthe oolished surface of a chocolate seawhere tiny golden boats are busy fishing.
￼The Climbing AccidentEven in this terrible cold, I can remember everything:THE WONDERFUL WORLD OF HORSES, my sister's hesitant bush.Christ's blood was shed for us. I've never been so happy]
￼Biscuits'If you stay here longyou start to smell it -a nleasant smell,like biscuits,or warm fur.People say it's got hypnotic powers.They say it makes you want to follow her. And people do.They do it all the time.They turn up late at night with plastic bags pleading with the guards to let them in.The nlace is over-run.It's like a nightmare]'And as he sneakshie strokes thespeckled headspushing up against us on all sidesin varying stages of delirium.'Revised version of The Hap)rVtoJD
￼The Hap'And. i<hen shea's asked, she alw^rys^days the same. She looksmrt: you and says The Rp?o,I gue^s.And if you stay here long,you start to smell it -a pleasant smell,like biscuits, or warm fur.People say it's got hypnotic rowers. They say it makes you want to follow he And neorle do.^ov rjo it all the time.The-7’ turn ur late at nivht with rlasric b a m "■leadinm with the nerds to let thesi inThe rlace is over—run.It's like a nisrhtmare.'And as he speaks,he smokes the mass of head.s seething in his arms conrinuously in varying shames of delirium.
￼Selima HillTHE ISLANDMen want to understand, and think they do, and maybe if they don't it's not their fault, but basically this place belongs to us.We like to organize ourselves ourselves. And anyway, anyone can visit -brothers, fathers, lovers, anyone.Mv son comes often; or I visit him.You ask us if we miss them. Not at all.W e don't use cars, or electricity,and men especially seem to find that hard. Another thing - we feel healthier.We work the horses; bear much fewer children and eat and dress and live very simply.We shepherd sheep. We scale trees for fruit. We abseil cliffs for samphire and fresh eggs; and some of us, as you have pointed out,, migrating to the cities, abseil glass.
￼The Man ManWho is this man?And why is time different here9And what does he say,with his mouthful of r's like blood?plunges his arms into rocks and puitls out lizards.Skinner of swifts, sucker of brittle eggs,easer of scented pianos down warmed ramps,who is this man,and what does he rromise me?My mother stops my mouth.She says I must never never tell him where I am.f<vQ
￼Standing Here Beside YouStanding here beside you makes me sad. You're like a house I watch the windows ofknowing I can never go inside.I see a woman passing to and froand envy her the freedom I can't have. I only watch.And you?You're watching too,frozenin your prison of white flowers.*CPD.
￼38 Poetry: Selima HillCOMFORTWho is this ‘Mother’with a splitting headacheand a fear of mice,who sits very still on her chair,like a trout,or an amputee,leafing through the nursery garden catalogue;who, when her son comes into the kitchen dressed in a towelafter posing in the nude as San Sebastian, passes him a delicious home-made rock-cake with the raisins already picked out?Who has lost herself among the lupins searching for the insects with a teaspoon?Whose home is remorse,like the home of a calf is a crate the farmers and graziersseem to prefer to ignore?Who is this ‘Mother’with a hand like a traywho passes us frail slices of white bread■peeled from the bladeof Elly’s electric bread-slicer?Whose eyes are like bowls of shells, or the bluebell woodswhere old men have kept boats ever since anyone can remember?Who is this person called ‘Mother’ who will not be comforted?Selima HillA
￼WolvesNormally a rather timid man,he knew exactly what he had to do -find a wolf,and,watching every movement, kneel down before her in the darknesswhere endless little bands of beady nightlif stream like gold across the forest flooras if there's been some terrible mistake that only they are able to correct,only they and those like them who know.Most of all,he needed to kneel down - something not encouraged in an office. Offices are not the place for tiptoing, . gazing,kneeling,anything like that.Offices are not the place for wolves,or anyone involved with them,or nmght. Offices are meant for office-workers.Anybody else will be pnovedand flattened out in basements by machines. Nothing is the name they'll be remembered by lots of it,as ordered,nice and flat.
￼SilenceHer path,if you can call it one,is silence, obviously quite different from our own,and one,as I have said,that we will monitor. It's true she makes my oeople here uneasy - she makes it hard to go on acting normally, and not to call in question one's beliefs. Another thing - her smell of chickenfeed.To be precise,of chickenfeed and lemon.Curled up on my eiderdown this morning,she looked like something nut there to annoy me —and I n*fet admit I felt a strong temntationto wring her little neck and dispose of her,which would have been quite easy in the circumstances, there being no bright feathers to betray us.K$>.
￼The JourneyI net him on the stairs quite unexpectedly, and there and then I left the little hospital and,trusting him as much,or more,than humans, followed him,without a word - to you.Some of you,I know,have been expecting-usr have waited years,in fact,for our arrival, so can I take this opportunityof thanking you for your encouragement? Your country,as you know,is not well liked, and anyone who comes,must come alone.We have to make our way across the mountainsby intuition,some would say mistake,not really knowing why we started out,or who we are,or what we're looking for.It's like the special side-room at the hospital that patients other patients were unsettled by, patients needing quiet,used to sleep in.And people loathed it.Anything but that!Why? Becausejit's up a little stair,and looking out on nothing but the moors.But once they did,and this applied to everyone, a subtle transformation would come over them.
￼BoatingFew,if any,went to bed that night,and in the morning rescue teams set out.Only those too weak to help remained- the littleman,the children,three small hens. They waited ip the house for what seemed days until a river made of melting snowcarried them away towards the sea - everyone,that is,except the man,who had a boat,and rowed upstairs to bed,but even that,his fifty-year-old bed;slipped away as he approached,like sand,and then the house itself was washed away,and he was left to roam the world alone, rowing through the treetops in hidjnightshirt,or sometimes rowing,sometimes simply drifting, feeling too relaxed to really think;but once he saw,or thought he saw,a woman, waving from the rail of a liner;but when ha called,she didn't answer him - as if to stop him calling out like thatand spoiling the whole joy of the occasion.
￼Everything Is WonderfulEverything is wonderful up here - the flowers,the view,the way the setting sungilds the children,and the children's horses.And everyone's so kind.And seems to know me.It's like a sort of friendly hotel. But all the sameit doesn't feel quite right.I sometimes wonderif there's some mistake. And if my other life's still going on.And where my friends are*, and the house I knew.Who booked me into this one,anyway? Ask.Why don't I simply ask someone*5I'll ask this parson trimming the hydrangeas. Maybe!*®®, hq/my son.You never know.What I want to know isIs it serious?And do I live here? Normally,I n"ean. Or is it just a joke? An exercise?How boring of me if it is.I'm sorry!Perhaps there's someone I can talk to somewhere? Or is it up to me to do whatever?'Thanks-a-1ot-I'11-take-it' type of thing? The nice hydrangea man says Feel free.It sounds so easy,doesn't it -feel free?
￼SparkleI'm not as unprepared as you might think.Take a look outside my window.Dors.All day they wait like soldiers for my voice, a voice so beautiful that everyone -no,not so beautiful,a voice so clear -that everyone who hears it,dogs included,will leave the hospital,without a fuss,some with chocolate,some with fish,or fruit, and make their way into the distant mountains. And if they want to dress in dresses,let them.Let them wear the shiniest materialsthe nurses and the clergy can provide,so when they reach their final'destinationthe rocks will sparkle with them - for one year. Then men will come,attracted by the light, and,armed with i?lames,expertly incinerate them;returning with the ash to the valley,where things have changed,and even dogs are burnt,and $elstre&sd desflicjhted leaves go clacketty, in at the hospital windows,clacketty-clack.(palmitrees1/