￼VTcss, in TunisiaReleased,she tilts over on her side.‘The Fall is only that,’ she says shaking sand from her hair, ‘when voi^wish returnsto Paradise. G o on, forget her.’She says we are inventingnew ways of shipping men and women and all her art is aiming fora raft that swimmers reach and share.She says this that it may be so.You did not worry as you laybeached together through a starless night; an obscured moon still pulls the tidesof billow-talk and pillow-friends.These words comefrom Proverbs, Tess, and the Koran; dogs bark above our heads and yet the caravan moves on.26
￼Love-Torn Squaddie in Rannoch TormentBeing, show me your ground.Only the moor and a keepo f castellated cloud and the wind moving on as she did, snagged enough to make roots whinelike children left behind.He waits for his heart to stop but it won’t.That’s all the ground there is, soldier, it’s all ground, even the airy-fairy cloud-castle on the hill, eventhe shrilling in your chest.Being torn between moving on and being left behind, he wavers shredded among heather.
￼The House-Builder Variations A workshop - principal materials:saw. drill, rule, nails, a plain deal tableUnemployed? Growing rusty? You wanta house that is unique - home in on this!1lere’s your drill, the hammer-action for concrete, this is your saw, your rule, your plain deal table. These are the trees. The compassionate State awards you with a gross of nails.Such are your true materials. Confused?You want to shelve it for today? Believe me,if you pass on children you must make something o f your own, or live aloner than alone.A better deal! Unemployed, not unique,this was his drill: plane it true,hammer the State, nail it to a tree.But the old saws were rusty, the rulewas bent, he made nothing at the table.(He could have said it in spades, butspades are disallowed materials - you think association’s free?) What frame could housesuch passion? It must be concrete, too gross to shelve. Confused, alone, he passes on today.Concrete poems? A house of cards, shuffle them as you will! Deal anyway. What was it she saw that made the trees seem jungular today? (Nothing’s disallowed, but old drills are bentas is the State and its materials.)As a rule, truth’s a shelf that takes unique confusion to nail it to the wall. Unemployment takes a hammering today as she sits making passionate childrenin her swaying home high in the trees.56
￼Here’s what I saw when I tookthat hammering: alone is gross.Let us live in free association, where is not material. Plain dealing! Believe me (though I am swaying),a bent rule is unique. We shallbe shelf-employed! Today is concrete passion. Nail down this truth:I love you though the drill be rustyand the state confused.
￼Copyright (C) Andrew Greig 1990 ISBN: 1 85224 102 0First published 1990 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern ArtsLEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. N o part o f this book may bereproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without the prior written permission of Bloodaxe Books Ltd.Typesetting by Bryan Williamson, Darwen, Lancashire.Printed in Great Britain byBillings & Sons Limited, Worcester.
￼For my father, who over his lifetime wentfrom Red Clydeside to Old Tory but aye said‘No one ever got rich hut at the expense ofthe widow, the orphan, or the stranger at the door'And my mother, who sang when I was wee0>x‘Far across the firmament The floating sausage blows He seeks his little frying pan, The only home he knows..Somewhere between them, this hook.To my friends —thanks a bundle.fA
￼Acknowledgements^ Moo ) (3 0 W V f -------------------Acknowledgements are due to tkjie editors of the following publica­tions iikwhich some of these points first appeared: AlpineJournal, 5 ChapmaruLandfall(NewZealand),bJewStatesman, New WritingScot- land, Poetry Review, Poetry with an Edge (Bloodaxe Books, 1988), TheScotsman and Verse. ‘T itle of Pqfem’, ‘etc.’ were broadcast on Poetry’ Now (BBC Radio 3). ^vea-S.The author gratefully acknowledges the help of a Scottish Arts Council Writers’ Bursary in completing this book.
￼The Order of the DayIN THE MOUNTAINS10 Back Again11 Interlude on Mustagh Tower12 Sandy, Topping Out on Mustagh14 Entering Askole15 The Winter Climbing16 Crux18 Three Above Namche Bazaar19 After Everest20 AvalancheIN 1,0VE & POLITICS22 A Reader’s Note23 Mazed24 Shetland25 About Tess26 Tess, in Tunisia27 Love-Torn Squaddie in Rannoch Torment28 Still29 Visiting30 Annie, in Spring31 Treaty32 Annie33 Gulf34 Annie, in November35 Ruth Says36 Spello, in the Afternoon37 Nut38 Covert Action39 Young American40 Fishing41 D, in a Checked Shirt42 D, Riding43 Heart & Irish44 Up the Baobab45 Exit46 Fictionsr
￼Back Again On Lliotse SharWe’re back againwith our tents, our trash,our high ambition. We’ve come to be both audience and show.Mai flicked his lighter, an avalanche roared - we have come to assert everything fitsand we believethe true scale of thingsis the entire mountainhung mirrored in our shades.#All day snow sank in the billy,was boiled, drunk, peed, replenishedas we passed the mountain through us.The chat was home and axes, hopes, seracs.The voices tire, yellow lights hiss as night comes onto very few witnessesbut enough.Lnblinking stars and lightning — the theatre’s hushed.From the heights we proposeto the depths we’ve leftour shadows gesture and stretch.10
￼Interlude on Mustagh TowerIn these high places we are melting outof all that made us rigid; our ice-screwshang loose on the fixed ropes to the Col. Monday in the Himalaya, the clouds are down, our objective is somewhere, but obscure -let it soar without us for a day!We lounge in thermals on the glacier,brewing and shooting the breeze, that improbable project of conversation among the living. Laughter rings across the ice. Why not?None of us will die today - that’s immortality'you can draw on in a cigarette,harsh and sweet, the way we like it.Steam rises from the billy, Sandy pours.It is true high, worked for, that we passhand to hand between us with our brews.Men on ice, going nowhere and laughingat everything we cannot see but knowis there - among the cloud, on the Col,a hand of some sort is tightening our screws.
￼Sandy, Topping Out on MustaghSo began to lead the last of the TowerQuite hard more bold than difficulttough ice loose snow but soon brainbegan to play the game My points investigated stabbed good placements to be hadamong loose choss Crucified by altitudeI bridged a steepish rockwall Goodvalue that I remember everythinglike ice-slivers in my windsuit’s creases Camp 4 a thousand feet beneath mv heels climbinginto my shadow the sun flashed off my axeJon he was somewhere giving good rope and no advice the ideal secondbut me I was goneNice work when you can get itthe hardest the best hours passedtill I wanted a think and a restso thumped in an ice-screw and hung out awhile —Like I cannot spell, speak porter-talk but who does not who’s lived like me with oil roughnecks and a French girl? One look in her eyes, I know.One straight hit, I find good ice.Climbing's not so much, my life's more in the way I eat myfood, the man I rise above, the roads I drive tofriends,these suit -Re-engaged myself and winkled on with patient pickers unlocked the crux set my axes well and at full stretch pulled over the top and saw into China12
￼HEAD WAS MUTE□felt ok^felt well(a cheval across the summit)K2 in the distance looking good (suspicion of moisture behind my shades)Made a belay and took in the ropes as Jon came up. So how’s it going? Oh, wasted, youth...‘From Base Camp to the stream there is a path now and the grass is yellow at the centre o f the path. ’t13
￼Entering Askole (for Malcolm Duff)On the eighth evening we entered Askole. How can I tell you? We had seenno habitation in two months. Brown dogs twitched in the shade, a chicken screamed; we smelled dung, dall, smoke, lentils; many voices, the bronze fields shone.Lean as schoolmasters, tall wheat rapped our knuckles as we limped into the square.Say there are miracles betweenwhere babies twitch and sleep and old folksleep and totter. Water-mills spun,yaks plonked circles round the threshing floor. Evening prayers, a sleeping miller, tawny goatsstole husks of wheat. Goitres hunglike apples on the children’s necks.The Hadji lightly touched our backs, Summit good...We had been above ourselves, hooked to pure worlds of black & white & blue,the narrow world of sleeping bags.In Askole we smoked and talked till dawn then rose and crossed the river,paid the porters, jeep did the rest.We broke down, sang ‘It will come hardto sleep on beds as soft and wide as ours.’J/14
￼The Winter Climbing (forM arj)It is late January and at last the snow.I lie back dreaming about Glencoeas fluent, hungry, dressed in red,you climb up and over me. That passion claimed the darkest, useless monthsfor risk and play. You riseup on me, I rise through you...The shadowed face of Aonach Dubh where M ai first took me climbing and as we clanked exhausted, happy, downwards through the dark, I asked ‘What route was that?’ ‘Call itwhat you want - it’s new.’You reach the top and exit out;from way above, your cry comes down.The rope pulls tight. What shall we callthis new thing we’re about?These days we live in takingcare and chances. Why name it?My heart is in my mouth as I shout Climbing...t15
￼A Reader’s Note b c BMazedCall him anything, call him Jim . At any road a Scottish male of a certain agestands hopeful, hesitating, lost.He scuffs the dust, unable to go on or back.I want to see him on the rack.Compressed or stretched, the heresies will show. And mock him carefully, you who goto govern or deplore, judgingor not judging, in all events undone.The riders of our times left notes behindof intrigues high and low; one sings of love, another of the shredding of a document...He scans these tales of power - screwed up, corrupt, infolded, though I would not have it so.It was the things the women saidfair mazed our Jim; contrary shockscrazed him as they do with rats.First they taught him sensitivity, to choponions very fine and cry, prioritisethe lady of his life. He got the knack.Applause! Then she whose absence still definesthese screwey situations, left to flame itwith his pal Bill. Liveforfriends, get in touchwith your distress. But soon enoughhis distresses got in touch with him -a right good kicking filled him in.His bruises were stupendous; in diverse bedshe was rewarded, sundry titbits showered on him.Then Jenny came from Aberdeen to say Enough. Binge-time is over, the cheese is moved.Worh, discipline, avoiding dread diseases will be the key-notes ofthe 90s.Without political understandingthere is only pain - go sniffit out.Certitude o f the educators, high groundof the women, tests of the high heid vins! Quivering, ardent - a rapier, a whippet,as easily broken - she raps him on the chest: Now you mustforgetyourfeelings.Sod this for a game of mazes. He resigns.On his back for days, pinky feet in the air.What you doing, Jim? Minding the ceiling, and its bars...22/ IW XVTAV.VC.S©
￼ShetlandHe sailed for Shedand, very near the edge, to bog & cliff & a celibate friend.She did her helpless best by him.He climbed all day and failed to fall.Light-hoarding stars above her bed,a full moon on the wall - he wanted to be dead, and badly. A mortal sin, she said, I tried it.Well, she was Catholic but that stuck.No way out but up. At the cruxyhe clutched into the chimney’s heart and heaved...He taped his knuckles, she poured the wine.Only reflected light this tenderness, but stillthat night they lay like pardoned thieves - baffled, eased, beside her moon, beneath her paper stars.24
￼About TessShe cocks her head, considersanother country, you. Smoke infiltrates your throat. The rasp that says you’re not dead yetis the trigger of seductions.‘And do you evervfishe enquires,‘act on your irresolution?’T h e bar’s de-stabilised, you colonize each other as folkies sing of Nicaragua.‘All right,’ one hand on hers, the other grips your car keys, ‘Why not?’There are reasons, but they melt like wax.Relax. Tonight you cross the border.You cast huge shadows as you get into the car./' A \ V ^t25
￼lLIn the MorningThe white cat at the window knows being composed around itself.Two mechanics lean over my car; today’s composed around what goes and what does not —New points, son, condenser'sgone. The philosophical one borrows a smoke, pokes the engine, spak^s ofMaya, the VeilofIllusion.Stuff and nonsense! This no-start’sstuff enough - No problem, a tenner -that’s the nonsense. Make it five?Money’s real too, there should bemore poems about money. Six and it’s done.This is not counterfeit. You’re on.In the AfternoonSo get cracking, hand me back my life-enhancing cigarette!That Veil: rend it as you will, nothing’s hung behind. Is she not beautiful, tranced in the doorway? In her breathed warm breath there is no other.O f course I’m scared - to love and risk it while todaygoes up in smoke! Go, rollone of your own. My car goes, our hearts ease off the brakes -We’re jn a spin somewherethe white cat at the window knows.Annie32
￼GulfNothing is missing, said sheon Cairn Gorm, world turns and we turn with it, not losing touch.I'll always loveyou and butIn the Gulfa frigate lowered its defensive screen for a chat —men were blown away.Sorrypal, I didnVmean... The plane flew back to base in some confusion.Soon she did too.M en yearn, metal yawns, verses implode memory and daily news. Between I & I the holy wars elide; between us rose words - lovely, direct, misguided,like love, an Exocet.
￼Annie, in NovemberA last pibroch in South QiteettsferryEnough fourteen-bar compressed & gurgling pibrochs for you, Annie, whoever you were(I mythed you). There are affairsmore pressing than love, say they who have it.So look around. The satellite disc shines on the new deli; library hours are cut; my neighbour’s roof leaks into mine(would we were separate, or one)...The Chancellor parks his belly on TV, proclaims Auld Scotia is a bag of wind squeezed in History’s oxter. Behind my town the fields are burning, it is time to leave.Rush hour. The trucks point North and whine the wild notes, the low sun splitsthe Road Bridge like a reed.
￼Ruth SaysThis is not passion, but with pleasureI see you note how well I amundressed in black. Clear sight shows our age, lines curved around the mouth like brackets, as though we smileas an aside (as though desire were a little joke we like to tellfrom time to time).We are not in love, we are not drowning in needy dreams, so we may lay down our weary arms, unconfusedby fate and feeling; I am composedas we surrender, eyes wide open even as they close.
￼Covert ActionBeneath the coverlet the President’s mind is acting up; he dreamshe is the President, which meanshe is responsible. For what? The lotof The Free World & dirty doings without number such as haunted the Macbeths. Pick one:Jungle, clearing, hut. D oor’s kicked down/ bullets fan the air; the wife, the son^,the daughter, redden and fold. Rocksdrop from their hands. Yup, guerillas!The Peace Force torch the lot, exit right up the sleeve of the star-spangled night...To pay for this he must raise taxes!He sweats, fumbles for light. Dreamed I wus the President, he tells his wife.You are, dear, you are. She sleepsand sees the Nobel Prize for Peacecrowning hubby’s noble head.His pyjamas cling, the nightlight flickers,Old Glory stirs upon the wall. Aw', who among us lacks his Banquo? Pay the First Murderer,let the drunken Security weep, for all the screw-ups check in here. Who screams? Who knocks?Mr President - it would make one mad, if not already
￼Young AmericanI sleep, I don’t, she listedall the heart-crimes I’ve committed. Cover-ups, plots, double-cross, betrayalin diverse jungles —truths most economical swooped from her throat. W orse,wheeling in her nightdressshe released her lovers’ names.Her words cling, burnlike our modern Nessus shirtf, napalm. Worst,when I wake there is no angryyoung American at my side. Men cry but are not cooled, just terrified;the imperial wingsstill burst above my head, within.
￼FishingHe may love her whenhe does not say ‘I love you’ thenhang on her reply. Whodoes not go fishingwith such lines? Across the livingroom her wrist flicks, the hook digs in.In the kitchen heis floundering - who knows when to cut the line? He twists the tap and sees down to the bottom.He could leave coffee where she sits, smile, say nothing, driftinto the garden...She crochets steadily, taking him in.40"1 <1
￼D, in a Checked ShirtI’ve chopped all dayand stacked my pile. Father taught me no one else was good enough -little wonder Imust work till I bleed, boptill I drop at local dances.I can split a match with a woodsman’s axe and have no lasting lovers.The way I roll my sleeves, that final tuck’s my father; the shirt is yoursas I am mine - I’ve taken every risk but that. Father told me:give up nothing. So I don’twhen I undress; you saw my eyes when you asked me to unbutton more.No can do. Your shirt is wringing but I like sweating meas you did. My body’s perfect,my skin|| tight as a drum,nothing rattles me -The perfect barbarian with a PhDj aches and lies down again, alone.How that single candle spits and yearns! Why should you call? The axe is bedded in the log. I have a winter’s burning.
￼The Maid & I‘At this stage, I work must closely with theMaid' New York composer -j\|rO g c b T C SIt’s nothing personal when she slips inat half-dawn, half-dusk, any driftingtime of day, to make mere solitude complete. That’s how come we get onso well, so long. You smile, you pictureblack seamed stockings, white muslin crown on hair that’s poised to be let down? No,she is not Naughty Lola -no/Mrs Mopp! With us it isimportunate to talk or stare;touch is right out. This fortunateproximity is all we share.She has arrived.You are in the backroom,by the Steinway, fiddling with the Blues.You hear her humming as she movesamong the papers and abandoned meals, clearing up the ashtrays, scripts and coffee cups,the litter of aloneness. Redeeming fingers touch your old scores lightly, as if it were yourselfshe dusts and settles on the shelf. Praise the maid who sets out flowers and white cloudswhere you might see them and be glad!The ha^ie would be total were it not for her.Now she is singing an old refrain you can’t quite...The skyis pale, washed clean by rain, hung up against the evening.As you attend, a melody floatsthrough apartment walls so intimatelyit is as though you quote yourself -debris is sorted, orderis invented or restored.Now she is done. You will work on alonebut that’s all right. Grace must have its means. She flicks the light on as she leaves.
￼Wallace Stevens in East FifeIf it is anywhere, it must be everywhere - the mind stumbles after the divinefinding nowhere to halt or grip.It must be the bush and the wind that wrassles it,the invisible shook by the visible,the howl shaken from wind by telephone lines.It must be speech on the phone and the silence that resumesand speech resuming that conversation between speech and silence which soshook Sam B., discerning howl in music, music in the throat of howl.It must be anytime and at all times, in the living man and the dead,in the greatcoat stumbling on the coast,in the grey coast stumbling through the head.
￼A North Sea Twist-ofTI got oiled on my last night on-shore, recalling lovers thrown overshoulders like peel so we could readthe initial of the one we shoulda married or eaten whole... These drastic shifts caught up wi me; if I’d worked todayI woulda crushed my hands.So I’ve arranged things so I can’t, wrote off fifty grand’s machinery. It has long been my ambitionto make a major blunder;now I’ve succeeded, for today at least. The shaft is plugged, it’ll take days more to extract the cock-up from the core.#Too much was going down.We grouped like para-medics rounda cardiac arrest to boltanother section to our mile-long probe.I did it then. Som e suspect, nane sawt+wt flick of the wrist. We swarmedin oilskins around catastrophe, pumped down urgent cooling mud, muttered soothingangry words, Come on beauty, donVbreakoffnow...Too late.The twist-off was complete.We shrugged, separated, hurtby our incompetence, glad of the break.
￼I need the money, I need the work,I need the green grease on my palms. These are the first and last,the fast realities that let us roarto vanishing-point on our machines.But there are times I canna watchthe whining, blurry revolutionsscrew the planet and ourselves as we shudder into pay-dirt. Yet I’m convinced I need the money, so I do.*We can’t work till the technicians come. Could stay on, doing nothing on half-pay, skimming girlie m ags... I’ll pass,chopper out and lie for days somewhere, a long-abandoned spanner in the grass, rusting, unadjustable.She phone7frae Ullapool last night, thick with the cold, or maybe she wis gre^tin, I never will dare ask.These needs that grow...It was fun once, nowI’ve packed my gear - let’s go.Boom-time’s over and we aa got shafted.
￼Bagatelle DreamsA Canadian rock star has 'a had case offlu ’TRACK AMy doctor said I have nervous exhaustion. This must be why I’m water-skiingon my back along a blue canal.The wake fans out. I cannot seewhat’s coming but there is no fear,all is blue rush and surrender.Bless the doctors for this rideof unexamined joy! My nerves are young in summer; above, the boat’s exhaust makes temporary clouds...TRACK B1 need a holiday, this m ust be whyI’m side-stepping the concrete bagatelle of Yonge Street’s high arcade.Muggers? No fear! I’m wearing elbow-length gauntlets, my blue plexi-glass diver’s helmet - Iout-weird everyone here. When the steel ball thunders, I wrap around it,waving goodbye. I am being rolled head-first towards m ore...FIRST MIXThe doctor said I need a nervous holiday.This must be why I’m back skiinghigh on a street canal, young fansin my wake. I’m wearing elbow-length muggers and unexamined joy - doctoring the weird!All is Blues rush and plexi, a bit mixed.No fear yet —thunder is a blessing,the boat steals the gauntlet.My nerves are rapping, temporarily exhausting the clouds...
￼S I D E - T R A C K (second mix)Wake, wake. This is your head doctor. We must be concrete now. No rush,no fear. Exhausting to step from dreams into another blessed arcade?You get so mixed. There areno muggers, no bagatelles. Wakingis temporary? Balls! You need a summer holiday from plexi-fans. Blue Gauntlet, believe me these pills will see you examining the clouds.FINAL MIXIs this concrete, or unexamined dream?A plexi-question! Exhaust it in surrender. I can’t wear waking, my head skis oK\the high canals. Fear is at elbow-length - will doctor turn mugger, or wavediverse gauntlets? Thunderous nerves! The Neil Young fans are singing‘0 Steel Summer Cloudsj‘* I as they carry me wavingto the Arcadian ball...
￼/Sunk sloop John B., I have to talk at you/seeing you around no more. (Slid offthe bridge, waved not.) Give me your duedeaf ear & pardon, who hassled audience with Yeats before you was halfways great.Them dislocations still appeal - appallinghigh-minded & randy, compulsive chaser, awful and true. Suffered for it too -booming out & cringing in,rampant & trembling for thirty years. Resigned great shade, those ways are out:we dream o f reputation, and we fall in line.Well-mannered, discreet, soberlypolishing the obvious —Are thesefolks for real?you enquire. Who live by the word must beready to die by it. Else not serious people.I don’t want be badly & cracked! But that’s the deal, But...for this Dream Song form, John, I need more lines -Thanks. Art, decency, sanity - can’t square it?Loopy Cal, Mr Lowell toyou, scampered undermy tree all afternoon, throwing up sticks. We laughed, werebrieflyhappy(5unmarked. Werenotallsobad.Therewereothers honed for the chop? Oneclaimed dying was an art,did it so badly shefinally succeeded. And succeeded.And your fearful double Henry, sunk with his gripes & lust & glass? Yet raged & weptat McCarthy, the dying children in Delhi.And deluded Delmore, Anne who tolled too early -All you crazy bad and great: was Serious People, pal.Were you still with us I could not breathe, you being too much. Brow-beater -tearful, fearful, loyal & all - I take my leave. My times you urge and warn and flashdark lightning exact. I commit you & salute one friend of timing wayward, absolute.Homage to Master Berryman60
￼Mexico‘Dona Barbara,que devora a los hombres'In the truck she let the Octopusopen her shirt, also the blonde divorcee’s - it was her divethrough dark heat, she could not rise till everything was lifted from her. She had kept herself apart for years, virtuous, no affairs with lecturersas she surveyed the glitteringsurface and swell of Yanqui power.Night rose round her and she laughed, appalled, assenting as he grippedthe blonde heads back, rinsed mouthswith beer and marijuana. Out the window her hand spread, released wallet and I.D. What a burden righteousness becomes!The divorcee peeled mangos with her nails, licked dark fingers one by one before inserting them beneath her skirt.Cooler up front with the driverwho drank white rum and kissed her eyes while he spoke poetry about the moon flowering over Vera Cruz, the shackwhere she could stay, indebted, in roses, good and chattel like his countryto the Yanqui dollar. Headlightsskewered the jungle, her eyes streamed.He spoke beautifully but was gentle-souled, was not the Octopus who devoured gringa.She buttoned her shirt and clambered back. The divorcee lay unconscious on the sacks, graceless, released. What had passed here? The Octopus shrugged. Self-respecthad kept her on the surface all these years, buoyed up by her critique - timeto meet what lay beneath.