￼AJ¥IE, VISITIFGI went into your housewhile you were away, I thoughtso this is his chair, this is his cat, here are the trainers he wears.I sat in the chair and stroked the cat. I sat on the cat and examined the shoes:you'd broken a lace and re-tied it -We've all tried that and it seldom fails to fail, and love like your catis tough and wails when sat on or scared -This foolishness won't recur.When you get home, I'll have gone running miles from here; catch meif you're fit, if I tire, if we dare.t
￼AH5IE, 15 SPRIIGI'll say this much and once only: life is not a dream. The dreamers who say so never loved you; they were misinformed who never laid a finger on your skin. As you wake in Springthe fuzz on the pussy willowand the willow itself are one.There is nothing out of focus here.The sun on our shoulders blooms, passes,but what more would we ask of light?What is seen, is; the eyes have it.Now the sheen on the chestnutand the chestnut itselfembrace in her hair - there is no further waking.
￼AFFIE, IF THE MDRFIFG£0,The white cat at the window knowsbeing ever composed around itself.Two mechanics lean over my car;today's composed around what goesand what does not - New points, son, condenser's gone. The philosophical one borrows a smoke, pokes the engine,speaks of Maya, the Veil of Illusion. Stuff and nonsense! This no-start'sstuff enough - No problem, a tenner - that's the nonsense. Make it five? Money's real too, there should bemore poems about money. Six and it's done. The world's not counterfeit. You're on.Anoit , in Hht ?A rnee..')So get cracking, hand me backmy life-enhancing cigarette!That Veil: rend it as you will, nothing's hung behind - yet isn't she beautiful, tranced in the doorway?In her breathed warm breaththere is no other.Of course I'm scared - to loveand risk that word, when today's going up in smoke! Go, rollone of your own. My car shakes, our hearts take leaps and bounds - we're going on a spin somewhere the white cat at the window knows./
￼ASFIE, LATEREnough fourteen-bar compressed & gurgling pibrochs to you, Annie, whoever you were before (I mythed you). There are affairsmore pressing than lave, say they who have it.In my town the bookie's gone up-market,we've opened a deli, cut library hoursbut still my neighbour's roof leaks into mine. Would we were seperate, or one ...The Chancellor parks his belly on TV,praises the economy, burps; Auld Scotiais a bag of wind in History's oxter,endlessly lamenting. Time to leave, leave off orRush hour. The trucks point forth and whine, the low sun splits the Road Bridge like a reed.- Stay to squeeze out notes, wilder than before.