￼BluebellsBut then her name, coming to her avertedAnd more than waist-deep in the ground’s embrace, How queer it sounded, like screaming swallows, Like bats hurting her ears. Still, she turnedAnd lifted her face to the rim of beech-lightAnd the lea^sieved sky. And again her nameCame down the slopes to her, tugging like grief With little cries. So she was drawn. The blue groundLet go of her in a white furrow and where She had entered at the horseshoe’s opening Now she began in earnest her long haul Against the streams, ascending slowly byDegrees of blue under the cavernous light,A floppy corpse of flowers on her left armWith midnight hair, with blue dark thoughts, with white Uprooted feet. Standing in the shallows,Black to the waist, cradling the lolling doll, She had no sight nor sound of her lost name. Her bluebell lips, smiling at nobody, Clouded the cold air with a breath of roots.
￼Autumn Lady’s TressesIn late summer the Lady’s Tresses Spiral to light leafless and standAlmost as bare rods. But flowers Proceed upwards by an upbraiding or as When the wind fraysThe scything edge of a wave. Thyrsus,Snake of ivy. FlowersWithout energy of colour, at the least remove From the stem’s green. Torch-flower, Faintlight, but prized by findersAs much as wentletraps The white unicornThe winding stairway shell.Autumn CrocusesThe naked boys, entering the light,Their root-whiteness suffuses upwards with a colour. Then, So long as they hold the sun’s eye,Light through and through and barely tethered,They stand hovering. They dieWhen they empty of sun, sleevesOf their life lie on the soil crumpling.40/