￼effit* nmi/'At this stage, I mark must closely with the A la id 'NewYorkcomposer^ 6 | j-fo SusCCJIt’s nothing personal when she slips inat half-dawn, half-dusk, any driftingtime of day, to make mere solitude complete. That’s how come we get onso well, so long. You smile, you pictureblack seamed stockings, white muslin crown on hair that’s poised to be let down? No,she is not Naughty Lola -no^Mrs iMopp! With us it isimportunate to talk or stare;touch is right out. This fortunateproximity is all we share.She has arrived.You are in the backroom,by the Steinway, fiddling with the Blues.You hear her humming as she movesamong the papers and abandoned meals, clearing up the ashtrays, scripts and coffee cups,the litter of aloneness. Redeeming fingers touch your old scores lightly, as if it were yourselfshe dusts and settles on the shelf. Praise the maid who sets out flowers and white cloudswhere you might see them and be glad!The htpijfcAvould be total were it not for her.The Maid & INow she is singing an old refrain you can’t quite...The skyis pale, washed clean by rain, hung up against the evening.As you attend, a melody floatsthrough apartment walls so intimatelyit is as though you quote yourself -debris is sorted, orderis invented or restored.Now she is done. You will work on alonebut that’s all right. Grace must have its means. She flicks the light on as she leaves.48
￼Wallace Stevens in East FifeIf it is anywhere, it must be everywhere - the mind stumbles after the divinefinding nowhere to halt or grip.It must be the bush and the wind that wrassles it,the invisible shook by the visible,the howl shaken from wind by telephone lines.It must be speech on the phone and the silence that resumesand speech resuming that conversation between speech and silence which soshook Sam B., discerning howl in music, music in the throat of howl.It must be anytime and at all times, in the living man and the dead,in the greatcoat stumbling on the coast,in the grey coast stumbling through the head.
￼A North Sea Twist-ofTI got oiled on my last night on-shore, recalling lovers thrown overshoulders like peel so we could readthe initial of the one we shoulda married or eaten whole...These drastic shifts caught up wi me; if I’d worked todayI woulda crushed my hands.So I’ve arranged things so I can’t, wrote off fifty grand’s machinery. It has long been my ambitionto make a major blunder;now I’ve succeeded, for today at least. The shaft is plugged, it’ll take days more to extract the cock-up from the core.#Too much was going down.We grouped like para-medics rounda cardiac arrest to boltanother section to our mile-long probe.I did it then. Some suspect, nane saw t^^flick of the wrist. We swarmedin oilskins around catastrophe, pumped down urgent cooling mud, muttered soothingangry words, Come on beauty, donVbreakoffnow...Too late.The twist-off was complete.We shrugged, separated, hurtby our incompetence, glad of the break.
￼I need the money, I need the work,I need the green grease on my palms. These are the first and last,the fast realities that let us roarto vanishing-point on our machines.But there are times I canna watchthe whining, blurry revolutionsscrew the planet and ourselves as we shudder into pay-dirt. Yet I’m convinced I need the money, so I do.#We can’t work till the technicians come. Could stay on, doing nothing on half-pay, skimming girlie mags...I’ll pass,chopper out and lie for days somewhere, a long-abandoned spanner in the grass, rusting, unadjustable.She phone frae Ullapool last night, thick with the cold, or maybe sheThese needs that grow...It was fun once, nowI’ve packed my gear - let’s go.Boom-time’s over and we aa got shafted.
￼Bagatelle DreamsA Canadian rock star has ‘a had case offlu ’TRACK AMy doctor said I have nervous exhaustion. This must be why I’m water-skiingon my back along a blue canal.The wake fans out. I cannot seewhat’s coming but there is no fear,all is blue rush and surrender.Bless the doctors for this rideof unexamined joy! My nerves are young in summer; above, the boat’s exhaust makes temporary clouds...TRACK BI need a holiday, this must be whyI’m side-stepping the concrete bagatelle of Yonge Street’s high arcade.Muggers? No fear! I’m wearing elbow-length gauntlets, my blue plexi-glass diver’s helmet —Iout-weird everyone here. When the steel ball thunders, I wrap around it,waving goodbye. I am being rolled head-first towards m ore...FIRST MIXThe doctor said I need a nervous holiday.This must be why I’m back skiinghigh on a street canal, young fansin my wake. I’m wearing elbow-length muggers and unexamined joy - doctoring the weird!All is Blues rush and plexi, a bit mixed.No fear yet - thunder is a blessing,the boat steals the gauntlet.My nerves are rapping, temporarilyexhausting the clouds...**/52
￼SIDE-TRACK (second mix)Wake, wake. This is your head doctor. We must be concrete now. No rush,no fear. Exhausting to step from dreams into another blessed arcade?You get so mixed. There areno muggers, no bagatelles. Wakingis temporary? Balls! You need a summer holiday from plexi-fans. Blue Gauntlet, believe me these pills will see you examining the clouds.FINAL MIXIs this concrete, or unexamined dream? A plexi-question! Exhaust it in surrender. I can’t wear waking, my head skis 0/the high canals. Fear is at elbow-length - will doctor turn mugger, or wavediverse gaundets? Thunderous nerves! The Neil Young fans are singing‘0 Steel Summer Clouds[ ^as they carry me waving to the Arcadian ball...
￼In an Italian FieldIn the dazzling world the peasants are working. With bowed heads and backs they drag in line their dark comb through a field of corn.They will never get rich. They will never livein bought houses. Their lives will remainobscure as their dialect, secret as the women’s hair.Bent as their sickles they shuffle on.One sings, another mops her brow.At each row’s end they pass the jug around,at noon chew bread, spit, then sit for an hour beneath the poplar trees and silently rise up again...No wonder we feel flimsy,returning to our books. The pages blur, letters start to wave before our eyes -we are unfocused by the glare outsidewhere a sickle flashes at the margin of a field, its shape unchanging as the great stalks yield.54
￼Aide MemoireBeing eighteen,light-headed, hormonal, daft, there is much to be said for it. I said it at lengthon the Fife coast that winter.I donned my Doric cap,took a stiff whisky,walked out the door.In town the lights were blazing but no one was at home.What of the white lineI toed by the sea?The wind blew apartthe clouds round the moon and I stepped through.
￼The House-Builder VariationsA workshop - principal materials:saw, drill, rule, nails, a plain deal tableUnemployed? Growing rusty? You wanta house that is unique - home in on this!Here’s your drill, the hammer-action for concrete, this is your saw, your rule, your plain deal table. These are the trees. The compassionate State awards you with a gross of nails.Such are your true materials. Confused?You want to shelve it for today? Believe me,if you pass on children you must make something of your own, or live aloner than alone.A better deal! Unemployed, not unique,this was his drill: plane it true,hammer the State, nail it to a tree.But the old saws were rusty, the rulewas bent, he made nothing at the table.(He could have said it in spades, butspades are disallowed materials - you think association’s free?) What frame could housesuch passion? It must be concrete, too gross to shelve. Confused, alone, he passes on today.Concrete poems? A house of cards, shuffle them as you will! Deal anyway. What was it she saw that made the trees seem jungular today? (Nothing’s disallowed, but old drills are bentas is the State and its materials.)As a rule, truth’s a shelf that takes unique confusion to nail it to the wall. Unemployment takes a hammering today as she sits making passionate childrenin her swaying home high in the trees.56
￼Here’s what I saw when I tookthat hammering: alone is gross.Let us live in free association, where is not material. Plain dealing! Believe me (though I am swaying), a bent rule is unique. We shallbe shelf-employed! Today is concrete passion. Nail down this truth:I love you though the drill be rustyand the state confused.
￼JapanA Romance o f Two Empires‘No empire in debt has ever lasted long’ - gore vidalLove fell on you, twice.The world turned white. You vanished, you became a shadow on the wall.The war ended.You came back from the dead, speaking our language, meaning business. This time you would produce the goods.We met her on timeat the American movie. We sat through it twicetill we could make it better.Then we kissed and took her home. None o f us had anything to loseand after allwe made it cheaper and we made it best.Now your round e)>esflicker when we stir. You kiss our neck,we like that. Energetically, we takeyou again. You try hard to please. You do. You will.For the most partour protests are conventional as we subside; arms are weak when we are in your debt.And though we sulk, remembering our time of power, for the most partwe were tired of Empire.58
￼This is the reconstruction, our royal we need not be discussed.You will accept reversal in good time.Aspire to our eyes and bea credit. You were tiredand we need each other, ofcourse we do. This is only the old order renewed.It will be a reliefto be so in love,to be colonised in turn, repentand loose the burden of our power.Here in the shadow of our master’s kimono we bite our fingernails and aspire.
￼Homage to Master BerrymanSunk sloop John B., I have to talk at you^seeing you around no more. (Slid offthe bridge, waved not.) Give me your duedeaf ear & pardon, who hassled audience with Yeats before you was halfways great.high-minded & randy, compulsive chaser, awful and true. Suffered for it too -booming out & cringing in,rampant & trembling for thirty years. Resigned great shade, those ways are out:Well-mannered, discreet, soberlypolishing the obvious —Are thesefolks for real?you enquire. Who live by the word must beready to die by it. Else not serious people.I don’t want be badly & cracked! But that's the deal, But...for this Dream Song form, John, I need more lines -Thanks. Art, decency, sanity - can’t square it?Loopy Cal, Mr Lowell toyou, scampered undermy tree all afternoon, throwing up sticks. We laughed, werebrieflyhappy(5unmarked. Werenotallsobad.Therewereothers honed for the chop? OneThem dislocations still appeal - appallingwe dream of reputation, and we fall in line.claimed dying was an art,did it so badly shefinally succeeded. And succeeded,And your fearful double Henry, sunk with his gripes & lust & glass? Yet raged & weptat McCarthy, the dying children in Delhi.And deluded Delmore, Anne who tolled too early — All you crazy bad and great: wus Serious People, pal.Were you still with us I could not breathe, you being too much. Brow-beater — tearful, fearful, loyal & all - I take my leave. My times you urge and warn and flashdark lightning exact. I commit you & salute one friend of timing wayward, absolute.60
￼Mexico‘Dona Barbara, que devora a los hombres ’In the truck she let the Octopus open her shirt, also the blonde divorcee’s - it was her divethrough dark heat, she could not rise till everything was lifted from her. She had kept herself apart for years, virtuous, no affairs with lecturersas she surveyed the glitteringsurface and swell of Yanqui power.Night rose round her and she laughed, appalled, assenting as he grippedthe blonde heads back, rinsed mouthswith beer and marijuana. Out the window her hand spread, released wallet and I.D. What a burden righteousness becomes! The divorcee peeled mangofc with her nails, licked dark fingers one by one before inserting them beneath her skirt.Cooler up front with the driverwho drank white rum and kissed her eyes while he spoke poetry about the moon flowering over Vera Cruz, the shackwhere she could stay, indebted, in roses, good and chattel like his countryto the Yanqui dollar. Headlightsskewered the jungle, her eyes streamed.He spoke beautifully but was gentle-souled, was not the Octopus who devoured gringa. She buttoned her shirt and clambered back. The divorcee lay unconscious on the sacks, graceless, released. What had passed here? The Octopus shrugged. Self-respecthad kept her on the surface all these years, buoyed up by her critique - timeto meet what lay beneath.
￼There was sand, water, men in a circle, some ceremony she could not masternor deconstruct away. One shotwhite arrows at the moon and felltwitching, ecstatic. The Octopus took peyote, his tongues thrust mush into her mouth;she nodded, choked, tore off her shirt and spun the world round her jittery hips as though it were a hula-hoop and shea child in her Mid-West backyard.None looked her way, he swam,she could still run for it.He found her dreaming on the sand,arrow in her fist. Crossing himself,Dona Barbara, he took her to the truck. Conscious and unconscious breasts compared were found wanting. Leeched upon,she strained to drain into his mouth;her inverted nipple hurt, swelled,would not come free. Another town,she stumbled out for beer and tacos -no shirt, no money, still she knewblonde hair, white skin would see her through, and despaired. How may power resignfrom its high place? This nervy diver had come teetering to the edge...At the end there was a room. Men sleeping stirred in their hammocks when she plunged to meet the Octopus in the tightening net. They grappled, clasped, fought limb to limb, snapped beak to beak till in the meshhe suckered the Barbarian. She clasped the arrow, he rose shouting - puddled, ecstatic,she drifted while he lay harpooned.Then there were many hands, some kind.62
￼They carried her out at dawn,trembling, bloody, white as salt.A bus pulled up, she gripped her blanket then rose and in the loving tongueshe mastered her first lie.*Her thumb on the inside of my arm still lightly stroked the vein.We lay in her hammock strung above the porch, Toronto, Little Italy;the old insomniac next doorpruned tomatoes in the dark and hummed his exile, it would soon be day.‘But that was in another countryand besides, the hombre’s dead.'I held her, sweating, knowing she’d said all that she would say.