￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:01 p m t e j e 3 8The Seashore HouseThe sound of wavescomes creeping through the houseto stroke the sullen watersof the garden, and my body,like a stone, beside the garden, begging, begging to be left untouched, because she’s bruising me:may all her slow attemptsat getting close to mefly off into the sound of waveslike birds with rock-grey wings!I lie as still as someonebalancing a bowl of fruitor rabbits on their head.Beside the pond my dogis gnawing bonesthat crawl with ants,and every now and then he stops to rub his lips and nosealong the grassthat closes over him.This afternoon acheslike a bell,the sea is slow,and if you come and look for me beside the pool of melted water you will find a stoneas cold and passionless as silk.Silk is the liquid stonemy mother wore,I see it slipping, slipping, like a skin;I wear a scarf myself sometimes, I know, to hide the scarmy mother madeI do not want to show :^my mother is afraid of love
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:02 pm E0aje 39 -and I, her silver-skinnedburnt only daughter -tissue-head, peculiar, queen of pain -I cry for kisses like she cries for shame. The sound of wavescomes creeping through the house.