￼The Ballad Singer at the Pardon of St Anne(from Corbiere)IBlessed the barren dunes,Stark nude like the sea -And the chapel of Anne-of-Palud Is crude, too, and holy,O f St Anne, the Good Gossip, A granny for young JesusIn rotting oak beneath a rich Cope... richer than Croesus.Beside her, the Virgin is small - Fragile distaff, waiting for Angelus - And St Joseph, upstaged, in his niche Shoves his candle at us.It’s H er Pardon - fun and gam es and Mystery - the stubble’s hopping with fleas - Anne, Sainted Ointment, cure-allFor mothers-in-law, and husband’s ease.From the parishes round about,From Plougastel and Loc-Trudy, They’ve arrived already, camping out Three nights, three days, up till Monday.Three days, three nights, the salt-marsh blares With music - the rite’s traditional -Heavenly choir and singing drunks - Beginneth the SACRED CANTICLE.II0 M other, carved out with a chopper From oak heart, hard and good,Your gold robe hides a solid Breton Soul, all one piece, honest wood.
￼l 62Green crone with a used-up face, Boulder under the flood,Fretted by tears o f love,Parched by tears o f blood.You, whose shrivelled breasts Were plumped again, to carry A purposeful virginity -The Virgin Mary.Proud housekeeper, mistress and servant, Related to the Almighty,The poor are pleased to talk to youFor you answer them politely.A wand for the blind, and crutchesFor cripples, arms for the new-born,A mother for Madame your Daughter - You’ve adopted all the forlorn.Blossom of new maidenhead! Fruit o f wife’s swollen udder! Garden of rest for the widow! District Nurse for the widower!Joachim’s Arch! O Ancestress! Four-leaf clover! Misdetoe bough! Medallion with a rubbed-out face! Horeb! Jesse’s Rod! Our way!You kept the Fire inAnd went on with your knittingAs darkness came down round your lap Where the Child was sitting.You were there, the one who could cope, Making garments in Bethlehem,Still there, stitching the shroud, Grief-stunned in Jerusalem.I11
￼Your face is a wrinkled mapO f crosses - your hair white as linen — Keep from pedantic evil eyesT h e cots o f our grandchildren.The born, the not-yet born,Bring on, and keep them well,And smuggle water from your tears When God isn’t looking, to Hell.Take back little childrenIn white nightgowns, fading away, And summon the old who are bored T o the everlasting Sunday.O growl! The Virgin’s Dragon! Keep the crib safe and secure, And keep bitching at JosephT o sweep round the front door.Pity the girl in the family wayAnd the small boy lost on the road - If anyone throws a stoneChange it into bread.Beacon on sea and on land,Harbour, stars over heath,Good Lady, through tempest, through You beckon towards a good death.Humble; no star at your feet - Humble and strong to save -Your veil in the clouds means peril, Pale halo over the wave.Those whose lives are a mess- Begging pardon - sunk in the booze Show them the steeple and clock,The road back to the house.
￼6364Fire the Christians hereaboutsWith your own zeal, gentle and chaste, And gather your simples, Wise Woman, To soothe the homed beast.Be an example to housewives O f work and fecundity -And say hullo to our relations Already in eternity.We’ll line up an army of candles - Spermaceti - the best - all the way Round your chapel. We’ll celebrate Low mass at the break of day.Keep our hearths safeFrom spells and folk who are spiteful... We’ll give you at EasterFlax, a whole distaff-full.If our bodies stink on earthYour grace is a bath for our good: Shower on us in this graveyardYour wholesome odour of sainthood.Till next year, then. Here’s your candle, (Three half-crowns it’s cost me). Respects to Madame the Virgin,Not forgetting the Holy Trinity.IllAnd the faithful, in penitent nightshirts, - St Anne, have pity, please -Drag themselves round the church Three times, on their knees.And go on to drink the waters, Miraculous now, from the hole Where scabby Jobs have bathed... Your faith has made you whole.
￼Down there they hold their suppers, The wretched, Jesus’s brethren, And you won’t see any miracles,But real holes: Put your finger in ...On their hurdles they look like saints, With scarlet nimbuses, each oneAn owner of extensive soresLike rubies glinting in the sun.A barking man with ricketsJust can’t stop his arm-stump’s twitch -Can’t help elbowing the epileptic Having a fit in the same ditch.By a tree-trunk, misdetoe-bitten,Stands a man with an ulcer that bites - And a mother and daughter are dancing Choreography by St Vitus.A father heats up a poulticeFor a small son who’s not thriving: A boy owes a lot to his father - The chancre earns their living.There’s an idiot since he was born, An angel-blasted simpleton, Ecstatic in his innocence -The simple are close to heaven.Watch, passer-by, all passes...but The idiot’s stare is stone and firm - He must be in a state of grace,For grace is outside time.Among the crowd after evensong, When the holy water’s sprayed us, A corpse sticks out, alive, a long Leper... relic of the crusaders.
￼65 66Then those who the kings of France Used to cure with a touch -Since France has cut off her kings, Their God’s cut his mercy by that much.Put something into their bowls - All our forefathers carried it,The Fleur-de-Lys of King’s Evil Which these are chosen to inherit.Miserere then for the junketingsOf these dirty old outcast Bretons...But stumps can be managed like pincers And crutches are weapons.Venture among them, able-bodied, But take care to keep your fleece on - Beware o f Fingers that hook, o f legs Fixed in Kyrie Eleison.And if you’d be sight-seeing, dear, Take a look and turn back quick - From under these scraps o f ragsA scrap o f flesh might prick.They’re hunting on their own estates With Arms emblazoned on their skins! Their hands have the droit de seigneur Over anything clutched therein.Offerings heaped - of rotting meat - Heaven’s elect - with death-house features - They make themselves at home with God For surely they’re his creatures.They’re swarming in the churchyard - As if the dead mistook the Day OfJudgement, crawling out from stones That crush the limbs they drag away.
￼We’ve no right to talk - they’re sacred.It’s Adam’s sin they’re punished for.The Almighty’s Finger has marked them, The Almighty’s right be praised therefore!The scapegoats of the bellowing flock, Loaded with every sin we’re at,God works his anger off on them!The vicar of St Anne’s is fat.IVBut a palpitating note,A gasping echo in the breeze, Cuts across the grumbling drone O f this walking purgatory.Keening like a beast in pain, She stands beside the Calvary, H alf a blind beggar, as it were, No dog and only one eye. -A weather-bitten ballad-singer,Drop a halfpenny in her hatAnd she’ll do you Abaylar, Wandering Jew, Or any other old favourite.O but her song is long-drawn-out, Complaining like a thing ill-used, Like a long day with nothing to eat, So lamentable her blues.She sings just as she breathes, a bird Without a nest, with no Fine feathers, Battering blindly as she fliesRound granite God, in granite weather.She can talk, too, if that matters,As far as she can see she thinks -The main road keeps stretching before her If she gets hold of sixpence, she drinks.
￼6768A woman, oh dear yes - her skirt Is strings held together by string: Black teeth grip an empty pipe - Life is full of excellent things!Her name? Call her Misery.Got herself bom, somehow, somewhere - Somewhere, someday will be found dead - There’ll be no fuss, no one will care.If you come across her, poet, Humping her army kit-bag - Please recognise our sister, Give her a few fills of shag.You’ll see on her furrowed faceA smile crack right acrossLike splitting wood, her scaly hand Make a genuine sign of the cross.W