￼Randa11 9-36 25/3/93 12:38 am Page 20.Glad DayTake a boy. Make a man.He stands.See mother.The wilderness hasn’t harmed me.Though I spent forty days And forty nightsIn that place.I’ve brought you samples Chipped from those rocks.Take. Eat.This is my body.This is my blood.And still you tell me father It isn’t enough.The next time you both come looking for me, I shall deny you.Mont BlancStanding at your shin Looking up.The giant-killer boy Knew this thrill.A moment slung between surrender And his own power.20-e-
￼Randa11 9 -36 25/3/93 12:39 am Page 2»And I made up my mind that this would never do.jSo after think-ing a little more about it, I resolved that at any rate I would actI 4ras if the Bible were true:jthat if it were not, at all events I shouldI______________________ w . i _____t ____ be no worse off than I was before.Sunday’s ChildThey slaughtered me with the Sabbath. It was no bloody thingBut a slow reckoning,Repeated week by week.I was made to contort my limbs Into that day.They pushed my headBetween my kneesThe Earth in Fruit(for Elizabeth Siddal)Lamb with the burnished cordsWhose feminine imperative inspiredThe eyes to smoke and oil to impersonate Your beauty.Nature put the earth in fruit, Nature put your beauty there.And you think beauty can save you. I’ve seen your masters rub it out.21Until I fainted.“ 0-
￼Randa11 9-36 25/3/93 12:39 am Page 22,Art has you by the milky throatAnd you have art enough to dote on death As sacrifice.And you think nature is beautiful.