￼(£)JHE THRUSH^C^ 'Z.efV'iI sat in a mild orchard, but had no pleasure there,clutching my jaw to muffle pain I could hardly bear: toothache made my senses \irince; but suddenly I heardthe pretty thrush performing impressions, clever bird.She stretched her throat and uttered a 'Cock-a-doodle-doo', followed by the blackbird's tune and the kite's piercing mew.Two notes in combination then issued from her bill:the wren's miniature piping and the oriole's trill. Stunned by this exhibition, my torment let me be:its gnawing grip relented, and left my tooth pain-free. Off to her nest the thrush went, and I took up my pen. >*ay God send her back to me if toothache strikes/Jcr/o-K1£
￼Vestiunt silve tenera ramorum Mr*— virgulta, suis onerata pomis, ^ — canunt de celsis sedibus palumbes —carmina cunctis.Eic turtur gemit, resonat hie turdus, pangit hie priscus merulorum sonus; passer nee tacet, arripens garritualta sub ulmis.Hie leta sedit philomela frondis; longum effundit sibilum per auras sollempne, milvus trenmlaque voice[I_] aethera pulsat.Ad astra volans aquila, per agros alauda canit modulus quam plures; desursum vergit dissimili modo,r \ ) dum terram tangit.Velox impulit iugiter birundo, clangit coturnix, grajcula resultat; aves sic cuncte celebrant estivum n | undique carmen0Nulla inter aves similis est apif que talem gerit tipum castitatis nisi que Christum baiulavit alvo1) )inviolate. ^26 ^
￼^THE_ BIRDS .AND THE BEE [cmJ^Now in the woodlands every branch is softlydressed in its leaves, and bearing fruit or berries, while from their perches high among the treetopspigeons are cooing.A-Here is the crooning dove, the thrush's warbling; here is the blackbirds' well-remembered chorus; even the dunnock chirps its lowly twitterm under the elmtrees.4sHere in the leaves the nightingale is joyful,pouring her long sweet whistle on the breezes; meanwhile the kite's voice, quavering and vibrant, m creaks through the heavens.Up soars the eagle, aiming for the stars; while lower the skylark floods the fields with music, rising and swooping, plummeting to earthwardr a in her own fashion.#•Swiftly the swallow darts without alighting;quails are heard calling, jackdaws make their clamourso all the birds are celebrating summer, C P all of them singing.4=None of the birds is like the little bee, though —model for maidens, chastity's example:no, only she who once cocooned the Christ-child r a safe in her belly.
￼Iuvenilis lasciviaet amoris suspiriatam sunt delectabilia ; qu* En Rosseinos en cante.4Kec est amoris nuncia,et hec inflammat basiaet accendit incendiamei estus, que s'en vante®4Audivi sepe merulamdum movet ignis stipulam et hec pungit puellulam mil fiz desob quarante.Que durior est marmure et es habet in pectoreut hanc audit sub arbore tut est reridue ardante.Hec est avis Cupidinis, que post ictum harnndinis movet estus libidinis'ocii ocil' dum canter 28 <3- r^n-rc-d
￼who love and sigh and touch and toy . inflames the nightingale with joy: ' she has to trill and coo it.+She's love's announcer and town-crier; she lights the spark and stokes the fire; she swells the lover with desire,then boasts that he'll pursue it.4I've heard her in a leafy gladeencouraging some heated bladeto pierce a girl who was a maid — and countless times will rue it.¥A lady may be made of stone,her heart encased in bronze, not bone; but when she hears this melting tone her body burns to do it.-4The nightingale takes Cupid's part: when he's installed the teasing dartshe makes the inflammation startby wanton warblings to it. < D '
￼(£)®&3B V r^erMi ^Pulcher valet ver in silva, * *—IQ ET^S ~[/florigera tempora,quando humus fert erbarum * •— J/^opia titanica,vernat silva frondosarum ^L.^pecies virencia.C DIbi cantant tunc caterva________ Ivolucrum lustrancia,ex quarum huna plus manet2 corporis exigua,nomen clara hac robusta2 Philomela nuncupat.&Salliendo nemorosapetit alta silva diesphilomela titubando] arborum chacumina,nocte numquam cessat densaIZ Z clangere armonia.#Prolixa non rauca mittitvoce sepe sibila, plura canit incantandosaltuun prostibula, gliscit mirabilis membraludens menia carmina,40 tu parva, cur non cessas[ clangere, avicula?Estimas nunc superareJ omnes arte musica?Aut quid cum lira contempnis
￼X)r£EEANTI-NIGHTINGALE SONG^ (T^ (/ B r «Pretty Spring has dressed the woodlandsfc£tv\S with her floral artistry, —while the earth brings forth its herbage *"*>— in titanic quantity —and the leafy trees are loaded ^ (—handsomely with greenery. ©There a strolling company ofvocalists is audible,out of which one narrow-guttedlittle bird is notable,making clear in sturdy accentsthat she's called the nightingale4^In the daytime she's retiring,~I fond of shady privacy:off she tittups through the branchesto the summit of a tree;but at night she never ceases~)blaring out her melody.Her incessant, not untunefulwhistling voice is never mute,as she chants her incantationslike a woodland prostitute,puffing up her puny figureI full of music and conceit.’Will you never stop that racket,I overrated little bird?Do you think your art surpasses1 all the singing ever heard?Don't you know that other musicis quite frequently preferred1]^]^3r^
￼Ultra vires iocabunda_________1/4uctas thimfanistria, Xl,te auscultant vigilando j(Ti— . __________________ j/regalisinsignia, % I_laudat procerum caterva_______________ tuaplnracantica.Cessa, cessa fatigandolassata iam bucula,quia premia dormizantes3 clam iugiter nausia,omni ora pro quid canis_i digna ovans sidera?*Misers, infelix ilia,tam tenuis viscera,que nec tumes saciata3 opima cibaria,speras cautizando cunctisimperare gracia?Iam cessato laborando,non premitit brachia, ... te cuncti auscultant,nemo dat iuvamina nisi ipse, qui te fincxit________ U propria spiramina.*Parce vatem iam secura,conticesce, conticesce,ancxiata vires nollis,heiulare tardita,ne crepando clangita,locum tuum propera<*Ilia vero stringens paucain estate stupefactaBruma tegit nebulosamodulorum garritapro natorum gloria,32 ^-----corpus sua funera^ )
￼As you bash your tinkling cymbalsGErxxS with excessive jollitywakeful crowds of listening gentryegg you on with flattery:your eternal serenadingwins the praise of royalty. (^)Stop it, stop it, you're a nuisancesurely now you've tired your beak?When I try a little snoozing_________________ 1 on the sly, you make me sick.Must you fill up every momentwith pretentious rhetoric?krWretched, miserable birdlet,with your skinny little chest,you're not stuffed up like a gander[ which has feasted on the best:do you hope that through your warblingall will bow to your behest?Now a pause in the performance;but you're singing on the cheap:out of all who listen to you,J no one offers you a tip —only God, perhaps, who made you[ with his special workmanship.+-Have some pity on a poet:please control your nagging tongue;shut your beak, and let's have silencefrom that boring, jangling song.Save your energies for later:go off home where you belongI1But in summer, what relief! She3 gives her voice a little rest,stupefied with admirationof the offspring in her nest.And xdien winter comes, she's vanished,~1 dead beneath the freezing mist.33
￼Trinitas sancta supernaregnareque nos concedatj/per secla in aeterna. Amen.lO 6fOS_______ Jsnostra purget crimina, ut ad alta poli summiintroducat limina34ringed 1-e^ts