￼ytM,rJncS Ui?il ^Y-F 77 --p-rH5Y~•>P'OC./ '-'*.,w
￼vir<ri.MARTIN BELLCOMPLETE POEMS COMPLETE POEMSt
￼
￼MARTIN BELLCOMPLETE POEMS COMPLETE POEMS
￼
￼Copyright © Estate of Martin Bell 1988 Introduction © Peter Porter 1988ISBN: 1 85224 042 3 hardback edition 1 85224 043 1 paperback editionFirst published 1988 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.The poems from page 31 to page 131 inclusive are reprinted from Martin Bell’s Collected Poems 1937-1966 (Macmillan, 1967).All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without the prior permission of the publisher.LEGAL NOTICETypesetting by Bryan Williamson, Manchester.Printed in Great Britain byBell & Bain Limited, Glasgow, Scotland.
￼Contents) W33 El Desdichado34 A Benefit Night at the Opera35 Usumcasane as Poet Maudit36 The Enormous Comics37 Fiesta Mask38 Railway Pieces41 A Game of Royal Families42 A Prodigal Son for Volpone44 To Celebrate Eddie Cantor46 Ode to Groucho48 Headmaster: Modern Style52 Ode to Himself54 Reasons for Refusal56 Dreams of Evasion58 Winter Coming On61 The Ballad Singer at the Pardon of St Anne 69 Blind Man’s Cries71 Democracy72 Instruction for my Godson73 Letter to a Friend75 High Street, Southampton 77 Three Days79 Bell’s Elegy80 Ode to Psychoanalysis82 Manicure83 Techniques for Detente87 Zen for William Empson88 Grass, alas90 With Heads Uncovered91 David Guest92 Gabriel Peri93 Verdi at Eighty94 Requiem for Norman Cameron95 MidsummerIntroduction, Memoir and Critical NotebyPETER PORTER ,, . . . ---------------------\ >»«.<?"fe, spiccaea31 Unfriendly Flowers31 My Blue Heaven32 Lecture Notes32 Prospect 19391
￼96 Leonora97 Miss Moore on Madison Avenue 98 In Memoriam: J.B. Leishman100 From the Irregular Stanzas of Don Senilio 103 Senilio’s Distraction Song104 Senilio’s Broadcast Script108 Senilio Re-reads Baudelaire109 Senilio Remembers his Grandfather110 Senilio Passes, Singing111 Words for Senilio to Work into a Patter-song112 Senilio’s Weather Saw113 It Is the Blight Man Was Born For114 Senilio and the Moon117 Mr Hobsbaum’s Monday Evening Meeting118 With a Presentation Copy of Verses119 It Was a Violent Time120 Ultimate Anthology121 Footnote to Enright’s ‘Apocalypse’122 Couples123 Anecdote124 Dialogue125 Ponge: Tree-Trunk126 Whistling a Sober Little Tune: Sunday Lunchtime 127 Pensees for Blaise128 Axioms129 Pets132 Obsequies for Senilio135 Senilio Again136 Miaou for Senilio137 From the City of Dreadful Something140 For Good Wednesday141 To David Broomfield142 Written in January143 Tight-rope Walker144 And Welcomes Little Fishes In144 Poem for Gunter Grass about Askesis145 Poem to pay for a pair of shoes146 Variations on Francis Bacon147 Cauchemar148 And now here is the Financial News150 Rasputin Messing with the Rose Madder152 Wordsworthian/Ovidian Episde to Patricia Highsmith 154 Lament for Bing Crosby
￼LETTERS FROM CYPRUS156 158 159 159 160 161 162 162 162 163 164 165 165 166 166To the GoddessIllumination on Mockers Wish in HeatPussyPart of LamakaCyprus MonasteryQuatrain for Christine ClerihewsCricketing SongCyprus: NoonFrom Rimbaud on Qyprt& The ----------- Sleep167 168 169 169 170 171 172 173 174 174 176 177For C. in Cyprus Over-stimulation Municipal Moor Monastery Cats Accident Prone Letter to Alcohol One178In Bedroom Recollections of London London, Again, Dreams Stass’s PicturesAdam and EveKyrjeniaPyromaniacDear Peter180 181 182 183 184 185 186 187For StassNon-Mediterranean Life‘In the endless boredom of the plain’Letter to President JohnsonLetter to W.H. AudenWallace Stevens Welcomes Doctor Jung into Heaven Translating Reverdy188 189 190 190 191 192Autumnal for Reverdy‘Peret, assist me’ Hutchinson’s Collected Haiku For Pearse HutchinsonI>»Poem of CongratulationMarine Easter Poem for Wendy Refolding Ruth’s Umbrella ‘Why, Mr Lancaster’T V oo do S.
￼194 195 195 196 197 197 198 199 Joo" 201 202 202 203QuestionToMyWatchGiven to JanniceFor Horn Obbligato by Jeff Nuttall For Peter RedgroveReading a 1914-1918 Anthology Poet and SocietyFor Pasolini’s Friend205 206 207 208 208 209 209 209 210 210Reference to Thurber‘There was a bloody-minded poet’ Poem for the National Westminster PissingPlease re-apply on the dotted line Innocent FencingIncidentally in praise of Barbara Castle About BombsAlter Ego211 212 213ntrrr22, \22.2. 220 22} -224 22> 222/Will-4!ou-To Sovte.Private Seasonal GreetingsFor C. ANewLeafinaDiary:ForC. For C.. with. I suppose, gratitude PoemDream/Letter/Poem for Christine214 215 216 216 217 218The Maenads Dream(Tune: Anything Goes) Loyal AddressKilling FliesWriter’s BlockNew LitaniesInertia (Spleen) Against-Lies- A'dovj'c Ode to Education Victory of the Yobbos Solitude Is Everywhere GreenPour L’filection2o3. A'fFragments-oH&ggshellWin N/oo To Exorcise Baba Yaga29/12/77 Didactic PoemA Bad Day in the Bedsitter A Vocation Possibly_______ ‘And here I am still’\oAex titles 3oc\ \\oeS
￼Introduction, Memoir and Critical NoteWhen Martin Bell died in Leeds in the winter of 1978, he had just turned sixty years of age. He was far less well-known as a poet than he deserved to be. This claim is made regularly for writers once celebrated and thereafter neglected, when their works are reintro­ duced to the public. With Bell, it is nothing more than the plain truth. Martin Bell is one of the major poets writing in English in the second half of the century, and the fact that his work has been largely unobtainable since his death (and fugitive even in his lifetime) makestheissueofthisCompletePoemsanimportantandtimelyevent.Bell’s publishing history is singular. His first book was also his Collected Poems and his last publication. His precocity as a poet suffered an early frost due both to war service and to personal circumstances, so that his flowering came in early middle age - especially in the decade 1955 to 1965. He was one of the three poets included in volume three of the newly-established series PenguinModem Poets in 1962 (the others were George Barker and Charles Causley). The poems in this Penguin formed the basis of his hardback Collected (Macmillan, 1967). The hundred-odd pages of this book are a brilliant distillation of his talent, and, until his death, comprised his life’s work on view. He published nothing further, other than to contribute occasional poems to magazines and journals. Several of his enterprises for publishers, during his years living in Leeds, included poems, though none of these larger designs was brought to a successful conclusion.Many poems were written and given to friends, and much other material was left among his papers at his death. The greater part of his legacy to posterity from this period is contained in his translations of French poets of the Surrealist epoch, which I refer to later in this introduction. Nevertheless I have had a considerable mass of poetry to go through in order to compile what I feel may justifiably be called the Complete Poems. Complete here means everything of Bell’s which is original poetry, and not translation, prose exegesis, memoir or diary.The book inevitably falls into two parts. The first consists of the 1967 Collected which I have reproduced unaltered, other than to place four pieces ofJuvenilia at the front instead of assigning them to the end, as made sense originally. It seemed to me unquestionable that a book which Bell himselfprepared for the press must be made the heart of this new enterprise, a conviction sharpened by the high
￼quality of almost everything he had chosen in 1967.The second part of the book is inevitably my choice of the poems which, as Bell’s literary executor, I received from his heirs andfriends. I had one crucial decision to make right at the start. Was I to include at least a sample of Bell’s copious and brilliant work at translating from the French - say his versions of Rimbaud’s Les Illuminations, those most difficult to render marvels of proto- modemism (nobody has done ‘Depart’ as well as he has)? After all, his own 1967 selection included his version of Nerval’s ‘El Desdi- chado’, his Laforgue fantasy ‘Winter Coming On’and an even more direct translation from Corbiere, ‘The Ballad Singer at the Pardon of St Anne’. But in that volume the balance was exact: translations were set against the power of original poems and thus could be seen to carry the full weight of the poet’s own personal style, however well they achieved the intention of the original French. The mass of post-1967 poems with which I was dealing was more disparate and was outnumbered threefold by the quantity of translated poetry I had to choose from. I decided, therefore, to leave out any poems which originated in other men’s and women’s imaginations. Sucha decision does not exclude from this book, however, all trace of the presiding preoccupation of his last decade: poems, wholly his own, pay tribute to Benjamin Peret, Pierre Reverdy and Max Jacob, and the shapes and forms of much of his later verse reflects the manner of the French Surrealists.One further area of the Bell archive worried me. Joan Russell, one of his circle of friends in Southampton before the war and a regular correspondent of Martin’s during the hostilities, sent me samples of the poetry he composed while in the forces. Martin Bell had decided when choosing for his Collected Poems to ignore all this material, perhaps because he had preserved little o f it. Instead, he represented his early years by merely four pieces ofJuvenilia, where the Surrealist influence is already recognisable. Mrs Russell con­firmed that she and her surviving friends ofthe Southampton circle did not possess more than a part of the work which Bell sent home to Southampton from camps in England and the Mediterranean. The passages which she sent me decided me to imitate the poet’s example and not collect any of this verse here. What I have read is characteristic and touching but organised at a much less concise and powerful level than anything which Bell chose to print in his mature years. It is heavily reliant on parody and is quite derivative: nor did I ever hear him refer to his poetic output during the war. Had more of his poetry of this period survived, I might have made
￼a different decision.Martin Bell’s life can be seen all too easily as a cautionary tale ofthe price the poet pays for inspiration. Indeed, it is already being represented this way in some quarters. It is no secret that his later years were blighted by addiction to alcohol, and complicated by depression, lack of recognition, shortage of money and touches of paranoia. It is quite easy, of course, to accept this pattern and still go on to praise Bell as a poet - indeed, if one wants to achieve the full romantic apotheosis, the life’s agony is a necessary pre-condition of the ultimate vindication. That Bell deserves wholehearted vindi­ cation for a life almost religiously devoted to poetry is beyond doubt, yet such an approach to him and to his verse is both a simplification and a misrepresentation. All who knew him well will assert that he remained at all times, to use an appellation which Auden was fond of, ‘no wet-iag.’.He was a man of great charm, enormous erudition and, despite his devotion to serious literature, someone who observed the world around him with extra-journalistic sharpness and wit. The hermetic poet in him shared a sensibility with the worldly moralist and social critic. He was the true inheritor of the Auden mantle (his only rival the slightly older Gavin Ewart), and, even during his later concen­ tration on twentieth-century French poetry, he kept faith with the thirties’ creed of poetry as an agent of moral healing, a tracking down of the spoor of history as it is imprinted on our world. He had a highly developed sense of the poet as magus, refiner of the tribal language and high priest of psychic understanding. Sometimes it seemed paradoxical, in his later years, to find him, broke and slightly bewildered, speaking of the poet’s power and pride which made him a dangerous adversary and forceful catalyst. Music andJungian con­ cepts were the only orders which came near to sharing the supremacy ofpoetry in his imagination once his disillusion with the Communist Party took him out of active politics.In one of his best poems, ‘Reasons for Refusal’, Bell invokes his friend Roger Frampton, ‘desert-killed in ’40’, as ‘a pattern of accomplishments... johj^ed the Party first, and left it first’. These words can be used of Bell himself if the accomplishments be taken further to include infallible taste in literature and moral generosity. Nor did he ever desert the idealism which possessed so many of the finer spirits of his generation: he was always a man of the Left, even if he loved to add a Gidean ‘helas’ after claiming to be so. He was prescient of the dreadful blight of right-wing reaction in which we find ourselves today, recording as early as 1961 the way things were
￼going in an England bored with the egalitarianism and libertarianism of the post-war Labour governmentsWe didn’t want to say the way things went Pissed on the hopes we entertained, Naive, of course, but vivid and still (Christ, boy, they’re reading The TimesWhat he would have made of Thatcher’s Britain I cannot imagine. My feelings vary between relief that he is out of it and regret that the philippics it would have spurred him to will never be written. We have many pre-echoes, however, in his poetry of twenty years earlier - ‘But the terrifying thing/ Is houses/ A stake in the countrySomething to hand down Dismal boxes voting tory.’ Martin Bell was bom in Southampton in 1918 and lived there until he was twenty-one. His father worked for the Southern Rail­ way, and Bell always described his parents as lower middle-class. Certainly, there was not much money about during his childhood and manhood, and this prevented his profiting from his education to enable him to set out on a literary career - at least until he was in his thirties. The war, of course, was a further obstruction to his progress. But it was not poverty which rankled with him so consis­ tently, but the fearful gentility which went with it. Poem after poem testifies to the warping influence of lower middle-class respectabil­ ity, most clearly felt in people’s sexual lives. Only D.J. Enright, inThe Terrible Shears (‘Whatever sex was, it was another enemy’) has covered this ground as effectively: the novelist’s world of keeping up appearances, sexual timidity and class embarrassment has never much appealed to poets, and only Bell and Enright have made it eloquent as verserv,<His relationship with his mother was close and neurasthenic, as late memoirs, letters and a dream-diary indicate. One of his most sardonic poems is called ‘Ode to Psychoanalysis’ and it indicates clearly that this expensive therapy could not lift the weight of child­ hood neurosis from his mind. But Bell was always able to place themin a larger context where the personal becomes the general. His perfect command of rhetoric never deserted him. The ‘Ode to Psychoanalysis’ ends with him ‘suffering Hell because I’m always overdrawn/ At the bank whose manager hovers/ Clacking revengeful shears/^Heythere!Nob^daddy!/That’smyflamingsword...’The lo''^ Blake reference is not just a neat summing up, it ties in with all the invocations to penis, bowels and negative transference, and reminds us that Freudianism is based in prophetic religion as strongly as in medical science.
￼Bell was ‘a scholarship boy’ at Taunton’s School, Southampton from 1928 till 1935, and then took an external London Honours Degree in English at University College, Southampton (now South­ amptonUniversity)in1938,andaCambridgeDiplomaofEducation in 1939. Again, he held a scholarship. It was clear to all who met him in these years that Bell was a brilliant scholar, but he was also not a conformist and he attracted as much hostility as support from his superiors. In fact, the Principal of University College considered him a misfit (no games, not even any bird-watching or brass-rubbing, but an interest in French Symbolist poetry) and a ring-leader of the subversive element among the students. The opposition he aroused prevented his being recommended for academic posts, just as his parents’ poverty caused his headmaster at Taunton’s to advise against trying for Cambridge.Despite all this, Bell’s pre-war career was not undistinguished. Two of his teachers, Vivian de Sola Pinto and J.B. Leishman, were distinguished men of letters, the first being a pioneer editor of the Earl of Rochester and the second the best-known translator (with StephenSpender)ofRilke’sDuinoElegies.Therewasneveranything provincial about Bell’s attitude to literature, and however hard he fought the class war he was|intimidated in the slightest by literati from the public schools and ancient universities. He knew he had read more than they had, and he knew he could write better. The paradox of his early years is his combination of confidence in his own powers (far greater than that of most budding poets) and an accompanying diffidence of expression. It was shortage of money, pressure of family and the onset of war which cauterised his career.By the time he began to bring his poetry to fruition, he was no longer a young man. Men of his own generation had pushed ahead, and it waslefttothosetenormoreyearsyoungertobecomehiscolleagues.His allegiance to the Communist Party was the talisman of those years in Southampton. It was also the centre around which his net­ work of friends revolved. Many years later, in his CollectedPoems, he wrote a threnody for David Guest, one of the Southampton lecturers and a leading party member, killed in the Spanish War fighting the Fascists. Bell and his friends took Communism seri­ ously, both for its doctrine and for its strategic directives. In an extended curriculum vitae, compiled as late as 1977, he describes why he volunteered for the army in October 1939. ‘At the beginning of the war I made up my mind I was going to survive it, and told people so. I was not the type to make a military hero: in cold bloodI was cowardly, I was physically clumsy, hopeless at games and PT,
￼had a slightly deformed foot which stopped me marching in step, and bad eye-sight. I would, out of conviction at that time, have been a conscientious objector, but therparty line forbade that. In order to avoid being called up into the infantry, I volunteered for the Royal Engineers.’The party line was something they all took seriously, and although the Ribbentrop/Molotov pact was signed in these months, most Communist supporters, including Bell, did not leave the party until the full horror of Stalinism was revealed in the immediate post-war period. Bell, like so many others, began his disillusionment by read­ ing Koesder’s Darkness at Noon. The Party makes several appear­ ances in his poems - as the true faith betrayed, as a sort of parallel to the Catholic Summa, abandoned but not forgotten (‘the Party Line’), and as a substitute for the gorgon images of Freudian theory. ‘Ode to Psychoanalysis’ shows Bell coming to terms with two father-figures, Marx and Freud.So the analysis was cut off After I hadn’t paid himFor over two months -He took two-fifths of my wages.I still wanted to kill StalinAfter that. But I felt I’d let Freud down. The cook would not run the State,And the State wouldn’t wither away, And psychoanalysisWas very expensive indeed:Postpone, for the time being,The New Jerusalem.Joan Russell’s memories of their Southampton Carcle identify Martin as the inspiration of a whole Hampshire generation launched into higher education at the end of the Depression. Though he wrote regularly to many of these friends during his six and a quarter years in the Forces, he did not return to Southampton when the war ended, preferring to take up teaching in London. Southampton seems almost to have dropped out of his life, coming back only in brief appearances in poems (the fine ‘High Street, Southampton’, with its memorable comment on the blitzing of the town centre, restored in so ugly a fashion - ‘Where is the Phoenix? Surely there was burning’). Marriage was another cause of distancing. He acquired a completely new set of friends and colleagues, very much London-based. The fact that he preserved none of the poems he
￼sent in letters to Southampton points to a resolve, however uncon­ scious, to make a new start in life. But his early leadership was prescient of what happened later. With the Group, he found a new circle in which his talent could prosper, and this time he was tooled- up to take full advantage of it.Martin’s wartime experience was formative in another way. It freed him from English provincialism. He served in Lebanon, Syria and Italy mainly. His war was like so many bookish persons’ wars, mostly boredom in camp and apparently pointless enterprises abroad. But he relished the chance to speak French and to attend the opera in Italy (San Carlo Opera House, in Naples, where he was introduced to the basic Italian operatic repertory, and where he first saw and heard Tito Gobbf. Opera was to remain for him the art closest to poetry in its combination of humanism and irrational emotionjj. There were other aspects of army life which he appreci­ ated: the 1977 c.v. has a remarkable tribute to the Royal Engineers. ‘In the unit with which I served longest, the whole company, from the OC and Adjutant (who kept sometimes ignorant junior officers in order), through the Sergeant Major and NCOs^ (I was a lance- corporal), to the Sappers and Drivers, all conspired to keep the Com­ pany’s good name in spite of its short-comings, lied for each other, and kept one another out of trouble.’The same devotion to ateam characterised Martin Bell’s relations with those of us later who formed the Group. He enjoyed the con­ spiratorial mode of rivalry in the world of poetry, and once he had made his reputation, he never departed from a concern for the republic of letters. In this, his highmindedness was out of tune with the increasing fashion-consciousness of the sixties and seventies and led him into many disappointments. He could not understand that many of the well-known poets of his time were ruthless egotists who had little interest in promoting anyone but themselves. The pro bono publico aspect ofhis nature made him awonderful teacher of poetry, if his student was talented and genuine. He can claim to have discovered one of today’s leading poets, George Szirtes, who was an art student in Leeds while Martin taught Liberal Studies there and whom he encouraged to write verse. Many other students in Leeds learned how wide and diverse European poetry is from Bell.Bell ran a sawmill in Lebanon and polished up his French there. The first poem in his Collected comes from his time in Italy, and it is a translation from Nerval’s French, ‘El Desdichado’, the sonnet which T.S. Eliot gave wider immortality to by quoting from it prom­ inently at the end of The Waste Land. Bell’s version is not only far\1^
￼and away the best that has been done, but it launches his published poems on a virtuoso note. Because he is essentially a realistic and vernacular writer, it is important to underline his virtuosity. His style is a yoking o f salient detail to rhetorical projection. T o achieve this, the poet needs to be a master of phrasing, syntax and drama: from ‘El Desdichado’ onwards, his verse is never afraid to be flamboyant, but always stays close to the spoken word. His erudition is so natural that the many references and quotations in his poetry (a tendency both natural to him and imitated from Eliot, who was his ideal model all his life) dovetail into the pattern neatly. The opposite of the ‘know-nothing’poet, Bell nevertheless has little ofthe cold academi­cism of many educated and ‘serious’ poets. He is clos^to Wallace Stevens, who felt simple emotions voluptuously, and a similar fond­ ness for ‘essential gaudiness’informs Bell’s verse. However straight­ forward and lean, it is always rhetorical.He settled in London after the war, married and had two daughters. His first appointment as a teacher with the LCC was in a junior school whose IJeadmaster he found sympathetic. He worked as a teacher there for ten years. This part of his life is the least well- documented, since Martin rarely spoke of it. It was clearly a period of calm and consolidation in his career. The very decade itself was a time of hope but also a time of austerity, as the post-war govern­ ments called on the nation to make sacrifices to build the new and hopeful Britain promised by the Labour Party. He must have read a great deal and begun to write again.Clearly, there had been troubles. Soon after demobilisation he entered psychoanalysis, which was not a success. He tells how he wrote limericks against his analyst who, while attributing them to aggression, went on to encourage him by saying something could be made of them. Bell, however, had been apologising for their imperfections, and not for having written them, and angrily told his analyst that he knew the precise weight of words and could tell a good limerick from a bad one. The upshot was uncomfortable: he appreciated that the last thing he consciously wanted the analyst to find out was that he thought of himself as a poet. It would not be going too far to suggest that he had no further need of analysis once he had accepted his calling to poetry. It was to bring him close todestitution, but it also liberated him from suburban despair.At the beginning of the fifties, he was writing poetry again, though not yet regularly. The second poem in his Collected, ‘Benefit Night at the Opera’ was accepted by J.R. Ackerley for The Listener. Bell recalls that he had worked for three years on its twenty lines. It is
￼his first characteristic poem, being an amalgam of several actual operas, most notably Un Ballo in Maschera, plus memories o f evenings spendl in the San Carlo house, all worked into a menacing mise-en- scene in Auden’s manner.A few years later, he went into his usual pub in Chiswick where an encounter with a young man changed his life. He was reading quiedy when a youthful gentleman with a cultivated and resonant voice approached him and said: ‘Excuse me, sir, but does that happen to be a volume of verse you are reading?’ ‘It is indeed, sir.’ ‘May I enquire what it is? Surely it is Norman Cameron’s translation of Rimbaud’s verse-poems.’The young interrogator was Peter Redgrove, also living then at Chiswick, who immediately invited Bell to come to the newly-con­ vened meetings of aspirant poets which were being held in Philip Hobsbaum’s flat. This conventicle had been founded by Hobsbaum in Cambridge at the same time that Redgrove, an undergraduate who had turned from Natural Sciences to English, founded the magazine Delta. Hobsbaum continued these sessions in London and thus the Group, as it came to be called, began its ten-year life. Hobsbaum was the first chairman and may be called the Group’s ‘onlie begetter’. Early members included Redgrove, Edward Lucie- Smith, Alan Brownjohn, Margaret Owen, Martin Bell, George Mac- Beth and myself.From the very first evening he attended, Bell became the father and tone-setter of Group discussions. He had read more than any of us; was, of course, older, but was also more audacious, intellec­ tually wide-ranging and freer from prejudice. This is not the place to explain the Group’s principles, other than to state that Hobsbaum’s rule was that we should look for everything we wanted to say in the text itself, and that the person whose work was being discussed was not allowed to intervene in the discussion with explanations of his or her intentions. My memories of Martin at Group sessions are vivid: he would begin with a cough of emphatic intervention and immediately develop brilliant technical fantasies on the roneo’d text which left the rest of us labouring behind. He was also a fine delineator of versification and verbal troping. He loved the camaraderie of discussion, the sense that, like any of those involved in the peripateia of the past, we were pioneers of creativity and understanding.I doubt that Martin learned from us, his juniors, much in the way of useful knowledge for his work, but he gained confidence in his audience, and, encouraged by more worldly figures, he began to
￼send out poems. Soon after joining the Group, he read a poem, ‘The Enormous Comics’ at one of G.S. Fraser’s meetings in Beaufort Street, and George Fraser took it for the TLS. In the period between 1955, when he began to come to Group meetings, and 1962, Bell wrote most of his first wave of poems, and saw them published, sporadically but with mounting success, in various journals. Group members began to make their first excursions into book publication as the decade ended. First was Peter Redgrove, whose debut was in 1960, with The Collector. Edward Lucie-Smith and I followed in 1961, and George MacBeth soon after. When my poems were accepted forthe launching ofPenguinModem Poets (publication early 1962), Bell’s were already being considered for the series in Pen­ guin’s offices. His inclusion in Number Three of the series came later the same year. Martin Bell was now securely on the Poetryits liberating insistence that poetry was not so arcane an art that it could not be discussed helpfully. And I remember Martin as the epicentre of Group activity. Nevertheless, my strongest and fondest memories of him come from outside Group meetings, though still within the ambience of literature. He was a marvellous talker, rang­ ing in all directions and into hundreds of special regions. He and I loved Auden and the thirties, while Group orthodoxy, influenced by Leavis, was suspicious of that decade and its poets. Martin and I were less than enchanted with Lawrence, another aberration byMartin’s love of opera into an accompanying enjoyment of instru­ mental music. We also deviated in our opinion of Britten’s operas, Martin having an unswerving dislike of Billy Budd, for its sado­ masochism and homosexuality, which he later passionately argued with Anthony Burgess. This analysis of Britten also informed his views of Wilfred Owen’s poetry, so that when the War Requiem was performed,itwasloadedwithadoublehelpingofobloquy.Stravinsky’s collaboration with Auden was a different matter and his affection and understanding of The Rake's Progress was intense. He also esteemed Der Rosenkavalier and Mozart’s operas. His greatest love was reserved for Verdi, and several of his poems pay tribute to this most manly and accessible of composers.Scene.I am grateful to the Group for all that it did, and especially forGroup standards.Music was a further affection, and here I was unable to extendMartin and his wife and my wife and I exchanged visits many times in the sixties, until Martin’s marriage broke up. Bell-and I also did poetry readings, travelled over England and, all in all, saw
￼a great deal of each other in this, his high noon as a poet. I owe him more than I could ever repay for his kindnesses and understandings, and for his sheer human warmth.My memories of Bell in his heyday would not be complete without some recall of the extraordinary partnership he made with Peter Redgrove. I have never met two people with a greater knowledge and relish ofpoetry in English. Their fondness was almost a musical one, in that it was the sounds of English verse which excited them - not sounds in any Sitwellian sense, that would be too limiting. Rather, it was a love of the way syntax, meaning, resonance and recall are all woven into the greatest English poetry. Sitting in the Mandrake Club one dark afternoon, I heard Redgrove and Bell give an inspired duo performance ofWallace Stevens’s ‘Sea Surface Full of Clouds’. The different tones of their voices as they dealt in turn with Stevens’s refrain ‘In that November off Tehuantepec/ The slopping of the sea grew still...’ was a revelation to me, always someone more moved by the phrasing of poetry than by its sound, and their concern for the dramatic poise ofpoetry approached sacer­ dotal intensity.In more uproarious mood, they would give a performance ofMac­ beth in cod Scottish accents, which were hardly more ridiculous than Orson Welles’s voice in his film. It’s surprising how well Shakes­ peare’s lines appear to support some kind of accentual Doric - viz. ‘The air hath bubbles as the water hath.’ One of the regular pieces in their double act was a performance of Redgrove’s dialogue poem ‘The Play’, a rather Beckettian piece in which two old gentlemen outbid each other in fustian and second-childhood-fantasy. When taking part in this, Martin’s residual Hampshire accent would swell to high camp Mummerset, and his intoning of the final couplet was worthy of his idol Groucho Marx:Is that my part? Now watch my artAs I die as I scream as I die for my art.The serious aspect of Bell’s generosity in these remarkable years, as the fifties changed to the sixties, was his own poetry, which came from him in an undiverted stream. Always a careful and revising writer, nevertheless he produced poem after poem with splendid facility. At Group meetings, we encountered many examples ofvin­ tage Bell: ‘Headmaster: Modem Style’, ‘Reasons for Refusal’, ‘Winter Coming On’, ‘Ode to Himself’, ‘High Street, South­ ampton’, ‘Ode to Groucho’ and ‘Letter to a Friend’.With ‘Techniques for Detente’, ‘Zen for William Empson’ and ‘Verdi at Eighty’ we approach the last stage of Martin’s London
￼period. His fantasias of an old man, whereby he invented for himself the persona of Don Senilio, show his imagination modulating out of the essentially happy years of his discovery of the Group towards the alienation and disorientation ofthe Seventies. When Don Senilio was conceived, Bell was hardly more than forty-five years old, but the character of a man washed up on the shoals of redundancy came to him with the sharpness of a revelation. His life was changing, and not in hopeful directions, despite some initially favourable moves.In 1964, he was awarded the first Arts Council poetry bursary, which enabled him to work part-time. Then, in 1967, i^e was appointed Gregory Fellow of Poetry at Leeds University for two years. He abandoned teaching, the job he had laboured at unhappily for almost twenty years. He separated from his wife, a separation felt bitterly by her. His removal to Leeds was to prove final. He never lived in London again, and saw the city only as a visitor. He regarded his life from 1967 onwards as exile.Martin always believed that if he had remained in London, both success and failure would have been more manageable. There is some reason for agreeing with him. For instance, in the early sixties he formed a close relationship with Anthony Burgess and his first wife, Lyn, then living in Chiswick. Bell and Burgess formed a double- act only slightly less playful than the Bell/Redgrove one. Burgess had him appointed opera critic for Queen magazine in 1965, in suc­ cession to Burgess himself. Martin was an idiosyncratic critic of music and opera, but, in many respects, a sound and unsnobbish one. His hand lay behind some of Burgess’s own judgments, especi­ ally of Stravinsky and Britten, though it was Burgess who was the trained musician of the two. Bell was a jaunty figure at the opera, and claimed that the Glyndebourne authorities had waived the requirement of evening dress for him, considering him sufficiently well accoutred wearing a bow-tie to go with the small dapper beard which he affected at this time.The year 1965 was a crucial one in Martin Bell’s life. In 1963, some Group members, including Bell and I, had read on the Fringe at the Edinburgh Festival. On this visit, he met and formed a lively admiration for the Scots poet Robert Garioch. Though not a partisan of Lallans, he always advocated a wider audience for Scottish poetry in England, and once persuaded several of us to put our names to a letter to The Times proposing Hugh MacDiarmid, another of the poets we met in Edinburgh, as Poet Laureate in succession to Masefield.In 1965 poetry was included among the official performances at
￼the Edinburgh Festival for, I believe, the First and only time. A.week of readings was organised at the Freemasons’Hall in George Street. Bell and I were again in Edinburgh, hoping to meet Randall Jarrell who was due to arrive from America. Alas, he walked into the freeway a month before. W.D. Snodgrass came in his place, and was wel­ comed by us enthusiastically. I had been commissioned to interview W.H. Auden for BBC radio. Auden was the star of the Edinburgh series, just as he became later at London’s Poetry International. Bell and I spent an evening prowling round Edinburgh desperately trying to think of things I could ask Auden. In the event, the interview was a fiasco, for which I do not blame Auden.It was an exhilarating time, in and out of the Festival Press Club, drinkingwithsuchnotablesasVernonScannell,HughMacDiarmid, Sydney Goodsir Smith, and the whole corps of London theatre and music critics. Bell had to write notices of the operas at the King’s Theatre (Don Giovanni and a rare Haydn work, Le Pescatrici, unfor­ tunately very dull), and I remember how thrilled he was to both stand next to Carlo Maria Giulini at the Mayor’s reception for the Festival artists and to ask the maestro sympathetic questions at a press conference about the stage mechanics’ strike which robbed Don Giovanni of all its scenery.The most important aspect of Edinburgh that year for Martin was his falling in love with Christine McCausland, who became the Muse of his later verse. He returned in the last year of his life to this brief episode of impassioned involvement in a verse-and-prose fantasy left unfinished among his papers. He called it Operatics and Intrusions, and the part of it he completed recreates those days at the Edinburgh Festival, on to which he grafts a few new poems and works in some of his best-known previously published verse. From this time on, Bell was determined to change his life, but the Rilkean sense of the phrase came out in tragic guise rather than in life-asserting shape.His period of office as Gregory Fellow was not a success - at least from his own point of view. He was now cut off from London, and the romance for which he made the break from his previous commitments could not be sustained - chiefly his own responsibility, since he was now drinking very heavily. A year or so previously in London, during the interregnum between his giving up teaching and his removal to Leeds, he had been take^to hospital for an emergency operation for a ruptured duodenal ulcer. He appeared to make a complete recovery from this, but his stomach was now weakened and his health in general began to decline.
￼After the Gregory, he was taken on as a teacher of Liberal Studies at Leeds Art School, later Leeds Polytechnic. Though he carried out his duties with sporadic brilliance, he began, with the seventies, a long personal decline, coming close to despair on many occasions. I do not intend to describe, even if I could, his life in Leeds. One point needs to be stressed strongly, however. He remained an inspi­ rationtoawholegroupofpeopleinthatcity- EnglishandPhilosophy teachers, students, painters, aspirant writers - persons of widely varying backgrounds and interests. Nobody talking to Martin for any length of time could miss his originality of mind. And the dis­ location of his brain and his body was a tragedy for his body more than for his intellect.All the while he was lurching from one crisis to another - taking cures for alcoholism, seeking refuge in hospital from bank managers as much as from booze - he was adding methodically to his archive of translations of the French Surrealists. In this work, he was methodical and exemplary - the manuscripts are cleaner and more impeccably set out than almost any I have seen. Of course, such enterprises did nothing to improve his immediate circumstances, financially or in any other way. He was driven to all kinds of resorts to make money.One undertaking which has left behind a welcome legacy was an expedition to Cyprus in the late sixties with his friend, the painter Stass Paraskos, and Stass’s family. From this visit, Martin was com­ missioned to produce a travel book along the lines of Auden’s and MacNeice’s,tentativelycalledLettersfromCyprus.The‘letters’which got written were mostly in verse, and I have included most of them in this volume. Bell met and fell completely for President Makarios, but much else on the trip was as nightmarish as anything Rimbaud could have imagined. Bell even hated the France he travelled through. His love was always for the language and literature of that country, not for the people - or the landscape.Before he died Martin Bell had applied to the Arts Council for a bursary to enable him to complete several projects, including his translations. By the sort of irony common in poets’ lives, the money arrived after his death. I met him in London less than four weeks before he died in his sleep, and he seemed more hopeful and relaxed. What surprised most people, in the weeks after his demise, was the scale and scope of work which he left behind him. Nevertheless, it has taken many years to bring this Complete Poems into existence. The taste of the times has so far not been encouraging to a poet of Bell’s commitments - he would see the point but not admire the
￼2S'Sf
￼performance of today’s dandies, the Martians, and he would be disappointed at the re-emergence of Oxbridge fashion as the dominating tone of English poetry. A programme on Radio Three which I compiled of his verse in 1983 merely earned censure from the network’s cultural officers. But I trust that such neglect is a thing of the past.I have already outlined the principles on which this collection has been made. All that remains to be done in this introduction is to offer some notes on the poems printed - an editor’s justification. Everything up to ‘Pets’ (page 129) comes from Bell’s own Collected. I do not feel that any notes are needed. Bell offered none when he first gathered these poems together. The music which Anthony Burgess wrote for ‘Senilio’s Broadcast Script’ has been retained. It presents a challenge to any amateur pianist, with its florid Lisztian bravura. All poems after ‘Pets’ come from the mass of material inBell’s possession at his death. He had some major enterprises on hand, as well as others which he had abandoned in various states of completion— — E-o1. (J7rom~JTicCityofDreadfulSomethingThis was tcTbe a sort of mini-Waste|Land, castigating Leeds and all its works. At various stages, poems were added and deleted. There are other poems, which he did not include in this sequence, which also apostrophise Leeds. I have included them here, after the specific sequence under the above title. The text I have^phoaed for the sequence appears to be the closest to a definitive one among themany recensions he preserved. The title is parodied from James Thomson’s City ofDreadful Night.2. Letters from CyprusI have given this sequence its title, since Bell’s definitive text, clearly gathered from among the many pieces he had intended for the book of that name/swe, in his final fair copy, unheaded. The sequence is his own, though he obviously intended the book to contain much in the way of prose letters, as Auden’s and MacNeice’s did, into which these poems would have been leafed. Clearly, he regarded the project as a sort of gallimaufry where many different sorts of poem could be accommodated, even if they had little bearing on Cyprus itself. Thus the sequence includes poems about cats, London life, French poets, Leeds, his old friends, Stass Paraskos’s pictures etc. At the end, I have added five further poems which may not be specifically for this undertaking but are connected by subject matter.
￼3. Operatics and IntrusionsI have described this previously, and have taken only two short poems from the text in my possession, the others being works included in Collected Poems and here used in a different context.4. Translations from FrenchThough I have excluded everything in this great mass of material, I shall list what is included under this heading to demonstrate Bell’s application to projects which fired his imagination:MAXJACOB: Le Comet a des, 226 pages of prose poems.ANDRfi BRETON and PHILIPPE SOUPAULT: Les Champs magnetiques,117 pages.ROBERT DESNOS: A la mysterieuse, 24 pages; Les Tenebres, 46 pages. BENJAMIN P£RET: Le Grandfeu, A selection.PIERRE REVERDY: Poemes en prose, /T7 pages; ftoiles peintes, 20 pages;La balle au bond, 40 pages.Selections from ARTAUD, BECKER, fXUARD, HfBERT, MESENS andQUENEAU, 70 pages.There are also versions of Rimbaud, which Bell seems to havethought of as lying outside this specifically twentieth century file.5. DiariesThese are in prose. One is a dream-diary he kept in the last years, in which he interprets his dreams according to Jungian lights. An extensive autobiographical diary also exists. Many letters from him to Peter Redgrove and Christine McCausland have also been pre­ served.In deciding which order to put the post-1967 poetry, I have been, of necessity, somewhat arbitrary. First come his resumptions of the mask character of Don Senilio. Then Leeds is celebrated and execrated, and poems dedicated to Leeds friends are added. Some of the larger shapes among his later works are the next in line, including his addresses to Patricia Highsmith and Bing Crosby. After this, I have placed Letters from Cyprus and further poems inspired by the island and the Mediterranean. Now come poems addressed to father-figures and the Frenchmen he translated, together with ruminations on translation. Then some engaging squibs for friends and colleagues in Leeds and elsewhere.Where Bell did not provide a title, I have, in general, not invented one, so that several poems are listed in the Contents merely by their opening line or lines. This section of the book contains much of the light verse and lampooning which he wrote, including some more savage satires on literary people. Some are fragments. The tone
￼darkens towards the end of the book. Social poems, not satires but denunciations of a crass and materialist society, follow, interspersed with mysterious, almost cryptic laments. Bell’s increasing sense of his own mortality emerges in this part.As far as I have been able to date them, I have kept his final poems to the end. His parents come back in these short verses, as they do in his accounts of his dreams. His love for the lady who was his Muse is faced up to once more. Poem after poem is ‘For C’ or C’s name is worked into its pattern. Their being what he calls defiantly ‘love poems’ does not prevent his weaving much self- reproach and well-observed pain into them. Almost ^ the end, dated the year before he died, is his ‘A Vocation Possibly’ which he sent to Anthony Burgess. It is a quiet poem, but a desolate one.The great majority of Martin Bell’s manuscripts, in long-hand or typed, insist on capitals at the beginning of lines, and I have kept to this preference strictly. His punctuation is a much more open-ended matter. H e tended to punctuate in a lordly way, as Byron did. Perhaps both poets expected their editors to put the punctuation in for them. I have done so very gently indeed, so that there are many poems in which punctuation is sparse or non-existent. Meaning, however, is seldom in jeopardy. Lastly, there may be further poems I have not seen. This book reproduces all the original poetry that Martin Bell and his circle kept intact, except for some clearly incomplete and uncompletable pieces.Amongst the prose Bell left is a brief manifesto which is worth reproducing since its various maxims help a reader not well acquainted with his verse and the thought behind it to understand his procedures, and the strange combination in his nature ofsardonic doubt and idealist enthusiasm. He entitled itAgainst the Grain: Con­ tradictory Theses.Poetry is too popular. What occurred in the Albert Hall was disaster. Poems should be detested, but irresistible.‘Doing one’s own thing’ is as obscene a pun as ‘doing one’s bit’. Crowds are for contracting out of.It is necessary to postulate the existence of absolute standards, and to endeavour to approximate to them. These standards are ratios.There must be formal etiquette to disinfect applause.We are not elitists, but nevertheless have chosen ourselves. Enemies: the Don, the Administrator, the Impresario, the Journalist,the Anarchist, and Old Charlie in the corner with the squeeze-box. Conspiracy is necessary to Democracy.Ancestor-worship is essential. Pope, Baudelaire, pray for us!Th ' o necessity to satirise popular art: this function it perf<^I'l
￼foritself. 3Some peophThave not yet heard that Dada is dead!The Unconscious should be treated with courtesy, not raped. Again and yet again: to purify the dialect of the tribe.We are on the Left, helas!These admonitions could be taken for reactionary only in a debased age, though they were written at the end of a simple-minded one. TheirauthorknewmoreaboutpoetrythananywriterIhaveknown.I should like to thank especially the following people for helping t o b r i n g t h i s e d i t i o n o f M a r t i n B e l l ’s p o e m s t o a s u c c e s s f u l c o n c l u s i o n -John Milne, Philip Hobsbaum, Alan Brownjohn, George Szirtes, Peter Redgrove, Joan Russell, and, the most essential person of all, without whose devotion to Martin’s memory and his legacy ofpoetry, nothing could have been done - Christine McCausland.PETER PORTERt