￼SRI LANKABeing nearly heart-shaped made me seem a ham On early spice trade navigators’ charts Tinctured with cinnamon, peppered with Torts,To be eaten up under a strong brand name Like Taprobanc, Serendib, Tenarisim —Copper-palmed lotus island slave resorts —And I succumbed to lordly polished arts That cut me down to stem a white king’s gem, A star sapphire tear-drop India shedOn old school maps, a lighthouse of retorts Flashing from head to head. My leonine blood Throbbed wildly when resplendent freedom cameMouthing pearl tropes with Pali counterparts, Exalted, flawed; and made me seem as I am.
￼The Mirror WallRichard Murphy
￼I
￼also by Richard Murphy SAILING TO AN ISLAND(1963)THE BATTLE OF AUGHRIM(1968)HIGH ISLAND ( 1974)THE PRICE OF STONE( 1985)NEW SELECTED POEMS( 1989)
￼RICHARD MURPHYTHE MIRROR WALL
￼
￼AcknowledgementsThe Government of Sri Lanka granted me permission in 1987 to use copyright material by the late Professor Senarat Paranavitana in writing these poems. I acknow­ ledge this debt with gratitude. Sigiri Graffiti by S. Paranavitana was published in two volumes by the Oxford University Press for the Government of Ceylon in 1956, and reprinted at the Government Press in Colombo for the Government of Sri Lanka in 1983.The phjtographs of the Sigiriva frescoes were taken by Nihal fernando for this book. I thank him for his gift.I am grateful to several writers who helped meto work on these poems in Sri Lanka. Ashley Halpe, Professor of English at Peradeniya University, introduced me to the Sigiri Graffiti, showed me some of hisown versions, and encouraged me to persevere. Anuradha Seneviratn^, Professor of Sinhala at Peradeniya, gaveme instruction on the Old Sxnhala texts, includingtheir background, and critical advice on my adaptations. Senake Bandaranaike, Professor of Archaeology at Kelaniya University and Director of the Sigiriya Project, provided me with much information and special accessto the Mirror Wall and the Frescoes. An essay by P.B.Meegaskumbera of Peradeniya University influenced my response to several lyrics.[Paragraph of acknowledgement to the editors of the TLS and GRAND STREET for publishing substantial selections of these poems will be included here.]The British High Commissioner to Sri Lanka, David Gladstone, and his wife April, sponsored a performance of these poems, with music by Lalanath de Silva,for two hundred guests at Westminster House, Colombo,vii
￼on 24 March 1988. I thank them for their hospitality. Finally, a word of thanks to my native country.My work on The Mirror Wail, requiring long visitsto Sri Lanka, was continuously and generously supported by Aosdana, the Arts Council and the Departmentof Foreign Affairs in the Republic of Ireland.
￼Contents[The numbers in square brackets refer to the Old Sinhala songs in Sigiri Graffiti by S. Paranavitana-]Acknowledgements PrefaceThe Frescoes at SigiriyaInvocationKassapa [153]Falling and falling [477] Climbed up the Lion Rock Coming up the mountain track Look, my darling [14]The king's palace rockAll over the Lion Rock"I'm dying" [61]Who got angry?When spoken toLonging to singHer loose appearanceThey deck you [30]vii xiiixvii1 234[1] 5 0 6 67 8 10 11 11 12 13 14 15 15 16 [69] 16 16 17 18 19 20Some of the figuresGood Luck! [4]Adorable mountain girlYou who remain [22]With her hair tied upWomen like you enable peopleDoes the blue waterliiy In your eyes the lustre Your eyes have turned Eyebrow's midnight blue No, don’t look at her![24] [50][40] [90][71] ix[446] [620] [84][33] [76][45][156] [482][13] [25]
￼I am Friar... [349]FrrTBati [72]Beyond looking brilliantI was in paradise [104] Her hand is given like w ater Superlative make-up artist21 22 2326Yes/She is beautifulShe’s planting [103]From Hunagiri TempleNo! You must not believeJust let me creep awayDoes a good lover [86]She stopped me feeling sad [32] 30 Thinking endless thoughts [129] 30 The song of Lord Sirina [134] 31Pure as the hare with spotsI looked [203]The virtue of this breeze Doesn't the Sanskrit "apsaras"The moon roseThe wet monsoonWow! [126]0 no! [196]If you examine the wayA meion-pip smileBecoming attachedHow can that dancerAs a woman [272]He kept coming back to look[135] 32 33[382] 34 [175] 3535 3638 39 404041 4142 [170] 43 44 4546 47 4748Once he'd imagined them[192] [340]Crushed by1 am KitalaHis ployThis act of his WTien I approach[299] [595]ill treatm ent [336][565][492] [405][95] [88][87][325] [331][306] [327]x24 [110] 24 [52] 25 2527 [118] 27 [122] 28 29
￼Women, please wave [64] 48 The subtie and etherial [556] 49 The message I received [484] 50 A nectar-soaked bee [582] 51 No. We do not know [488] 52 "Do we know why?" [63]The good luck and joyWhile swans are making Governor Nakka's poemI don't believe [651] Sigiriya, 11 January 1987If happiness could come"You won't remember" [54] Maybe when royalty had gone On our way [35]Entangle [334] They came here[677]xi52 [94] 53 [580] 53 [652] 54 55 [249] 56[108]5858 [79] 59 59 60 61
￼
￼PrefaceMuch of my happy childhood was spent in Ceylon, where my father was the last British Mayor of Colombo. After a gap of fifty years, I returned to Sri Lanka,and found the inspiration for these poems. It camefrom songs written in Old Sinhala during the 8th.,9th. and 10th. centuries. The original holographs remain on the curving, parapet wall of a footpath half wayup the rock fortress of Sigiriya in the central province. The wall is about a hundred metres long, and overtwo metres high. Incised with metal styles in the polished plaster, the songs relate to mysterious, 'golden'’ women in frescoes painted on the undulating rock above this "mirror wall ’, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these portraits have survived since the end of the 5th. century."Sigiriya", or "Sihigiri" n Old Sinhala, means"Lion Rock”: and the Sinhala people are the "lion” people, mythically descended from a lion who rapedan Indian princess. From some directions, the rock resembles a crouching lion tnat has lost its head:and from others, a massive iingam, the symbol ofShiva. Rising 600 feet above the forest, tanks and paddy fields of the peneplain, it stands on the island’s main water parting, where the rivers that flow east into the Bay of Bengal part from those that flowwest into the Indian Ocean.Sigiriya was fortified by a king called Kassapaor Kasyapa, who reigned there from A.D. 477-495,the only king of Lanka to have done so. The Mahawamsa, an ancient Theravada Buddhist chronicle written in Pali, accused Kassapa of slaying his father by having him sealed up in a niche inside a wall:Xlll
￼and said that he chose Sigiriya ’'through fear’’, because the rock "is difficult of ascent for human beings.He cleared (the land) round about, surrounded it witha wall and built a staircase in the form of a lion.Thence it took its name.... Then he built there afine palace, worthy to behold, like another Alakamanda and dwelt there like Kuvera’'.Kuvera was the god of wealth in the Hindu pantheon, and Alakarnanda, or Alaka in Sanskrit, wasthe city he occupied on the mythical Mount Kailasain the Himalayas. The Sanskrit poet Kalidasa, wholived a century before Kassapa, alludes to Kailasaas "the mirror for goddesses", and to Alaka as adorned with paintings he compares to the cloud's rainbow.Four of the Sinhaia songs refer to the women in the frescoes as asaran, from apsaras in Sanskrit, thecloud nymphs who frequented Kailasa. One song suggeststhey were the king's five hundred wives. Were they ''stuck to the rock" as offerings to Kuvera or theLion or the local mountain god? Perhaps their function was to ensure sufficient rainfall to grow rice in this dry zone: rain was sometimes regarded as the semenof the gods.After Kassapa was defeated in battle by his half-brother, Sigiriya was abandoned as a royal residence, but greatly revered as a place of secular pilgrimage. People were drawn there from all over Sri Lankaand southern India for the next seven hundred years. Eventually the ruins were smothered in jungle, until the site was opened up in the last century.Some of the writers signed their names on the wall, declaring their rank, profession and place of residence. They were members of a feudal nobility and its entourage; officials, merchants, clerks and Buddhist monks. Only two of the authors professedto be "poets". At least twelve poems were written xiv
￼by women. Monks had occupied Sigiriya centuries before Kassapa's reign, and remained for centuries thereafter. In some of their puritanical songs, they condemnedthe fresco nymphs as faithless wives or prostitutesor dancing girls. Theravada Buddhism never encouraged erotic art or sensual passion.The women in the pictures were seen by the writers from various contradictory points of view, but never rearing children. War, famine, plague, or what wemight call reality, did not enter into their stylised world. Nor was it necessary to describe what couldbe seen on the spot. No song implies that Kassapawas a parricide, though several argue about his wives' behaviour after his death. There is no definitive version of why the women are on the rock, or what theyare doing, or who they are: and the songs grow from this fertile mystery.Called gi in Sinhala, the lyrics were sung, perhaps with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery under theportraits where they were written. There are poems about love, rejection and the separation of lovers; satires and complaints; joyful, erotic celebrations;and rueful ironies. Much of tie writing is light verse or vers de societe. There is at least one prose inscription, which says: I am Budal, I came in company and saw Sihigiri. Many peopie who saw (Sihigiri) have written verses. I therefore did not write one.The forms of the gi are syllabic: usually 38 to 43 syllables, divided into two lines, each of which contains a "breath", or caesura, after 9, 10 or 11 syllables. An English quatrain could match this, but Sinhala verse has no stresses. End rhymes are rare, though internal rhyming, assonance and alliteration frequently occur. Some short Sinhala words can have several meanings that deepen the ambiguity, or the irony of a lyric.xv
￼A few of my poems are versions that keep closeto the syllabic count and meaning of their Old Sinhala sources. But more often 1 use a variety of freer formsto elaborate images and ideas evoked by the sources;to bring in modem voices; to include some description and context; or to combine material from severalsongs. My sources are among the 685 songs that were transcribed, edited, translated and introduced by Senarat Paranavitana in his Sigiri Graffiti, a two volume masterpiece of Sinhala scholarship, which informedand inspired my work.xvi
￼xvii
￼xviii
￼xix
￼
￼XX
￼InvocationAll you feel on the Lion Rock won't come by breathing heavily.Take up a styleAnd let the Rain Girls give you airs to lift songs from the scoresthat pierce the Mirror Wall.1
￼KASSAPAPerhaps the king, whose name evoked the sun, Riding his elephant, under a pearl umbrella, Through parched rice-fields on the dry zone plain,Had seen this rock aspiring from the earth To penetrate the clouds loafing in heaven: And put five hundred of his virgin brides,Dressed in cascades of jewellery, to makeA splash on the summit, and entice the gods To cast their semen on the ground as rain:Then shone here, as the god of wealth, supreme In rice and gems, going about on three legs, Devising arts to give the gods sublimeErections that would last: broad galleriesOf golden girls the rock itself embraced Inside a wall whose mirror caught their souls:And sheathed the rock-head in a lion mask To father a strong race, out of whose mouth At festivals he made great fountains pour.>
￼Falling and fallingthrough feverish junglewith leeches sucking our blood, pythons dangling from creepersover the footpath, leopards in ebony treeslooking us in the eyes, and herds of wild elephantstrumpeting on our tracks,We found our way exaltedby this massive monolith,and began as we climbed to love each other better,leaping into fountain tanksto quench fiery thirst.Our thanks to the Lionwho protects Sri Lankafor sparing us one glorious day.3
￼Climbed up the Lion Rockand met the King himself:Bricked alive in the mountain with a lion face of brick.His power house ocourinduced feverish sweat.We stepped through his open jaws and came out on top,Where earth’s wheel is joinedto the great wheel of heavenA sky palace water towerwhose old courses cracked.His rain girl collection filled the rock's driest hollow.4
￼Coming up the mountain track singing a songI never got a wordfrom the golden girlskept here by their loverendlessly apart:so I poked around the Lion Rock and was stunned.Look, my darling, how the people Who chatter to each other Lightening the hard way upAre drawn without a wordTo a woman whose beauty Irradiates the silence of the rock.5
￼The king's palace rock is delectable - or so I had always heard,,and a picture had formed in my mind. Now on the spot, I think 1 will needmore eyes than the starsfor my mind not to go completely blank.All over the Lion Rockthe king had his womenfixed up as water nymphs pretending this was heaven:And hared off to lookfor salvation as a turtleseeking throughout the ocean for a yoke to fit his neck.6
￼"I’m dying”,the king thought,a while beforehaving to leave this world.He couldn’t takehis wives,all tarted up in rich distemper. "Hang on”,he jeered at them,
￼Who got angry,you or your husband,(the same word can mean lord).In a song by Mital,''slovenly w ritten in scriptattributable to the ninth century”?Were you happy climbing to the mountain top,or dragged by your hair?"The writing is blurredby the weathering of the plaster,and scribbles of later visitors”.You lept down, they said. Mital was not sure:you could have been thrown.Did you dance on the terrace that hot blustery daytoo close to the precipice,While the king, smoking ganja, sat calm as a lotuson a solid rock-crystal divan?8(continues)
￼Mital does not mention,because Vagi verse is too spare,your opulent jewellery:The oval aquamarinesabove and between your breasts,the ponderous goid ear-rings,And arm lets adornedwith cats’ eyes and chrysoberylswhich kept you chained;Or the rope of pearlshung round your neck enslavingly.He refers obliquelyTo a tree calied kolomba,(a bad, or a grieving, mother?),able to surviveTeetering on the rcck-edgewith roots going far down the cliffclinging to every moist crevice.He leaves you in his, poem branching out and blossomingas you fall to this day. 9
￼When spoken tonever to speaka word to anyoneand to keep to our rock.This irrevocable oaththey ail had to takebefore the king’s deathwhen those forest girls were stuckOn the mountain, skin dyedto look golden. Hard luck!It was a royalOld Sinhalese trick,Making a political pun to lockthe gold girls up in a vocable meaning word and rock:Letting the public try’by seductive lyricto break them freeof their graphic mental block.
￼Longing to sing and playmusicshe'd brought the luteup to her shoulderwhen the king's deathstruck a chordand being as good as gold didn’t she strike the luteto smithereens.Her loose appearance may give offence, But I'll stand up for her innocence.tWhen told that her prince was dead She tore off her flowery tiara.The blossom in her hand isn’t beckoning: It happened to fall from her head.11
￼They deck you with iove-makmg flowersarrange your hairto fail in seductive tresses put waterliiiesand a sapu bud in your handNow fair girlyou are ready for them to attach you12to the dark rock for ever
￼Some of the figures look painfully deformed: all their lustrehas long been dimmed.These were pliant girlswho had a good "imein their timewhen somebody was fond of them.13