￼In 1966, shortly after its move to Newcastie, Stand magazine (8 no.2) published a survey of contemporary writing inNorth-East England0 The editors' conclusions, given in an article by Rodney Pybus, were that most of the work by newwriters submitted for the 'regional writing' issue was 'worse than third-rate...abysmal'; the exceptions were Tom Pickard,Barry MacSweeney, and the dialect poet Ered Reed.a The Stand survey presented ' a depressing picture of theregion's literary talent'; the outlook, moreover, was said to in-lhe Norlh-Eastbe 'jpleak'. But much has happened^since 1966: several importantpoetsy'established or consolidated their reputation s ^ )—■MM— — — U— — — I— — |iTand there are also a number of talented-4^4^ writers whose work is not yet widely known. The ten North-East poets of this selection have previously only beenpublished in magazines, anthologies and pamphlets. They do not comprise a group, nor do they hold any common poetic allegiance; indeed, their only link is in being published here together.But they do share a freshness of approach to their craft which invigorates whatever style each has chosen to develop. It is my hope that this anthology will introduce their work to a wider readership. Three of them have collections of different kinds published by or forthcoming from Bloodaxe Books/, and their selections here are mainly of other poems. Any consideration of their work should also take account of those collections: David Constantine's first book, A Brightness to Cast Shadows; Vincent Morrison's pamphlet, The Season of Comfort; and Stephen Dunstan's Tarot Poems, his first publication (as well as his forthcoming book of translations of the Chinese poet Ma Zhi-yuan).O In order to place the poets of this anthology in some kindof context, I shall attempt some updating of Pybus's essay - which is still the best historical account of the literature of North-East England. The only other guide to contemporary poetryin the North-East has been William Parkinson's 4— contribution—. —*to the critical anthology British Poetry since I960 (Carcanet, 1972).This negative, didactic essay is unbalanced, in particular, by
￼i,44over-long, heavy-handed attacks on Pickard and MacSweeney, viaBasil Bunting; it ends, however, on an uncharacteristic noteof optimism:fr­it is as well that Jon Silkin and Tony Harrison are now living and working in the region; their presence, and the Stand quarterly now published in Newcastle, may well influence and encourage the next generation of poets...We can hope that [they} will find the means to express the impulse and experience of their region and produce a literature of repute, based on the best/folk tradition and continuing the high-level of achievement represented bythe novels of Sid Chaplin...But these, I shall argue, are two separate issues - sometimes complementary, sometimes n o t0P It should be possible now to consider the influence of Harrison, Silkin, and Stand. Tony Harrison’s work has presentedan inspiring example: its technical virtuosity, classical precision and colloquial vigour are so unified that the poet's tone and voice are exact, individual and unaffected., This alone would be a rare achievement nowadays, yet Harrison has soughtnot only to master(the}difficult mode of poetry but also to make it embody and serve his own cause. He has refused to detach himself from a world which would frustrate the artist's attemptuo articulate its contradictions; in this he is isolated, but not removed, for he voices both his own alienation and that of the working class, and, moreover, that of any disowned or repressed individual or people. That Harrison is a major poet has long been recognised, by poets; his poems from The Scnooi of Eloquence (Rex Collings, 1978), a continuing sequence, were said by Jeffrey Wainwright to 'speak of our culture in a way that makes them some of the most important poems of the present day' (Poetry Review,69 no.1 [1979]).mm—mmQ To have had a poet of Harrison's stature living in Newcastle has, I believe, encouraged many writers in the North-East, not least those represented in this anthology; but because he has in recent years mainly lived and worked in London and abroad, they have missed the stimulating readings, and magazine appearances of new poems have therefore assumed a special importance (it is
￼fortunatejin this respectj that many are published in Stand)„ I do not, however, find much evidence of direct poetic influence, either by Harrison or by Silkin, in the mature work of the newNorth-East writers; juh the whole it has been a case of influence by example rather than through uncritical stylisticmodelling jm rnm'm m m m m m m m m m m m m m BCfiarrisor)) has shown ways of exploring concerns that are vitally felt in the North-East:how to express what Parkinson called the region’s ’impulse and experience' with complete openness; how to balance what is salvagable and still relevant in 'folk tradition' with what thenational and international culture have to offer„ In Silkin's case, his editing of Stand (with its programme of committed art)has, I feel, been more influential than his poetry,, The presence of an international literary magasine is particularly stimulating in an area not noted for broad-mindedness; but the North-Eastnurtures a fierce spirit of independence, and this, paradoxically, fuels a drive for opennessin the regional culture„□ William Parkinson complained that modern poets in the North-Easthad lost the 'close creative relationship' with their communities which the nineteenth-century pitmap,-ppets .had dreyn uppn dtaforaifli^gflHgg?1 — 1Ji-fii— T- liitiTi11hhj ■The oral tradition, however, was a local phenomenon -to use the word, complimentarily, in Patrick Kavanagh's sense of the writer who 'is never in any doubt aboutthe social and artistic validity of his parish'. This is aquestion o belief: Kavanagh's commitment was rooted in ((Monaghan,his kingdom of 'banks and stones and every blooming thing' ( ' Inniskeen Road: July Evening'), its boundaries fixed eternally by 'incurious' black hills ( 'Shancoduff')„ Tarry Flynn, Kavanagh tells us, is'not a country man, but a man living,, And life was the same everywhere^) In the hands of a writer of genius, the intimately known local world becomes a microcosm; in 'Epic', a poem abouta dispute over the ownership of 'half a rood of rock', Homer's“ghost"whispers: 'I made the Iliad from such/ A local row ...'However, Kavanagh's definition of the 'parochial' writer (ojten eotSrtde its Irish content . , Jquotea/by defenders of "regionalism") characterises a 'mentality' which undoubtedly was a positive source of strength to poets like
￼Kavanagh, or William Barnes - ^as religion had "been for Herbert and Hopkins - but which oould as easily be applied to the dull verses of a country parson, or those of a "local poet"0Nor are such certainities as Kavanagh expresses so likely to be found now, except as negatives; or as a sign of immatureobtuseness.□ Parkinson’s attack on ^osse^North-East poets who, 'standingapart from their communities... are prone to the self-regarding excesses of an illusory idealism', displays a confused, anachronistic and doctrinaire view of poetry; it is, moreover, inconsistent both with his praise of Douglas Dunn's TerryStreet (Paber, 1969) - '(DunnJ is aware of the gulf betweenhimself and the people of the street and uses this separatenessto give us a sense of himself and them...' - and with thereality of Dunn's 'creative relationship' with the Terry Street community,, 'Terry Street,' says Parkinson, 'gives a rare senseof the quality of working-class life'; Dunn sees it differently: 'Iwas offended by their complacency: that is, towards theenvironment. . . I found the people infected by popular culture' (LondonMagazine, 19 no„8 QL979j)<> While that is a later reassessment, it is in no sense a re-writing; Dunn is sympathetic towards thepeople in most of the poems, but those which seek to show 'the country as a whole' (ibid.) through Terry Street focus his disillusionment and anger at the way their common culture has been debased or destroyed by the modern diseases of commercialisation and political self-interest (poems like 'The Clothes Pit', 'YoungWomen in Rollers', and, particularly, 'The Silences'). Dunn has become an outsider, standing apart from a working-class community whose values are no longer adequate, and which cannot be shared; his subject-matter may often be regional - life in Hull or his native Clydeside - but his concerns are wider. 'Poetry,' he has said, 'is a larger concept than nationalism or a national ideaof poetry' (Aquarius 11 Q l 9 7 ); and this, of course, is even more true of a regional idea of poetry.FI The alternative is a prescription for minor art. To concentrate on specifically local, social or contemporary issues is to narrow one's perspective to that of a "local writer", a politicalspokesman or a journalist. These limitations indeed characterise the work of the North-East's self-proclaimed "local writers"^
￼Xthe Tyneside Poets (who publish the magazine Poetry North East)\i r '*i /•maintain the poor standards noted in Pybus's account of 1966:little of their work is distinguishable, rhythmically, from prose, and much of it consists of sentimental journalism or jokey autobiography (traits typical also of the prose of "localwriters")0Q V/hen Stand was looking for signs ojf 'a strong regionalconsciousness' in the work of new writers living in the North-East, X how(^arro^was that definition? How central to a writer's workis his 'regional consciousness'? I ’m heartened by what Jon Silkin has said about 'genuinely regional literature' since then; hehas found 'an abrasive vitality in the North', and in Tom Pickard's first book, High on the Walls (Pulcrura, 1967), 'a sort of stubbornness and recalcitrance that I would associate with the Northern experience' ('The Small Magazine since I960 - a recorded conversation with Jon Silkin', British Poetry since I960)o Silkin's North is composite, including the various landscapes andcommunities of Tyneside, Coe Durham, Northumberland, and Leeds, his previous home; and Bunting's Northumbria is the old kingdom, stretching from the Humber up to the Tweed and to the west across the Pennineso William Parkinson, who believes that a distinctive regional voice is lacking in the poetry of Pickard, MacSweeneyand Bunting, does find it in 'the work of the immigrants likeJon Silkin and Tony Harrison'; yet that 'abrasive vitality' Iis, as Silkin says, of the North - in Harrison's case, one can /find it both in his poems about the North-East and in thoseabout his childhood in Leeds„ But this is still too narrow an approacho Silkin's Eillhope Wheel poems (MidNAG, 1971; The Principle of Water (Carcanet, 1974-3) express a deep-rooted historicalsympathy with the struggle of the individual against poverty and exploitation in the industrial North-East; it is the first timethat he has been able to identify himself with the region. Whilehe has written much since about Northumberland, his indignationhas not on the whole been so sharply focussed on the outrageous social conditions that the North-East has lived through; yet hehas written about the persecution of the Jews in Jerusalem andin medieval York, about love, death, grief, oppression, torture,^brutality - in short, about being 1a man living' —anddihe ^ Northern experience, while inseparable from his identity, isbut one aspect of it.
￼LHWhat I have been describing is surely committed art in itsbroadest and most proper sense. We can consider particular concerns - with work by Silkin or work published by him in Stand serving as examples - and find other poets in the North-East exploring similar areaso The historical struggle in Eillhope Wheel must have helped other poets focus their responses to the North-East, and one wondersif it didn't show the way for poems like James Longwill’s 'BobbyArnet' (see below, Po^M-)^ Jeffrey Wainwright’s poems about lifeduring the Industrial Revolution - for example '1815', firstpublished in Stand in 1968 (The Important Man ^Northern House,1970J ; Heart's Desire Qcarcanet, 1978]) - show a more restrained approach which may also have been instructivec While such poemshelp define the Northern experience, their basic concerns arewider; moreover, Stand' s internationalism provides a valuable perspective: a common chord is struck, for instance, by poetswriting about the oppressive conditions of life in Eastern Europe,the Soviet Union, and parts of Africa and Latin America,,4Many small presses and little magazines exist to publish particularly narrow areas; and they do a good job in providing a platform forpoets who share their limited concerns„ Yet too often theiradvocates will proclaim a certain approach to be the only valid concept of poetry; it seems to me that these "small critics" (why not give them the same adjective?) expect small presses to serve only these small areas - in particular, experimental and politicalwritingo The most prominent of the small critics is now Jeff Nuttall, whose monthly reviews of small press publications in The Guardian concentrate almost exclusively on experimental poetry; his4 arguments are not unflawed:in& ntcdThe pressure is such amongst the crowded readings and the hastily duplicated pages that a poet needs far more to register his professional identity in 1979 than the ability to saysomething special nicely„ Conventional articulacy and the heart's truth are all very well but the poets who emerge as the most rewarding from the seething literary scene are those who areaware that poetry is first of all made of words and that wordsare first of all made of breath, sound, time, ink, space and paper before they start to function as the bearers of dictionary meaningSo fThe Guardian, 14 July 1979]Such sophistry would be offensive if it weren't so patently absurd, It is a typical example of the small criticism (when did poetry1
￼ever serve merely to 'say something special nicely'?). The Nuttall alternative to craft and feeling is this slapdashprescription for knocking up "poems" out of hreath, ink, andthe other things, a recipe which is indeed followed by many of thew riters whom he praises (extravagantly) in his columns0 And tohese are our 'most rewarding' poets? £■■■■■■■£Reviewing the pamphlet The Season of Comfort, Jim Burns criticised Vincent Morrison for 'backing off from the contemporary' (Ambit 79 £l979}); to write about the past, or about Nature, is to 'ignore the fact fsicl that standing on a street corner in a sea of broken glass might be more typicalof the times we live in '0 I'm reminded here of Randall Jarrell's observation that 'a kind of nauseated brutality (in which the writer's main response to the world is simply to vomit) willseem to many critics and readers the inescapable truth' ('Poets, Critics, and Readers')„ Portunately, Burns'| sea of broken glassis neither wholly typical nor inescapable, and nor can it symbolise anything more than a fraction of human experience in the present daye I do not believe that one can possibly adopt this kind of street corner vantage-point and still write with authority^) APB(PI Edward Lucie-Smith, in the Penguin anthology B ritish Poetrysince 1949 (1970), categorised poetry in Newcastle as 'post-Poundian alluding .to the presence of Basil Bunting and to the group ofyoung poets then associated with him and with ^he Morden Tower - in particular Tom Pickard and Barry MacSweeney. Long before Bunting's reputation was properly established in Britain, withthe publication in 1966 of Briggflatts (by Fulcrum Press), hehad a strong following in the States among the avant-garde, the experimental writers, the Beat poets, the Black Mountain "school"; the American poets (like Greeley and Ginsberg) came to Newcastle to see Bunting, and to read at the Morden Tower, then enjoying its heyday as an important centre for the new popular poetry. The younger poets were not only reading Bunting and Pound (and Zukofsky), but were also discovering this new American poetry, little of which was then widely available in Britain; but small presses like Pulcrum, Trigram, Migrant and Grosseteste were publishing the poetry of the English and American avant-garde (including Pickard and MacSweeney). The ' post-Poundian1 group
￼in the North-East has been well served by its own presses: the Morden Tower 1 and MacSweeney’s Black Sueae Boot Press (nowin Folkestone), and later Brian Marley's Laundering Room Pressand the now flourishing Pig Press run by Ric Caddel 4)B0iHHHHNHHMMtfMPk[Tecentiy Peter Ilodgkiss ss&s brought PoetryInformation (replaced by Not Poetry) and Galloping Dog Press to Newcastle, and Colin Simms's Genera Editions is now alsoNewcastle-based„QThis strong local tradition of experimental/avant-garde writingis also something of a millstone,, When this anthology was first advertised, I was attacked by Yann Lovelock, reviews editor of Iron magazine, for claiming that it would'dispose of the notion that the departure of Tom Pickard left the North-East devoid of talented young writers',, 'Now, as things go,' I was told, 'poets like Koef Nielsen, Brian Marley, Tony Jackson, Ric Caddel, are generally reckoned to be the heirs of the departed and to share roughly the same ground as them,,' I don't dispute that the work of these writers is similar in approach to that of Pickard and MacSweeney, and I would not presume to deprecate their poetry (some of which is^g£o^); but they are the 'heirs’ only in continuing that same line. My intention was publish the best of the North-East's new generation of poets, and this I would maintain I have done; the poetry which appears in this anthology is to my mind more significant than that of the writers whomLovelock commends (all of whom have in any^case)been much more widely published in the little magazines and by the presses listedabove)o Lovelock accuses me of 'ignoring the experimental side and sticking mainly to safe traditionalists'; yet the anthology selection is quite wide-ranging, reflecting a catholicity whichI hope is evident also in the Bloodaxe list as a whole,. The phrase 'safe traditionalists' is pure jargon; one has presumably to exclude from it Eliot's 'historical sense' of tradition (which is anything but 'safe'), and to interpret it instead as the standard jibe against 'traditional' styles or modes of expression; one's 'traditional' sense of rhythm, form, sound, syntax^ipe1’ tonc^ may have been developed by poets over several centuries, but - according to the spokesmen of the avant-garde - the pressures of life today are such that 'traditional' poetry is now obsolete,
￼(9)tired, tame, academic, middle-class, irrelevant, etconfused liaison between modern poetry and pop cultureduring the 60s may have encouraged such fallacies. Of course popular writing is not necessarily significant, and often it is ephemeral (vide Michael Horovitz's Children of Albion 'underground' anthology); with its audience reduced to a (vocal) clique, the claims of the avant-garde now look rather inflated; and their pretence of authority shows an unintelligent lack of perspective,,In conclusion, I would argue that Patrick Kavanagh's view of regional poetry is oversimple; and that in the North-East thebest poets are neither inward-looking nor stand-offish. The North-East's literary tradition has become not folk-based but international in outlook. It seems to me not coincidental that several poets are also distinguished translators, notably Bunting, Harrison, Alistair Elliot, and Fleur Adcock, the current Northern Arts Literary Fellow (all four are classicists); Jon Silkin too has done translations, collaborating recently with his fellow editor David McDuff, another accomplished poet-translator0 Poetry in the North-East must not be separated from its national context; the "experimental" group is part of the present avant-garde, while the more important poets are contributing to the mainstream ofEnglish poetry. my consideration ofjrpoetfy^i?! the North-East■ M P IM should concentrate on the latter area, and in particularon the work of Tony Harrison, Jon Silkin, Rodney Pybus, Richard Kell and Alistair Elliot^ I would like to suggest that some of the poets in this anthology could be seen as extending that tradition.NEIL ASTLEYt2plcaps
￼oS / ^PREFACEIn 1966, shortly after its move to Newcastle, Stand magazine((8 (no. 2) published a survey of contemporary writing in North-East England. The editors’ conclusions, given in an article by Rodney Pybus, were that most of the work by new writers submitted for the‘regionalwriting’issuewas‘worsethanthird-rate... abysmal’; the exceptions were Tom Pickard, Barry MacSweeney, and thedialect poet Fred Reed.The Standsurvey presented ‘a depressing picture of the region’sliterary talent’; the outlook; moreover, was said to be ‘bleak’. But much has happened in the North-East since 1966: several important poets have established or consolidated their reputations; and there are also a num ber of talented new writers whose work is not yet widely known. The ten North-East poets of this selection have previously only been published in magazines, anthologies and pamphlets. They do not comprise a group, nor do they hold any common poetic allegiance; indeed, their only link is in being published here together. But they do share a freshness of approach to their craft which invigorates whatever style each has chosen to develop. It is my hope that this anthology will introducetheir work to a wider readership, three of them have collections of different kinds published by or forthcoming from Bloodaxe Books, and their selections here are mainly of other poems. Any consideration of their work should also take account of those collections: David Constantine’s first book, A Brightness to cast Shadouk V incent M orrison’s pam phlet, The Season of Comfort-, and Stephen Dunstan’s Tarot Poems, his first publication (as well as his forthcoming book of translations of the Chinese poet Ma Zhi- yuan).In order to place the poets of this anthology in some kind of context, Ishallattemptsome updating ofPybus’sessay—which is still the best historical account of the literature of North-East England. The only other guide to contemporary poetry in the North-East has been William Parkinson’s contribution to the critical anthology British Poetry since I960 (Carcanet, 1972). This negative, didactic essay is unbalanced, in particular, by over-long, heavy-handed attacks on Pickard and MacSweeney, via Basil Bunting; it ends, however, on an uncharacteristic note of optimism:It is as well thatJon Silkin and Tony Harrison are now living and working in the region; their presence, and the Stand quarterly now published in
￼Newcastle, may well influence and encourage the next generation ofpoets. . . We can hope that [they] will find the means to express the impulse and experience of their region and produce a literature of repute, based on the best of folk tradition and continuing the high-level of achievement represented by the novels of Sid Chaplin . . .But these, 1 shall argue, are two separate issues—sometimes complementary, sometimes not.It should be possible now to consider the influence of Harrison, Silkin, and Stand. Tony Harrison’swork has presented an inspiring example: its technical virtuosity, classical precision and colloquial vigour are so unified that the poet’s tone and voice are exact, individual and unaffected. This alone would be a rare achievement nowadays, yet Harrison has sought not only to master/difficult mode of poetry but also to make it embody and serve nis own cause. He has refused to detach himselffrom aworld which wouldj frustrate the artist’s attempt to articulate its contradictions; in this A he is isolated, but not removed, for he voices both his ownalienation and that of the working class, and, moreover, that of any disowned or repressed individual or people. That Harrison is a major poet has long been recognised, by poets; his poems from The SchoolofEloquence {Rex Collings, 1978), a continuing sequence, w e r e s a i d b y J e f f r e y W a i n w r i g h t t o ‘s p e a k o f o u r c u l t u r e i n a w a y that makes them some of the most important poems of the present day’ {Poetry Review, 69 no.l [1979]).To have had a poet ofHarrison[s stature living in Newcastle has, I believe, encouraged many writers in the North-East, not least those represented in this anthology; but because he has in recent years mainly lived and worked in London and abroad, they have missed the stimulating readings, and magazine appearances of new poems have therefore assumed a special importance (it is fortunate in this respect that many are published in Stand). I do not, however, find much evidence of direct poetic influence, either by Harrison or by Silkin, in the mature work of the new North-East writers; on the whole it has been a case ofinfluence by example rather than through uncritical stylistic modelling. Harri­ son has shown ways of exploring concerns that are vitally felt in the North-East: how to express what Parkinson called the region’s‘impulse and experience’with complete openness; how to balance what is salvagable and still relevant in ‘folk tradition’ with what the national and international culture have to offer. In Silkin’s case, his editing ofStand(with its programme ofcommitted art) has, I feel, been more influential than his poetry. The%yA./ XaVO ''(C O O 'tT zdvct.iirt^rXo
￼...William Parkinson complained that modern poets in the North-East had lost the ‘close creative relationship’ with their communities which the nineteenth-century pitman-poets had drawn upon for their songs. The oral tradition, however, was a local phenomenon—or‘parochial’, to use the word, compliment- arily, in Patrick Kavanagh’s sense of the writer who ‘is never in any doubt about the social and artistic validity of his parish’. This is a question ofbelief: Kavanagh’scommitment was rooted in Monag­ han, his kingdom of‘banks and stones and every blooming thing’ (‘Inniskeen Road: July Evening’), its boundaries fixed eternally by ‘incurious’black hills (‘Shancoduff). Tarry Flynn, Kavanagh tells us, is ‘not a country man, but a man living. And life was the same everywhere’. In the hands of a writer of genius, the intimately known local world becomes a microcosm; in ‘Epic’, a poem about a dispute over the ownership o f‘half a rood of rock’, Homer’s “ghost” whispers: ‘I made the Iliad from such/A local row . . . ’ Howeve^ Kavanagh’s definition of the ‘parochial’ writer (often quoted outside its Irish context by defenders of “regionalism”) characterises a ‘mentality’ which undoubtedly was a positive source of strength to poets like Kavanagh, or W illiam Barnes— just as religion had been for Herbert and Hopkins—but whichcould as easily be applied to the dull verses ofa country parson, or those of a “local poet”. Nor are such certainities as Kavanagh expresses so likely to be found now, except as negatives; or as a sign of immature obtuseness.Parkinson’s attack on those North-East poets who, ‘standing apart from their communities ... are prone to the self-regarding excesses of an illusory idealism’, displays a confused, anachronistic and doctrinaire view of poetry; it is, moreover, inconsistent both with his praise of Douglas Dunn’s Terry Street (Faber, 1969)— ‘[Dunn] isawareofthegulfbetweenhimselfandthepeopleofthe street and uses this separateness to give us a sense of himself and them ... ’—and with the reality of Dunn’s ‘creative relationship’ with the Terry Street community. ‘Terry Street,’ says Parkinson, ‘g i v e s a r a r e s e n s e o f t h e q u a l i t y o f w o r k i n g - c l a s s l i f e ’ ; D u n n s e e s i t differently: ‘I was offended by their complacency: that is, towards the environm ent . . . I found the people infected by popular culture’ (London Marine, 19 no.8 [1979])- While that is a laterPACtE HclEtpresence of an international literary magazine is particularly stimulating in an area not noted for broad-mindedness; but the North-East also nurtures a fierce spirit of independence, and this, paradoxically, fuels a drive for openness in the regional culture.
￼f(/*reassessment, it is in no sense a re-writing; Dunn is sympathetic towards the people in most of the poems, but those which seek to show ‘the country as a whole’(ibid.) through Terry Street focus his disillusionment and anger at the way their common culture has been debased or destroyed by the modern diseases ofcommercial­ isation and political self-interest (poems like ‘The Clothes Pit’, ‘Y oung W om en in Rollers’, and, particularly, ‘the Silences’). Dunn has become an outsider, standing apart from a working- class community whose values are no longer adequate, and which cannot be shared; his subject-matter may often be regional—life in Hull or his native Clydeside—but his concerns are wider. ‘Poetry,’ he has said, ‘is a larger concept than nationalism or a national idea of poetry'jAquarius 11 [1979]); and this, of course, is even more true of a regional idea of poetry.The alternative is a prescription for minor art To concentrate on specifically local, social or contemporary issues is to narrow one’sperspectiveto thatofa“localwriter”,apoliticalspokesman or a journalist. These limitations indeed characterise the work of the North-East’s self-proclaimed “local writers’^ th e Tyneside Poets (who publish the magazine Poetry North East) m aintainthe poor standards noted in Pybus’s account of 1966: lirt4tf'dtthcir f W»H- distinguishable,-rhythmically, from prose,-and much of-it-(Yonsists of sentimental journalism or jokey autobiography (traits typical also of the prose of “local writers”).W h e n Stand(was looking for signs of ‘a strong regional consciousness ’in they work of new writers living in the North-East, how narrow was that definition? How central to a writer’s work is his ‘regional consciousness’? I’m heartened by whatJon Silkin has said about ‘genuinely regional literature’ since then; he has found ‘an abrasive vitality in the North’, and in Tom Pickard’s first book, High on the Walls (Fulcrum, 1967), ‘a sort of stubbornness and recalcitrance that I would associate with the Northern experience’ (‘The Small Magazine since I960—a recorded conversation with Jon Silkin’, British Poetry since I960). Silkin’s N orth is composite, including the various landscapes and communities of Tyneside, Co. Durham, Northumberland, and Leeds, his previous home; and Bunting’s Northumbria is the old kingdom, stretching from the Humber up to the Tweed and to the west across the Pennines. William Parkinson, who believes that a distinctive regional voice is lacking in the poetry of Pickard, MacSweeney and Bunting, does find it in ‘the work of the immigrants like Jon Silkin and Tony Harrison’; yet that ‘abrasive vitality’is, as Silkin says, of theNorth—in Harrison’s case, one can find it both in his poemsbracket^)—MILLER^—^ervvb.ncw
￼about the North-East and in those about his childhood in Leeds. But this is still too narrow an approach. Silkin’s Killhope Wheel poems (MidNAG, 1971; The Principle of Water [Carcanet, 1974]) express a deep-rooted historical sympathy with the struggle of the individual against poverty and exploitation in the industrial North-East; it is the first time that he has been able to identify himselfwith the region. While he has written much since about Northumberland, his indignation has not on the whole been so sharply focussed on the outrageous social conditions that the North-East has lived through; yet he has written about the persecution ofthejews injerusalem and inmedievalYork, about love, death, grief, oppression, torture,/N orthern experience, while inseparable from his identity, is but one aspect of itWhat I have been describing is surely committed art in its broadest and most proper sense. We can consider particular concerns—with work by Silkin or work published by him in Stand serving as examples—and find other poets in the North-East exploring similar areas. The historical struggle in Killhope Wheel must have helped other poets focus their responses to the North- East, and one wonders if it didn’t show the way for poems likeJames Longwill’s‘Bobby Arnet’(see below, p.74).Jeffrey Wain- wright’s poems about life during the Industrial Revolution—for example ‘1815’, first published in Standin 19/8 {TheImportantMan [Northern House, 1970]; Heart'sDesire [Carcanet, 1978])—show a more restrained approach which may also have been instructive. While such poems help define the Northern experience, their basic concerns are wider; moreover, Stand’s internationalism provides a valuable perspective: a com m on chord is struck, for instance, by poets writing about the oppressive conditions of life in Eastern Europe, the Soviet Union, and parts ofAfrica and Latin America.Many small presses and little magazines exist to publish particularly narrow areas; and they do a good job in providing a platform for poets who share their limited concerns. Yet too often their advocates will pr^fclaim a certain approach to be the only valid concept of poetry; it seems to me that these “small critics” (why not give them the same adjective?) expect small presses to serve only these small areas—in particular, experimental and politicalCt ,Tl - im m inent of the small critics is now Jeff NuttaH whose monthly reviews ofsmall press publications in TkCBLEAK PA6€ HCEE
￼add»r+The pressure is such amongst the crowded readings and the hastily duplicated pages that a poet needs far more to register his professional identity in 1979 than the ability to say something special nicely. Convention­ al articulacy and the heart's truth are all very well but the poets who emerge as the most rewarding from the seething literary scene are those who are aware that poetry is first of all made of words and that words are first of all made of breath, sound, time, ink, space and paper before they start to function as the bearers ofdictionary meanings. [TheGuardian, 14July 1979]JervcS16 |JQPrefaceGuardian concentrate almost exclusively on experimental poetry; his arguments are not unflawed:add Vffc#Such sophistry would be offensive if it weren’t so patently absurd. It is a typical example of the small criticism (when did poetry ever serve merely to ‘say something special nicely’?). The Nuttall alternative to craft and feeling is this slapdash prescription for knocking up “poems” out ofbreath, ink, and the other things, a recipe which is indeed followed by many of the writers whom he praises (extravagantly) in his columns. And these are our ‘most rewarding’ poets?Reviewing the pamphlet The Season of Comfort, Jim Burns c r i t i c i s e d V i n c e n t M o r r i s o n f o r ‘b a c k i n g o f f f r o m t h e c o n t e m p o r ­ ary’{Ambit 79 [1979]); to write about the past, or about Nature, is to ‘ignore the fact [sic] that standing on a street corner in a sea of broken glass might be more typical of the times we live in’. I’m reminded here of Randall Jarrell’s observation that ‘a kind of l^iauseated brutality (in which the writer’s main response to the world is simply to vomit) will seem to many critics and readers the inescapable truth’ (‘Poets, critics, and Readers’). Fortunately, Burns’ sea of broken of glass is neither wholly typical nor inescapable, and nor can it symbolise anything more than a fraction of hum an experience in the present day. I do not believe that one can possibly adopt this kind of street corner vantage- point and still write with authority.Edward Lucie-Smith, in the Penguin anthology British Poetry since 1945 (1970), categorised poetry in Newcastle as ‘post- Poundian’, alluding to the presence of Basil Bunting and to the group of young poets then associated with him and with the MordenTower—inparticularTom PickardandBarryMacSweeney. Long before Bunting’s reputation was properly established in Britain, with the publication in 1966 of Briggflatts (by Fulcrum Press), he had a strong following in the States among the avant-/arde, the experimental writers, the Beat poets, the Black Mountain seEAtc pAee neee0 cnlCSV VuV
￼"t I A< .it?school”; the American poets (like Creeley and Ginsberg) came to Newcastle to see Bunting, and to read at the Morden Tower, then enjoying its heyday as an important centre for the new popular poetry. The younger poets were not only reading Bunting and Pound (and Zukofsky), but were also discovering this new American poetry, little of which was then widely available in Britain; but small presses like Fulcrum, Trigram, Migrant and Grosseteste were publishing the poetry of the English and American avant-garde (including Pickard and MacSweeney). The ‘post-Poundian’ group in the North-East has been well served by its own presses: the Morden Tower imprint and MacSweeney’s Black Suede Boot Press (now in Folkestone), and later Brian Marley’s Laundering Room Press and the now flourishing Pig Press run by Ric Caddel; recently Peter Hodgkiss brought Poetry Information (replaced by Not Poetry) and Galloping Dog Press to Newcastle, and Colin Simms’s Genera Editions is now also Newcastle-based.This strong local tradition of experimental/avant-gatde writing is also something of a millstone. When this anthology was first advertised, I was attacked by Yann Lovelock, reviews editor of Iron magazine, for claiming that it would ‘dispose of the notion that the departure of Tom Pickard left the North-East devoid of talented young writers’. ‘Now, as things go,’I was told, ‘poets like Koef Nielsen, Brian Marley, Tony Jackson, Ric Caddel, are generally reckoned to be the heirs of the departed and to shareroughly the same ground as them.’I don’t dispute thatjjie work of these writers is similar in approach to that of Pickard and MacSweeney, and I would not presume to deprecate their poetry(some of which is very fine); but they are the ‘heirs’ only in continuing that same line. My intention was to publish the best of North-East’s new generation of poets, and this I would/ ----J A — -rrmgt more significant than that of the writers whom/ ^Lovelock commends (all of whom have in any <^eTreen much more widely published in the little magazines and by the presses listed above). Lovelock accuses me of‘ignoring the experimental side and sticking mainly to safe traditionalists’; yet the anthology selection is quite wide-ranging, reflecting a catholicity7which I hope is evident also in the Bloodaxe list as a whole. The phrase ‘safe traditionalists’is pure jargon; one has presumably to exclude from it Eliot’s'historical sense’ of tradition (which is anything but ‘safe’), and to interpret it instead as the standard jibe againstg£EAK PAGt HQStmaintain 1have donejjjthe poetry \l[ddrnjifjiijjjjg>in this anthologyreface IOJHJ17
￼Preface‘traditional’ styles or modes of expression; one’s ‘traditional’ sense of rhythm, form, sound, syntax, tone, may have been developed by poets over several centuries, but— according to the spokesmen of the avant-garde—thepressures oflife today are such that ‘traditional’ poetry is now obsolete, tired, tame, academic, middle-class, irrelevant, etc. The confused liaison between modern poetry and pop culture during the 60s may have encouraged such fallacies. O f course popular writing is not necessarily significant, and often itisephemeral(videMichaelHorovitz’sChildrenofAlbion ‘underground’ anthology); with its audience reduced to a (vocal) clique, the claims of the avant-garde now look rather inflated; and their pretence ofauthority shows an unintelligent lack ofperspect­ ive.In conclusion, I would argue that Patrick Kavanagh’s view of regional poetry is oversimple; and that in the North-East the best poets are neither inward-looking nor stand-offish. The North- East’s literary tradition has become not folk-based but inter­ national in outlook. It seems to me not coincidental that several poets are also distinguished translators, notably Bunting, Harrison, Alistair Elliot, and Fleur Adcock, the current Northern Arts Literary' Fellow (all four are classicists); Jon Silkin too has done translations, collaborating recently with his fellow editor David McDuff, another accomplished poet-translator. Poetry in the North-East must not be separated from its national context; the “experimental” group is part of the present avant-garde, while the more important poets are contributing to the mainstream of English poetry. Any consideration of contemporary poetry in the North-East should concentrate on the latter area, and in particular on the work ofTony Harrison,Jon Silkin, Rodney Pybus, Richard Kell and Alistair Elliot I would like to suggest that some of the poets in this anthology could be seen as extending that tradition.
￼pother. /' »21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28Silent Ancestry /■We arc drunk/-TollesburyAt Evening‘All day north’‘At the field’s corner’ Artesian‘The shack’s chawn timbers’ Plain Kate‘Footprints’The Remaining/GEORGE CHARLTON29 Night Shift Workers29 Sea Coal30 Friday Evenings31 Retired Men31 Hunting the Hare32 Durham Miners’ Gala32 Remainders33 An Affair of Places34 A Return to Newcastle34 Rooney’s Rainbow35 Singleton35 Postcard Poems37 Dog Exercising Man37 Gipsies38 Missing38 War Widow39 Researching W ar Poetry40 The Done War41 Post Op.ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS 11 PREFACEPETER ARMSTRONGCONTENTS
￼kZW^r without End----------- 48 Caravan. *****DAVID CONSTANTINE42 ‘Eyes wide with the moon’42 ‘As our bloods separate’43 Birdsong43 ‘Daffodils in vases’43 ‘But most you are like’44 ‘Someone at least’44 Locus Amoenus44 Musee du Louvre45 Musee Rodin45 Chartres and Avignon45 Gothic or Classical46 ‘Themindthen’46 Rodin 46 RenoirSTEPHEN DUNSTAN47 Black Earth47 man observing landscape feels alienQ acceoG )-4749 49OctoberNight Thoughts‘The marshes are evil’ Spartacans51 And then there was52 ‘What am I writing about’53 I believe in stolen orangesDESMOND GRAHAM54 Remembering the War 56 ‘I have turned’56 The Parthenon Frieze58 Portraits of the Artist59 Isabella in the Mirror60 RainQCKw ceu/c 6262 AfterwardsThe choice: Two Riddles of Feeling 63 ‘I am lying stretched out’‘•'Tomb* of -the unknown dLezd
￼63 Death64 A Set of Love Poems X 66 Living on an IslandPETE LAVER67 Placing Sensitivities67 Two W ood-Gathering Poems69 Cragfast70 Rydal M ount, 184071 At Blintarn Moss71 Speeding72 Holding the Impulse73 That Mythical PoetJAMES LONGWILL74 My Father 74 Bobby Arnet80 The Hawk81 BlackamoreVINCENT MORRISON83 The Schonau Express83 The Polish Rider84 Our Lady of the Nettles85Gwen PullenClosing Time86 In Memoriam Michael Smith Killed 188087 In Sickness and in Death88 Henry’s Dilemma88 The Incas8589The Eve of AbdicationLAWRIE WALKER90 Landscape90 Head (Christ) XVIth Century91 Old Master93 F.loisp93 Seaside 194394 Skiddaw /W ar Effort96 Reasons for not enteringMIKE WILKIN97 The Intrusion97 Autumn98 At the Start of Day98 M etam orphosisMoment100 Disturbance: 1 a.ta100 ForJean 102 Haiku99
￼yfGEORGE CHARLTON.I0£c\i?>pt t*ic' C A P^>CONTENTS<r mmT'thin role^A —. X3He«v\iJNbcMTrr\C 2s.ocznumeral ± lOOcro 3j f y r~ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS L_i PREFACEI n d l n T - ^ l O IINDENI21 21 22 23 24 24 25 26 27 27 28y3fARMSTRONG ©Silent Ancestry ’We are drunk1Tollesbury At Evening'All day north''At the field's corner' Artesian'The shack's chawn timbers' Plain Kate■i'Footprints' The Remainings#-S29 Night Shift Workers29 Sea Coal30 Friday Evenings31 Retired Men31 Hunting the Hare32 Durham Miners' Gala32 Remainders^ mocniTAnAffairofPlaces3334 A Return to Newcastle34 Rooney's Rainbow35 Singleton35 Podtcard Poems37 Dog Exercising Man37 Gipsies38 Missing38 War Widow39 Researching War Poetry40 The Done War41m Post O^v,bold0A■q 7 <3©
￼«*-.,DAYID CONSTANTINE42 Eyes wide with the moon' 42f::As our bloods separate' 43 Birdsong&  43  43  44  44  44  45  45  45  46  46  46■a#'Daffodils in vases' 'But most you are like' 'Someone at least'Locus Amoenus Musee^du Louvre^f ^ cotC. sect-nCJj----------Black Earth47 Man observing landscape feels alien 47 War without End|43 Empty House48 Caravan49 October49 Night Thoughts50 'The marshes are evil'50 'Tombs of the unknown dead'51 Spartacans51 And then there was52 'What am I writing about*53 I believe in stolen oranges■a*«-DEgyr0ND GRAHAMMuse^HodinChartres and AvignonGothic or Classical 'The mind then'Rodin Renoir•e-STEPHEH EUHSIAHUA545656585960626263m 11 am lying stretched out'iiRemembering the War 'I have turned'The Parthenon Prieze Portraits of the ArtistIsabella in the Mirror RainThe Choice: Two Riddles of Peeling /a AfterwardsPfX:£ 7 LNI>SV< --
￼#83 83 84 85 85 86 87 88 88 89The Schonau ExpressThe Polish RiderOur Lady of the NettlesGwen PullenClosing TineIn Memoriam- Michael Smith Killed 1880 In Sickness and in DeathHenry's DilemmaThe IncasThe Eve of Abdication0LandscapeHead (Christ) XVIth Century Old MasterJ .J^ ~190 90 91  67  67  69  70  71  71  72J73BLAMES74 74 80 81Placing Sensitivities Two Wood-Gathering Poems CragfastpaH | 6 3 ;I cl jPh : D e a t h^- vA ^ove?oems J66 Living.on an Island■PETE LAVER©Rydal Mount, 1840 At B1intarn Moss SpeedingHolding -the Impulse That Mythical PoetLQNGWILL ^My Rather Bobby Arnet The Hawk Blackamore^-VINCENT MORRISONc©93 Eloise93 a Seaside 1943 941T1 Skidd aw0!EbcAdI PHsE 8( ends
￼[95QJWar Effort\96T Reasons for not entering197 97 98 9899 100 100 1023# 103The IntrusionAutumnAt the Start of Day Metamorphosis MomentDisturbance: 1 a.m. Dor JeanHaikuL bBioGRAPHic.iL5?notes1 PA£E 9EMOS