￼AT THE GRAVE OF THE UNKNOWN AFRICAN -1-Two round, cocoa faces, carved on whitewashed headstone protect your grave against hellfire and brimstone.Those cherubs with puffed cheeks, as if chewing gum, signal how you got here and where you came from.More than two and a half centuries after your death, the barefaced fact that you’re unnamed feels like defeat.I got here via White Ladies Road and Black Boy’s Hill, clues lost in these lopsided stones that Henbury’s vandalhelps to the ground and Henbury’s conservationist tries to rectify, cleaning the vandal’s pissy love-nest.African slave without a name, I’d call this homeby now. Would you? Your unknown soldier’s tombstands for shipload after shipload that docked, unloaded, watered, scrubbed, exercised and restockedthousands more souls for sale in Bristol’s port; cab drivers speak of it all with yesterday’s hurt.The good conservationist calls it her three hundred year war; those raids, deals, deceit and capture (a sore still raw).St. Paul’s, Toxteth, Brixton, Tiger Bay and Handsworth: petrol bombs flower in the middle of roads, a sudden growthat the feet of police lines longer than any cricket pitch. African slave, your namelessness is the wick and petrol mix.Each generation catches the one fever love can’t appease, nor molotov cocktails, nor when they embrace in a peacefar from that three-named, two-bit vandal and conservationist binning beer cans, condoms and headstones in big puzzle-pieces.
￼-2-Stop there black Englishman before you tell a bigger lie.You mean me well by what you say but I can’t stand idly by.The vandal who keeps coming and does what he calls fucks on the cool gravestones, also pillages and wrecks.If he knew not so much my name but what happened to Africans, he’d maybe put in an hour or two collecting his Heinekens;like the good old conservationist, who’s earned her column inch, who you knock, who I love without knowing her name.The dead can’t write, nor can we sing (nor can most living). Our ears (ifyou can call them ears) make no good listening.Say what happened to me and countless like me, all anon. Say it urgently. Mean times may bring back the water cannon.I died young, but to age as a slave would have been worse.What can you call me? Mohammed. Homer. Hannibal Jesus.Would it be too much to have them all? What are couples up to when one reclines on the stones and is ridden by the other?Will our talk excite the vandal? He woz ere, like you are now, armed with a knife, I could see trouble on his creased brow,love-trouble, not for some girl but for this village.I share his love and would have let him spoil my image,if it wasn’t for his blade in the shadow of the church wall taking me back to my capture and long sail to Bristol,then my sale on Black Boy’s Hill and disease ending my days: I sent a rumble up to his sole; he scooted, shocked and dazed.Here the sentence is the wait and the weight is the sentence. I’ve had enough of a parish where the congregation can’t sing.Take me where the hymns sound like a fountain-washed canary, and the beer-swilling, condom wielding vandal of Henbury,reclines on the stones and the conservationist mounts him,and in my crumbly ears there’s only the sound of them sinning.
￼1972Year of departures and arrivals,Goodbyes and hellos,big hugs and waves,Promises and sworn affadavitsof the soul, acrosstime zones and seas,blood ties and wet eyes.Rain sagged power lines after it rained:miniature silver bats hung out to dry;seamless pockets of light; colourlesstadpoles and targets. We pelted themto see light shatter.Light fell in sprinklesour stones loosened.The ones we missed did disappearingacts, fuelling talk about how eachhad gone to heavenin a great handthat grips a raindrop/between the indexfinger and thumb,and keeps a raindrop’ssad, teardrop, shape;each one raised to where tired raindrops go,where they never dry up or lose shape:join us, we prosper.
￼CANARDThe days lance off windscreens blindingly.Nights fall hard on distressed furniture,on our heads soaked by pink soft tone bulbs.Dark glasses are worn in and outdoors.Pidgeons neck, preening on ledges tenfloors up. Come, there is room for another.Kiss the nights and days goodbye. You’re dizzy;when those birds push away, follow me.
￼DOMESTIC FLIGHTI heard what I took for wind chimes 3000 feet above London’s lights, each light a small sound.The pearl necklaces of traffic break, trying to get roundmy neck of the woods.The Thames ribbed and corseted by traffic despite its peregrinations in a black wetsuit.Occasionally real diamonds startle at high points in the city.Gold is on the horizon, a rim.Some distance below us an insectwith a compound look and rotating wings hightails it home with bare ski feet.The river is Sanskrit in black ink scribbling away into the dark, turning over with each tide.
￼GREENWICH REACHMy mind fastened onto the rod. The fishes that are there answermy hook’s singular enquiryonce they have read the correct line:"How do I know for sure you’re fish and not pieces of old rubbish?"Typically, fishes replyby swallowing the hook and bait.The Fisher of Men is Old Nickwho wields a big death-dealing stick,he wishes to rejuvenatethe Thames, not with scaly fishes.He means to relocate people.The question his hook asks doublesas his hungry hook’s sole answer: "You really don’t want to die?You don’t really have to die!" Death winks at you in the water.Take the niggling, needling bait.Let your poor soul swim off the hookas a fish, not like those big fins stuck at Woolwich, too proud to eat,too fat to sink to a sound sleep. A fish’s nightmare: to be in airlike the thinner half of a line; to belong to a school whose daynever ends, like those stranded fins floating in a giant soup, the Thames.
￼STONE NESSThe river bends back on itselfas ifto assess its own considered progress or missionThe river counters this double back move with a twist in an opposite chartless directionThe river sheds old skin in waves currentsand sea tides a snake renewing reaching perfection
￼SILVER SONGI know little about water, even less about light;all I see is the quick silverdancing there day and night.I want it all in my pocket.I wish it was my bank.In dream after dream I lock it up like fish in a tank.Don’t ask what light has done to me, or what water has said;Not much, I’ll say, they looked through me like I wasn’t there or dead.Miles clocked up on city bridges, dawn and dusk by those shores,countless flat stones found and skidded on water’s polished floor.Water and light, I must decline your invitation to meto dive and dive again for coins that you two mint for free.
￼MAR- 6-93 SAT 17:46 ENGLISH DEPT FAX NO. 4135422141SONNETS FROM WHITLEY BAYTroubled but not distressed.’(from a window in Durham Cathedral)-1-Stretches of this country smell so bad,I apologise, We laugh at your, T d think About my love for an Island that stinks." Those hours we took to find the North had Become a straight line: imperceptible curves Broken by an occasional roundabout,Until talk ran out and we banned ourselves From idle thoughts about the distant South,Wake up love. We’ve long passed the border. The South is irredeemable. The slanted light From the early summer sun is colder,Now it casts elongated shadows of you and I Ascending the stairs to our love-nestWhere we smell tired and unwilling to rest. -2-We always star in one another’s dreamsIn full technicolour and super sixteen.We fall asleep like spoons and only turn When one or the other decides to turn. Morning is a silence that won’t fracture.An elbow-room closeness and the odd gesture Confirms the other’s thoughts in sea-air thick With desire. We nod our approval at brickIn a city where I first said, I love you,Climbing the cathedral’s 325 steps to viewOne shire shouldering the next, like molars,As God would have it or Buddha, or some polar Icecap and then the warming of the globe, Exactly as the heat I feel when inside you.
￼These are the people I told you about,The ones with mostly goodness in their mouths. They treat us like old friends come back at last. The pints you and I lever to nought renew fast, Faster than we can toast the water of Tyneside. Late into the evening we find seats side by side. Our legs touch and when I shift it’s to feel your hip As I see it through this straight glass at my lip^.I’ve brought you here to be undressed by allTheir kind and hungry eyes, only to takeYou to a Hi-Fi lit dark, Motown Soul,And enough spring water by the bed to slakeThe thirst of two flushed, open-mouthed lovers, Through locked-eyes, locked-arms, lockcd-hips hours.4My love you fill my head to distraction.I am pacing a room you hardly looked into, Furthest from the bedroom-cum-granaryWhere we lived and loved and woke in an aviary That quietened as the light intensifiedAnd objects muddled by the dark, clarified.All that night nothing could come between us,A sliver of light or dark couldn’t separate us.By morning the bed had split into half- Us in a dividing current on two rafts;Us in our deep dreams, private and sweet. How did we drift apart, even in sleep? One look from you of panic, loss, love, And I leapt from my raft to share yours.
￼I hold up your 501s against my waistTo get the measure of you: come back, now, From that big, big city that pulled you away,To this one main street, coastal town,With five minute jams and one of most things.I knew between us, me and Whitley Bay,We couldn’t make you stay. We tried everything: Flora and fauna, the seas light displays.Your long, elegant legs opened fluently.I eased into a wet, warm, silky placeThat made us gasp, quicken, then rock gently- Our eyes searching one another’s eyes and face, When not one of ninety nine cars registered Passing the house in the rush-hour was heard.-6-This kind of loving wrecks the body,Makes it impossible to function properly.You wake up mid-morning feeling like the night before. But to go back to bed would turn your head forever.You stay on your feet and sway like a ship Becalmed, waiting for anything to happen, to slip Your world back into orbit, but nothing does, Except the light slips and you register a dull pulse.The ship is hers and the sea is hers, the lightYou see the world by, hers; the loving that night Was all hers; the feeling that you’re wrecked, hers.The love you think is a blessing is a curse,A weakness, something not hers, but yours: stop, Before you have no pulse, before you drop.
￼1:MAR- 6-93 SAT 17:47 ENGLISH DEPT FAX NO. 4135422141 P.10You're in the bedroom, I'm in some g^m.I'm wanting to grow more big, youdoubly thin.Our love is somewhere halfwav/oetween the two, Looking fol\someone that’s neither me nor you.You ask, what’s up? I haye to tell you straight, Our precious lov&s in trouble, the worst state,You stop in recognition, give me your all, I start to talk but/reall}N^ant to bawl.Love was the/Eve that madOdife with you Eden. Now love’s gone my life’s the Vorld’s worst garden.Look atyhow our love ends in some\rorridor, That's^nobody's quarters, nor a safe rhjor:When all we ever wanted and couldn’t get eqough of Was love, just love, pure love and more love.-8-Your touch, I’d nearly forgot ton your touch! And you've been gone less than a month, much- Less; yet here I am using poetry as hypeTo conjure you from a Daguerreotype;From a past neither of us could have known. The fine tremour in your hands is mine now,As is that chain of sweat on your upperlip.I offer my China silk hanky whose tipSticks out of my top left hand jacket pocketAnd a half-smilc: take it, use it to mopThe sweat beaded on fur so delicateIt might be kissed away, not electrocuted.All I can do is call you up and hope you’ll come, And pray that in calling you, no harm’s done./
￼-9-The miles between you and I open up.The days stretch out against all my wishes.I fight betrayal when a hand brushes mine, Prefering a bruise from an upper cutDelivered by one of Whitley Bay’s British Movement. A stranger’s eyes make four with mine, I hot up instantly like a four bar bluesLaunched by Muddy Waters or B.B. King.Not so long ago we watched a moon in a shoe Step from that shoe which changed to something We couldn’t name, as clouds do, then the moon Perched on a lake big like the sea; that moon Looked like it owned the lake and all around. But we watched it fall into that lake and drown.r- 10-When I turn my back on this North of NorthsAnd I kiss you goodbye, how come it hurts?When sealit winds loosen a stinging rainOn Whitley Bay, your tears drown out mine.This curved beach of seaweed and stones Shows from my wavy footprints I’m all alone.The waves form an orderly queue to see Who’s the miserable man bringing misery.When those waves wreck in despair on sandstone, It’s my back breaking with my need for home.I give up town and sea for glass and concrete, And a capital adding to itself,House by red brick house on the For Sale shelf, And new-post-code street by tarmacked street.f
￼FRAIL DEPOSITS( for Wilson Harris )
￼The Trench RevisitedW e’re being driven past when you point to Where you’d pushed in a friend long, long ago, Into what was a trench, to test its depth.You say it taught you how a civilisation, Feeling a blow or tug may still not knowA hand’s involved, so can’t feel indebted.I was falling, horizontally, justTo keep up and lucky to win your trust.Push him again, he’ll fall on land that’s dryThis time and think nothing of it, and you’ll Bank all that knowledge lifted from the sight Your friend made clad in mud, convinced totally That he slipped and your hand on his ribcage Was your brave, unlucky, one-hand-clap save!
￼A Jealous GodThe light on our first morning at breakfastIs such that three women as many hundredsOf yards away in pleated, cotton frocks’/asBlinding as if the green, yellow and redAre light sources and we’re in some studioWithin touching distance of them; we lookTheir way, quiet and still, more like studyThan look, they are grouped close, signing their talk.The sun is a jealous God are your words. Suddenly nothing means much anymore; Watching those three women, a timeless world Regards us as much as we regard her:We feed like enraged Ugolino fed,Though captive, on his captured jailer’s head.
￼- iii -Bone Flute"This your son?" enquires the curator As we waltz in for our official tour.You finger the thousand year flute of bone As if about to burst out with a tune.You tell how the bone came from an enemy, Morsels of whose flesh is consumed by them.When air is blown into the fashioned bone,The enemy’s knowhow and plans are summoned.The flute I’m trying to blow a tune on Belongs to you, got by me over years fromStringing your thoughts sentence by sentence, Or what must stand for you in your absence:Having to check when I’ve said something To see if it’s yours since it has your ring./
￼- iv - SeawallYou explain rudimentary quantum theory: The frailty of us jetting above weather From one world touching down in another With a wheel-screech equaling our surprise.Ah, to leave marks in this life that survive! That outstrip the skids of a jet’s tyre!The stretch of seawall we walk looks breached. A man who seems too fit to beg wants change.The sea is muddy, loud and creased in the distance. We have to lean a little into a welcome breeze, Our heads bowed from the direct beat of sun.The soldiers in barracks reach us in waves Dictated by the wind’s direction and pace; / Dear God, I think, don’t let this moment pass.A-
￼Rain on the slate roof and more rain collects in gutters then down drains.Where does the picture come from of it falling up? I hear a rhythm:drips, slips, taps, smatterings rattles; out of this a pattern surfacesthat is thought itself. Then the thought purely to do with rain, turns righton itself, as if against all that water washing the world, reverses waterup drains to rise off the roofslatesto where it’s still, floats, and is weightless.
￼- ii -Cold in a room that won’t be driven out by heat, hangs solid like a gas lanternor mosquito net or drapes or a web dangling preciously in a strip of light.I look at why it has settled for here.The shape of the room is no longer room-shape but the form cold takes settling in a place;and I don’t belong; heat doesn’t belong.I am no longer simply feeling cold,I am being asked to leave, pushed outby it into another cold, into the openwhere size and blue puts the cold in capitals.t
￼Early morning light weighs nothing. Lacking the conviction,it cuts in windows, but avoids corners; filling the room with live shadows.The roof over my headtakes on extra layers and new pressures.I am instructed not to move, even a mere flickercould demolish this delicate balance. The main beam is not the main beam I takeit for but the veryweakness I see and criticise in light.I begin this apology,noiseless, urgent and scaredthat the roof might collapse and light fall flush on me, and I might end up crushed.
￼NOTTING HILL-i-car-ni-val car-ni-val car-ni-val this is car-ni-valpeacocks with feathers of the rainbow wings’ spread held all daythe robes of kings drag yards behind heads-above-their-own crowns swaycar-ni-val car-ni-val car-ni-val this is car-ni-valbare-b^ced straight-backed princes strapped to the steel pan and the bassprincess in a tassle of diamonds glitters as she rattles her waistcar-ni-val car-ni-val car-ni-val this is car-ni-valfreedom fighters in battle dressthe spirit of their banners in their dancetinselled toddlers on shoulders wide-eyed in the wildest of dreamscar-ni-val car-ni-val car-ni-val this is car-ni-val/