￼29/12/77 Didactic PoemSleeper, demi-sleeper,(For you are so cunning)Sprawled on your bed/litter/couch,At floor level(Surprising what one picks up at floor level) With a red quiltOperatically spreadAnd darker blanketOperatically spread further -What news from your objective psyche?Are the thwarted archetypes stirringOut of their fairy dark forest?Very little clueAs you twist and tossOperatically asleepAnd make a further spreadingOver the bedclothes, operatic,Of a mane of dark hair.'Behind3opv$Behind despair is forlorn hope. Inside the sinking heartIt cherishes a place to mope Though ordered to depart.
￼A Bad Day in the Bedsitter(to the shade o f Thomas Hood)Where to find the poem for a bloody day like this?Cup after strong cup of tea and then upstairs to piss, Too damned idle otherwise to drag myself from my seat, With far too many books and not quite enough to eat.Nightmare had nudged into waking its nagging disquiet And kept my nerves shaking with panicky rumours of riot. The postman went by the house without leaving a letter. It took a good few cigarettes to make me feel better.Odd passages of verse and prose consumed but no pattern Emerging to any purpose. I sat and sat onWith no inspiration, listening in vain for the doorbell. Boredom turned my friendly room into a quiet comer of hell.Then my blank poise is shattered by afternoon noiseWhen the school pours into the street all the horrible small girls andboys,And the clatter and banging and screeching are starting the dogs off- I’ll go mad, run out howling, and ripping my togs off.Remembrance of things past is sad in my situation -Where are my girl friends and old friends and witty conversation? Not enough P for a pint, which makes things a bit worse,Ju st enough energy left to jangle a few lines o f verse.May this next night bring dreams according to the good Doctor’s prescription,Prospective not reductive to the imagination.I’ll get up early and calm and wash out a few pairs o f socks, And some kind ofletter, not O .H .M .S., will come through the box.
￼A Vocation PossiblyThis tiny room, this cabin, this monk’s cell Pantaloon decrepit scholar’s denShuffles me like a full pack of cards(One has to be firm and extricate the Jokers) Although there’s hardly any roomBetween tall Wardrobe, piles of BookcaseGreat Raft of Bed in the middle, almost unmadeNarrow corridors to squeeze sidewaysPast Chair, Armchair, Wardrobe, Table, SinkThe books refuse decorum on their shelvesBut leap into heaps on to table, chest of drawers, bedOr sprawl face downwards open on the floorAmong footprinted newspapers, crosswords half filled in Then on the shelf between clock, cotton-reels, postcards, The villanous small transistor wafts meA ridge of high-low pressure, round and round and round (For five whole weeks I was mad Robert SchumannUntil I said Thank God, Thank God for Ludwig Van) The typewriter gnashes angry silent teethI almost forgot dead matches, crumbs on the rugIt’s safest in the armchair in front of the electric fireRegarding the Mandala and then the Sacred CatReading or better writing without falling asleep(I’m afraid to sleep at the moment for dreams are refusing to c I almost forgot the coiling, creased and soiling clothes Wreathing into a snake-pitSuggesting I go out or at least get washedBut No, No, someone is playing meLaying me out as PatienceGenerally the game known as DemonThat comes out only once in fifty-seven timesI wish I knew what card I really wasThe Jack of Hearts, Dame Pique the Queen of SpadesOr else the Curse of Scotland
￼tT’6' start- 'to -shift uphilto start to shift uphill such load, Sisyphus, needs your ex.tra effort, Indeed, one needs.one for the road, Art is long and time is short ,*Already on its modest way Towards the crematorium,My heart, regardless of display7 Beats like a muffled drum .‘And here I am still’And here I am stillAnd even olderWith all my anxieties onAnd the stink o f old corruptionAll is still in print And still reprinting Glaring headlines Ribbons of old fears23,2- ^ 2301"