￼/Y\\c^ntrrd Co c \ tAv,d\qc5ZP+HF ferc^krSt Francis's 'Cantico di frate sole' done into Hollywood gangsterese jpA#Boss, you got it all - admiration, pull, status, the works -it's all yours.It's you4rs for being top - there ain't no guy not too greento mention you.Thanks, for yoc^and your organisation, specially this guy Sunwho's always around with some light;"uthere's class stamped all over him,a real smart guy -he could only be one of your boys Boss.Thanks, Boss, for^these dames Moon and Stars, platinum blondes in the nightyou made real sweet.4aThanks, Boss, for this guy Wind and the Weather boys, Air, Cloud, Sky,bringing your gang the goods.Thanks, Boss, for this dame Water - she1s a cute kidand don't try,to come over too big.Thanks, Boss, for this guy Fire who keeps his eye open after dark,don't squeal and can handle himself.Thanks, Bos^C, for old Ma Earth - she looks after us real good,always flowers and stuff around the joint.Thanks, Boss, for the guys who take the rap when you tell 'em,that get roughed up and see trouble;the smart guys know to keep their mouths shut 'cause you'll see to it Bossthey're on the payroll.Thanks, Boss, for this cold dame Death no guy can escape.Nuts to the guys that die playing dirty.Smart guys die in your good books. There ain'J^no second show-down.O.K. you guys, get prayin' - say thanks to the Boss and don't get big ideas.k'2 l~f5?