￼As the squalid deflowerings they were; And less likely encounter dryads at play Than in darkness, from a wild boar Maddened by pain, a huntsman’s spear In its side, go running for cover.
￼In Monte Mario(for Patrick Rayner)I lie stanng at the ceiling, unable to sleep.In the room opposite, surrounded by scalpelsAnd glass-topped bottles, Ettore restores lovinglyA Bassano landscape clamped to its easel.Over my bed, in an oval frame, Kilt but unadorned, JjIQlll rto Leonardo: The :>amc muuci, as nis virginOf the Rocks; the tilt of her chinCaught on canvas at the time of the Borgias; Surveying this room, in a Rome torn by explosion; Even in darkness, radiating tenderness.Her presence makes me more tense than were any W oman of flesh beside me. Each time I stretch For the light-switch, a single mosquitoSettles just out of reach. At last I riseAnd tiptoe murderously across the room -To be drawn back to her portrait. SoExquisite the dilemma: the wiry creaturePerches precisely on the nose of the MadonnaX109i
￼‘Springtime’In front of me a girl with bare feet,In a beribbonetl dress, picks whiteFlowers in a field somewhere near Pompeii.Each day I look at her, head straight, Right hand outstretched as she delicately Plucks the stem. Was she there that nightThe lava flowed, birds shrivelled in the sky And lovers turned to ash, where they lay? If so, what had she done to deserve it?I wonder, will it ever ber»•.••.111inriWe are on borrowed time, you and 1, And have been from the outset.All that is left, is to live lovingly.f/110
￼
￼Stewart Conn was born in Glasgow in 1936, and brought up in Ayrshire. In 1958 he returned to live and work in Glasgow’s Hill- head, close to the Botanic Gardens with their distinctive Kibble Palace. Married with two sons he now lives in Edinburgh, where heJworks-aj^a BBC radio drama producer.He has published five books of poems. Stoats in the Sunlight and Under the Ice received Scottish Arts Council Awards, while An Ear to the Ground was a Poetry Book Society Choice.His published plays include The Burning, The King, TheAquarium, I Didn't Always Live Here, Thistlewood and Play Donkey. His stage play Herman won an Edinburgh Festival Fringe First Award in 1981, and his dramatisation ofBloodHunt was recently shown in the BBC’s Screen Two series.
￼