￼canadaGUELPHI've got a gig at lunchtime. University of Guelph.And guess how I pronounce it? I just can't help myself.The students are all eating -yes, it's a real mean trick.But it seems that, when this town was named, Someone was being sick!WINNIPEGI am playing at a plush, antiseptic businessman's dinner and dance establishment called the Norwood Hotel; it's my first gig in Winnipeg, and it seems completely self-evident that no-one round here has the faintest idea what Attila the Stockbroker is. The gig has been organised at very short notice by the Winnipeg Folk Festival; as far as I can tell, the publicity consists of a box ad in the hotel restaurant menu and a couple of leaflets shoved between the Greatful Dead albums in the local second-hand record store. There is a two-dollar admission charge, waived for anyone staying at or entertaining in the hotel.The majority of the audience consists of businessmen; corporate males, each with one of those little cardboard identification badges which middle-aged executives wear in lieu of personalities when they go to business functions in hotels. They are all rather drunk, and obviously under the impression that Attila the Stockbroker is some kind of country and western act.There'fe a smattering of Folk Club regulars, mostly Woodstocksurvivors and Arun sweater victims, and, to my pleasuretand surprise, a group of ten or so who look like punks arid show every sign of interest- in fact virtually all of them come up to me individually during thecourse of the evening and ask me why the hell I'm playing at a country <, and western club instead of the local anarcho-veggie commune, and willI come and play for them there after I've been booed off?At the appointed hour I take the stage. Directly in front of me, and seemingly oblivious to my presence, four gentleparfrof the wrist talk corporate gunk - their lapel badges indicating an umbilical allegiance to a local computer firm. Summoning up all my considerable energy reserves, I launch into an extra loud, extra fast version of'Libyan Students From Hell' and await the onslaught.An hour and a half and three encores later, I leave the stage -very worried.
￼I'm not much one for snapshots, though the world is now my oysterI chronicle my wanderings in poem and in song But when I went Down Under, I brought along my camerato photograph the wildlife, that rich and teeming throngOn my first few days in Oz, I wasn't sure that they existed -those strange, awaybat on the way apparent;if you want to motorway...exotic species, they mostly hide to Melbourne the truth became see some wildlife, then take theThere are wallabies and wombats, there are possums, birds and lizardsand kangaroos of all sorts, yes, even a big red and all these different species have one quality in commonyes, each of them is wonderfully, spectacularly dead....There are lots of flies in Oz, and now I know where they all come fromfor there were lots of maggots in the creatures that I sawyes, every little corpsie was a blowfly kindergarten -more wrigglers and more squirmers than I've ever seen before /now I've made my contribution to Australian natural historyand it's by way of a tribute that I decomposed this songbut one word of advice to all you wild death photographers:stay inside the car because the bastards don't half pong!'cos I'm chronicling nature, and I'm going to do it my waytaking photos of dead animals along the Princess Highway.....(
￼jgNm-iFTiLS(a satirical look at the English attitude toEurope - strange how the xenophobic attitude of 'our' football thugs is mirrored, albeit in a slightly more subtle way, by the ConservativeGovernment, and in a slightly less subtle way(!) by the tabloids)THE DUTCH the Dutch they're much too much we're gonna kick them in the crutch flick bogies at the slimy wogs and trip them up with their own clogs we'll twist their ears and break their glasses stick their tulips up their arses foul their windmills with our bowels and vomit into their canals the DANES the Danes we'll bash their brains and wire their willies to the mains boycott their bacon and their prawns and go and piss over their lawns the scabby Scandinavian scum got scrotal scabies of the bum they live on fish heads and weak tea their lager tastes like canine pee the SWISS the Swiss they stink of piss no race more tedious than this with cuckoo clocks and huge amounts of money in their bank’accounts they may be rich but we don't care we'll shave off all their pubic hair and make them live in Belgium - that's the right place for the boring prats the FRENCH the French they smell ]_ike tench we'll chase theiri all into a trench get loads of garlic on our breath and suffocate them all to death we don't like onions snails or Proust so srneg off Frogs we rule the roost you may be existentialists but we're dead hard and we get pissed the CZECHS the Czechs they're scared of sex they've all got crabs and skinny necks their cars are shit their beer's too strong we're not gonna stay there for long there's absolutely zilch to do there's no Black Label and no glue so we'll just wreck the place and go and leave them to their queues and snow the FINNS the Finns live out of tins they all look like the Cocteau Twins their scenery's not very nice 'cos most of it's a mass of ice so don't go there it's much too chilly you'll end up with a frozen willy it's a godforsaken hole obscenely close to the north pole the KRAUTS the Krauts they think they'relouts but I've seen nastier Brussels sprouts they strut around like football yobs but they're all talk and cheesy knobs they live on pickled vegetation what a fucking stupid nation all their nipples are bright green the strangest folk I've ever seen the SWEDES the Swedes well they're all
￼weeds and all their cities look like Leeds they walk around with plastic bags and noses stuck in porno mags they live on fish just like the Danes but they've got even smaller brains their language sounds like double dutch their land smells like a llama's crutch the GREEKS the Greeks those fucking geeks we'll lock 'em up in bogs for weeks puke in their restaurantsandbars and write rude slogans on their cars we'll get a load of herpes scabs and stick 'em all in their kebabs and write a note - in puke - to say 'CLUB18-30 RULE OK! the POLES the Poles eat toilet rolls their underpants are full of holes they have to queue over an hour to get a mouldy cauliflower they whine and whinge and gripe and moan and play the hairy pink trombone they're always wanking in the loo there's fuck all else for them to do the YANKS the Yanks........der, many thanks for bringing in your bombs and tanks protecting us from Arab hordes and bringing herpes and skateboards you're foreignersbut you're alright cos you speak English andyou fight or so it tells me in THE SUN.. Oi! Being a moron is such fun!V
￼i'uz<(£/[_.THE PEN AND THE SWORD (for Salman Rushdie)You never thought that it would come to this they took your freedomnow they want your lifeHere's to you in your distressPoet on the run to a safe addressMan of words in the shadow of the knifeYou told of life in an inliospitable land of a satiristand a city made of sandYou wrote it for your brothersand they burned it in the streetand the Union Jack said 'send them back'to make the irony completeA refugee from another century where the world is absolute and words queue up to die where the page is a flameand the truth has a single namewhere womanhood is crushed to the sound of an anguished cryThey say the pen is mightier than the sword The poet will never call the tyrant lord But when the sword is raised what can you 'do when all you've gotis a penand they're coming after you....?When they were brownshirtsthey were soon abasedBut a new disguise leaves some people confused But if we won't stand up and be counted - well, it happened once beforeRemember Pastor Niernolleras you hide behind the doorA refugee from another century where the world is absolute and words queue up to die where the page is a flameand the truth has a single namewhere womanhood is crushed to the sound of an anguished cryto the sound of an anguished cryin the name of an ancient lie.....
￼2 ,THIS IS FREE EUROPEDead of night in Carpentrasbrings the ghosts from the days of Vichy Broken windows in the high street Swastikas in the cemeteryBlond young men on a Dresden evening Beer and loathing on their breathTen to one like their cowardly fathers Arms outstretched in the sign of deathCHORUSIf it takes a voice then shout the truth If it takes a hand then hold them back If it takes a fist then strike them down From Cable Street to HoyerswerdaParryat, Schonhuber and Le Pen -THIS IS FREE EUROPE...NEVER AGAIN!Afternoon in a Soviet cityNow they don't even need to hideBlue shirted thugs advertise their pogroms None are arrested, none are tried'Parryat' means 'a memory'-What memories for these Russian Nazis? Children killed in front of their mothers Human skin turned into lampshadesCHORUSOnce more we see the darkness in the European soulAs the chains fall there comes an awful beast His eyes are staring, and there is hell upon his brow -Oscar, Francois, Gregor, Tanya listen to me now...I'm a Jew in CarpentrasI'm a Jew in that Soviet cityI'm an Asian in the East EndI'm a Cuban in East GermanyDon't tell me it doesn't concern us It's not sometiling to ignoreThey are feeding on our apathy - That's how it began before.....
￼This is for Jorg Wolter and all riy friends in East Germany» MARKET SECTOR ONE (SUMMER 1990)Another new year and too much beer and goodbye to the WallBut now there's only disappointment, nothing left at allThe dreams we marched and fought for have faded and turned sourThe cabbage is a king now, it's Helmut's finest hourand on the streets the people want it 'as seen on TV'and a big bunch of bananas is a sign that you are freeIt's just begun - Market Sector OneAs in the East they talk about a futurebold and newa thousand Western businessmen are celebrating toothe vultures are all circling 'cos there's money to be madea multinational carve - up, a bank to be obeyed and now the old, rich foreigners make claims on every hand'you're living in my house, mein Herr, you're farming on my land'It's time to run -Market Sector One fIs that all that we were fighting for? Landlords and sex shops, nothing more? Welcome to the Western dreamWelcome to the cheap labour schemeThe whole of Europe's changing - Big Brother's on the runIt could just be a brand new age of freedom has begunBut freedom doesn't bow its head to some financier's willAnd Europe is our common home - not some gigantic tillSo send the rnoneygrabbers riding off into the sun And take your assets in your own hands, answerable to noneThen we'll have funAnd justice will be done....
￼.TYLER SMILES (22/11/1990)Here's to you, the sceptic fewin the dark old days of '82when a thousand corpses stoked an awful pyre Here's to '84 and '5when all our dreams took another divemidst the jeers of Mammon and the howls of the Digger's choirThere were times I really thoughtthey'd all been conned and all been bought ^ too much Chingford on the brainand never going to think againbut it's a taxing time for Essex now....And Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson an angry crowd stretching miles and miles six hundred years but the lesson wasn't learned And Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesthrough a hail of bricks and stones and tiles now history rolls back,the worm has turned,retribution earned.Tell me why it took so longall these years we've sung this songand will the spectre ever go away?A hundred thousand garden gnomesoutside a hundred thousand homesare 'standing on their own two feet' today No strident tones now, just a whinea hand picked bank clerk holds the line The same song with a few new chordsfor Albion's user friendly hordesA thornless rose is bending in the breezeAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesthrough the acid rain and the sheepdog trials perhaps he never really went awayAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson the village greens and the seven dials - there's still a bit of fight in us today! Tyler smiles.And if it's really over, and the swords turn into ploughsharesShe'll go to Eastern Europe, oh they really love her thereThe fool Walesa and the iron curseAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesas Labour's leaders close their fileson 'Wat's his name' from their own history
￼And Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson that angry crowd stretching miles and miles'Hey - Gotcha, lady! Gotcha, finally....' Tyler smiles.Written a few days after the fall of Margaret Thatcher