￼Thunder in MissouriAll night a drum-roll of thunder had parallelled sleep.Even at daybreak green swathes of light flickered incessantlyagainst the sky and into our dull room.Headlamps along the highway beamed into walls of rainfalland across the Missouri river billows o f smoky downpourwandered away over Iowa.It was a day like other days,a Tuesday morning and workspreading its routines and rumbling on: every' driver behind the darkholes the wipers evenly madein the windshield’s skin of wet was stuck there in his Tuesdaymorning seat and going all out whereyTuesday took him.The spray was yards high for miles.The sky was bigger than ever going on over all horizonsveruJheret/trbeyond the penetration of the eye;its thumping mallet blows(flattening the whole land outmaking everything metal-colouredriver / road / buildings j grass #and the leaning-over trees:the brave shines of the chains of traffica ridiculous minute defiance.Ov'cT15vfyJ
￼1New OrleansThe moon hangs like the last cantaloupe <Kj on the market, in its net of cloud.Even at this small hour there will be someslung yet over quiet traders downthat end of town. Musicsplutters out of the bars and fallsinto the streets, where tangles of people mooch and spread, their faces agleam like the pottery' carnival maskshilarious in the stores; they are glazedit seems armoured in joy.Out further, in the wide reaches o f darkness,police-cars howl like sad catsand forage among shadows.There is a blood-scent on the grid. No night can be different.Later, the moon slips from its netand lifts, brightens into a white dominance, and pulls what could be hope, what feels like hope, necessary' neutral illumination,along the glittering and enormous river.16f