￼Back Sc Front 9-64 20/4/90 4:30 pm Pagft"Np8MesallianceI am divorcing my dog.He never cared for me: we were unsuited. His lickspittle allegiancelies wetly elsewhere, his easy bonhomie bounces over others.I am barely acknowledged: a mere opener of tins, prison warder, valet.In front of other dogshe is insubordinate.I mean to dispose of himby auction. He suspects this/snuffs and sighs as I batten down for the evening. (A window left ajar and he’s gone.)The back-up plan involves garden work. He peers into my excavations glaucous-eyed and curious,but feints and weaves at my attemptsto catch and measure him.