￼H; £rr, iYork MinsbarSilver early-moming silhouette, -iJrectangular ghostevaporating on the horizon ias I walked to school.Those were the sixth-form days,□ the thrill of the startof the mind's future: books, plays, G theories of love and sex,the birth of articulation; and you Q shining like an emblem,a hazy great emblem, of lifeQ waiting me across the fieldswith all its promises. For to walk Q down your aisles under hedgesof flowering glass; to inspect□ pompous Latin tombs, grey slabsof chill Norman floor, or review□ the screen's line of Gothic kings%was part of a gigantic romance, □ the threshold of a plotstarring me,university and women. Q You were all that York was not:4routside, bikes and coats, muffled greysQ of city life; here, no arcade,no vista of columns, that she□ hadn't just left, trailing elusively a trace of brown hair; no footstep□ behind, where I didn't turnto see the sudden absence of her shape.)«:---- IIAll the same, you Gothic bitch, Qyou were always aloof,impassive; thousands like meQhave come with conspiracies•and your clean stone soars enormous,D washed of us all.4Or you teamed against me: G middle-class club,owned and staffed by middle classes, Q like the women I wantedyou were clear and cool, well-bred,□ stocked with silver;*33*---=>bceaXc
￼your spaces rang with trained voices, Q choir of boy sopranos,Oxbridge priests: ray dreams focussed Q into having the dean's daughteron the soft, green closeQ while the organ pounded midnight mass.i. ULi 1ts- -III44Oh, I knew that 'heart of Yorkshire1 stuff: Qcoach-loads of Leeds grannies,outings from west-riding mills, claimingQ their place inside a people's church; and sometimes like a people's ladQl've arsed about under your eaves.Nights of disco's and drinking in York: Q girls, fish and chipsand kisses tasting of vinegarQon a bench by the west front:¥to look at arc-lit limestoneQand saints nodding down from ogees makes a pretty intervalQin bouts of furious smooching;when unknown perfumed armpits □ and breasts damp from dancing and Decorated architecture Qmix into moments of glory.You took me, like a neutral mother, O in all ray adolescent shapes,whether I fingered female crevices Qor, studious, your own carving,always the same, always radiant; Qand if I'd sunk completelyyour smile wouldn't have changed, Qyour shining supervision of York.1X71 IVThen these notes changed to sober ijthe gradual declineof growing up. The plot thinned. Q l B.Ajd in art historyand cycled over Normandy □ visiting your sisters.4I learned a new languageQ to appraise them in: tierceron, clerestory, corbel - HAthe practised wooer.fS.43 L*z-up ' X>
￼But it wouldn't work with you. UToo near,tooresented,too full of earlier selves -pi took my technique elsewhere.Visiting York in vacations jpl felt like my own ghost,stumbling between past and future, £3not seeing our separationbegin: you just leaked away£3 during a decade of hard work.Being eighteen leaked away too. P Belief and emotion contracted, wariness and snobbery grew.D So we swapped lives:I could look at your lovely body Qand feel unmoved as stone.—vNow past thirty I approach you again, Qtrying a new language,trying to make up; settling for□a placid, easily worn relationship, a no-hard-feelings Ohow've-you-kept truce;congratulating you on another yearO in your permanence,with wishes for the next five hundred; Oand since you ask,while our paths were parting fjl've done quite well:I love my wife, though not as I'd expected; Dl likemyjobthough it isn't what I thought;Oand existence -well, it's not the Gothic garden Ql once knew,*being young, in the 60s, in York.□ You should learn that too:I read last month of the party, Dyour great roof down,butt-ends of beams all over the floor Q smoked by the storm.*The time's gone for glory blazgs, Q so follow after me:I used to love storms, run mad. Oto act my age._______________________________ [ \srCXkPin rain, not knowprotestfrompraise;nowI'velearned 3^----)i
￼SjlZ 2/<**//0C?--------------------------- Virgil---------- ^ sA X<£<*QH<S------------(^Messina,21B.c.-5 0 ^ 4 =1* (after Pound) I-*('Z vic^-KtSjI\? cr\i^Come on, damn it! Three long daysof provincial pentameters, prologuing me,the climax, at the end. As with a cookto friends, Imperator farms me outround far-flung festivals, strengthening local talent like a verse-stud. Day three:hot southern hours we've had of Cn. Piso's(talents thoroughly suited to invoicing grain) Apollo-assisted (sic) 'Seven outside Thebes', me waiting to read II, III, andVI (by public request) ]Finished at last! Sporting applause j.f^.j. ■JLQuiet, suddenly. My introduction. Usual honours, and ('nectar-nursed') excesses.Lapping it up,the tanned amateur faces beneath me like a sea, heartily awaiting this weary oldmetropolitan to heave into his opus, his standard, household opusReady, I think. Ready? Ready.INFANDUM, REGINA, IUBES RENOVARE DOLOREM, TROIANUS UT OPES ET LAMENTABILE REGNUM ER^ERINT DANAI, QUAEQUE IPSE ....Cheers exploding. God damn Imperator.c)4'Dh>4-j -27
￼Found on a Junk StallA thirties schoolbook of Standard French Poets^ card-covered, ink-creased. In the frontthe motto-crowned ladder of signaturesshows the notes on the poems are Dorothy's,a few soft scrawls in the marginsin the same loose hand as her name: ancient wisdom she'd taken downto knit into essays and hand back in.I can see the classroom as she writes:the dense weight of a pre-war summer drenching the rows of bent heads,a teacher talking and a pen scratching what I read now: 'Death's inescapability','the illusion of hope'; and with hopes of sloughing gymslips for evening-gowns,'a poem that shows the inadequacy of Love'.good to get marks with but useless for life? that she enjoys life still: the old dear living next door seems happy enoughand might be her. Her son's down now:his car in the drive, the rose-bushes scrupulously circled with plots of lawn, it all looks fine: just as if a childhad carefully built the street from a kit (yet mightn't be trusted not to get bored).