￼eBelgiumIn the mountains of Belgium, just outside Gent,I take your armand, apprehensively,we begin our descent.On chariots of wire, we wander the high walled peaksof this consumer paradiseand I marvelat the natural beautyand fertilityof a Flemish valley.Suddenly the checkout lady, noticing my vacant stare, enquires if I need the toilet, curses in a guttural burp,and throws us onto the street. Mountaineering in Belgiumis not as simpleas it looks.Attila 3-27 3/9/92 12:26 am Page 1717
￼W orthingOn the beach at Worthingthe lugworm castsby the sewage outfalllook like dirty shepherds'’ pie. We walk the shinglehand in handand the crabson the nearby groyneremind me of more intimate times. Your hand resembles a limp flounder. I squeeze it dispassionately.The seaweed smells like a dirty toilet. Refreshed, we return for dinner.1c0*e
￼e9 April 1992(thefourth term) HarlowThere was a grey fellow called Jerry* who made us all nauseous, very.But in Roydon and Nazeinghis vote was amazing!I hope he falls under a ferry(then he really would be a herald of free enterprise)BasildonIn a carefully executed manoeuvrewhich had been planned for several yearsand to the chagrin of those on the Leftwho still had faith in her,a proletarian chirpy cockney sacred cow suffering from terminal BSE(Brain Surgery by Editorial -otherwise known as Mad Cower Disease)was led, mooing contentedly,into a polling boothand from thereinto an economic slaughterhouse;stunned by a series of shocks from the Treasury bled dry by the building societiesand thrown into the dustbin of historyshe still could be heard lowing pathetically‘it’d be worse under Labour...it’d be worse under Labour...’Ja*d-ene-trfT5nTTfew^ successes)Atcila -27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 19*Jerry Hayes, MP (sadly)19
￼0^Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 23Recently that friend of intelligent journalism and editorial free­ dom, Rupert Murdoch, took over William Collins - a publishing house which, among other things, produces the Bible. I can now reveal the planned New Revised Version...The Bible according to Rupert MurdochIn the beginning was the Word, and the Word was ‘Gotcha!’ And the Lord Rupert said let there be a Royal Family, and let enormous quantities of trivia and drivel be written about them, yea even unto the point where a mentally subnormal yak couldn’t possibly find it interesting any more,-and let babies be born unto this Royal Family, and let the huge swathes of sycophantic^-nauseating sludge written about them surpass even that written about their parents, even though these babies and their parents are about as interesting as a wet afternoon on the terraces at Selhurst Park.And the Lord Rupert said let there be soap operas, and let each of these soap operas be so mind-numbingly moronic as to make a wet afternoon at Selhurst Park seem a truly uplifting experience, and let entire forests and the ecological balance of several continents be destroyed in the endless vistas of retarded outpourings about these unspeakable transmissions.And let there be enormous breasts, and endless bonking, and hours and days and weeks and months and years of chauvinisticcjjes so that the brain-dead prats who like the bonking and the soap operas and the breasts and the royal stories get the politics as well.And let any journalist who tries to stand up to the proprietor and editor in the name of truth, and intelligence, and integrity, and journalistic standards, be summarily dismissed, and cast forever into a bottomless pit of decomposing chimpanzee smegma, and let those journalists who suffer this fate rejoice at the great career move they have just made.And the Lord Rupert looked at his work, and even he saw that it was a load of crap, but this was the enterprise culture and it sold millions so it was good. And on the same basis he decided to take over the television too, and the earth itself wept, and little robins vomited, and cuddly furry animals threw themselves under trains, and the whole thing was filmed by Sky Channel for a horror nature programme, and the most awful thing of all was that this was just th(jbeginning...23&ricj^f
￼QA poem I wrote ten years ago, but which is, sadly, just as relevant today. A High Court Judge called Judge Richards ruled that a woman who was hitch-hiking late at night and was picked up and raped was ‘asking for it’ and guilty of contributory negligence...Contributory NegligenceHitching up the M ilcoming back from an Upstarts gig got picked up ’bout half elevenby this bloke in a funny wig...Flash M ercedes, new and gleaming deep pile suits and deep seat pilesI got in and sat there schemingwhile the dickhead flashed me smilesTold me he was back from sessions with a load of brain!dead hackstold me he’d made no concessions to the bootboys and the blackssaid he thought that it was stupid fuss ’bout rapists on the news bloke was only playing Cupid girls like that they don’t refuseAsked me if I thought him enemy asked me if I bore a grudgetold me that he came from Henley said he was a High Court judgeI asked him to stop a second ‘need a slash’ that’s what I said when he did the anger beckoned and I smacked him in the headtook his keys and took his moneycrashed the car into a ditchthough he moaned ‘they’ll get you, sonny!’ got away without a hitchI don’t think they’ll ever find me’cos I’m many miles awaybut if one day they’re right behind meI know what I’m gonna say -24Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 24
￼eACtila -27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 25LHE ASKED FOR IT! He’s rich and snobbish right wing, racist, sexist toobrain-dead, ugly, sick and slobbishshould be locked in Jgndon Zoo!He wanted me to beat him up - it was an open invitation!Late at night he picked me up - an act of open provocation!High Court Judges are a blight -they should stay home in nice warm beds and if they must drive late at night should never pick up Harlow Reds!A five pence fine is right and properand to sum up my defenceIt was his fault he came a cropper - CONTRIBUTORY NEGLIGENCE!25
￼Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 26THE WHITE HOUSESpring 1991Dear Saddam, (of Co—( ca.11 )Well, it’s all going wonderfully according to plan - thearmsdealers are absolutely over the moon, the best sales demonstration inlhistory, and we’ll split the commission 50-50 as arranged - just don’ttell that funny little Major guy or he’ll want some, and that’d welland truly scupper our Harrods takeover bid, which’d be a real pity.Major’s loving every minute of it - he thinks war’s even more excitingthan Trivial Pursuit and doing the washing up, and just as we pjannedthey’ve forgotten all about his poll tax fiasco, our balance ofpayments deficit and your little Kurdish and Shi’ite problem.1..Oh, by the way, that nice German pesticide firm wanted mee totell you that they’ve found a new gas formula which works evenbetterthan the old one; and M itterrand says that even if I have to rearrangeyour air force in the next couple of weeks there are plenty more planes\vhere those came from. Don’t worry, feller, I’ve made sure that it’djbusiness as usual. There’s going to have to be a bit of a turkey shoot,as we agreed - the folks back home are gagging for it - but I’m sureyou’ve done as requested and conscripted all the political prisonersand Islamic militants into the front line so we can both kill two birflswith one stone, as it were. God knows you don’t want them taking theplace over any more than I do.,And that brings me on to the bit I know you’re worried about. Ofcourse, we in the Pentagon are absolutely determined to keep you safelyat the helm, don’t worry - we never forget our old friends, and yourtontinued presence is essential to maintain the balance of forces withthose fundamentalist nutters, as you know. But just in case, we’ve gotthe escape route all worked out. We’ve found you and your lady wife tlovely little place in Guatemala City, right next to some of younfavourite Nazi war criminals; Imelda Marcos does a lovely CHow Mein andyou’ll find Noriega26^ T T
￼Atcila 9-27 3/9/92 12:27 am Page 27and those Contra death squad chiefs great, er,shooting partners! I’m pretty confident that after the turkey shoot anda few bellicose swaggerings from yours truly the whole thing will blowfover and we can come the good guys with the non-interference fn theinternal affairs bit, leaving you sitting pretty.But don’t worry - if the worst comes to the worst and we getrumbled, the exit is sorted. And you’ll be back in the ‘hot seat’ in^ny case by mid-1992,^cos as you know, you’re my trump card in theblection - forget that idiot Quayle, you’re my real running mate, Saddjpoy! Just make the right noises, put on the tin hatand make sure those^nilitary installations of yours are knee-deep in our least favouritejsort of colitical prisoners - I’ll do the rest! Maggie in^2, Georg4n^2! It’s amazing how the scent of blood gets<^fem going, isn’t it?jAmazing, when I think about it, how the Republican Party delegates -j:he ‘Party of the Family’ - will be absolutely desperate for me to boml|a few Iraqi families to get myself elected again! Oh, well, that’s war,J suppose. Isn’t itw onderful?Take care and get your handicap down - we’ll be back on thejinks soon!Y ours, Bushy27/