￼what I thiphand earn a living as a poet - something which all the critics tellyoTT is impossible "ps-eta in this country. I've often wished I could tell you, Bill - I've managed it since 1982!But this is not so much a living as a vocation; I really did begin this thing believing I - we - could help to make this world a happier and more equal place, and the fact that Newspeak is now reality, everything that my parents' generation fought for is being destroyed and the atmosphere in this country is getting more squalid, selfish and unpleasant by the minute just makes me angrier and more determined not to throw in the towel! For all those on the Left throughout the world whose eyes are dulled and spirit shattered by years of defeat I say: do not go gently! SCORNFLAKES is for you.