￼THE ORDER OR THE DAY ' M C^Also by Andrew GreigCrVJ)—Men On Ice (Canongate, 1977)Surviving Passages (Canongate, 198g)A Flame in Your Heart, with Ka3fdb\leen JamiefTi(BloodaKE Books, 1986)4ri«.-\QMOUITAnEERIIG —Summit Fever (Hutchinson, 1985)Kingdoms of Experience (Hutchinson, 1986)At '■^"tiP 0 E T R Y~"~'8|'1Boats (Garret Arts, 1972)
￼An^r<xo G'tvf, lcic'oCopyright (C) Sjmotr-Arpiirage C9&9 ISBN: 1 85224 0*3 *First published £989 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SNBloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern ArtsLEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without the prior written permission of Bloodaxe Books LtdTypesetting by Bryan Williamson, Darwen, LancashirePrinted in Great Britain by-Bell &^amT^mked^Glasg1 5 >i\\inus,' Lr<v\vAeA
￼For my father, who over his lifetime went it ■j-| from Red Clydeside to Old Tory but aye said I-— '; ’ho one ever got rich but at the expense of (I3 ) the widow, the orphan, or the stranger at the door*, l!And my mother, who sang when I was wee14. <2# 3pt"S'Far across the firmamentThe floating sausage blowsHe seeks his little frying pan, .The only home he knows^r*;.'N 3' |^34 \4-phSSomewhere between them, this book.4' 2 8pt-sTo my friends - thanks a bundle.kAVs
￼AcknowledgementsAcknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publications in which some of these poems first appeared: Alpine Journal, Chapman, Landfall (New Zealand), New Statesman, New Writing Scotland, Poetry Review. Poetry with an Edge.(Bloodaxe Books, 1988), The Scotsman and Verse. 'Title of Poem', 'Title of Poem* and 'Title of Poem' were broadcast on Poetry Now (BBC Radio 3)®Q The author gratefully acknowledges the help of a Scottish Arts Council Writers' Bursary in completing this book.f
￼The Order of the Day"''IN THE MOUNTAINS —2?tb10n~]Back Again11 N Interlude on Mustagh Tower12 Sandy, Topping Out on Mustagh14 Entering Askole15 The Winter Climbing16 Crux18 Three Above Namche Bazaar19 After Everest20 Avalanche 4 \2piAIN LOVE & POLITIUS22CD A Reader's Note 23V Mazed24 Shetland25 About Tess'S\\Z *~>odjsscc Wc\ spaced cap\26 Tess, in Tunisia27 Love-Torn Squaddie in Rannoch Torment28 Still29 Visiting30 Annie, in Spring31 Treaty32 Annie33 Gulf34 Annie, in November35 Ruth Says36 Spello, in the Afternoon37 Nut38 Covert Action39 Young American40 Pishing41 D, in a Checked Shirt42 D, Riding43 Heart & Irish44 Up the BaobabX £WVS-45 A Exit-----46lidFictions\1_^ bcW (Lr>rWzrtU )/ f//j
￼AT HOME & ABROAD 4^Trss^acec\ CAy-S .48 The Maid & I49 Wallace Stevens in East Eife\50 52 5f 55 56 58 60 61 64A North Sea Twist-off Bagatelle DreamsIn an Italian Field Aide MemoireThe House-Builder Variations JapanHomage to Master Berryman. MeiicoOH A Good Talking To/ |vi t-f/\ ?I. \
￼IN "TV-Ati NOu\ATNi s mpVb>oU\C^pi T\2_\'l bck\gACK AGAnr'Qn~Vb'otse Shar--— 1O3 In l&Wo# lo,7T,Ve're back againwith our tents, our trash, our high ambition. We've come to be both audience and show.•#Mai flicked his lighter, an avalanche roaredwe have come to assert everything fits4and we believethe true scale of thingsis the entire mountainhung mirrored in our shades.4ndtnb □ □ □ * ---xsbxik4"All day snow sank in the billy,fZ.OrtL'&Z. c\ \»Y<C Vestwas boiled, drunk, peed, replenishedas we passed the mountain through us.The chat was home and axes, hopes, seracs.The voices tire, yellow lights hiss as night comes onto very few witnessesbut enough.4-Unblinking stars and lightning -the theatre's hushed.From the heights we propose to the depths we've left4bour shadows gesture and stretch.i h ft-^ vsv-y ez.ccyt wiVxsiV \oKv.cibd
￼INTERLUDE 0H MUSTAGH JOVER* ^>o|7T^In these high places we are melting outof all that made us rigid; our ice-screwshang loose on the fixed ropes to the Col.Monday in the Himalaya, the clouds are down,our objective is somewhere, but obscure -let it soar without us for a day!Ve lounge in thermals on the glacier,brewing and shooting the breeze, that improbable project of conversation among the living. Laughter rings across the ice. Vhy not?None of us will die today - that's immortalityyou can draw on in a cigarette,harsh and sweet, the way we like it.Steam rises from the billy, Sandy pours.It is true high, worked for, that we pass hand to hand between us with our brews.Men on ice, going nowhere and laughingat everything we cannot see but knowis there - among the cloud, on the Col,a hand of some sort is tightening our screws.3.0^4
￼12.a£AJTDY, TOPPIIG ODT 01 XUSTAGH'From Base Camp to the stream there is a path now. and the grass is yellow at the centre of the path. '__tT ~ ~ -------------------------------------------- So began to lead the last of the TowerQuite hardQmore bold than difficulttough iceQloose snowGbut soon brainbegan to play the gameQMy points investigated stabbedOgood placements to be hadamong loose chossDCrucified by altitudeI bridged a steepish rockwall □ Goodvalue thatLpI remember everythinglike ice-slivers in my windsuit's creasesGCamp 4 a thousand feet beneath my heels □climbinginto my shadowDthe sunflashed off my axe;Au6M.TfjiTnn he was somewheregiving good rope and no adviceDthe ideal secondbut me LJI was gone =fr-’Nice work when you can get itthe hardest □ the bestD hours passedtill I wanted a think and a restso thumped in an ice-screw and hung out awhile -7Like I cannot spell, speak porter-talk but who does not who's lived like me with oil roughnecks and a French girl? One look in her eyes, I know.One straight hit, I find good ice. Climbing's not so much, my life's more in the way I eat my food, the man I rise above, the roads I drive to friends,these suit -Re-engaged myself and winkled onwith patient pickers unlocked the crux set my axes well and at full stretch pulled over the top and saw into Chinainoentt tAPWAS iWo .— G.Hfelt ok felt well(A cheval across the summit)K2 in the distance looking good (suspicion of moisture behind my shades)Made a belay and took in the ropes as Jon came up. So how's it going?OK, Wasted, ^ootV-r.../
￼\x|\i bol«\EITERIIG ASKOLETfor fclcoliTDuff) vOvt,\VL v.'3-Vvdi«jV 3>0^>On the eighth evening we entered Askole. How can I tell you? Ve had seenno habitation in two months. Brown dogs twitched in the shade, a chicken screamed; we smelled dung, dall, smoke, lentils; many voices, the bronze fields shone.Lean as schoolmasters, tall wheat rapped oup knuckles as we limped into the square.Say there are miracles betweenwhere babies twitch and sleep and old folk sleep and totter. Water-mills spun,yaks plonked circles round the threshing floor. Evening prayers, a sleeping miller, tawny goats stole husks of wheat. Goitres hunglike apples on the children's necks.The Hadji lightly touched our backs,Ve had been above ourselves, hooked t- pure worlds of black & white & blue,the narrow wc ags.In Askole we :till dawn then rose and crossed the river,[irufcin rratr-porters, jeep did the rest.Ve broke down, sang 'It will come hardto sleep on beds as soft and wide as ours.'
￼THE VIITER CLIMBIIG4 L,opi?>It is late January and at last the snow. I lie back dreaming about Glencoeas fluent, hungry, dressed in red,you climb up and over me. That passionclaimed the darkest, useless months for risk and play. You riseup on me, I rise through youpTTr,__The shadowed face of Aonach Dubh where Mai first took me climbing and as we clanked exhausted, happy, downwards through the dark, I asked 'Vhat route was that?' 'Call it what you want - it's new.'You reach the top and exit out;from way above, your cry comes down.The rope pulls tight. Vhat shall we callthis new thing we're, about?These days we live takingcare and chances. Whvj name it? tfffUrfid?1My heart is in my mouth as I shout Cl1mblng^.T7j>nVfc-t
￼CRUXDelicate, hell-cat, at the crux on Hoy, last word in day-long conversewith rock above deep blue, climbing into pale blue, aiming for grace -A hard way to be normal. The gods of agility took him this far, 800 feet, soloingand high on that mug's game.Row they desert him. His fingers stutter below the bulge - he's run out of waysto speak to sandstone. Gripped? Mummified. This rock is smooth as political tongues.Hung from a hand-jam,rock crystals enquire of his skinHow much you want to live, sweet youth? Some questions draw blood and pride equally, he answers, smears his right foot, gets his left edged high. Chalk-bag, plnch-grip^rr^ Row he's kiltered out,all trussed up and nowhere to go.The world waits with casual interest. Gooseflesh, a draught blows throughfrom the next world - roIur there soon?Adhesion's mostly faith for intricate movers but he's shivering agnostic nowreleasing the hand-jam hestretches,''CEJHis right boot slipsright hand up)5UI ■ O fast as a prayerItgrabs his Grail o lovely jugthen cranks like a maniac over the bulge. Thugged it to the top, sat and was blank,was gone, was everywhere in Orkney longligh^T,Ve met him in Stromness, it was etched in his eyes he'd dipped deep into more than his chalk-bag that day.Vhite as cocaine his fingersdrummed the bar, awaiting tequila. 'Been pushing the envelope, matey?' His eyes were mica as he consideredour question, glinting and flakey his smile: 'Aye, licked the stamp too.' Revving kiteon a taut string, could plummet or soar -delicate hell-cat, you'll do.11
￼THREE ABOVE IAJCCHE BAZAAR' iTeS3i^-rBrfK5tsr-----\i\\T bCiJA . .•. r r ,Sandy, feeling somewhat queasy, squatted above Namehe,shat a foot-long worm. My life's like that, he said as welaughed and took our photographs, a thread of consistencythrough unconsolidated crap.things passas expeditions through the Bazaar,joking & Jiving & ripping each other off. Got a bad feeling about this trip, boss.Some days you scoff and scoffbut just get thinner,Mai grinned. Had a friend,dead now, he always swalloweda tape-warm before he came this way - never got ill. He'd sayjust to be here, we must have been promoted. , oo^r |- Think that's true?A monk once stopped me on the trailbelow Temboche monastery, said hesaw death in my eyes, *jj$c I'm wondering whose.Ve rounded the corner and there -the big Mothers: Muptse, Lhotse, Everest. My heart battered1i^ w c n t ('in my chest like a man1^ o c x t ______ Jbeat ingon the walls H/of the cageitMPCv-rr Isurrnundl ng himIr-vco^and I thought,'IrMOuNT 1'Clhuhf~lClimbing -
￼/AFTER EVEREST4 -soprsBetween one expedition and the next we buried the tiny Buddha's bones upright, with respect,at the bottom of the garden.Then we were driven back to the mountain.Between the highway and the ditch the restless VestNo one said we are too oldto die young, too young to retire as we left Lhasa in dust./
￼AVALAICHEHe's at it again,first time in yearsa woman's hips hands eyes, wherever the categorical resides, have issued the imperativeScrew our liffhts out.Hot bulb! (Cooling in the dark.)*He dreams of ss avalancheutcVC & wblts.he regards her where she lies face down.The terror liesin the tenderness derivedbetween the slope and shiftings of her ribs.IM UC>\Jt $< POLITICS bbc\
￼-A,v _________________ A READER'S NOTE % IsOpi? —Call him anything, call him Jim. At any road a Scottish male of a certain agestands hopeful, hesitating, lost.He scuffs the dust, unable to go on or back.I want to see him on the rack.Compressed or stretched, the heresies will show. And mock him carefully, you who goto govern or deplore, judgingor not judging, in all events undone.The riders of our times left notes behindof intrigues high and low; one sings of love, another of the shredding of a documentc-TC^He scans these tales of power - screwed up, corrupt, infolded, though I would not have it so,\22_/
￼/I-' -X-'MAZEDIt was the things the women saidfair mazed our Jim; contrary shockscrazed him as they do with rats.First they taught him sensitivity. to chop onions very fine and cry, prioritisethe lady of his life. He got the knack. Applause! Then she whose absence still definesthese screwey situations, left to flame itwith his pal Bill. Live for friends, get in touch with your distress. But soon enoughhis distresses got in touch with him -a right good kicking tilled him in.His bruises were stupendous; in diverse bedshe was rewarded, sundry titbits showered on him.Then Jenny came from Aberdeen to sayEnough. Binge-time over, the cheese is moved. Work, discipline, avoiding dread diseases will be the key-notes of the 90s.Without political understandingthere is only pain - go sniff it out.4-Certitude of the educators, high groundof the women, tests of the high heid yins! Quivering, ardent - a rapier, a whippet,as easily broken - she raps him on the chest;Now you must forget your feelings. ■jrSod this for a game of mazes. He resigns.On his back for days, pinky feet in the air.What you doing, Jim? Minding the ceiling, and its bar^rr>1
￼SHETLAIDHe sailed for Shetland, very near the edge, to bog & cliff & a celibate friend.She did her helpless best by him.He climbed all day and failed to fall.&Light-hoarding stars above her bed,a full moon on the wall - he wanted to be dead, and badly. A mortal sin, she said, I tried it. Veil, she was Catholic but that stuck.Ho way out but up. At the crux,he clutched into the chimney's heart and heavedHe taped his knuckles, she poured the wine.Only reflected light this tenderness, but stillthat night they lay like pardoned thieves - baffled, eased, beside her moon, beneath her paper stars.f
￼ABOUT TESSC^^^_She cocks her head, considersanother country, you. Smoke infiltrates your throat. The rasp that says you're not dead yetis the trigger of seductions.'And do you ever', she enquires, 'act on your irresolution?'The bar's de-stabilised, you colonize each other as folkies sing of Nicaragua.1 ,r one hand on hers, the other grips your car keys, 'Vhy not?'There are reasons, but they melt like wax.*Relax. Tonight you cross the border.You cast huge shadows as you get into the car.^ <3.5f
￼TESS, II TUHISIA—_30-jrKReleased,she tilts over on her side.=4'The Fall is only thati^\ she saysshaking sand from her hair, 'when you wish returnsto Paradise. Go on, r ^ her. 'She says we are inventingnew ways of shipping men and women and all her art is aiming fora raft that swimmers reach and share.44She says this that it may be so.You did not worry as you laybeached together through a starless night an obscured moon still pulls the tidesof billow-talk and pillow-friends.44-These words comefrom Proverbs, Tess, and the Koran; dogs bark above our heads and yet the caravan moves on.
￼LOVE-TORI SQUADDIE II RAIIOCH TORKEITWt- ta. "3- a. _^ 3,oy1\Being, show me your ground.Only the moor and a keepof castellated cloud and the wind moving on as she did, snagged enough to make roots whinelike children left behind.He waits for his heart to stop but it won't.That's all the ground there is, soldier, it's all ground, even the airy-fairy cloud-castle on the hill, eventhe shrilling in your chest.Being torn between moving on and being left behind, he shredded among heather.\wav«.r.s/
￼•*- STILLHere is stillness, there is still more while the light is fading. Hands slow then settle, they could meditateor just be resting while birds pour late songs from (TV aerials. — — - How whatever is trying to .find you, finds you; tea-pot, vase, radiobegin to shine, the early stars tune in.Vhere are you when the light is fading? Pulling on the red nightdress, half-listening to the radio?You are somewhere doingsomething shadowy to me - thanks be for that obscurity.I loved you once; now you've gone dim I still love someone, that is bearable.This is the dusk of loving;the birds are empty and theseare little sorrows,'*pin-prick ones. Bearable instances, sad pretty stars now dribble out above the lastnote of the concluding song.Here comes the calm, the insurmountable parting. The aerial shakes still.//
￼d AIJTIE, VISITIIG -d.v. -d ' — "eI went into your housewhile you were away, I thoughtso this is his chair, this is his cat, here are the trainers he wears.4V-I sat in the chair and stroked the cat.I sat on the cat and inspected the shoes: a re-tied lace?Ve've all tried that. It fails.^■d'The heartjlike your cat^ is“toocn f1 1 sfcgsgfa-but wails when sat on or scared --4-This foolishness won't recur.Vhen you get home, I'll have gone running miles from here. Catch as catch can,if you're fit, if I tire, if we dare.*f
￼AUIE, /s SPRIIGLife^t a dream? Tb«^M*inrti misinformed who never laid a finger an your skin.■fcVhen you wake in Springthe fuzz on the pussy willowand the willow itself are one: 3jfe£fr^fg*_jiothing out of focus here.4V-The sun on our shoulders blooms, passes,what more should we ask of light? Vhat is seen, is.The eyes have it.Now the sheen on the chestnut and the chestnut itself embrace in her hair,there is no further waking.a
￼TREATYI love you, she says without triumph or apology, then seeing his expression, addsDon't worry. I lave also him and himand her, my parents too. That word so weighty, who'd deploy it? He's puzzled butsomething gives across his shoulders.America and Russia made advancesmeant to be rejected, broad & narrow interpretations of a treaty. Row they're talking verification, alliances. How did this happen? They look at each other, puzzled butsomething relaxes across the globe.Reading Sunday papers it is clearwe could destroy each other. Yet may not. From time to time, something lets up.Ve are what we're devoted to, she said in Spring as outside birds proclaimed the lawsof mating and territory in our time.f
￼bcMThe white cat at the window knows being &vi&r composed around itself.mechanics lean over my car; today's'Composed around what goesand what does not - New points, son, condenser's gone. The philosophical one borrows a smoke, pokes the engine, speaks of Maya, the Veil of Illusion.42pV&Stuff and nonsense! This no-start's stuff enough - No problem, a tenner - that's the nonsense. Make it five? Money's real too, there should beabout money. Six and it's done. counterfeit. You're on.I;
￼\1 bolc\ \_'&Xv.fc3 So get cracking, hand me backIn, -<th<eL. Ajtimloon.my life-enhancing cigarette!That Veil: rend it as you will, nothing's hung behind. Is she not beautiful, tranced in the doorway?In her breathed warm breath there is no other.Uf course I'm scared - to love and risk it while todaygoes up in smoke! Go, rollone of your own. My car goes, our hearts ease off the brakes -we-re on a spin somewherethe white cat at the window knows.3>2_ <5-
￼GULF 4\2»o^>Nothin# is mlssin#, said sheon Cairn Gorm, world turns and weturn with It, not losln# touch. I'll always love youlAand □ butIn the Gulfa frigate lowered its defensive screen for a chat - men were blown away.4=Men yearn, metal yawns, verses implodememory and daily news. Between I & I the holy wars elide; between us rose words - lovely, direct, misguided, like love, an Exocet.t/ /
￼AHTIE, fl NOVEMBER* . v N w-— - - -A last pibroch in South Queensferry^ 3>opT^Enough fourteen-bar compressed & gurgling pibrochs for you, Annie, whoever you were(I mythed you). There are affairsmore pressing than love, say they who have it.4So look around. The bookie's satellite disc shines on the new deli; library hours are cut; my neighbour's roof leaks into mine(would we were separate, or one)r-rvT^-4 •+IThe Chancellor parks his bellyproclaims Auld Scotia is a bag of wind squeezed in History's oxter. Behind my town the fields are burning, it is time to leave.4Rush hour. The trucks point North and whine(ttre=l=g»f attfi apfcbfca the-ttavmMA nc*es,;iYie IovjSun spcfcS-fV &>rvt(je |ikca_nted„SM-w 1/
￼4This is not passion, but with pleasure I see you note how well I amundressed in black. Clear sight shows our age, lines curved around the mouth like brackets, as though we smileas an aside (as though desire werea little joke we like to tell from time to time).Ve are not in love, we are not drowning in needy dreams, so we may lay downour weary arms, unconfusedby fate and feeling; I am composedas we surrender, eyes wide open even as they close.
￼SPELLO, II THE ^FTERIOOIbcyy'She has gone a long walk in the afternoon. Only she knowshow close to home she is.the outline of a dress,a coolness on the eyes,it is scarcely morethan a manner of speaking.Registered withinthe steady lengthening of all her gestures -the by-blow of body and light, coming home to one in the afternoon.2b cr/(
￼BTJTLove hammers on the roof with a starting handle, yells 'Open upi I can kill ya..1 You must be joking.It's been hard work, growing up. He wants to stay an uncracked nut. He lies in the bowl of the city with a million othersgoing fousty at the heart.Bone must pick him, he'll not nourish causes, nor desire dangerous as gunsBut a hand is reaching downand sorting through the streets towards him comes one whose fingers could caressor crack him like a flea.f
￼/COVEKT ACTI01_Beneath the coverlet the President's mind is acting up; he dreamshe is the President, which meanshe is responsible. For what? The lotof The Free World & dirty doings without number such as haunted the MncBs. Pick one:I'AacbehisJungle, clearing, hut. Door's kicked down bullets fan the air; the wife, the son,the daughter, redden and fold. Rocksdrop from their hands. Yup, guerillas!The Peace Force torch the lot, exit rightup the sleeve of the star-spangled night<^T7^To pay for this he must raise taxes!He sweats, fumbles for light. Dreamed I wus the President, he tells his wife.You are, dear, you are. She sleepsand sees the JTobel Prize for Peacecrowning hubby's noble head.&His pyjamas cling, the nightlight flickers,Old Glory stirs upon the wall. Aw, who among uslacks his Banquo? Pay the First Murderer,let the drunken Security weep, for all the screw-ups check in here. Who screams? Vho knocks?Mr President - it would make one mad, if not already so.1
￼YOUHG AMERICAISL,2- ■4I sleep, I don't, she listedall the heart-crimes I've committed. Cover-ups, plots, double-cross, betrayalin diverse jungles - truths most economical swooped from her throat. Worse,4rwheeling in her nightdressshe released her lovers' names.Her words cling, burnlike our modern tfessus shirt, napalm. Worst,k-when I wake there is no angry young American at my side. Men cry but are not cooled, just terrified; the imperial wingsstill burst above my head, within.I
￼FISHIIGHe may love her whenhe does not say 'I love you' thenhang on her reply. Whodoes not go fishingwith such lines? Across the livingroom her wrist flicks, the hook digs in.In the kitchen heis floundering - who knows whento cut the line? He twists the tap and sees down to the bottom.He could leave coffee where she sits, smile, say nothing, driftinto the garden^jTTyShe crochets steadily, taking him in.t
￼I* ------- ^ A CHECKED SHIRT # 3Cypd<,I've chopped all dayand stacked my pile. Father taught me no one else was good enough -little wonder Imust work till I bleed, bop4till I drop at local dances.I can split a match with a woodsman's axe and have no lasting lovers.The way I roll my sleeves, that final tuck's my father; the shirt is yours4as I am mine - I've taken every risk but that. Father told me:give up nothing. So I don'twhen I undress; you saw my eyeswhen you asked me to unbutton more.4No can do. Your shirt is wringingbut I like sweating meas you did. My body's perfect,my skin3* tight as a drum, nothing rattles me -The perfect barbarian with a PhD. aches and lies down again, alone.How that single candle spits and yearns! Why should you call? The axe is bedded in the log. I have a winter's burning.
￼4D, RIDING 1* Cl-sHas found nothing could unhorse her yetand so rides on, head up, heels down, believing nothing ever will; fear's not admittedto blue eyes shaded by a cowboy hat.No grief's so ornery, she swears,it can't be bridled, mounted, ridden4to some useful task. Listen,those hands break horses to her will, then with her sister on the greyshe rides down to the creek where men hand-roll her cigarettes. Mother's blownlike tumbleweed, but she'll not be.Once a month she may slumpsaddle-weary on the endless plainsof an undulating blues harmonica,when friends won't write or when a lovermoves on with his useful pair of hands.But too much needs fixing round these partsfor private groaning, too many stray head and idle hands for her to pine -she straightens, flicks the reins again. Something else, these assured young womenwho have not lost, who train their luck and ride it, sure they always will -4-SphGet off with it? One day she'll be thrownand twitching in the dirt will suss she can't get up again. No blame,but she'll be frightened and ashamed.May someone be bending over her then, hold out a hand and drawl 'Welcome-4'Sph)to the world of mortals, angel, it's tough not being tough enough. Now impress me - take my hand and with your othersalute those griefs we cannot master, stumbling home behind themas they stamp so proud.' H-2./
￼HEAST A IRISHYour man's been ambushed by a holiday near Cork years back with lady, Paud & Annewith acre marijuana and desire for children. Peace broke out for days on end, fat porkand laughter, winning at the dartboard & love, :T~r^4rVith such memory, bent on re-unitingor at least revenge (the unequal parting), no peace for heart & Irish, no finiswants blood, and his Mum says 'There's always one who kisses, one who's kissed.' Vho wins the struggle? Vhoever daresto need it less. Anyway, the vehicle's doomed when a man squats on the roof and lets rip.￼t
￼up -The baobab -— t-Fiends besdlfged his wigged-out tree all night, green-eyed & rabid.Into his brain they flashed their teeth.Vith hip-flask and deep breathing, he hung in.A yellow paw reached overvast savannas, the tall grass purred,d lay down around him. Eden without tricks.He stretched. Sever had he needed lessnor felt quite so ridiculous. Friends back home had homes, and incomes, lovers, plans,were hard at it, not up a baobab -Alone, unmarked, he stretched & grinned.His fiends from worse things had protected him. The problem now was coming down.
￼Time to pack it up and move.This performance Is becoming smooth,Jim notes as he caressesthe one he loves, the 14 strings:4this will become technique.And he thinks of poor Bill sentenced to kiss-curl andJRock(Around/The Clock for the rept of his natura jS|j^ -- V -......Jings! And those builders In their squash court, perfect, smooth, without a door,Imprisoned by their mastery,-fTTHall, and farewells. Outside the small rain down doth rainand he must be a journeyman again.ibikes7
￼FICTIOHSjt-_________ __This is more arrogance! she shouted and threw the book at the head it came from.But this is fiction, he protested, ducking - You call it fiction, I call it a fucking liberty. Such a bind to be a man,all that anger and still can't hit me -4His fist went through the window, draggedback, hard - She swayed?He aimed to miss? - sprayed blood and glass. You need a doctor? _I needan editor of genius, what d'ya. think?I think it's just a vein butf.TT^=4They wait for taxi in darkening room. Fiction? Ve wrote the book on it./
￼3t^ |MOCr'nG>CT'° . MiX>fipvs 'iTHE MAID 4 I7Tf~TEls~'s:Eage, I work most closely with the fyaid1'IJiNL^o composer •4> Z l+p^>It's nothing personal when she slips inat half-dawn, half-dusk, any driftingtime of day, to make mere solitude complete. That's how come we get onso well, so long. You smile, you picture black seamed stockings, white muslin crown on hair that's to be let down? Ho,she is not Haughty Lola -nor Mrs Mopp! Vith us it isimportunate to talk or stare;touch is right out. This fortunateproximity is all we share.She has arrived.You are in the backroom,by the Steinway, fiddling with the Blues.You hear her humming as she movesamong the papers and abandoned meals, clearing up the ashtrays, scripts and coffee cups,the litter of alaneness. Redeeming fingers touch your old scores lightly, as if it were yourselfshe dusts and settles on the shelf. Praise the maid who sets out flowers and white cloudswhere you might see them and be glad!The shaaSfes would be total were it not for her.How she issinging an old refrain you can't quite.<rT7'-Y!he skyis pale, washed cTean by rain, hung up against the evening.As you attend, a melody floatsthrough apartment walls so intimatelyit is as though you quote yourself -debris is sorted, orderis invented or restored.How she is done,-, You will work on alonebut that's3^ riit Grace must have its means. She flicks the'light on as she leaves.4:&M' Horrve A^eoAp Vh-rAiVvD if\v>J■bl/t
￼WALLACE STEVEITS IS EAST FIFE -2 3- ,_ ___ 2 'aL __,3o ^>-rsisIf it b« anywhere, it must be everywhere - at£tthe mind stumbles after the divine4finding nowhere to halt or grip.It must be the bush and the wind that wrassles it,4the invisible shook by the visible,the howl shaken from wind by telephone lines. 4It must be speech on the phone and the silence that resumes4and speech resuming that conversationbetween speech and silence which so4shook Sam«0t B. , discerning howl in music,music in the throat of howl.4It must be anytime and at all times, in the living man and the dead,4in the greatcoat stumbling on the coast,in the grey coast stumbling through the head.■+?f
￼5#A SOETH SEA JVIST-0FFI got. oiled on my last night on-shore, riggiQBilaying lovers thrown over shoulders like peel so we could read the initial of the one we shouldalor eaten whgle These drastic shifts caught up «« me; if I’d worked todayI woulckh^ac crushed my hands. 4So I’ve arranged things so I can’t, wrote off fifty grand's machinery.It has long been my ambitionto make a major blunder;now I've succeeded, for today at least. The shaft is plugged, it'll take days more to extract the cock-up from the core.iT~j 1*"2sAcAsV<L4Too much was going down.Ve grouped like para-medics rounda cardiac arrest to boltanother section to our mile-long probe. I did it then. Some suspect, njjne saw that flick of the wrist. Ve swarmedin oilskins around catastrophe, pumped down urgent cooling mud, muttered soothingangry words, Come on beauty,don't break off noy^-:7\Too late.The twist-off was complete.4j Ve shrugged, separated, hurtby our incompetence, glad of the break. 450 DD*I need the money, I need the work,I need the green grease my palms.These are the first and last,the fast realities that let us roar to vanishing-point on our machines.But there are times I cannot watchthe whining, blurry revolutionsscrew the planet and ourselves as we shudder into pay-dirt. Yet I'm convinced I need the money, so I do.4CD *4
￼Ve can't work till the technicians come. Could stay on, doing nothing on half-pay, skimming girlie mags(J.T~'I'll pass,4-chopper out and lie for days somewhere, a long-'^abandoned spanner in the grass, rusting, unadjustable.She phoned M a m Ullapool last night, thick with the cold, or maybe sheI never will dare ask.These needs that grov(. .TIt was fun once, nowI've packed my gear - let's go.Boom-time's over and we got shafted. S I Arfr^ 51f
￼BAGATELLE PREAMSA Canadian rock star has 'a bad case of flu'4= 1.0a --*!«- swrotf«A atrh>-— f1 'My doctor said I have nervous exhaustion. This must be why I’m water-skiingon my back along a blue canal.The wake fans out. I cannot seewhat's coming but there is no fear, all is blue rush and surrender.Bless the doctors for this rideof unexamined joy! My nerves are young in summer; above, the boat's exhaust makes temporary cloudsr ..~ollF* # L - a UT p/*>cW 8 '^F^I need a holiday, this must be whyI'm side-stepping the concrete bagatelleof Yonge Street's high arcade.Muggers? So fear! I'm wearing elbow-length gauntlets, my blue plexi-glass diver's helmet - I out-weird everyone here. When the steel ball thunders, I wrap around it,waving goodbye. I am being rolledhead-first towards more,:'. 4apt) -fi^ST rm-*, 3(*2-^ a r',vThe" doctor said I need a nervous holiday. This must be why I'm back skiinghigh on a street canal, young fansin my wake. I'm wearing elbow-length muggers and unexamined joy - doctoring the weird! All is Blues rush and plexi, a bit mixed.No fear yet - thunder is a blessing, the boat steals the gauntlet.My nerves are rapping, temporarily exhausting the cloudqrrr>
￼■a ''xcpr'CCC>a <\'y \ ^(second mix.)"wake, wake. This is your head doctor.Ve must be concrete now. No rush,no fear. Exhausting to step from dreamsinto another blessed arcade?You get so mixed. There areno muggers, no bagatelles. Vakingis temporary? Balls! You need a summerholiday from plexi-fans. Blue Gauntlet,believe me these pills will see youexamining the clouds. ^1pi m (vuv;V -Vrtf-----js this concrete, or unexamined dream?A plexi-question! Exhaust it in surrender. I can't wear waking, my head skis onthe high canals. Fear is at elbow-length - will doctor turn mugger, or wavediverse gauntlets? Thunderous nerves!The Neil Young fans are singing'0 Steel Summer Clouds'as they carry me waving to the Arcadian ball(777^?_________ 53If
￼II Al ITALIAI FIELDIn the dazzling world the peasants are working. Vith bowed heads and backs they drag in line their dark comb through a field of corn.They will never get rich. They will never livein bought houses. Their lives will remainobscure as their dialect, secret as the women's hair.Bent as their sickles they shuffle on.One sings, another mops her brow.At each row's end they pass the jug around,at noon chew bread, spit, then sit for an hour beneath the poplar trees and silently rise up again^TT)lo wonder we feel flimsy,returning to our books. The pages blur, letters start to wave before our eyes -4rwe are unfocused by the glare ousidewhere a sickle flashes at the margin of a field, its shape unchanging as the stalks yield./
￼AIDE KEHOIRE•a*- x x4 s.&p'UBeing eighteen,light-headed, hormonal, daft, there is much to be said for it. I said it at lengthon the Fife coast that winter.I donned my Doric cap,took a stiff whisky,walked out the d o o r.In town the lights were blazing but no one was at home.4VVhat of the white lineI toed by the sea?The wind blew apartthe clouds round the moon and I stepped through.\f/
￼tty A,^|a rww/O1!hi - 1fciAvVi/THE HOUSE-BUILDER TARIATIOHSj^~ Workshop principal materia IsT)lilsa w, drill, rule, nails, aienable'4h 3.0]^Unemployed? Growing rusty? You wanta house that is unique - home in on this!Here's your drill, the hammer-action for concrete, this is your saw, your rule, your plain deal table. These are the trees. The compassionate Stateawards you with a gross of nails.Such are your true materials. Confused?You want to shelve it for today? Believe me,if you pass on children you must make somethingof your own, o^e live aloner than alone.A better deal! Unemployed, not unique, this was his drill: plane it true, hammer the State, nail it to a tree. But the old saws were rusty, the rule was bent, he made nothing at the table.(He could have said it in spades, butspades are disallowed materials - you think association's free?) Vhat frame could housesuch passion? It must be concrete, too gross to shelve. Confused, alone, he passes on today.plain deaConcrete poems? A house of cards, shuffle them as you will! Deal anyway. Vhaji, was it she saw that made the trees seem jungular today?(nothing's disallowed, but old drills are bent as is the State and its materials.)As a rule, truth's a shelf that takesunique confusion to nail it to the wall. Unemployment takes a hammering todayas she sits making passionate children in her swaying home high in the trees.Here's what I saw when I tookthat hammering: alone is gross.Let us live in free association, where is not material. Plain dealing! Believe me (though I am swaying),a bent rule is unique. Ve shallbe shelf-employed! Today‘s £■***" concrete passion. Hail down this truth:I love you though the drill be rustyand the state confused.si\/c.qfrceb \
￼r'J r/,<Cj-jtUin /nfrjhl (?r J<tr~U J :'Wo -'trtJ{£tJtAtf^/K fAft<J "J "Yj/r<Vi'J*/-JAPAN\ - A Romance of Two 'EmpJres^^^il^^^r^<yl^afh3oyl^ 1 SIGT J-___ =*---------Q3 fNo tmptVcJiri dtbU has *vir IasVe.4 —GoitE vioAu. ~tJ Ib ( PrTj4- 3op-V*>Love fell on you, twiceThe world turned white. You vanished, you became a shadow on the wall.The war ended.You came back from the dead, speaking our language, meaning business. This time you wc^uld produce the goods.We met her on timeat the American movie.We sat through it twicetill we could make it better.4VThen we kissed and took her home.None of us had anything to loseand after allwe made it cheaper and we made it bestANow your round eyes flicker when we stir. You kiss our neck,we like that. Energetically, we take you again You try hard to please. You do. You will.-#For the most partour protests are conventional as we subside; arms are weakwhen we are in your debt.AAnd though we sulk, remembering our time of power, for the most partwe were tired of Empire.This is the reconstruction, our royal we need not be discussed.You will accept reversal in good time. Aspire to our eyes and bea credit. You were tiredand we need each other,of course we do. This is only the old order renewed.ItalicsiuIlo
￼/^rbr~fZT^■^ /VIt will be/reliefto be so in ________-Idve^ to be colonised in turn, repent and loose the burden of our power.4hHere in the shadow of our master's kimonowe bite our fingernails and aspire.ry,
￼HOMAGE TO MASTER BERRYMAS t- t_____Sunk sloop John B., I have to talk at youseeing you around no more. (Slid offthe bridge, waved not.) Give me your duedeaf ear & pardon, who hassled audience with Yeats before you was haIfways great.Them dislocations still appeal - appallinghigh-minded & randy, compulsive chaser,awful and true. Suffered for it too -booming out h cringing in,rampant & trembling for thirty years. Resigned great shade, those ways are out:we dream of reputation, and we fall in line.Veil-mannered, discreet, soberlypolishing the obvious - Are these folks for real?you enquire. Vho live by the word must beready to die by it. Else not serious people.I don't want be badly & cracked! But that's the deal,But ...for this Dream Song form, John, I need more lines -t4-Thanks. Art, decency, sanity - can't square it?Loopy Cal, Mr Lowell to you, scampered undermy tree all afternoon, throwing up sticks. Ve laughed,were briefly happy & unmarked. Were not all so bad. There were othershoned for the chop? One claimed dylnx was an art,did it so badly she finally succeeded. And succeeded.And your fearful double Henry, sunk with his gripes& lust & glass? Yet raped & weptat McCarthy, the dyinx children in Delhi.And deluded De1more,Q Anne who tolled too early - All you crazy bad and great: wus Serious People, pal.4 3ft*Were you still with us I could not breathe,you being too much. Brow-beater -tearful, fearful, loyal & all - I take my leave. My times you urge and warn and flashdark lightning exact. “I commit you & saluteone friend of timing Q wayward, absolute.4)KpH £>0 —■>
￼9ct4^ 3oy4sIn the truck she let the Octopusopen her shirt, also the blonde divorcee's - it was her divethrough dark heat, she could not rise till everything was lifted from her. She had kept herself apart for years, virtuous, no affairs with lecturers as she surveyed the glittering surface and swell of Yanqui power.Night rose round her and she laughed, appalled, assenting as he grippedthe blonde heads back, rinsed mouthswith beer and marijuana. Out the window her hand spread, released wallet and I.D. What a burden righteousness becomes!The divorcee peeled mangos with her nails,licked dark fingers one by one before inserting them beneath her skirt.Cooler u p front with the driverwho drank white rum and kissed her eyes while he spoke poetry about the moon \ flowering over Vera Cruz, the shackwhere she could stay, indebted, in roses, good and chattel like his countryto the Yanqui dollar. Headlightsskewered the jungle, her eyes streamed.He spoke beautifully but was gentle-souled, was not the Octopus who devoured gringa. She buttoned her shirt and clambered back. The divorcee lay unconscious on the sacks, graceless, released. What had passed here? The Octopus shrugged. Self-respecthad kept her on the surface all these years buoyed up by her critique - timeto meet what lay beneath.There was sand, water, men in a circle,some ceremony she could not masternor deconstruct away. One shotwhite arrows at the moon and felltwitching, ecstatic. The Octopus took peyote his tongues thrust mush into her mouth;she nodded, choked, tore off her shirt and spun the world round her jittery hips as though it were a hula-hoop and shea child in her Mid-West backyard.None looked her way3 he swam, she could still run for it.4MEXICODofia Barbara, gue devora alos hombres)-=T £> I
￼He found her dreaming on the sand,arrow in her fist. Crossing himself,Doha Barbara, he took her to the truck. Conscious and unconscious breasts compared were found wanting. Leeched upon,she strained to drain into his mouth;her inverted nipple hurt, swelled,would not come free. Another town,she stumbled out for beer and tacos -no shirt, no money, still she knewblonde hair, white skin would see her through, and despaired. How may power resignfrom its high place? This nervy diverhad come teetering to the edg^-rTC)*At the end there was a room. Men sleeping stirred in their hammocks when she plunged to meet the Octopus in the tightening net.They grappled, clasped, fought limb to limb, snapped beak to beak till in the meshhe suckered the Barbarian. She clasped the arrow he rose shouting - puddled, ecstatic,she drifted while he lay harpooned.4?Then there were many hands, some kind.They carried her out at dawn,trembling, bloody, white as salt.A bus pulled up, she gripped her blanket then rose and in the loving tongueshe mastered her first lie.c n *---2S.’k/'K5V<1VHer thumb on the inside of my arm still lightly stroked the vein./ffls to . the^re&t^—saairLJLJL-Agi' J t n » ^ iAow-J-wftatruob'Tt ‘dayts day. JAJrl—love-io opaejlilooj in—t-fre—©#*«. We lay in her hammock strung abovethe porch, Toronto, Little Italy;the old insomniac next doorpruned tomatoes in the dark and hummed his exile, it would soon be day.But that was in another country — — — ----------------------------------------------and besides, the hornbre's dead.I held her, sweating, knowing she'd said all that she would say.
￼/A GOOD TALKIIG TO *2^^ ^*4 3>Op1>When the din fadesand ghosts of the day disperseinto the wallpaper of an ordinary room a voice speaks quietlyand I listen.*It has recently begunto address the divine.pa not be alarmed! I am always politeit says in an aside.4Vhat does it say to the divinethis pertinent voice?pleased sustain meQ thank youCommunications are simple among the advanced.,adtyt.dVI would wish to be someonewho could without nates .~tg*a vast stadiumeven if the multitudeshave picked up their coats and streamed home.64" ------------------t