￼Return of Sensitive EddieWelcome back from the health farm, Eddie you’re looking well, are you sick?after all that fresh air & herb tealay off the auld Clandew, Eddielay off the auld Scotsmacor next month you’ll just be back propping up the wine bar alter a'1 rambling & gambling & shambling, Eddie your crooked wee eyes cockedat any tight skirt in sightWas not meditation blissful, Eddie? was not brow n rice beneficial?so don’t end up back in bedlam, Ed up to your oxters in shiteno more wacky backy, stay steady, Eddie keep your zipper in its clipperno more pervy polaroids eitheror horsing back the jungle juicethat sends you, Ed, all of a ditherSOBERSOBRIETYthere, I’ve said it, Eddie now that was fairly painlessNot a bit of wonder, Eddieas in the good old fruity daysyour covering your ears with your paws & sprawling about on the stormy seaof your bed-settee-put-me-uplike Caligula on a bad day, EddieI hate to see you suffer like this, Ed, here, have a blast of this...
￼Cleary 9-22 13/7/93 6:46 pm Page 21Pooh-poohSure we should have known you’d be out of your dome on solvents, Eddie, glueis there no noble causes left to catch a feeble grip of?lighter fuel won’t make you cool if you igniteits gentle barbarismwill trail you offstage early blithering & babbling& Evostik just drives you screwy, Edfierce stuff altogether the auld glueyou’ll wander through this riot footage, Eddie like a headless horse in a cartoonlike the legendary Mr Magooyou’ll glide blithely through the m urders through the gutted polling booths& when it all goes dangerously askew amid the sizzling barricadesin the heavy truncheon chargethere will only be hypermarkets, Eddie belonging to zipperheads & sharks& you’ll end up hyperventilatingliving in the doorway of Marks & Sparks& your face will stick to lamp-posts, Eddie it’s sticky gunge of tearscome out of this lustrelet me soothe your crazy fearsJUST SAY NO & crawl back to bed why not wait for the state, Eddieto kill you off instead...21