￼88Manic on Wednesday Panic on ThursdayDrunk on FridayHung over Saturday Slept all SundayBack to work Monday— That’s the lifeFor Solomon Grundy.u o ^ ----------------
￼WORDS /fOR SENILIO TO WORK /I1VTO '2 *4 ^ \ d=- — ---------------- ---- — -> ~C j ‘M r body is a broad and blossoming meadow.'My body is a relief map in eruptionWrinkles wrinkles wrinkles riddle the landscapePimples keep on erecting and detumescing all the timeMy face swells and subsides and always finishes olderI have one or.two grey hairs among the hairs around my JtesticlesI give my eyeballs everyday marks for yellowness andI blow my nose hard each morning to find out how deaf I am My handkerchieves are filled with snotW hen I make love I do it fiercely several nights in a rowAs if it were the last time each timeThen go on the booze for a fortnight Insulting my dear wife with silencesWhen I wake at four in the morningThere are always two landscapes insideOne is the mess one has made of one’s human life (I can say it only in dreamsI am always trapped in the leaking submarine, the^^executioner taps on the doorI am always back at school or in the armyHaving lost my rifle not read Beowulf) TwoisAloe-gnrgling and splashing and undermining in thi() bowelsThe snuffle in the bronchi and the sinuses Orchestrating with bloody birds and aeroplanes outside Cancer has captured this town and that town one says, ,
￼P^iniOne gets up makes teaDiscusses the possible public image with the shaving-mirror Trims the beard sharpOne walks into the sunlight rehearsing wisecracks^.One’s wife will, mercifully, give one breakfastConsents to gossip.
￼Senilio’s W eather SawIf Church spire be clear Twill be daamp round hereIf it be notTwill be bloody hotWhen thee caan’t see spire Church be on fire■k-And we’ll hang parson, squire And the whole bleeding choir.\Z
￼It Js the Blight Man Was Born ForDon’t knock the door. She’s not at home To chat of Crabbe’s or Cowper’s verse— Miss Austen’s got the curse again,This time, worse.*Strides over the moorsA recalcitrant Amazon— Emily BronteW ith the jam-rags on.Tears are replaced by Crimson confetti— Goblins get hold of Christina Rossetti.4rPoor girls,I bleed for you.JUII^Not given a classical treatment By any English poet—Not even Shakespeare.Whose needling bloodied Duncan, Sulks lost Actium,Temper cast out Lear?l2^ r
￼— U-jpt- b>olA 'J \lIc- senilio And ^he mooncteVc^rd'——: skhz The moon is having her revengesInventing girls like the moon.A sharp blade Sails the sky.I saw her through glass, through glass— No cancelling that out.<=^-What is it that I haveTo repent of or relent?I was stammering like a pundit. At the back of the room appeared-«■A girl,Clear and radiant,Piercing. I glanced. Stammered again. She went on shining, quietly.24hP ^ lob/ll b&WIT Senilio to Christine^—---Thus Louis Jouvet with his fine rolling of R’s-‘Ah! Ch-r-r-istine!’
￼loW llIn the film ‘Carnet de BalThirty years ago.I was a boy when I say it,And now I say to you, ‘Ah, Christine!’‘Dans le vieux pare solitaire et glace’— Jouvet in the same filmReciting Verlaine.I would like to walk with youIn an old worn parkW ith fingers entwinedChastely, nostalgicallyO-111,/Dotible Sonnet t o Somebody Else^-""l o t ) 12-c t i U 'g sCL >— 24//LIf Ityou- would were notLady need iMachc'ili anyI additional would witches. murder TheDuncan, Queen’s Banquo crown and youall have MacpufPs already. children Bitch!s
￼□AvjTo the Same Qp+y^Madamina:You treated me like a dog. Condemned to some machineWith whirring bladesMincing to dog-meat. To be tinned.It was true. I was cut into Gobbets. How they flew!But I’m back now, not tinned, An old dog withIntelligent eyes.I^^V^nother Letter to the Moon \I p 'U ■riitY our re-appearance \ New as LauraRestored my sanity4rHow refreshing a cupOf water, cool friendship And how flatteringW ith Primavera stockings And a talent for verse.3opti # D<£-VI iRS^fHaiku)Moon, I tooCan spell:C, h, r, i, s, t, i, n, e ...hd<S1£
￼Mrj Hobsbaum’s Monday Evening MeetingITradition’s fine-meshed sieve will sift Each man’s re-gurgitated toad.The thin pulse of the word must drift Up the vague tides of Edg^ware Road.—$ -They jostle in the crowded room Severely, not to be out-doneIn rich Antipodean glcomBy MrsJPorter’s favourite son.Below the ceiling, guardian of the Grail The ghost of Drj Leavis floats.A trim breeze stirs the fragile sailsOf Lucie-Smith’s expensive boats.-*‘Another spider!’ groan the flies,And stagger down the autumnal grove: The honest gardener’s mouse-bound eyes Protest that he decays for love.AtPoems condemned must lose their bowels: Knit brows acclaim the execution-— Expressive consonants, rich vowelsladies trained in elocution.A slow breeze stirs a beard Lear-sized (Edward not King) to stringent rage: ‘Not in the poem! It’s not realised! ‘An abstract statement on the page!’niskj-—-3^.f\z
￼With a Presentation Copy of VersesHow nice to know Mr^ MacBeth,That Harlequin glinter and frisker! What a gay air of ‘I’m Colonel Death!’ Sets twitching each end of his whisker.4His appearance is feline and elegant.He is certain of each fact he states. His spectacles prove he’s intelligent. His degree is a good one (in Greatsj),•fcMay the verse-form remove my remarksA little bit higher than platitude;Though we’re off after different Snarks, Accept this book, George, with my gratitude.Hemingway, Jimmy Bond, and D’Annunzio Are not in my line and you know it—You would surely have been Papal Nuncio If you were not (hdlas) a good poet.May History’s mischievous glass Not show us out of our decades, With me primly holding the pass, And you at the barricades.Ibi4 MS«=-