￼The Dog-Man- for JanieBut something is certainly movingdown at the lair-like,scented,sudtenly-0C'•■upiedother end of the room. -the dog-man from next door has come to play the piano,to pour out his horrible noteslike a deluge of ripe,exhausted plums:thaj^ stick in her hairand mess up her ironed,imported,daisy-spangled, cotton dress that glares out sententiouslylike one of those little flower-gsrdensharbour-masters and. sandwich-bar—ownersdedicate their lives towith the kind of murderous possessivenesssmall seaside townsobssessed by being the nicestgo over the top with;she's pressed against by plums as big as radiators, emperors,sweating Clydesdales,suicide,over-heated Japanese 'bath-houses for sexual relief'she's read about,and puxzled over,and tried not to see herself inplums buzzing, with bright wasps'that cross and recroas the precinct of her chairlike a switched-on electric fence she can't move through.Her eyes are glazed.,and her face could be basked on by lizards it's so still. She's mistress of the art of frozenness,hiding at the side of herselflike a pilgrim bathing in the Gangesbeing cruised past by loudspeaker-toting boats;like a diseased tomato;like a brain-damaged child, strapped in a vanwho's watching,or anyway parked in front of, an open-air,wrap-around,drive-in, completely incomprehensible picture-show, and the van has a sliding doorthat might accidentally slither open any minute and send a whole avalanche of untouchable things that have no business to be there, /and should nevex\be seen,tumbling out into the open like mutes or brains;and. at night;,when r'in nearly asleep,I sometimes come across her -•vicious,hunched^up-and-incapacitated, •still hugging her hairless awkward little thighs.
￼MY FIRST BRAA big brown bearis knocking at the door:he wants to borrow a dress and matching knickers.The smell of lilac smothers me like wool;beyond the lawns,I hear my naked sistercrying in the nettles where I threw her:nobody else is having my first bra.
￼1 warnSELIMA HILL 5S The Villai9 His famous cock10 that he goes on about’s11 about as much fun12 as a frozen lamb,13 and I just ran away14 across the heath15 one night;16 I left the moonlit villa17 far behind,18 the helicopters, chainsaws,19 parrots, knives,20 and little maids who specialize21 (he gives them sweets)22 in screaming23 at the parrots;24 I slipped away,25 and came back26 here,27 to you:28 breathing gently29 like a giant flower30 smelling of custard31 being stirred,32 and licked -33 custard34 madeofeggs35 and warm vanilla pods,36 where egg-white isles37 float38 to Paradise.1231I
￼SELIMA HILLLilies of the ValleyThe flying-helmet my late father wore smells of seals,cloud-banks,German blood.I stand in silence,shouldering a broom.At night I draw huge maps in the mud.We live in woods,beside a quivering fire, tattooing Ban the Bomb signs on our thighs.We wrap ourselves in clouds like sleeping moons.We'll sing our songs together till we die.*We stay indoors. We dye our jeans and hair. We sew black lace round everything we wear. We soak our feet in bowls of turpentine.Our knickers twinkle like a diamond mine.*Office-workers watch us from their windows coil like a snake around the square.NAGASAKI SMELT OF BURNING PIGS. Hush, he wants to sink his lips into my hair . . .*Tea-coloured soup pervades the Infant school.The boy I want to sleep with's disappeared.The one I'm being kissed by looks like Jesus -His smile, His flowers, His pale ginger beard . . .*As soon as I walk in, my mother knows.She throws away my banners and my jeans.I said I'll march for everfor this garden,this lily-of-lhe-valley, this white rose.*I'm dancing on the air-base with Teresa.Her father will be furious.She is blind.*Beneath the planes, beside the muddy river, we're waiting for the march to move again. Lost children. Sheena Easton quietly singing. Three vicars mend a Trident in the rain.*I've got little ones myself,the airman said,his uniform as cold and metallicas lilies-of-the-valley;panic; tin.♦I live on bread the nurses leave in bowls, while in my dreams the bullets turn to bees: I feel the sunshine rub against my thighs, the drip drip drip of honey in the trees.