￼At the HairdresserBehind white astragals, I sitWaiting to have my hair cut.Soon it will flounce, a greying frazzle, at my feet; The face in the mirror, sharply lit,Resembling mine, but with more linesThan I’d care to acknowledge, deeply slitInto the features as by theatre make-up.All round, women flit - as though partO f some Japanese ritual: brown-smocked, Hair rolled, silent as steam risesAnd water swirls and plopsIn each dazzling sink. Resorting to no tricks O f rejuvenescence, I face facts;Ask simply that it be trimmed, not too short.On glass-topped tables Cosmopolitan and She, Sheer gloss, assist in the processO f holding time, momentarily, at bay.As the scissors snip, I become consciousO f plants in their pots, smooth leaves polishedOn the surface but each underside frayed, Marking the tiny red spiders’ unyielding progress.80
￼SnowfallSlow l/iawSlabs ol snow, stacked against the guttering, Keel on the lip, then slop downOn the tarred tubs litteringThe area. Each clearance bringsFilthy water, as from a gushet;A juddering of clogged veins.W e switch off television, sitW atching nothing. Each of us wonders what To say. Tomorrow we shall have the great Thaw to discuss. Meanwhile there is tonight.'-week.‘Like fellcd-tajs’you say. And l^ps, the alarmHas gone, did you not hear?’ A"small child charms Us with ‘Open the shutters, so I can see out.’The mind wallowing from last night’sTrough, I go through. The rutted snow1las gone to slush, not frozen. Along the Row Cars start. People pass, looking in.I switch off the centre light. Our binIs on the pavement, on its side,Its lid gone. Is there nothing we can hide?’Jajumese bowlThey are bringing the dead off the mountain. It has been the worst winter for years.You ask, can we go sledging. In the Gardens Yesterday a father sat his small daughter, Shrieking with laughter, on a new toboggan, Then watched helpless as it careered Downhill into a tree. I still hearThe crack of her skull - and cannot tear My eyes from this glazed Japanesefiowl, its surface minutely crazed.81
￼SpoilageAfter a fortnight, snow is no longerA novelty. The drop in temperature Has made a rink of Ann Street. MoreThan old ladies teeter. The children Give up looking for dragons’ Footprints, having found none.It seems an age since the world was clean And we went sledging in the Gardens. Now any pretence at purity has gone:In my heavy coat, and since last night Nursing a chipped humerus, I concentrate On skirting ice patches and areas of dogshit.82%
￼Sorley MacleanSome poets erect edificesSimple or baroque in accordanceWith taste; then with icePick and pitons, do a danceOn the sheer face. Others Thrive underwater;Pot-holers, skin-divers For sunken treasure.Your rareness lies inOut-doing these; who conquerThe princely Cuilltm, Plumb the chill of Morar.Against both you pit Y ourself ultimatelyT o preserve love’s heartbeat In the face of eternity.And 1 think of LearOn the edge of the abyss,So tenderly awareO f human helplessness.83
￼Pentland Poems(j'orJertiny Bruce-Watt)Above Glencorse bolc\In the lee of a stunted pine, we pour Coffee from a thermos, adding whisky To keep out the chill. Perched hereI It is/ht>t-e* ! ^ o escape from history.Vigorous on the summit of Castlelaw Scott would tell of CovenantersJoyless on the sward below. Earlier, startled worshippersW atched jk highland soldiery swagger T.owards'Holyrood; the Young Pretender, Unaware of Derby, impending Culloden, Flicking at flies with a blotched cane.Breathing deeply, the air keen, I keep thinking of Stevenson Longing for home. How soon, In some Samoa of our own,Will we sense the grim-visaged visitor come And, peering through time,W onder when next we will, like Cromwell’s Men, eat biskett and cheese on Pentland's hills?Lothian bum A 2Av.Cb Up here, scarcelyBirdsong even: onlyThe labials and gutturals Of this burn as it gurglesDownhill, locality of accent In vowel and consonant,cuI vATv I84
￼Each circumlocution'1'hrough heather and sandstoneTraced by inflection And sharp interjectionUntil, in a mossy outcrop, It comes to a glottal stop.Westlandman looted1 lie here, who for Christ’s interest did appear Amongst those martyred on Rullion Green, 1laving trudged from Dumfries through Ayr, Knowing I was unlikely to see my family again; Even then, not anticipating such slaughterAs would befall us, such numbers slain. All to see the Episcopacy overthrown.Tor days, drizzle steamed on a stew of limbs; Those who fled being hewn downIn the mirk, between here and West Linton, Their deathgasps reaching me like an exhalation.So I lie, deep in Pentland bog, my person Preserved perfectly, my spirit broken. Ilow many must perish/in God’s name?
￼Cherry Tree, in December—(forJudy) *The cherry tree outside my study window, heavy^ ith blossom, is an elaborate bouquet,TTcelebration or renewal of vows, this December day.In your white dress, you walked smilinglyDown the aisle, then were whisked awayT o the reception, the remainder of the lives we,Together, would share. 1 regret only That the years have passed so speedily; Each moment, rushing by,Leaving less time to enjoy.I thank you for your love, and pray Death when it comes, may come gently.Meanwhile on this December day I seeFrom my study window, with a new intensity, The delicate blossoms on that cherry tree.86
￼Bedtime Story‘I don’t like that one, HanselAnd Gretel, I told them so, little Children enticed by a wicked witch Into her marzipan cottage - such Goings-on - too fearsomeFor words, just before bedtimeI'oo: keep them up half the night ’They recognise her plight, Interpret it differently:Grandma would be upset, you see They confide later, from tact,It ’.v the old woman who gets cooked./87
￼InteriorOur sitting-room at last furnished,The clock ticks on its marble shelf, Paintings hang more or less permanendy, A bron2e horse makes space for itselfBehind the door. Lares and penates are placed In the hearth. And noticeOur Lady of the Crinolines in the high chair, Whoin we pretend does not exist.Will she hold sway, I wonder,In centuries’ time? Or, this still a home, Will it have become your ghostThat flits lovingly, from room to room?
￼Fiefore Dark(for Douglas Dunn)They are so confident, the young, who strutThrough thcy4eiHy-avenues that once were ours;So sure of themselves, knowing the future is theirs;So cool and relaxed, as they scale the sweet Octaves of love; so self-possessed,Desire not yet on the wane, or become lust.A bell sounds. The end of lectures for today. They fan out across the pasturesO f the city, filling the nearest barsOr returning to bed-sitters, wearily.The old smells linger: in Gibson Street,Gurry powder; stale urine, from the Pewter Pot.In my mind it will always be early winterIn this Victorian sector of the city',Its terraces squandered by the University,1leaped with swept leaves, a rotting /mber; Kelvingrove a vast litter-bin; children Playing, generation upon generation.I still have black-and-white snapshots takenIn front of wrought-iron gates, in the earlyDays of the War; my father wearing a kipper tie.How long I wonder, before our children, Asked who we were, explain idly if lovingly? In old age perhaps the rarest quality -Certainly the one I most envy - is dignity, Especially in the face of pain. I cannot bear The thought of what loved-ones may suffer.Phis is partly what drives me to poetry.The Missa Solemnis on, we sit and listen: From the heart, may it go to the heart again.X/\89
￼In the Gallery(National Gallery, Edinburgh)Heading for the National GalleryTo renew acquaintance with the Turner watercolours I find I am formulating an analogyBetween this aesthetic pleasure and the urgencyWith which we must face fierceMortality. For one month only of each year Are these paintings on display,Lest their coloursSuccumb to the sun’s rays.So in marriage, we must seizeEvery opportunity to act lovingly,While fire is kept at bay. MayGod in his mercy let us shareA little longer the charmed lives we bear.So I make for these subtle blues and ochres,Illustrations on smooth-grained paperO f weightless lakes and rivers; treesLike plumes, waterfalls suspended in mid-air; On the bank, tiny transient figures -Only when I get there to discoverThis is already the first of February.Accepting the fact as salutary, I take awayIn my mind’s eye a graver imagery; Rembrand/ ageing; and Goya’s seated doctor, That basin of blood between his knees.90
￼Turn of Century(late Gallery)Sickert’s Minnie Cunningham stands alone In the gloom at the Old Bedford,From the top of her wide-brimmed hatT o the frilled hem of her gownRich red; one fore-arm Languidly showing; face tilted T o catch the light’s sheen.She glows, glamour of loneliness.Is it wistfulness merely,Regarding an audience who are there Or who have deserted her?In her solitariness, a fragilityWhich, garbed in white,Would draw a ghostliness about her.What, almost a century ago,Was to be her future?Did she, like those back-cloth blooms Left of frame, just fade away?Is it their fragrance she inhales? Explaining the slight pregnancy O f posture, skittishness of pose?To so much, there is no answer:Like the Music Hall, goneInto darkness; chandeliers brought down, Stucco crushed to powder.The death of a theatre, a whole era.And she still solitary there -Girlish in red, with so sombre an air./f91
￼Summer, Assynt(forJohn Amott)Drumbe^After three weeks’ ram, Drumbeg is a swampland; Suilven’s tonsured skull lostIn mist. T h e forecasters extendA blessing everywhere ‘except the north-west’.Marooned cattle peerThrough columns of moisture. The lochs are less Landseer Than Japanese watercolour.By evening, we can seeThe nearer hills. Under pale skies Summer visitors emerge - like empty Vessels, shifting in the breeze.River KircaigDear Lord VesteyHe had to write, PleaseAccept my apologies Forfishing your waterWith worm: otherwise The ban would remain. This after the discovery O f two cock salmon Along with his bait tin.He gazes at anglersIn green chest-waders Casting monotonously. Suddenly his expression Changes. Light glances In his eyes as he sees,Through the birch trees, Two boys stealthilyPursuing old ways...)1
￼LochansYou, Loch Torr nan HidheanIn the lee of Canisp, took some persuasion.Loch a Braighe, you too showed a firm willBefore yielding a speckled fighter from your cross-ripple.Despite your chill, Loch Gorm Mor,A change of fly finally got your measure.Then on the way homeTo fail with you, lochan-of-no-name:Naive enough to tryAnd outreach pads of water-lily1 left in your dark bed an imprint deeper Than I care to remember.Departure‘Leave the cooker and kitchenAs you find them: clean.’So on our last afternoon, as is proper, We eliminate any reminderO f our presence - so that whoever Is next hereFinds no cup-ring or soup-stain, But all spick and span.As for the land around, little need For circumspection. A neap tide Laps where we clamberedOr sat pullovered -While long before we drive awayWe will trickle into anonymity;The wader-prints round each lochan Fished, by brimming waters filled in./rJhcM.93