￼.k 7~no talk of deprivation, of mitigating circumstances - Kingston-on-Thames?No, these were just mean-spirited scum,celebrating the values of the last thirteen years -the values of crass ignorance selfishnessviolenceand of course‘pride in being British’Was it for this, the 1944 Education Act?People are murdered every day, of course- in this nasty, brutish zit of a country,often for even more unbelievably banal reasons -so why this poem?Simply that I remembera visit to a pubmy own bilingual conversation(it’s a skill, you know, you learn it, like medicine or carpentry - a skill that most Europeans take for granted)and the broken beer glassand the contorted face of the thugwhen I replied to his insult in his own tongue - ^ For me it ended differently V7~“but when I saw that story in the papera shiver ran down my spineI remembered that evening in the puband the impotent anger swelled uncontrollably in my guts...One final thought;I bet THIS senseless murderdidn’t make the tabloid headlines:After all,The Paper That Supports Our Boys wouldn’t want to alienate its readership, would it?11Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:24 am Page 11_
￼Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:25 am Page 12In the vanguard of the stultifying wave of social and political apathy currently festering across our nation we findThe Kids. Their immediate forbears were radical hippies and wild-eyed punk rockers who rioted, vomited, went on demonstrations and generally stood up and spat. This bunch - who’ve actually got far more to be angry about than the last couple of generations — -a*e ahppier with a sensible haircut, a nice cup of cocoa and a Chris Rea LP. . . .If /<Tire'Yuuill of Today- "The fe'anK(A new slant on an age-old theme)The youth of today don’t know they’re born ...at the age of five, they’re mowing the lawnby the time they’re eight, their golden dream is a foolproof, high-yield pension schemeAs puberty strikes, know where they are? Out there on Sundays, washing the carBirthdays and Christmas, the same old cry: ‘Please, please, Mum, can I have a new tie?’Games: ‘You be a company director, I’ll be the local tax inspector.’Teenage rebellion: ‘Grow up, Dad, and buy a suit, you look real sad!’Music: Doors and Rolling Stones (!) and bleepy acid monotones*(*though some are really daring creatures - they like Blur and Manic Street Preachers)Politics: Grey. A tinge of greenfrom time to time, to suit the scene.12%
￼Attila 9-27 3/9/92 12:25 am Page 13Ideals? ‘Er...well...to earn a wage, and quickly attain middle age.Changing the world? For god’s sake, no! Our parents tried THAT years ago!’I see no need to mince my words.HEY, GET A LIFE, YOU BORING NERDS!-e13