￼Dry River Bed, ArizonaWater spills a few threads over Those wideyiwarm rocks, Buries itself in the gravelOr slips into cracksAs if asking for dark/Like the gophers that quiverTheir muzzles in quickInterrogation out of their clever Network of tunnels, then double backSinuously into the dark,So that everything moving Seems to be moving inward, Sliding a glance then diving Out of the air’s vacuous regard,Choosing again the dark.So the vital must take cover, Deeply away from the sunAnd the other raptors that hover And swing in ferocious light, downTo investigate the darkAnd its multiple promises, neveri jFinal in all its windings, norStark, nor positive. The dead river World, so absolute, so clear,Should recommend the dark.>//vu<n/e
￼Boulder CityIn late afternoon the sunhas begun its drop.There are shadows now, precise as black paint. Not evena flurry of dust movesnot even a hint of cirrus.The thermometer standsthirteen.Easterners settle hereout of the river fogsand the greening rain.Their sprawled houses are silentbeside the blue geometryof their deserted pools.That water now must befit to simmer a chicken.Indoors these pioneers lie lowin the blast of the air-conditioning. Should they step from home the sunwill lean on their skulls like a ton of fire.22/f
￼Sea Lions off MontereyTfalf a mile into the Pacifica rock like the back of a sea-beast humps itself out; the swell sounds hollowly as it bumps the sides even in slack water, the sides the only bits visible under the sea lionscrowding the top, still, mostly,as clusters of mussels.On shore round the coin-op telescopethe children bounce and wrangle,and the cars slide down to the shore and slide away again. An encounter on the edge of things, the sea’s curled lip, the end of a continent,the abounding other, leavingnoting to be said.* The still, head-up animals stare indifferently out of the ocean.