￼“0-UJSecond CantoGEORG FRIEDRICH DAUMER1 January 1875IBorn in the spring of the century’s first yearLately the big questions have seemed to him answerable. Where were we going after all? Answer:Head down into the Age of Iron.And thereafter? Nowhere. Iron is the last. Or maybe lead. Some days it has that taste.Iron or lead. Lead in the souls (the souls?) O f such as us, the poets and the scholars, Iron in the fists of those who govern us.I should have been born in 1770With Beethoven, Wordsworth, Hegel, Holderlin, I might have gone to Paris at the age of nineteen.1*0I should have moved nearep the centre. .Caspar 9-39 5/7/94 1:53 pm Page 20Goethe might have welcomed me, we had'fly / Tb©-peet Hafiz but by then he was dead.1 toI am as old as the century.I might have gone to Paris at the age of thirty (Heine did) and in ’48I could have been in the Paulskirche.There was never any shortage of barricades I might have been on. Deeds,However, were not his forte and look whereWhat was has got him, the reading and writing - here: Loneliness, penury, a sad endAmong the poor who were always poor, Poorer than they, they address himAs what he has been for fifty years: Professor,20