￼The Diktaen CaveChildren, attend. The myths are bloody. In this wet crack For Mother Rhea, weary of fruitless birth, the KouretesHid God the usurper, little Zeus, from the cunning,The child-swallowing pronos—himselfa son who for his mother, Gaia, the Earthfweary of copulation, reaped from his father, Vast Ouranos,'tne parts necessary with a jagged sickle.The cry a hurt sky makes echoes for ever.His fading semen splashed Heaven. SeabornO f the rosy froth where the unspeakable fell, our fierce And gentle need grew. Blow out the candle. DarkerThan this and unimaginably deeper is Tartarus where grown Zeus confined outwitted wily Kronos, having exhumedVigorous brothers and sisters from his guts. Zeus livedThe life of Riley then in the upper air, with cloutsO f thunder and strokes of the rod of lightning lording it; And pressed divinity small into the bull, the swan, the eagle, The golden dancing gnats, when tugged by Love, the immortal, For one of the black earth’s mortal sons and daughters.
￼A Relief of PanStanding behind you in the looking-glassI saw my foolish admiration crossYour own dispassionate appraisal of your dress. I met your eyes, I saw you wished me gone,I thought of that man by the ZappeionWho likewise could not let you be in peace.I had gone looking for a sanctuary of PanAlong the dry Ilissos, you by the drinking-fountainSat eating cherries. I had gone-------------------------------------Looking unsuccessfully/-! had goug_________________-or a re-Uof- of Pan and k eMeanwhile, your gentleman of the Zappeion,Was proffering you his member round an ilex tree.Brother of mine, the Nymphs will not come down To dead Ilissos, nor can you watch at homeA girl before her glass from nakedness become Clothed like a stranger at the drinking-fountain Nor watch her put off every ornament again Saving a jewellery o f cherries. I can,I do. Yet I imagine being foundOne day in shrubs below her window or by stairs She might descend or shuffling after her in queues, Eyes down, with cunning mirrors on my shoes.I think it will amaze the officersTo learn what lady I have importuned.:----------------------------- ----------------J——J______.___________50/
￼PerditaThe brusqued sun returned, but milder, as Through leaves over water, and silence too, After the sprung lock, a clamour of birds On the lake in the heart’s forest settling.Then nothing was between them but her bed And that narrow. Come near to either bank And staring neither saw when they beganAt the throat the undressing very much ofThe other’s appearing nakedness since the eyes Across the pause held them to their purpose By force of looking face to face. OnlyWhen she reached for the counterpane he sawHow bare her hand was and how thin her wrist When she took off the covers and they stood Shivering and unable to get breathBeside a girl’s sheets who with solemn dollsBehind thin flowery curtains lesseningThe strongest light had owned, until he backed With pressing hands the blank door to, a room As still as the heart pool of a forest.
￼Love in the DarkWe loved the rain, it bathed our minds to think of The replenishing rain. On a morning thenThe cloud had lifted and we saw the whiterSplash of the stream at the cwm mouth and the wallThrough which the bracken trickled. Behind that dyke Ownerless herds of fire cropped, unhousingLittle birds but leaving springs in hoofmarks andOn a craterous level above two valleysThe lake where once in a cotton grass summer White gulls lifted quietly from the surfaceAnd we undressed to bathe. I showed you afterwards Blood on a stone, feathers and a bridge of bone.Love of the dark, love of the falling silentO f everything but the stream... We left the road At nights, we trespassed over the propertiesBy the white clue of the climbing stream, by redLanterns of rowan. Above the stepping fallsUnder the lintel of the lion-gate foldAnd through a hog^/hole in the cyclopean wallWe entered our sleep like children. Hand in hand weRan some distance to the last skyline. The lake Still lay in a sun- and moonlight at a timeO f the soft drifting o f cotton grass or whenIce clouded over our full crater of rain.