￼Fleur Adcock was born in 1934 in Papakura, New Zealand. She read Classics at Victoria University, Wellington, and afterwards taught at the University of Otago. She emigrated to England in 1963, and worked as a librarian until 1979; she is now a freelance writer.Fleur Adcock's Selected Poems (Oxford University Press, 1983) includes work from six previous collections, four of which were published by Oxford University Press: Tigers (1967), High Tide in the Garden (1971), The Scenic Route (1974),and The Inner Harbour (1979). It also includes the Lake District poems of Below Loughrigg (Bloodaxe Books, 1979).Fleur Adcock contributed translations to Peter Jay's The Greek Anthology (first published by Allen Lane in 1973 and now available in Penguin Classics). Her Oxford Book of Con­ temporary New Zealand Poetry appeared in 1982.Pete Henry was born in 1943 in Kingston-upon-Thames, and served his time as a hand engraver in London from 1959 to 1964. In 1976 he founded Aquila Engraving in Newcastle, and has since worked extensively for print, particularly intaglio and relief processes. His work has been shown at the Royal Academy and at the Royal Society of PainterEtchers.