￼BELGIUMIn the mountains of Belgium, just outside Gent,I take your armand, apprehensively,we begin our descent.On chariots of wire, we wander the high walled peaksof this consumer paradiseand I marvelat the natural beautyand fertilityof a Flemish valley.Suddenly the checkout lady, noticing ray vacant stare, enquires if I need the toilet, curses in a guttural burp,and throws us onto the street. Mountaineering in Belgiumis not as sirnpleas it looks.
￼WORTHINGOn the beach at Worthingthe lugworrn castsby the sewage outfalllook like dirty shepherds' pie. We walk the shinglehand in handand the crabson the nearby groynerernind me of more intimate tiroes.Your hand resembles a limp flounder.I squeeze it dispassionately.The seaweed smells like a dirty toilet. Refreshed, we return for dinner.j
￼APRIL 9 1992 (the fourth term)HARLOWThere was a grey fellow called Jerry* who made us all nauseous, very.But in Roydon and Nazeinghis vote was amazing!I hope he falls under a ferry(then he really would be a herald of free enterprise)BASILDONIn a carefully executed manoevrewhich had been planned for several years and to the chagrin of those on the Left who still had faith in her,a proletarian chirpy cockney sacred cow suffering from terminal BSE(Brain Surgery by Editorial -otherwise known as Mad Cower Disease)was led, mooing contentedly,into a polling boothand from thereinto an economic slaughterhouse;stunned by a series of shocks from the Treasury bled dry by the building societiesand thrown into the dustbin of historyshe still could be heard lowing pathetically'it'd be worse under Labour.... it'd be worse under Labour '(and one of our few successes) LEWISHAM WESTColin Moynihan's a unique specimen He's like a humanonly smallerOr, to put it another way, he's like a planktononly tallerI.D. cards, all-seater stadia -There's one thing you can't deny;Colin Moynihan did for footballwhat car travel did for Gordon Banks' left eye
￼IfImetMm onatrainI'd invite M m to a partyand all the other guests would be Rumanian SecuritateThough he's finally political Mstory that's not quite enough for mehe needs retrospective abortionto take effect immediatelyMay 1992*Hayes, MP (sadly)
￼irue^pi\a^dv>acf\Jitm?ato-ed [/e/Si(*_ .to aShix) I Mz^ra a gued^at the new revised Version.... — THE BIBLE ACCORDING TO RUPERT MURDOCHIn the beginning was the Word, and the Word was'Gotcha!' And the Lord Rupert said let there be a Royal Family, and let enormous quantities of trivia and drivel be written about them, yea even unto the point where a mentally subnormal yak couldn't possibly find it interesting any more, and let babies be bom unto this Royal Family, and let the huge swathes of sycophantic, nauseating sludge written about them surpass even that written about their parents, even though these babies and their parents are about asinteresting as a wet afternoon on the terraces at Selhurst Park.And the Lord Rupert said let there be soap operas, and let each of these soap operas be so mind-numbingly moronic as to make a wet afternoon at Selhurst Park seem a truly uplifting experience, and let entire forests and the ecological balance of several continents be destroyed in the endless vistas of retarded outpourings about these unspeakable transmissions.And let there be enormous breasts, and endless bonking, and hours and days and weeks and months and years of chauvinistic propaganda written by semi-literate sexually inadequate craven toadies so that the brain dead prats who like the bonking and the soap operas and the breasts and the royal stories get the politics as well.And let any journalist who tries to stand up to the proprietor and editor in the name of truth, and intelligence, and integrity, and journalistic standards be surranarily dismissed, and cast forever into a bottomless pit of decomposing chimpanzee smegma, and let those journalists who suffer this fate rejoice at thegreat career move they have just made. /And the Lord Rupert looked at his work, and even he saw that it wasa load of crap, but this was the enterprise culture and it sold millions so it was good. And on the same basis hedecidedto take over the television too, and the earth itself wept, and little robins vomited, and cuddly furry animals threw themselves under trains, and the whole tiling was filmed by Sky Channel for a horror nature programme, and the most awful thing of all was that this was just the beginning...WaJ c.■lkak*.
￼f\04rfvA poem I wrote ten years ago, but which is,sadly, just as relevant today. A High Court Judge called Judge Richards ruled that a woman who was hitch hiking late atAand was picked up and raped was 'asking for it' and guilty of contributory negligence....CONTRIBUTORY NEGLIGENCEHitching up the Milcoming back from an Upstarts gig got picked up 'bout half elevenby this bloke in a funny wig... Flash Mercedes, new and gleaming deep pile suits and deep seat piles I got in and sat there scheming while the dickhead flashed me smilesTold me he was back from sessions with a load of brain dead hacks told me he'd made no concessions to the bootboys and the blacks said he thought that it was stupid fuss 'bout rapists on the news bloke was only playing Cupid girls like that they don't refuseAsked me if I thought him enemyasked me if I bore a grudge , told me that he came from Henleysaid he was a High Court judgeI asked him to stop a second'need a-slash' that's what I said when he did the anger beckoned -and I smacked him in the headtook his keys and took his moneycrashed the car into a ditchthough he moaned 'they'll get you, sonny!' got away without a hitchI don't think they'll ever find me'cos I'm many miles awaybut if one day they're right behind meI know what I'm gonna say -HE ASKED FOR IT! He's rich and snobbish right wing, racist, sexist toobrain dead, ugly, sick and slobbish should be locked in london Zoo!He wanted me to beat him up - it was an open invitation!Late at night he picked me up - an act of open provocation!
￼High Court Judges are a blight -they should stay home in nice warm beds and if they must drive late at night should never pick up Harlow Reds!A five pence fine is right and proper and to sum up my defenceIt was his fault he came a cropper - CONTRIBUTORY NEGLIGENCE!
￼Q a /v-e 'The White House Spring 1991Dear Saddam,Well, it's all going wonderfully according to plan - the arms dealers are absolutely over the moon, the best sales demonstration in history, and we'll split the commission 50-50 as arranged - just don't tell that funny little Major guy or he'll want some, and that'd well and truly scupper our Harrods takeover bid, which'd be a real pity. Major's loving every minute of it - he thinks war's even more exciting than Trivial Pursuit and doing the washing up, and just as we planned they've forgotten all about his poll tax fiasco, our balance of payments deficit and your little Kurdish and Shi'ite problem....Oh, by the way, that nice German pesticide firm wanted me to tell you that they've found a new gas formula which works even better than the old one; and Mitterrand says that even if Ihave to rearrange your air force in the next couple of weeks there are plenty more planes where those came from. Don't worry, feller, I've made sure that it's business as usual. There's going to have to be a bit of a turkey shoot, as we agreed - the folks back home are gagging for it - but I'm sure you've done as requested and conscripted all the political prisoners and Islamic militants into the front line so we can both kill two birds with one stone, as it were. God knows you don't want them taking the place over any more than I do.And that brings me on to the bit I know you're worried about. Of course, we in the Pentagon are absolutely determined to keep you safely at the helm, don't worry - we never forget our old friends, and your continued presence is essential to maintain the balance of forces with those fundamentalist nutters, as you know. But just in case, we've got the escape route all worked out. We've found you and your lady wife a lovely’little place in Guatemala City, right next to some of your favourite Nazi war criminals; Imelda Marcos does a lovely Chow Mein and you'll find Noriega and those Contra death squad chiefs great, er, shooting partners! I'm pretty confident that after the turkey shoot and a few bellicose swaggerings from yours truly the whole tiling will blow over and we can come the good guys with the non-interference in the internal affairs bit, leaving you sitting pretty.But don't worry - if the worst comes to the worst and we get rumbled, the exit is sorted. And you'll be back in the 'hot seat' in any case by mid-1992 'cos as you know, you're my trump cap_L4n--the election forget that idiot Quayle, you're my real running mate, Saddy boy! Just make the right noises, put on the tin hat and make sure those military installations of yours are knee-deep in our least favourite sort of political prisoners - I'll do the rest! Maggie in '82, George in '92! It's amazing how the scent of blood gets 'em going, isn't it? Amazing, when I think about it, how the Republican Party delegates - the 'Party of the Family' - will be absolutelydesperate for me to bomb a few Iraqi families to get myself again! Oh, well, that's war, I suppose. Isn't it wonderful? Take care and get your handicap down - we'll be backlinks soon! Yours,elected on theBushy