￼Dear Mrs Thatcher,ALAN PLATERLondon NW3,intentions at the time.The first tangible result of this policy was the withdrawal of theThis from memory, is the second time I have written to you.The first time was soon after vour election in 1979. I don’t know how clearly you recall election pledges but one of yours was ‘to eliminate wastage in public expenditure’ - the words may not be exact, but the sense is clear and, I’m sure, matches the spirit ofyourtraffic warden (or lollipop man, to use the cheerful vernacular of the times) from the road outside the school then attended by two of my children. It was, and is, a very busy road, especially at commuter times, as eager motorists rush to work. Whether they are pursuing the market forces, or are pursued by them, is a fine point requiring analysis by greater philosophers than you or I.You did not reply to the letter, nor was the traffic warden restored, and there have been accidents on the road.I later wrote to Cecil Parkinson after he mouthed grotesque inaccuracies about CND during a television interview. To his credit, he did reply. He did not answer the points in my letter, and he totally misunderstood a modest joke in my penultimate paragraph cut it is, as you must i ave ooseiveu, airunpCiicCiAll that being so, there seems little point in engaging in policy discussions. Instead, let me tell you a story first told to me by a friend in Newcastle upon Tyne almost thirty years ago. I don’t suppose^you .tear too many stories on your daily round.The stoiy.After a shipwreck, a dozen people - men, women and children - are marooned in a lifeboat. They know the direction of the nearest land and they have limited supplies of food and water.They have a decision to make - and this is where the fun really starts because you, the audience, have to decide how the story ends. What larks!rDo they:1. Share the food, the water, and the work, and find their way toland by sensible cooperation?I
￼22ALAN PLATEROr:2. Do they fight each other, kill each other and eat each other, so that in the end one strong man or woman, the sole survivor, reaches the dry land alone?Most people choose Option 1, which is interesting since - give or take the odd semantic/ideological quibble —it is the socialist solution; whereas Option 2 —give or take similar quibbles - is the Monetarist/Market Forces/Capitalist approach, and finds few friends.I shall be sending a copy of this letter to Mr Kinnock who, I know, is interested in such concepts.Do not feel obliged to reply to this letter but regard it as a friendly contribution to the free flow of ideas - the good, the bad, the dangerous and the crazy - vital to the health and humour of a civilised democracy.Yours etc., ALAN PLATER,Voter.Alan Plater is a novelist and writer for theatre, films and television. His work for theatre includes Close the Coalhouse Door; his TV work includes three Beiderbecke series, The Fortunes of War and A Vety British Coup. Work in prospect includes Sweet Sorrow (for Hull Truck) and Going Home (for Live Theatre, Newcastle).