￼STILL LIFE --------fConsider the solidity of a pear, 1ti'tea r-drop in its bulbous amberp:ravity-downdrawn stretched from its stalki weight han^irvj;'_________ Idown outof clusters of leavesflower-end star measuring the diveto ground. / 4-«I.'Take noteof the taut skin-stretchthe about-to-break-out white pushing behind i t i1: 4vthe sweet wait for time or wind to brin£the severance1,4^the drop.ib-It is all a vast expectancy,promise, hope, \1 fear.ibk^-
￼WKLL-HE/P3The camel pads and pads to followa circle enclosing a well.The coupled horizontal polecreaks round, and the jups liftover, tip out their silver waterfalls and dive apain into the narrowdarkness of the well-shaft.The sand is hardly markedby decades of treadinp. The last thousand of the years these wellshave splashed and squeakedin a daily sun-hammered questare a snippet of their time; the miles of camel-track coil back intact.4^on-—?'I'L>ther climateswaist-hiph round walls mark outa preen dark where the bucketsdrop to a splash, hollow and distant; manhandled upwards they plintwith cold lipht,jewelled behind the parapets.
￼These places centred oncethe speech of parishes. They hunpon their flat-topped stones,in the cold morninp, the slow evening, encounters, ratherinps of chatter,round the windlass rroaninpover and over at the lift of water. .-i-lyb Q HI- 2>\'lSometimes a hedpe-bank leansover a plassy block of liquidheld at a slow tremble- — ------ — down amonp bundles of fernsor set in a blackberry tangle, brim-full and squaredby flat preen stones.$So clear as to be nearlynot there, the water touched has the shock of ice, breaking shards of brightness out of the deepest hollowdark. Purity clutchedfrom a ditch. The eternal surprise,Q IV 1112-They are all, of a kind,shrines. Carved with the titlesof saints, or decked in any case with wreaths at festivals,or round and tensionedlike hubs, each of them sipnalsa way to the rleam in the darknessrVi'
￼f\They all reach down to something other than water; they finda way to the vital, waiting above the fissured ground,above the inaccessible, intenton the slow flow of meaning,the resolving, plitterin/^ astonishment.6 0 -------------------------------------