￼Ayrshire FarmEvery new year’s morning the farmers Would meet at ‘Harelaw’ with their guns For the shoot. Mungo red in the face, Matthew hale as a tree, John hugeIn old leather. The others in dribsAnd drabs, shotguns over their shoulders, Bags flopping at their sides, collars up.We’d set out across the north park, The glaur on our leggings freezing As we left the shelter of the knowes. No dogs. Even the ferrets on this day O f days were left squealing behind Their wire. W e’d fan out, takingThe slope at a steady tramp.Mungo always aimed first, blasting awayAt nothing. Hugh cursed under his breath; The rest of us kept going. SuddenlyThe hares would rise from the bracken-clumps And go looping downhill. I rememberThe banks alive with scuts, the dead Gorse-tufts splattered with shot.One by one the haversacks filled,The blood dripping from them, staining The snow . Matthew still in front, Directing the others; the sun redBehind its dyke, the wind rising.And myself bringing up the rear, Pretending i was lost, become the quarry.Three blasts on a whistle, the secondTime round. And, in from the sleet,We would settle on bales with bottlesAnd flasks, to divide the spoils. The bodies Slit, and hung on hooks to drip. The rest Thrown smoking on the midden. The dogs Scrabbling on their chains, Todd’s stallion12
￼Rearing at the reek of blood. Then inTo the fire and a roaring new year:Old Martha and Mima scuffling to and fro, Our men’s bellies filling, handsSlowly thawing. And for me, off to bed,A pig in the sheets, the oil lampThrowing shadows of rabbits on the wall.Last winter I covered the same groundOn my own, no gun.fOM/.Martha and Mima 1lave gone to rest. Todd has tetheredHis horses under the hill. Mungo, too,From a fall at the baling. Yet my breathing Seemed to make their shapes; and Matthew’s And Hugh’s, and my own bringing up the rear.At the road-end 1 stopped and stoodFor some time, just listening. My hands Growing numb. Then 1 crossed the track To where a single rabbit lay twitching, lhg-headed, eyes bulging, in pain.I took the heaviest stone 1 could find; And with one blow beat in its brains.
￼FerretMore vicious than stoat or weasel Because caged, kept hungry, the ferrets Were let out only for the kill:An alternative to sulphur and nets.Once one, badly mauled, hid Behind a treacle-barrel in the shed. Throwing me back, Matthew slid The door shut. From outsideThe window, 1 watched. He stood Holding an axe, with no gloves. Then it sprang; and his sleeves Were drenched in bloodWhere the teeth had sunk. I hear Its high-pitched squeal,The clamp of its neat steelJaws. And I still rememberHow the axe flashed, severingThe ferret’s head,And how its body kept battering The barrels, long after it was dead.14
￼In a Simple LightXWinter in this placeIs a tangerin/sun. Against the skyline Nine Shetland poniesStand like cut-outs Fraying at the edges. Snow puffs and flurries In weightless dribletsAs they platter downhill, Pink-hooved, chins Stitched with frost, manesJiggling a tinsel trail.They clutter and jolt,Are pluff-bellied, biffPosts, thrum their trough With warm breathing, smeltIce. On the skyline Again, part fancy, they Freeze. In each eyeIs a tangerine sun.//H//15
￼On Craigie HillThe farmhouse seems centuries ago,The steadings slouched under a sifting of snowFor weeks on end, lamps hissing, logs stackedLike drums in the shed, the ice having to be cracked To let the shaggy cats drink. OrBack from the mart through steaming pasturesMen would come riding - their bestBoots gleaming, rough tweeds pressedTo a knife-edge, pockets stuffed with notes.Before that even, I could visualise (from coloured Prints) traps rattling, wheels spinning; furred Figures posing like sepia dollsIn a waxen world of weddings and funerals. When Todd died, last of the old-stagers,Friends of seventy years followed the hearse.Soon the farm went out of the family: the Cochranes Going to earth or, like their cousins,Deciding it was time to hit town.The last link broken, the farm-buildings stand In a clutter below the quarry. The land Retains its richness - but in other hands. Kilmarnock has encroached. It is hard to look Back with any sense of belonging.Too much has changed, is still changing. This blustery afternoon on Craigie HillI regard remotely the muddy trackMy father used to trudge along, to school.16
￼FarmThe sun drills the shire through and through Till the farm is a furnace, the yardA quivering wickerwork of flame. Pitchforks Flash and fall. Bales are fiery ingots.Straws sputter like squibs. StonesExplode. From the byre, smack on time, Old .Martha comes clattering outWith buttered bannocks and milk in a pail.Todd, his face ablaze, swims backIn what shadow there is. Hugh and John Stretch out among sheaves. Hens squabble For crusts; a dog flicks its tailAt a cleg; blueflies bunch like grapes.Still the sun beats down, a hammerOn tin. AndTiigh overhead vapour-trails Drift seaward, out past Ailsa Craig.t17