￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 4:31 pm Pa-#\Trembling Hearts in the Bodies ofDogsNEW & SELECTED POEMSSelima HillBlfiDDAXe BQDK5
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 12:16 pm P,wCopyright © Selima Hill 1984, 1988, 1989, 1994. ISBN: 1 85224 288 4First published 1994 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.LEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. No part of this book may bereproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without prior written permission from Bloodaxe Books Ltd.Requests to publish work from this book must be sent to Bloodaxe Books Ltd.Selima Hill has asserted her right underSection 77 of the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988 to be identified as the author of this work.Cover printing by J. Thomson Colour Printers Ltd, Glasgow.Printed in Great Britain byCromwell Press Ltd, Broughton Gifford, Melksham, Wiltshire.
￼—fA f-Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 12:18 pm P;i c7ciff-AcknowledgementsThis selection includes work from Selima Hill’s collections Saying Hello at the Station (1984) and My Darling Camel (1988), as well as the whole of The Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness (1989), all these previously published by Chatto & Windus. It includes a comp­ lete new collection, Aeroplanes o f the World (1994), but no poems from her recent collection A Little Book o f M eat (1993), which is available separately from Bloodaxe. A section of The Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness won first prize in the Arvon/Observer International Poetry Competition in 1988.Acknowledgements are due to the editors of the following pub­ lications in which some of the poems in Aeroplanes o f the World first_appeared: Agenda, Ambit, As Girls Could /(m s/(O scars Press, 19XX/, Buddhism Now, First and Always (Faber, 10CX), The Guard- ian, The Honest Ulsterman, The Independent, The Independent on.ISBi ’f* ) ^ jjgf e fe\ , (C id_Sunday, London Magazine, The New Poetry (Bloodaxe Books, 1993), J^New Writing (British Council, lSQCXj Poetry Book Society Anthology 1988-1989 (PBS/Hutchinson, 1988), Poetry London Newsletter, Poetry Review, Poetry with an Edge (Bloodaxe Books, new edition,1993), Proof (Hull), Resurgence, 16 Women Poets (Oxford University ^ ress> Times Literary Supplement, Tracks (Dublin), Tricycle (USA), What (Canada), The Wide Skirt and Writing Women.These poems are dedicated to friends: ‘The Dog-Man’ is forSftthe cp fk£ fcIUcis. /AJanie; ‘Brueghel’s Helicopter’ for Nicky; ‘Eating Lychees in South Kensington’ for Inigo; ‘Carnations’ for Bruce; ‘Orchids’ for Tom; 1^ P rneapple jukc—foi^the dancer and choreographer Emily Oaid;and ‘Silence’ is for Padraic Daly.-I- wouId like to -thank-Qswald-Tschirtner for his drawing Trembling -Hearts in the Bodies o f Dogs (1979) arid lor the title, which he in turn -borrowed from a poem by ErnstTlerbeck (seerpagc-4Q)< I am-also^ ^& f *^n . ~ Li nV iSMo grateful to the Arts Council of Great Britain and their judges for tcl U A v f t t r fthe writer,s bursary^ awarded in 1993 to work on this book_And finally I would like to thank Sanchir, Suydun and Taivan for introducing me to their beautiful country, Mongolia, where some of these poems first, in a way, began.nMtKt N^t*jru>cinfL~.Cg-.Ij/fc J..•ru 4 book ****^3h OsmU TShiNtHtY: Sebenplt tierzen/kli'eb-e T>brff £ w>v tS *--dv-pa5 U h i i H T U tv i/C\°ilc0•^l,J 1*/ErKS(rftfri»ecl<L due. f~D(ItcA fHcZSVs
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 12:17 pm P99It is with love and devotion- that I dedicate f this book to my dearfriend Amelia.^Ako-trrtherirtspinng singeflmdrsongwriter - ^-Christy Moore*—A *It/£with,hut— /W thttl/iftt S'pftwi (XOmSC fay piCC9\fi[\th ( Opktr —{^h/it I (StdiCfitC tl\iS bok
￼Hill Trembling 10-24 3/2/94 4:26 pm P. 10Das LebenDas Leben der Hiihner ist rot.Das Beben der nachstenliebe ist7rot.Das leben ist schOn.Beben der Herzen im Leibe der Hunde.Das Leben der Herzen ist liebe.Das Leben macht den Himmel heer. <•Das Leben mochte langer sei langsam er es Lebe die Li^be. / langsames Leben ist laiERNST HERBECKe life o f the cockerel is red.:st of translation to be added)193-
￼Hill Trembling 10-24 3/2/94 12:53 pme 11■€>SAYING HELLO AT THE STATION-0-(1984)
￼Hill Trembling 10-24 3/2/94 12:53 pm .Page 12Questioning Mr BonnetM r Bonnet, the helpful Egyptologist, explains the strange cosmologyin his Reallexikon der agypschen Religionsgeschichte that he wrote when he was dying in Berlin:Horus, the god of light, hid his semenin a dish of chopped lettuce leaves,and greedy Seth, the god of darkness, pig-headed, metal-boned, swallowed it, and so, by trickery, the moon was born: Thoth, on a lotus flower, the blue baboon!He crosses the celestial oceanas helmsman of the world,called Aah, the vizier of Ra, the sun.He loads the gleaming boatwith palm leaves which recordthe days and nights in notches,for he is the measurer of time,and he invented writing.He carries an ivory writing palettein his long black fingers, to instructthe scribes who squat before him on the sand.And he helps them on their later journey through the Night Of A Million Yearsas Thoth, the protector of the dead:he takes them kindly by the handand guides them through the underworld; his nine baboon musicians linethe long bank where the travellerspass on their way to Osiris,dreaming of playing draughtswith the gods and dancing with them in the Field of Reeds.
￼Hill Trembling 10-24 3/2/94 12:54 pme 13Mr Bonnet, did you meet him, and will I, when I step on board the silver barque? Will he be saying Pleased to meet you,Airs Hill, and how’s the writing going?as we descend the corridors of night into the Judgment Hall. Will he pat me on the shoulder with his cracked avuncular hand and, tucking my book inside his sky-blue cape, will he wink before he picks his tail up and climbs onto his special perch above the scales?-&