￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:03 pm Page 65On the borderOne minute I’m idle, glimpsing fields & catde, scanning drab scenery the English would gloat overnext I see neutral clouds spread their blemish, a chopper gradually swirling into view.I suddenly start to probe bushes for camouflage, envisage eyes from secret cameras clocking me,sweat on my pale hands, then to make matters worse we’re flagged down by a jeep, rows of guns.I can barely make out a nervous youngster’s face peering out from sandbags in the border pill box.Each day he learns to livejvith shits & shivers,the near-certainty of snipier’)bullets - they harden to it- they grow arrogant as the censor ersing History substituting a very British form of truth.Take for instance this cheeky cockney on the bus, eyeing up bags on racks, beneath the seats.Training his stare on my shaking face contempt spreads as when he thinks of vomit.He seizes up mutiny in our faces & I witness hate - if I had the guts, which I don’t, I’d spitconsider fields & cattle worth prison, or fighting for... *• n^f ^ ^ f-e-65
￼^1A ir0jj f iCleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:03 pm Page 66-World ViewI don’t claim to come from anyplace, ideally speakingI’m a World Citizen, sure saying so has got me in shtuck.At Stranraer when the plain clothes boys stopped me, turning out my pockets but I was clean & they were empty& they asked me if I smoked & rifled through my roll-ups;one cheeky fucker lifted my dreadlocks up, made snide comments.So when they asked me on their forms if I was Irish or British, I answered ‘World Citizen’ & they threatened to strip mehok^il& they hoiked through the 3 cases I was trailing home from Saltbum. ‘An unemployed World Citizen, you’re some boy’, one joker taunted& in the carpark later my mother was disgusted as still half-cut from the clatter of pints on the ferry, I raised my voice, excited,‘Someone has to stand up & be counted’, but I never did, nor will I, & my mother said ‘aye, you’re a big boy now & know it all’I suppose I thought I did but now I don’t. I’m ignorant...66
￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:03 pm Page 67 o - Down SouthThe day Derm drove me down south was a hoot, smashed out of our brains on bump roads& him pretending to be some heavy Ulsterman complaining about potholes & Galtee cheese,creeping Jesus statues everywhere in sight.It had been sunny in Belfast but by the borderon the incline of a hill he poked me, ‘There it is!’ he said, ‘the grey mist!’‘Why forsake the blue skies of Ulsterfor the grey mists of the Irish Republic?’We’d been pulled in & frisked in Armagh & Ed Koch was in town, propegangering.At the cathedral Derm used his wide-angle lens, held high over the top of preying pressmen.I’ve seen the snap since, Ed looks worried, the way anyone would considering gunmen.A Bishop was swanning about & this priest I’d asked directions from pointed him out -‘That’s the most powerful clergyman in Ireland!’so Derm fiddled with his bag, whipped out his camera,said ‘He must be worth a shot, d’ye reckon?’ & that priest looked just like Ed had, alarmedat how easy it would be & though helioptors_ _ would probably spot ye, you could dram the breathfrom anyone, just like that! So they pulled us, RUC, job, but we weren’t the hurtful kind, they knew it, just tourists.©67
￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:04 pm Page 68I feel like that amid all the roadsigns in gaelic & I’m not surprised after he dropped me offDerm got more grief from a patrol over the border& Bernard my host leaned over to me in ‘The Black Kesh’,asked me how long I’d lived in England for & when I told him, out of mischief he added‘thought there was a trace of West Brit in yer accent’...68&-CD-
￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:04 pm Page 69Ulster: A Tourist GuideNow when I return less with the latest gadgets, with more than a sliver of saxon on my tongue,I feel conspicuous like a tourist or being a ‘trendy leftie’ I become a crack reporter on an undercover expose.My judgements click together now in newsreel,the TV map of Belfast glowing, hangs on my brain& because I’m an alien now & usually stoned & rootless all the bombs & guns & bible thumping scare me more.Men I grew amongst, who never caught the ferry out, on my casual strolls hold sten guns to my throat.As a child I’d practise jumping hedges with cars in pursuit, now it’s no joke, I may have to take a frantic leap& the roadblocks leave me shuddering as my new friends would, all my drinking cronies in the gardens of English pubs.Let’s just say one wants to take his ‘wife & kid’ over,he’s heard me often recommend the crack, the drink, the fishing& I would have reassured him once, strenuously too,told him to ‘go for it’, not to bother changing number plates,Ji ■klr-eJtold him to get wire^ iit»to the authentic bars I immortalise, told him sure you could/get a bullet in the head anywhere.^ xh' /"/,J r ^h V^^ u. Xy>Let’s just say I used to/say that, confidei/& relaxed, 1 but having lived here, a stereotype, for nigh on 12 years/I have to admit, though it hurts, now I’m not too sure...( /)Pde-69e