￼Conn 1-9 3/5/9S 10:57 pm Page 6HrThe cover painting, InsertTit/e^Her^y Barbara Rae (Hi**), is reproduced by kind permission of the artist.\J9\-*MiXyXAcknowledgementsAcknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publica­ tions in which some of these poems first appeared: Cencrastus, Chap­ man, The Dark Horse, Edinburgh Review, Gairfish, Headlock, The Independent, Klaonica: poems for Bosnia (Bloodaxe Books/ The Ind­ ependent, 1993), Lines Review, London Magazine, New Writing Scot­ land,fThe Scotsman, The Southern Review (USA), Spectator, Spec­ trum, Stand, The Stony Thursday Book/ Cuaderno de Madrid, Under Cover (Mainstream, 1993), Verse and West Coast Magazine.The Upper Clyde poems are from a sequence originally com­ missioned by the Glasgow Herald which appeared, with photographs by Edward Jones, as a Weekender feature on 3 December 1994. ‘Strangers in the Night’ was commissioned for Fallen Angels by Jack Vettriano and W. Gordon Smith (Pavilion Books, 1994) and first read at the anthology’s launch in Edinburgh City Art Centre.^1 Jc*A.//
￼Conn 1- 3/5/95 11:51 pm Page 7<>Contents11 12 15f 1517\r18192022242526272830333436373840341T j?44454647484950Kilmarnock Edition Ayrshire Coast Early DaysConnections School motto New Farm Loch Arm's reach Mirror imageSpringWhite Tulips Troon Revisited Terra Firma Supper PartyPeace and Plenty DepthsCountry Dance Map of Coningham The American GirlII.Jawbone Walk Inheritance Previous Occupants At the Reservoir Three Ages of Man Losing TouchVisit-Losing touch Ghosts Reiteration OratorioStrathclyde Concerto SurfacesGlobe TrotterSainte FoyPresenceW hite-outAbove the Storm
￼Conn 1-9 3/5/95 11:51 pm Page57 58 60 62 63 64 iff 61 65 65 63 66 6768 69 70 71 72 73 74 75 76 77III.McGonagall’s Map Reconnoitring French ConnectionNorman Collie at Sligachan Inn Air and WaterCamp Jedibe Upper Clyde Upstream First lightVoicesWar memorialOrchard country ContrastsFrom the airEnvoiBody LanguageTe Maori5?Past Glories Choosing a Drawing Boudin at the Burrell FauveIn Your Dreams'cJ*.■fsSuOv/-£- .1\ Strangers in the Night■e_____Lady Anne’s DiaryOn her arrivalIn the Cape /InsomniafNOTES