￼Here’s what I saw when I tookthat hammering: alone is gross.Let us live in free association, where is not material. Plain dealing! Believe me (though I am swaying), a bent rule is unique. We shallbe shelf-employed! Today is concrete passion. Nail down this truth:I love you though the drill be rustyand the State confused.
￼Tess, in TunisiaReleased,she tilts over on her side.‘The Fall is only that,’ she says shaking sand from her hair, ‘when you wish returnsto Paradise. Go on, forget her.’She says we are inventingnew ways of shipping men and women and all her art is aiming fora raft that swimmers reach and share.She says this that it may be so.You did not worry as you laybeached together through a starless night; an obscured moon still pulls the tidesof billow-talk and pillow-friends.These words comefrom Proverbs, Tess, and the Koran; dogs bark above our heads and yet the caravan moves on.26
￼The Order of the DayIN THE MOUNTAINS10 Back Again11 Interlude on Mustagh Tower12 Sandy, Topping Out on Mustagh14 Entering Askole15 The Winter Climbing16 Crux18 Three Above Namche Bazaar19 After Everest20 AvalancheIN LOVE & POLITICS22 A Reader’s Note23 M azed24 Shetland25 About T ess26 Tess, in Tunisia27 Love-Torn Squaddie in Rannoch Torment28 Still29 Visiting30 Annie, in Spring31 Treaty32 Annie33 Gulf34 Annie, in November35 Ruth Says36 Spello, in the Afternoon37 Nut38 Covert Action39 Young American40 Fishing41 D, in a Checked Shirt42 D, Riding43 Heart & Irish44 Up the Baobab45 Exit46 Fictions
￼AcknowledgementsAcknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publica­ tions in which some of these poems first appeared: AlpineJournal, Chapman, Landfall (New Zealand), New Statesman, New WritingScot­ land, Poetry Review, Poetry with an Edge (Bloodaxe Books, 1988), The Scotsman and Verse. ‘Title of Poem’, ‘etc’were broadcast on Poetry Now (BBC Radio 3).The author gratefully acknowledges the help of a Scottish Arts Council W riters’ Bursary in completing this book.
￼HEAD WAS MUTEfelt ok felt well(a cheval across the summit)K2 in the distance looking good (suspicion of moisture behind my shades)Made a belay and took in the ropes as Jon came up. So how’s it going? Oh, wasted, youth...‘From Base Camp to the stream there is a path now and, the grass is yellow at the centre o f the path. ’13
￼Interlude on Mustagh TowerIn these high places we are melting outof all that made us rigid; our ice-screwshang loose on the fixed ropes to the Col. Monday in the Himalaya, the clouds are down, our objective is somewhere, but obscure -let it soar without us for a day!We lounge in thermals on the glacier,brewing and shooting the breeze, that improbable project of conversation among the living. Laughter rings across the ice. Why not?None of us will die today - that’s immortalityyou can draw on in a cigarette,harsh and sweet, the way we like it.Steam rises from the billy, Sandy pours.It is true high, worked for, that we passhand to hand between us with our brews.Men on ice, going nowhere and laughingat everything we cannot see but knowis there - among the cloud, on the Col,a hand of some sort is tightening our screws.
￼A Reader’s NoteCall him anything, call him Jim. At any road a Scottish male of a certain agestands hopeful, hesitating, lost.He scuffs the dust, unable to go on or back.I want to see him on the rack.Compressed or stretched, the heresies will show. And mock him carefully, you who goto govern or deplore, judgingor not judging, in all events undone.The riders of our times left notes behindof intrigues high and low; one sings of love, another of the shredding of a document...He scans these tales of power - screwed up, corrupt, infolded, though I would not have it so.22
￼The Winter Climbing(forMan)It is late January and at last the snow.I lie back dreaming about Glencoeas fluent, hungry, dressed in red,you climb up and over me. That passion claimed the darkest, useless monthsfor risk and play. You riseup on me, I rise through you...The shadowed face of Aonach Dubh where Mai first took me climbing and as we clanked exhausted, happy, downwards through the dark, I asked ‘What route was that?’ ‘Call itwhat you want - it’s new.’You reach the top and exit out;from way above, your cry comes down.The rope pulls tight. What shall we callthis new thing we’re about?These days we live in takingcare and chances. Why name it?My heart is in my mouth as I shout Climbing...15
￼About TessShe cocks her head, considersanother country, you. Smoke infiltrates your throat. The rasp that says you’re not dead yetis the trigger of seductions.‘And do you ever’, she enquires,‘act on your irresolution?’The bar’s de-stabilised, you colonize each other as folkies sing of Nicaragua.‘All right,’ one hand on hers, the other grips your car keys, ‘Why not?’There are reasons, but they melt like wax.Relax. Tonight you cross the border.You cast huge shadows as you get into the car.25
￼ShetlandHe sailed for Shetland, very near the edge, to bog & cliff & a celibate friend.She did her helpless best by him.He climbed all day and failed to fall.Light-hoarding stars above her bed,a full moon on the wall - he wanted to be dead, and badly. A mortal sin, she said, I tried it.Well, she was Catholic but that stuck.No way out but up. At the crux,he clutched into the chimney’s heart and heaved...He taped his knuckles, she poured the wine.Only reflected light this tenderness, but stillthat night they lay like pardoned thieves - baffled, eased, beside her moon, beneath her paper stars.24