￼Attila 43-64 18/9/92 7:39 am Page 49Did YOU buy a used British Gas share from this government?Tell Sidhe’s a nonexistent totally fictitious dork created at a ridiculous cost to us taxpayers by the spectacularly unimaginative alcohol-sodden Mogadon-brained gnomes of some tinpot advertising agency in order to persuade thousands of upwardly mobile and extremely acquisitive I’m-alright-Jack council-house-owning stone-cladding garden-gnome and MFI furniture-worshipping downmarket cut- price would-be J. Paul Gettys to open their poxy little piggy banks and invest their hard|®wned pennies in a public amenity which until very recently belonged to them anyway! TELL SID that it’s not travellers who waste taxpayers’ money as his amoeba-brained drinking mates seem to think but corrupt slimy government offi­ cials who sell off our industries at knockdown prices to their corp­ orate friends and puke-inducing scum in suits handed vastly profit­ able public monopolies on a plate who then pay themselves vast salaries while sacking half their workforce! TELL SID that the onlye reason the government wanted insignificant little nobodies like e him to indulge his pathetic Howard Hughes fantasies and grab apitifully irrelevant handful of meaningless shares in the first placewas so that they it could send him a threatening letter come elec­tion time telling him that should he have the effrontery to vote forthe evil Libyan-sponsored Saddam Hussein-fellating child mol­esters of the Labour Party his tiny little pound of flesh would go upin smoke and that therefore out of sheer naked nude bare unadornedself-interest he should vote Conservative! And if dear old non-exis­tent SID is so mind-boggiingiy, groin-tremblingly THICK that hestill can’t understand what the bastards are trying to do then justTELL SID that The Sun Says That British Gas Shares Give YouAids And Turn You Into A Lesbian And Gay!49
￼Attila 48-64 18/9/92 7:39 arn Page 50Dedicated to the considerable number of rappers who are for­ ever boasting bianely about their guns and their penises, talking about women in appallingly degrading terms, advocating violence against homosexuals, allying themselves with anti-Semitic crypto­ fascists lik^-±jO«is-£a4**kba*i, etc. If they were white, evwyeae would say ‘what a loud of misogynislic, homophobic, reactionary wankersP Because they’re black, loads of guilt-ridden white middle-class journalists - especially music journalists - fawn over them. This is exceptionally stupid and should stop RIGHT NOW.The Iron Men of Rapl"Teir itk'cM-*u.('Uu(cr\»| "iovi,t£-ae uJt>v«(,cJ| ^ 'You’re the iron men rappers with your big gold chains You talk like the clappers but you don’t use your brains The Grandmaster’s Message made me hold my breath but now I’d rather listen to Lawnmower Deth!You rap about your GOLD and you rap about your CAR and you rap about what good rappers you areyou rap about your GUNS and the money you make^ and the size oft yourr OUNE--EYED TRKOUUSERK SINAKE vy Yonu savy it’s bhifgfgser than the Albert Hallbut I bet it’s like an earthworm, very very smallYou say it’s bigger than the Albert Hallbut I bet it’s like a maggot or you ain’t got one at all! You run on stage with your guns in a ragelike angry prisoners fresh out of the cageYour finger’s on the trigger and you wanna ENGAGE turning on the chill in the new Ice AgeCMp A^hd there’s violence, violence in the air— ^jBut some of you like it, you don’t seem to care/• c- -And there’s violence, violence in the airbjBht some of you like it, you don’t seem to care50Now I don’t like the DOLLAR and I don’t like the GUN and the (w)rapping they come in don’t bother me noneI wanna rap fast and I wanna have funAnd I mean HAVE FUN not shoot someone!VLiUto‘•uo.nLui Uc if <ttxerp-t_/
￼^The rap I rap is black and whiteThis rap says unionise, don’t fightThis rap doesn’t wallow in liberal guiltIt just says equal up to the hiltThis rap’s got a penis of average sizeNot a huge great whale flopping out of its flies No gold, no chains, no hype, no liesJust a thinking brain and a pair of sharp eyes So wise up, rappers - and before you spout Find something original to rap about!I’ve had my say, now it’s over and outFrom MC Attila the poetry toutSaid MC Attila - signing out!Attila 48-64 18/9/92 7:39 am Page 51 eWith your massive testicles and concrete cock Gonna bust a gonad every time you rock! Every move in your body is designed to shock So yo! there shepherd boy, how’s your flock? Now I don’t wanna hear about segregation Don’t wanna hear about your perfect nation Don’t wanna hear about FarrakhanCos Farrakhan is an evil manAnd hey everybody, let’s make a showCos if Farrakhan gets you, you’re gonna go! From the hair on my head to my hairy scro’ I’m out of the bottle and I’m ready to blow...51/
￼Attila 48-64 18/9/92 7:39 am Page 52— ——IT’S NOT!All you need is a camera, notebook and penyou write down a number, then you write one down again We’re ignored by the nation, we go down the stationand we’ve got another hobby -masturbationBut, of course, not all rappers conform to this crude stereotype! MC Trainspotter, the world’s first rapping trainspotter, certainly doesn’t...He knows you don’t have to he really tough and live somewhere dangerous and have a gun and a hig penis to be a rapper!Boys in the Hood(Trainspotter Rap)MC Trainspotter, yeah, that’s me- and this is my homeboy,Nice-T!Now some people think that trainspotting’s rot... but me and my posse, we sayH/hey, don’t walk away, ’cos I’m talking to you "f /you know what they call us -The Platform 2 Live Crew!Now me & my homeboys work in a bank and at the weekend0 we go to the libraryXfn Saturday mornings we like shoppingand then we goamateur league groundhoppingI nearly caught pneumonia at Billingham Synthonia Wanna know the layout of the ground?I’ll phone ya!And at half time I’ve got everything I need' -j\ A nice telephone directory to readMC Trainspotter in the houseI’ve got the suss, and I’ve got the nousI don’t live in a ghetto like those rappers in the States I like the police— 'f yes, they’re my best mates...52
￼V7~~down at the stationjust ask me, it’ll fill me with elation! MC Trainspotter - yeah, that’s me Yo! there, homeboy!AtCila 48-64 18/9/92 7:43 am Page 53 e-I’ve never been arrested(that goes without saying)I’ve reported lots of people I’ve seen travelling without paying—f\dnd here’s what I say to every other rapping crew - well, I’m OK at rappingbut I’m not as good as you!But I do thinkyou spend far too much on your gearI could save you some moneyso please listen here:.Tue cuor-fitt Ou^e^I wouldn’t like a gold chain - somebody might mug meWg_'[tfo * P _\ .p jMy trainers are from Oxfani andthey cost 50p/• jyiy anorak’s my mum’s and the carrierbag was free!and I don’t want a baseball cap - they really bug me! i-sMuLDBrH»twsse we’re the ‘boys in the hood’and it keeps out the rain - now isn’t that good? A ydnd if you want informationWant a cup of tea?