￼'Defending Ireland's Soul1: Protestant Writers and IrishNationalism after IndependenceIIrish Nationalism, considered as ideology rather than practice,or faith rather than works, involves an intricate series of misunderstandings between Catholic Ireland, Anglican Ireland, and Presbyterian Ireland.These misunderstandings are reproduced in what I regard as misreadingsby some contemporary Irish writers and critics. Of course, at the present historical juncture no critic or writer can be detached from continuing processes. The critique of the past is the critique of the present.Yet a deconstructionist 'thirst for accusation' may lead us in circles. Thus W.J. McCormack might find a 'repressed ideology of sectarianism'^ in more places than 'Purgatory' (first published in On the Boiler, 1938)and Yeats's other versions of Irish Protestant history. Nationalismitself, as articulated by Protestants like Wolfe Tone and Thomas Davis, fiacL 'Cc repress sectarianism in order to include its authors. This has enabled Catholic Nationalism to deny its own sectarian constituents by invoking'theCommonMarneofIrishman'. Butperhapsweshouldapproachallrepressionwith analysis rather than accusation.2In a lecture last year Roy Foster observed that Yeats's ‘over-compensationas a marginalised l o s ft Protestant often led him into rigid and declaratory attitudes'. He then told an anecdote about a Dubliner who, after a similar remark on Foster's part, had protested: 'You can't talk about Yeats likethat! He was as Irish as I am.' In this essay I want to review some different strategies and rhetorics whereby Yeats and a -feu) of his Protestant literary successors, negotiate their marginalisation at thehands of Irishness as a Nationalist construct.During the fall-out after Partition and after Yeats the followingwriters found themselves implicated in the question of Protestantism
￼-2-and Nationalism: Hubert Butler (6.1900), Louis MacNeice (1907-1963)and John Hewitt (1907-1989). X *J«ll also occasionally Keep\n \n trPie. -fallout After H6S*.Macfteice occupies a point of intersection or transition between Anglo-Irish and Northern Protestant consciousness. He was, perhaps, partiallyrescuedfromeachbytheother,aswellasbyEngland. Inhis autobiography The Strings are False (mostly written in 1940) a memory from Sherbo rne, his English prep-school, epitomises divided allegiance :On the Twelfth of July Powys came into my dormitory and said: 'Whatis all this they do in your country today? Isn't it all mumbo-jumbo?' Remembering my father and Home Rule and the bony elbows of MissCraig and the black file of mill-girls and the wickedness of Carson and the dull dank days between sodden haycocks^man to man to Powysand giving the lie to the Red Hand of Ulster was power, was freedom,meant I was nearly grown up. King William is dead and his white horse with him, and Miss Craig will never put her knuckles in my ears again. But Powys went out of the dormitory and Mr. Cameron came in, his underlip jutting and his eyes enraged. 'What were you saying to Mr. Powys?' Oh this division of allegiance! That the Twelfth of July was mumbo-jumbo was true, and my father thought so too, but the moment Mr. Cameron appeared I felt rather guilty and cheap. Because I had been showing off to Powys and becauseMr. Cameron being after all Irish I felt I had betrayed him.MacNeice's situation as 'an Irishman of Southern blood and Northern upbringing, whose father was a Protestant bishop and also a fervent Home Ruleralso points to long-standing strains between Northern and Southern Protestants, not only with respect to Home Rule. This friction derived from Ulster's virtual monopoly of Presbyterianism. The established church throughoutthe island conspired to defeat the radical Presbyterians in 1798, andto secure the Act cf Union and its own privileges. During the nineteenth century, with nonconformist disabilities removed and Catholic solidarity advanced, Northern Protestants drew closer together. In 1834 the 'Oldand foghorn*, X said it K4S And L felt upffUJi. lo Speaking4
￼Light' Presbyterian minister Henry Cooke 'proclaimed the banns of marriage between the Presbyterians and the traditionally conservative Anglicans ... a move of great significance for the future of Irish politics'.^ Yet today's split between Official and Democratic (Paisleyite) Unionists reflects the original fault-lines. And the differing class-balance of Southern Protestants,whether Unionist or Nationalist, often set themapart from the industrialised bourgeoisie and working class of the North East. It's the contrast between the ethos of Trinity College Dublin(even up to the 1960s), and the belatedly^founded Queen's University of Belfast.Thus, for example, Tom Paulin misunderstands Yeats's share in these prejudices when he regards his dislike of the Northern Irish as instancing'the paradoxical, even lop-sided nature of Yeats's nationalism'. (Aswe shall see, there is a lot of paradoxical lop-sided literary Nationalism about.) In 1938 MacNeice, on more empirical grounds than Yeats's, favourably contrasted the (remaining) Southern landed gentry with the cultural cringeof their Northern Unionist counterparts:
￼d be said that the Southern gentry too usually sent their S o n sucated in England. Again, in 'Portrait of a Minority' (1954) iutler, speaking as a member of this class, regretted that itLcated from its natural leadership of Irish Protestantism:do not like solid blocks of opinion but, in fact, there is nothing ery reassuring about our Southern Protestant incapacity for congealing nto aggressive or defensive blocks. It merely means that thelster Protestant, a more fanatical and bitter champion of the eformation, assumes the leadership of Irish Protestant opinion,nd that leadership really belongs by tradition to the Protestants>f the South, the people of Swift and Berkeley, Lord Edward Fitzgerald, Jmith O'Brien, Parnell, men who often jeopardized their careersmd even sacrificed their lives in the cause of an Ireland, free and united. So now our amiable inertia, our refusal to express grievances or cherish hopes about Ireland, are really delayingour ultimategUnity and the reconciliation of our two diverging communities.Ime to question some readings of Yeats's own relation to 'Protestant .A,~iancy' in W.J. McCormack's Ascendancy and Tradition and Seamus Deane's£^*ctufic<7 -ftiurkic Revivals. I put the term in ^ because the historical geographerThat the eminently reasonable Butler should echo Yeatsian pedigrees9Whelan recently objected to its being used in social and culturalM,'ixts, whereas it strictly signified constitutional and politicalJ '•i.'ii.is 'Commentary on A Parnellite at Parnell's Funeral' associates Ascendancy l an eighteenth-century Protestant 'sense of responsibility' whichi way to the nineteenth-century 'Garrison, a political party of Protestant Catholic landowners, merchants and officials'.^ McCormack uses Z'.^. Commentary effectively to show that 'Purgatory' broods on this decline,i also that the daughter of the great house who marries a 'groom' has - >licitly transgressed sectarian boundaries as well as those of class:rimination in favour of Anglicans after 1690. The Unionist regime tormont developed a latter day brand of 'Ascendancy1-which explains term's currency in Irish literary-critical debates. Yeats himself ,i*
￼-5-'Evidence of the play's genesis, in the manuscript scenario and in earlier utterances of Yeats's, specifies its assumption of the Protestant/Catholic aru/tagonism as tribal if not racial, as the operational field of tabooand totem But McCormack does not discuss the mid-1930s context which links 'Parnell's Funeral', the Commentary, 'Purgatory' and Yeats's sense that two tribal forces were still fighting 'in our blood' to generate12the Irish nation.The commentary begins with the Battle of the Boyneand ends with the Parnellite window of opportunity. Even Parnell's falla,meant that'Unionists and Nationalists' stopped living behind‘party wall 1 AA'we began to value truth ... free discussion appeared among us for the first time'. 13 However, 'Parnell's Funeral' suggests, in the wake of Yeats's disillusionment over divorce, censorship and other matters, that Parnell's real funeral, the funeral of free cross-cultural discussion,is now taking place: 'Had de Valera eaten Parnell's heart', 'Had Cosgrove eaten Parnell's heart ...' Neither of the Civil War parties has absorbed the values which, for Yeats, link the eighteenth-century Protestant nation, Parnell and his own art.This incomplete mutual digestion between Catholic and Protestant Ireland troubles 'Purgatory' in the more extreme idiom of Yeats's last writings. His sexual and genetic metaphor implies that the Anglo-Irish have conspired in their woh downfall. TheB c a q q I groom evokes not only'0'Connellite democracy' but the 'loose-lipped demagogues' of de Valera's Ireland, the figure unpleasantly characterised in the preceding rant of 'On the Boiler' as ' some typical elected man, emotional as a youthful chimpanzee' and- p e r h a p s that 1drunken,vaingloriouslout1 with whom Maud Gonne/Ireland had contracted a mesalliance . Oiithe IBoiler begins with 'Why Should Not Old Men be Mad?' which laments Maud's and Iseult's fall from Yeatsian grace. In 'Purgatory' the old man who
￼has killed his father in the burning house now kills his son to prevent furtherdegeneration. Buthisghostlyparentsmustendlesslyrelive their mis-begetting of a nation? Yeats's imagination seems to inhabita purgatorial Ireland which so far mocks his hopes for cultural fusionsflrwjic-Irish fiooicji burned dcu)/i i* che a r c a. ‘juihtcsscintidl S>j/vtbcl. Through the 'mad' license of his old-man protagonist, fie ironically torchesthe devalued 'great gazebo' and pursues Lear-like revenges. So the spirit that*suffers because of its share ... in the destruction of an honouredhousederives more from the twentieth century than from the nineteenth as McCormack, or the eighteenth as Donald Torchiana suggests.^ In this reading 'Purgatory' represses worse than sectarianism. Yet we should surely focus on Yeats's disaffection from ruling Nationalism in the 1930s, rather than on the historical or literal validity of his Ascendancy myths •> His houses, dynasties and marriages do not only 'attend to the declineof Ireland's landed gentry'. *■As a form of cultural defence, they are metaphors for a wider Protestant predicament. We evade its nature, its cry of distress, if we exclusively follow Seamus Deane following McCormack:Yeats's account of the Anglo-Irish tradition blurs an important distinction between the terms 'aristocracy' and 'fiscendancy'. Had he known a little more about the eighteenth-century, he would have recognised that the Protestant Ascendancy was, then and since,a predominantly bourgeois social formation. The Anglo-Irish were held in contempt by the Irish-speaking masses as people of no without lineage and with nothing to recommend them other than^he success of their Hanoverian cause over that of the Jacobites.Deane's counter-assumption of Gaelic aristocracy indicates b^Ht the Yeatsian *rhetoric has some bearing on the reality of sectarian antagonisms bothin the 1930s and the 1980s. In neither case does the point seem to be getting eighteenth-century history right. Deane too goes back to the Boyne. Elsewhere he contests the indigenous claims of the Irish Literary Revival(asYeats'sIrishIrelandopponentshaddone): 'ThewholeIrish■Cevival is ... a movement towards the colony and away from the19mother-country, a replacement of "Englishness" by "Irishness"'.And
￼overtones in Yeats's later'his mature verse combines2^ an elitist dedication'.“writings^as does Tom Paulin when he says that muscle-flexing Protestant triumphalism with Yet to prove Yeats a colonialist or loyalist,-7-he avoids mentioning the occasion (divorce) of Yeats's most famous Protestant protest: '^jhen he told the Irish Senate that the Anglo-Irish were "nopetty people" ... He was translating into a proud assertion an almost comically absurd historical fiction'. 20 MacNeice^closer to the event,21and 'tike Yeats.,.. JoroV^hiC up id an Irish middle-class Protestant family1, Irish£0.0 translate Yeats's translation: 'Living in the Free StateAYeats had come to realise more vividly the drawbacks of Catholic Ireland* * and his opinion of the old Protestant Ascendancy rose accordingly'. 22 Detailed studies of Yeats's politics in the 1920s and 1930s, particularly those by Bernard Krimm and Paul Scott Stanfield, 23 seem more relevantthan reading 'Ascendancy' back over Yeats's entire career and its pre-history. Deane unhistorically contrasts 'Pearse's line of heroes (Tone, Emmet,Davis, Lalor, Mitchel ) and Yeats's line (Berkeley, Swift, Burke, Goldsmith)^ thus rewriting Yeats's Nationalist record. Was it for this he wrote'September 1913'? And when McCormack says: 'I take Protestant Ascendancy to be the central cultural assumption of Yeats's meditation on his own inheritance. By it he measured the politics of the Irish Free State ... he underplays the extent to which the measuring-instrument was shapedby what it measured. Yeats's fictions of Anglo-Irish history were a latent strand in his imaginative weave which might not have stood out so prominently if his early hopes for the new state had been realised.Deane, from his contemporary stancL-point, may be picking up Unionistis again not to Clear the distressed and squeezed Protestant Nationalist ^ —jforwhom 1CroSS»v)g the Border'MacNeice may phrase the matter more accurately when he refers to thewasneverreallyanoption.i2A:25
￼-8-'complex peculiarities of that Protestant minority to which Yeats, like28many another ardent nationalist, belonged1 . After quoting Shaw's prefaceto John Bull's Otfter Island ('I am violently and arrogantly Protestant by family tradition; but let no English government therefore count on my allegi^ance')MacNeice comments:Yeats too was born and bred Protestant (which in Ireland does implyboth violence and arrogance) and, whatever his flirtations withthe Cabbala, the Upanishads, and so cr., and however great and understandable his envy of Maud Gorge's conversion to Rome, his motto to the endwas 'No Surrender*.Yeats's poetic strategies for avoiding surrender became more extremeas he felt more besieged. The mutations of ancestral houses and eighteenth-u)hichcentury Protestant names are a graph of marginalisation reached its"Anadir in Purgatory. Besides the state-ideology's lack of attention toCCn Ci/ICmijProtestant liberties, there was also Protestant emigration and the gradualAdisappearance of Yeats's cultural world. Paul Scott Stanfield concludes:In the 1930s his solitude increased. The ascendancy of de Valera made the Anglo-Irish tradition of independent nationalism a virtually untenable faith. Most of those with whom Yeats had at one timeor another made common cause - John O'Leary,^ohn Synge, Lady Gregory, Kevin O'Higgins, George Russell - were dead.Marginalised groups assert their presence in territorial and genealogical terms:sI declare this tower is my symbol; I declare tThis winding, gyring, spiring treadmill of a stair is myancestral stair;That Goldsmith and the Dean, Berkely and B c r k e hes^Ctravelled there.('Blood and the Moon')The higher the rhetoric and the appeal to ancestry , the lower the influence and the population-level. Yeats's response in the later 1920s to themurder of that honorary Protestant Kevin O'Higgins, and to the dyingof Lady Gregory, already combines eleg y and defiance. However, 'CoolePark, 1929' concentrates on Coole as the symbolic locus of the Irish
￼-9-Literary Revival ('ft dance-like glory that those walls begot'); whereasParkin 'Coole and Ballylee, 1931' Yeats leads up to the Revival's epitaph - 'We were the last Tomantics' - with two stanzas affirming a dynastic'great glory' which underpins the artistic achievemgrr.ts. Presumably Yeats is using Coole to eulogise and elegise the totality of Anglo-Irish culturaleffort culminating in the Revival:Beloved books that famous hands have bound, Old marble heads, old pictures everywhere ...But boasted antiquity and fame, the metamorphoses of family into house into art, cannot withstand the sense of cultural crisis. Whereas themovement of 'Coole Park, 1929' is centripetal ('That seemed to whirlupon a compass-point'), that of 'Coole and Ballylee, 1931' is centrifugal and headlong. In the former the swallows come and go, in the latterthe waters and swan represent an intensifying flux:But all is changed, that high horse riderless Though mounted in that saddle Homer rode Where the swan drifts upon a darkening flood.The new context for the refrain of 'Easter 1916' must be deliberate.31 However we judge Yeats's interest in fascism or General O'Duffy ,it was crucially conditioned by his darkening situation as a marginalised Southern Protestant , anxious to be influential on an elitist ratherthan a democratic basis. When O'Duffy's school too proved 'a crowd'(not to mention a potential Catholic Front), like Communism and Nationalist demagoguery, Yeats opted for 'Anglo-Irish solitude', thus making a virtue of necessity. In On the Boiler his obsession witheugenics, with 'stocks', clearly originates in the dwindling of a community and itspower: 'Asthe nominated element began to die out - almost all were old men - the Senate declined in ability and prestige.' 32 The strident tone in Yeats'slast poems which approximates to that of On the Boiler also issues from Protestant marginalisation:
￼Or else I thought her supernatural;As though a sterner eye looked tftrough her eyeOn this foyj worldin its decline and fallOn gangling stocksgrown great, great stocks run dry; Ancestral pear|6 all pitched into a sty,Heroic reverie mocked by clown and knave, . And wondered what was left for massacre to save. C 'A/ i\ H?<d JWhereas in the 1920s, and in the Coole Park poems, Yeats kept aristocracyat a metaphorical distance from art, or separated his tower from Coole,in the 1930s there can be a crude convergence of aesthetic and social superiority: 'ancestral pearls', 'sing whatever is well-made1, 'iJe Irish ... Climb to our proper dark that we may trace/The lineamentsof aplummet- measured face'. Yeats'srhetoric like his imagery climbs on top of allhis precariously balanced assets, just as the mad McCoy — evidently a evangelical Protestant — ascends the boiler 'to read the Scriptures and denounce his neighbours.' 33Tom Paulin considers that Yeats resorted to 'a formless mysticrage' instead of 'attacking specific targets and injustices'. Rather, (CQCCryc RoHSdtl±Jperhaps, his weariness with the latter activity led him not to AE's^resigned exile, but to rhetorics of 'No Surrender' in which a mysterious elitedriven to the margins broods on its restoration: 'In cavern, crevice/or hole^/Defending Ireland's soul' /^Obviously, 'that unfashionable gyre'trad.!also has to do with Yeats's concept of art and his hatred of modern mechanicalAphilosophies. But one might, for instance, contrast the demeanour ofHenry Middleton in 'Three Songs to the One Burden' with 'the men of theold black tower'. Middleton is evidently a marginalised Protestant reducedi\itii o-to ineffectual moralising^and^doing his own house-work in;^'small forgottenhouse'. Unlike Mannion, tinker and practical eugenicist, in the previous song, Middleton's lifestyle is ironically at odds with the refrain -or is 'burden' a pun? -
￼- 11-From mountain to mountain ride the fierce horsemenThe men in the tower are certainly fierce, and would have been usefulat the Siege of Derry£ 'they but feed as the goatherd feeds' ^ unlike Middleton'stamedomesticity. Interaliatheblacktowermaybethelast redoubt of the Anglo-Irish Protestant nation, of Yeatsian Nationalism, of the dead king, Parnell:Those banners come to bribe or threatenOr whisper that a man's a foolWho, when his own right king's forgotte^ Cares what king sets up his rule ____ If he died long agoyWhy do you dread us so?Perhaps this is the Williamite spirit transposed into a Jacobite mode.Seamus Deane and Denis Donoghue have commented on Yeats's use ofCthe term Vvie Irish' at the end of 'The Statues':We Irish, born into that ancient sectBut thrown upon this filthy modern tideAnd by its formless spawning fury wrecked Climb to our proper dark that we may trace The lineaments of a plummet - measured face.Both, I think, take 'We Irish' to embrace Catholic Nationalist Ireland.Deane subjects what he sees as 'an abstract idea of essence' or 'mystiqueof Irishness', to a critique which seems more appropriate to Pearse than35 / 36 to Yeats. Doncghue is kinder to 'an acceptable degree of self-consciousness' ,but also misses the point that We Irish' secretesa mainly Protestant€S'sence of Irishness (years earlier Yeats had noted in his journal that ctlkjays 37SCn££has been Protestant in Ireland'Ireland, perhaps 'spawning' as much as 'this filthy modern tide', in a rhetorical turning of the tables. Like the 'indomitable Irishry' of'Under Ben Bulben'— 'No Surrender' with an Anglo-Irish flourish— the last stanza of 'The Statues' parallels the notorious passage in On the Boiler:). X'C’ marginalises Catholic
￼- 12-although the Irish masses are vague andexcitable because they have not yetbeen moulded and cast, we have asgood blood as there is in Europe.Berkeley, Swift, Burke, Grattan, Parnell, Augusta;. Gregory, Synge, Kevin O'Higgins, are the true Irish people, and there is nothingtoo hard for such as the^e. Ifthe Catholic names are ^gw> history will soon fill the gap.'The Statues' implies that Pearse could not have 'summoned Cuchulain tohisside' iftheAnglo-IrishorYeatsianplummethadnotfirstmeasured the nation. Hence Yeats's entitlement to reclaim the national soul even when his voices speak from their final dark margin:old bones upon the mountain shake?