￼AbelI seem to follow the lure and flow of a story. Then glimpses of a garden or a school dormitory Shift and interchange. The frames begin to slip Quicker than I understand. I'm losing my grip.Why this crowd? And why are they hunting me? Faster and faster. Suddenly I'm on a promontory", The frenzy of chase closing its faceless threat. Over the edge. I've woken in a snow of sweat.Frenchie, let's get Frenchie. Again a tableau Of schoolboy persecution sways in some undertow Of memory. I hear the swishing wavelike noise Of a mob in hot pursuit. Our ritual sacrifice. A sallow and dapper stranger weaves and dodges Down a corridor with a swarm of blurred visages Close on his heels, whipping boy and scapegoat, A swoon of oneness singling his difference out.This evening in a country that I'd first comeTo half a life ago, some blond youths loomUp the platform, beer-cans glinting in the dark. My suspicious swarthness. A Greek or even a Turk?’Is it here we trounce foreigners?' sneers a voice. Partly his show for the gang, partly his menace.An ugly moment. I hurry on trying to pretendI didn't understand, scanning exits for my friend.
￼Unbroken line of pogroms, this blindman's bluff.A planet now at stake, perhaps we know enoughTo reveal even the slants and bias of our lens?A stark figure transverses our shed millennia,That first victim forever crying his innocence. Stay the knife. Children of a jealous violence, Fugitives on the earth, may we still ask his pardon Say to me, brother Abel, that I'm your guardian.
￼BOUNDARIESSpringbrunn ar du, vars soligt glittrande str&le sk5n i sin jamvikt, skon i sin formstr&ngab&ge, skon i sin styrka, agermakten att alska granser och adla m&tt.A fountain you are, whose sunnily glittering beam,beautiful in its equilibrium, beautiful in its form-stx'ict arc, beautiful in its strength, possessesthe power to love limits and noble dimensions.♦Karin Boye(Translation: David McDuff)/
￼HopscotchOur chalked figure of boxes squared off and interlocked. Overlappingsof sides, t-shapes, half-shared divides. A groundwork for high jinks.'Your go! ' And everyone hunkers to watch if I toe the line. Footfall vigil.Is this why the Germans call hopscotch'playing a game of heaven and hell '?Such passion for limits and thresholds. Johnston 's shop in Pettigo, its entrances in both counties. A foot in two worlds. Abutment and frontier. Old ambivalences.Or the way sometimes exact same sounds seemed to slide and play with words;a child is riddling out how 'bounds' means 'confines' and 'bounces forwards'.Then, the pivot homewards. Our swift about-face. Thiyill and crisis of turning; one ankle clasped, one hand aloft,frail balance of gravity and yearning.
￼A skittish jump. Again our spi'eadeagle heavy-footed landings astride a border Stop-go momentum of hop and straddle. That need of lines. That leap 's desire
￼NoonI've fallen in love again with gazing. A lake is absorbing shimmered transfers of grey alders and ripplings of leaves.A hollow twig hesitates, then steers outward, canoeing this ice-age maw. Mountain eye. Basin of contemplation.A skimmed stone tumbles and disappears. Minutiae of an aeon. Noon is filling the air with its riddles. Who am I?Archaeologies of thought define me:the words I use, phrases, gestures.Is everything seen with an encoded eye?Piecemeal layers of address and response. Process of encounters: fall-out, settlings accruals, a womb of residues and ores.Silent undertows. Still-living sediment. A mountain lake swallows and endures these slow, deep accumulations of sludge.In the dark and light of every about-face some beckoning aim, a hovering remembrance My spirit is watching over the waters.
￼StoryA man turns hostage forhis friend's release:It is a faiy, far better place that I go to. ..Abandon without return. Gratuity of sacrifice.It is a far, far better thing that I do...that cadenza of Dickens' Tale of Two Cities and a child bursts in tears. Must it be so?One story will haunt him all his living days.The wartime girl with her German soldier flees over the frontiers. Or tell him, now as he greys,of an African spirit between one world and another who stays around as a child just to make happythe bruised face of a woman who'd become his mother.My name is made illustrious in the light of his.To break and enter another's brokenness and glory.This is the story I'll touch in every caress.
￼SunlightTwo children swimming out to the low tide rocks and a woman watching. Breaststrokes. Headlong aspirations of dips and bobs across the water.Her lovely givenness a vigilance of substitution, hostage to every breath and splash. Stange paradox the further they swim away, the nearer they are.'That 's my place in the sun ' is how the usurpation of the whole world began. And I fill with wonderwatching a woman watching. What is this reflex?An abandon and weightlessness of concern. Pure undergoing. Almost as if they float in the matrix of her being, drifting in passivities of creation.Some overflow of boundaries weaves its intrigues of motherhood. A debt being payed before the loan, as though she usurps herself in watching overthe whirl of their busy limbs oaring back water in sunlight, the whole gown of her life turned inside out. Her face glories in this reversal.Some obsessive patience hears an ungiven order. Does an echo somehow anticipate its sound? She's so full of answers before they ever call.
￼MergingNursing your cold's fever I'm forever nine Worrying there by my mother's bedside years ago.A blind is drawn low to guard her eyes from sunshine, Slowly I wipe her brow with a sponge. It's as thoughTwo women are merging into one. I swab her hairline, Breathing and undergoing all she'll have to undergo.A sudden exhaustion seizes me. Now I watch for a sign Maybe she's begun to doze. I leave. Sneaking. Tiptoe.I wanted to be the Samaritan pouring my oils and wine But was I some skulking Levite abandoning her pillow?I know to serve you better I need to hold the line, Yet where that line should go, how can I ever know?Here nursing your fever will I be forever nine?You gaze a gaze that seems to say: 'To think it's so'To think for someone else even this face of mineIs the face of a certain man going down to Jericho'.