￼Garrett 30/7/91 5:59 pin Page 35The gate, the yard, the window where I’d written Names, all welcomed my return.And still I’m on the outside looking in. OuvrefmoiTa porte pour que je puisse te revoir. ***Douai, Cambrai, Ecourt, Rumaucourt.It is not names that change or disappear,But faces and their features, like a rumour Tongues and time pull out of shape. HereI can turn my back on the unanswered door, Knowing who stands behind, my hand lightOn the latch to lift and open, ready to showMe round, knowing my way in, as out,By heart, a journey of the blood, the slow Footfall of diastole and systole through the night.***Turning back, I leave things as I found them:Place in its pot the bright geranium,By the door in a yard at the heart of Rumaucourt, Between Douai, Cambrai, the Pas de Calais and the Nord, In the crease of a map scuffed blank by endless folding.Only the map o f the blood I ’ll keep, to tuck In here, and here; the spacious holdingsO f the head; the heart’s soft ruck.■e-t35
￼RiddleI am the difficult silk that slides from your grasp, I am lace petticoats and the knee-high swirl,I am an old sea-captain’s white moustache,I am the perm that will not hold its curl,I am the land’s dropped slip and rising shift, I am a piece of froth, a bagatelle,I am relinquishment and eternal theft,I am a gesture of greeting and farewell.
￼GarretC 30/7/91 5:59 pm Page 37Lost PropertyKneel, and let us pray for the departed:A sulphurous incense chokes the station vaults,A pigeon coughs; the platform is deserted. Guilty-eyed, while others slept in prayerI scoured the hassock’s cross-stitch for some fault As though it were my soul; and found none there.A labour of devotion: pious kissesSmothering the cushion where my kneesGrew numb and bore the imprint of those stitches, Burden of the Cross. A priest intones,Feet shuffle for Communion to easeThe weight, and catch the last train home.The rails are silent, empty as the aisleWhen rush-hour’s past. A platform sweeper brushes Up confetti into piles.It’s growing dark. A thin girl stands and watchesAs he sweeps the crumbs that drowsy birdsHave missed. I wake. And there are wordsFor this; but none so fittingly expressedAs by my own hand cupped around my breast.037t-e-
￼30/7/91 6:11 pm Page 63ImpostorDon’t think that I don’t know your games, You understudy muse, with your acrostic Heart and chiffon soul - slickGloss on bloodless lips.I do. I know the closet whereYou lock your anagramatising mind, Word-flowers, word-animalsWith pop-in legs and petals.How, in the dark you take them out, Your poets, one by one, and count Them; tucking each bauble back Bright-brittle, in Christmas wrapping.And Oh when you hang them on your tree. Save on some branch a place for me - ' Sweet victim - your cutest fairy:And I shall honour you with suchHowls as would haul black hagsAnd matted beasts from their lairs, Dragging the reins of your blonde hair, Bare on the bare back of nightmare.That’s how we play. No six to start,No lies, no honesty. Only the heartWith its four black holes - See?There are no rules. Now hand me that key.
￼Garrett 29/7/91 10:14 am Page 64History Goes to WorkThe soft-boiled egg is emptiedBut makes a humpty-dumpty head Reversed. Numbskull! Bald pate! You know the spoon’s importunate Knock knock will wake the dead.The silver spoon lies on its back And spoons the room all up - Side-down but never spills a drop: The ovoid walls adapt their laws And never show a crack.The egg lies in the silver spoonAnd yok^less words lie on the tongue And all that’s in the spoon-shaped room Swears it is square; no booksWere cooked. The egg is done.Remorse rests in its velvet drawer Lapped in the sleep of metaphor, The soul rests in the open palm And will not put its shell back on, And calmly waits for more., ft /k64©