￼Garrett 29/7/91 10:06 am Page 31eTheir faces ghost elsewhere; but someone’s left His smile in a glassBeside the sink. The loving bubbles cling Where white and pink a plaster rictus driftsIn mute suspense: smothered laughter doubling His collapsed lips’ loss.When sourmouthed morning comes, he’ll find them both - The laughter and the loss -Swallowing grief with the inward gasp of mirth,Putting senescence in its place, teethIn theirs, hiding pointless truth beneath The necessary false.Beneath the door, a strand of strawlight slipping Dawn’s drawn lot.She’ll try to sweep it out, the woman sleeping Cruelly bare without her body’s apronBundled here, neat, far from the undone Flesh, its careful knot.ThresholdsLoosed in the yard like gangaboon hens, to grubFor treasure sunk in mud;Flouting defense de, verboten, forbidden, we robbed Decay of its blistered carapace, breaking the crustIn greed for communion: crumbs in our hands and rust In our mouths, like the taste of blood.Swung by day from disastered beams, swungAbove splintered kingdoms of straw, / Tossed like chaff through asthmatic halflight, spunInto darkness, drunk on parabola, high in the crooked Rafters’ cage, stalling the ripcord, hookedOn the lapse of the backward yaw.31