￼POEMS OF 2 POEMS OF ZjPOEMS OF ZIn crdkASGr edited, byPAUL HYLAND Pages from Z’s notebookPagesfrom Z ’s notebookCopyright ®Paul Hyland 1982 All rights reservedISBN: 0 906427 44 4First published 1982 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SNNewcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.The publisher acknowledges the financial assistance of Northern Arts.Some of these poems first appeared in New Poetry 5 (Hutchinson/Arts Council - P.E.N., 1979) and in South WestTypesetting & cover printing byTyneside Free Press Workshop Ltd, Newcastle upon Tyne.Printed in Great Britain byUnwin Brothers Ltd, Old Woking, Surrey.Review.
Z has left us forty poems.PREFACE￼It will be clear why it is difficult for me to disclose how these poems came into my possession. Their unexpectedness and their unexpected power, that made such an impact on me, are the important things about them. In any case, I have nothing illuminating to say about their background, for all my know­ ledge of it comes from them. All I have is a small, rather dog­ eared notebook of forty unlined pages, each with a poem pencilled upon it in English.The dedication and the quotations from Lear and Jonson are scribbled inside the front cover. At the head of the first page is written Poems ofZ.In passing Z’s notebook to the publisher I have become involved in preparing the poems for the press. When he made revisions Z ’s usual practice was, it seems, to erase the original— ‘pencil stitched/and smudged across a grubby page’—but where he has not done this I have taken the two readings as alternatives, and have chosen the one I judged the better. I have also made a small handful of amendments to Z’s sparse punctuation, for the sake of clarity of consistency.Lor] r/the U.K. for a number ofyears. The poems are certainly aboutZ seems to have been engaged in intelligence activities inthat, but I think it unlikely that our counter-espionage service will glean much from these pages. The poet—for this is what, in a crisis of self-examination, Z became—is not concerned with ‘Names and Places/^Technical Detail, Plans/iPolitical Praxis, M i s c e l l a n e o u s ’; h e a s k s ‘W h a t d o e s t h e h e a r t k n o w ’, a n d w r i t e s of his own tenderness and violence, duplicity and openness, his faithlessness and spiritual hunger. From his world within our world, employing our language, he casts a cool eye on E n g l a n d , ‘t h e E n g l a n d I l o v e ’. H e s p e a k s m o v i n g l y o f t h e w o r l d of his childhood; the spy remembers his father and writes:. . . all the seasonsgone for which he, his weathered faceupturned, gathered intelligenceHere we have an extraordinary view ofan extraordinary poetic development. The start must have been tentative, but once assured ofwhat he was about I feel sure that Z wrote the poems as they stand in the notebook, one after another, each dependent on the one before, each qualified by the next. They demonstrate a sharpening of vision and a hardening of intention probably unsuspected at the outset. The naivety of the enterprise was to Z, I think, an essential element of it. Its success was perhaps as much of a surprise to him as it is to us. He felt it was not attainable in his own language. That Z should write so well in English is surely remarkable, but it is also crucial to his purpose:I need decode the words I do it in EnglishI adopt that tongueTowards the end he anticipates returning home and recalls M*** (an informant?) who returned ‘from the fascists’ hands’ with his tongue cut out:muscles at his tongue’s root fought with the air in his open moutha crock at the endof an arc of blood. We cried out for himPAIR HYLAND
￼Towards the end he anticipates returning home and recalls M*** (an informant?) who returned ‘from the fascists’hands’ with his tongue cut out:muscles at his tongue’s root fought with the air in his open moutha crock at the endof an arc of blood. We cried out for himZ has left us forty poems.-in memory of my father who knew how to talk and of my mother who knew how to sing-in memory of my father who knew how to talk and of my mother who knew how to sing‘Thou whoreson zed! thou unnecessary letter!’‘Z is a letter often heard amongst us, but seldome seene. ’-Lear-JonsonPAUL HYLAND
￼This is sudden/ this to be a poet& need my comrades would scoff atif they knew, scoff in our own tongue -You an agentfrom a thriller’s cover you a blank face under a black hatYou a poet—I say it too in my own tongueI need decode the words I do it in EnglishI adopt that tongueit moves differentlyin my mouth, it swellsIf across these pagesit speaks I will hand them to my friend the professor at S***, he will translate back into my own tongueThat will not be suddenthat handing overthis notebook when it is full
￼IIThis is like taking off clothes heavy coats one at a time each one less burdenthe weight of keeping warm gone in ^room with oil-light and water breathing in ironThat’s what it’s like sheddingclothes, hardware, braces,trousers and at the endsno shame. No shamwShe sings to me in my own tongue songs I will forget in LondonI pitch my gurgles back to hermy poems she can’t understandIIIYou see there is nothing naive and sentimental asa grown man with soft hands and a calloused heart starting out as poetThe idea of it anyway. From my rented table through the spacious grid of sash windows I keep watch on Georgian LondonAs I once spied from a pane set into thick thatchon my father in the yard the pigs rooting, my sisters walking out in the woodIn a room with oil-lightlying in elbow-warm waterthe grown flesh fallen away bathing in the iron bath supported by my mother’s arm her free hand rinsing my limbswhen I should have been sleeping. Opposite, the porticoes in linethe columns and pedimentsall at once I am astonishedat the weight of masonryI walk in and out of every day________
IV￼In the streets of languageI need no maps any more.If I were to try words of love my tongue would tasteof their dust and litterIntimacy that is paid for -after sleepless nights sometimes street signs are foreign flags pinned to great architecture roads veer off at wrong anglesI am a beast turned drab driven in from the far country to scavenge in dustbinsand basement entriestainted by offal and old bonesMy lack of conditionmy dullness is protective colouration for missionthe noblest drive of my kind to survive, depraved appetiteThis pencil and papermy belling bark that shouldfly meadows and pierce woods pitched off monstrous buildings in the streets of languageVAs a boy I was one learning to be moreOne with the pigs in their pen far inland chucking the acorns from a holed bucket,the sea a dream of passionOne with my sisters’boys little man among little men One with my aunt in town in my white stiff thingsOne for my first communionOne for the party, party-manIn London now I am legion Legion for we are manyI would invite my pigs here for my first communion — they would rush outwards in all directionsAnd every English shore they dashed themselves over trotters gashing own throats would wash with their goreI would be oneI have learned to be moreI1^,
￼VIThe pigs stay at homeI wade the English shores where burns and becks empty with great sewers called riversOr I dive in the deep waters —one of my elements— rouse oysters from their beds like drowned corroded fruitThey are hard nuts to crack with crabbed brown hands and a stainless knife’ssharp point, broad haftI unhinge and chuck hundreds the years, a stinking middenthe pearls, mostly small and grey I send home to the pigsVIImy father points downriver to tell me that it runs through another country all the way to the seaThe sea trips off his tonguel(i>ke gossip—he has not seen it but knows it’s worth talking about —it is salty he saysand larger than all the landI lie dreaming of itits smell comes up through cracks in the floorboards from bacon curing under rafters under my bedW ith cows on the riverbank I sniff for it but turnto face the mountains where it comes fromwhere rain from the <pea fallsNothing, not thunder, not flood nor cataract prepared mefor the raw deep voice of it under the deck, the lullabyof her who bore me on her breastYears dulled that wonderthe shells a heap of deaf ears.Now I sift through their clatter clutching them at my head listening for the voice of my father
￼VIIII creep nearer and nearer —my sisters hide their faces even safe inside the house - the nuzzled ground slavers and sucks at my shoesI creep close to my father and his friend G***and the pale pig standing bound between themits father shaving ij^ throatA quick sliced stab and blood —though I know it trickledI see it spurt in an arca thick monotonous rainbow caught in a crockThe arc of the pig’s scream stopped in my ears—ten minutes before silence trotters trying to flail blond eyelashes stillOnly when the blood stopsat last 1 start to crya complicated wailingfather reproves with his glareto my sisters’ scorn I creep awayIXThat was the first timeI approached slow death under a waxing moonFather’s apprentice, I know the pig’s swan-song well never two the sameI know it well, I feel it coming from the throatthe beast’s strain in my handsMy hands shake as I write I can’t translate, in English I cannot make you hear itr
￼My mother’s stitcheryby oil-light, bright needle pricking linen with petals taut as a tambourine beneath tight black eyesCome quick, my father calls come do something useful. She anchors the skeinwho never did anythingThey kneel down togetherin the sty by oil-lightthe feverish sow between them a small sister, brown hands travelling her white lardYour mother was beautiful father tells me one day.It is a strange saying.His eyes that have known more than mine seem to see lessThat fine work by oil-lighthe tells her, wrinkles your eyes but occasions for itdon’t stop, nor she, save to suck new silk for the needle’s eyenot useful, but thisAll her care is dispersed now, given or gone away under some several roofs my sisters and Iall her useless stitchery
￼POEMS OF Z POEMS OF ZPOEMS OF Z J -ts? PAUL HYLANDPages from Z’s notebookPagesfrom Z ’s notebookCopyright ®Paul Hyland 1982 All rights reservedISBN: 0 906427 44 4First published 1982 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SNNewcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.The publisher acknowledges the financial assistance of Northern Arts.Some of these poems first appeared in New Poetry 5 (Hutchinson/Arts Council - P.E.N., 1979) and in South WestReview.Typesetting & cover printing byTyneside Free Press Workshop Ltd, Newcastle upon Tyne.Printed in Great Britain byUnwin Brothers Ltd, Old Woking, Surrey.%xsj\/</ hyl;i/e.
["fejthltSSZ seems to have been engaged in intelligence activities in the U.K. for a number ofyears. The poems are certainly about that, but I think it unlikely that our counter-espionage service will glean much from these pages. The poet—for this is what, in a crisis of self-examination, Z became—is not concerned with ‘Names and Places/tTechnical Detail, Plans/Political Praxis, M i s c e l l a n e o u s ’ ; h e a s k s ‘W h a t d o e s t h e h e a r t k n o w ’ , a n d w r i t e s of his own tenderness and violence, duplicity and openness, his faithfl^essness and spiritual hunger. From his world within our world, employing our language, he casts a cool eye on E n g l a n d , ‘t h e E n g l a n d I l o v e ’. H e s p e a k s m o v i n g l y o f t h e w o r l d of his childhood; the spy remembers his father and writes:rorn fI (f\In passing Z’s notebook to the publisher I have become involved in preparing the poems for the press. When he made revisions Z ’s usual practice was, it seems, to erase the original— ‘pencil stitched/and smudged across a grubby page’—but where he has not done this I have taken the two readings as alternatives, and have chosen the one I judged the better. I have also made a small handful of amendments to Z’s sparse punctuation, for the sake of clarity consistency.Z has left us forty poems.PREFACE￼It will be clear why it is difficult for me to disclose how these poems came into my possession. Their unexpectedness and their unexpected power, that made such an impact on me, are the important things about them. In any case, I have nothing illuminating to say about their background, for all my know­ ledge of it comes from them. All I have is a small, rather dog­ eared notebook of forty unlined pages, each with a poem pencilled upon it in English.The dedication and the quotations from Lear and Jonson are scribbled inside the front cover. At the head of the first page is written Poems ofZ.. . . all the seasonsgone for which he, his weathered faceupturned, gathered intelligenceHere we have an extraordinary view ofan extraordinary poetic development. The start must have been tentative, but once assuredofwhathewasaboutIfeelsurethatZwrotethepoems as they stand in the notebook, one after another, each dependent on the one before, each qualified by the next. They demonstrate a sharpening of vision and a hardening of intention probably unsuspected at the outset. The naivety of the enterprise was to Z, I think, an essential element of it. Its success was perhaps as much of a surprise to him as it is to us. He felt it was not attainable in his own language. That Z should write so well in English is surely remarkable, but it is also crucial to his purpose:I need decode the words I do it in EnglishI adopt that tongueTowards the end he anticipates returning home and recalls M*** (an informant?) who returned ‘from the fascists’ hands’ with his tongue cut out:muscles at his tongue’s root fought with the air in his open moutha crock at the endof an arc of blood. We cried out for himPAUT HYT.AND
￼and of my mother who knew how to sing-Lear-JonsonrvTowards the end he anticipates returning home and recalls M*** (an informant?) who returned ‘from the fascists’hands’ with his tongue cut out:muscles at his tongue’s root fought with the air in his open moutha crock at the endof an arc of blood. We cried out for himZ has left us forty poems.PAUL HYLAND - in memory of my father who knew how to talk-in memory of my father who knew how to talk and of my mother who knew how to sing‘Thou whoreson zed! thou unnecessary letter!’‘Z is a letter often heard amongst us, hut seldome seene. ’
￼This is sudden yThis to be a poet.a.need my comrades would scoff atif they knew, scoff in our own tongue -You an agentfrom a thriller’s cover you a blank face under a black hatYou a poet—I say it too in my own tongueI need decode the words I do it in EnglishI adopt that tongueit moves differentlyin my mouth, it swellsIf across these pagesit speaks I will hand them to my friend the professor at S***, he will translate back into my own tongueThat will not be suddenthat handing overthis notebook when it is full
￼IIThis is like taking off clothes heavy coats one at a time each one less burdenthe weight of keeping warm gone in a/room with oil-light and water breathing in ironThat’s what it’s like shedding clothes, hardware, braces, trousers and at the endi ng s*,1,1 In a room with oil-lightlying in elbow-warm waterthe grown flesh fallen away bathing in the iron bath supported by my m other’s arm her free hand rinsing my limbsShe sings to me in my own tongue songs I will forget in LondonI pitch my gurgles back to hermy poems she can’t understandIIIYou see there is nothing naive and sentimental asa grown man with soft hands and a calloused heart starting out as poetThe idea of it anyway. From my rented table through the spacious grid of sash windows I keep watch on Georgian LondonAs I once spied from a pane set into thick thatchon my father in the yard the pigs rooting, my sisters walking out in the woodwhen I should have been sleeping. Opposite, the porticoes in linethe columns and pedimentsall at once I am astonishedat the weight of masonryI walk in and out of every day
IV￼■1•''jVv.tv(Yt jIn the streets of languageI need no maps any more.If I were to try words of love my tongue would tasteof their dust and litterIntimacy that is paid for -after sleepless nights sometimes street signs are foreign flags pinned to great architecture roads veer off at wrong anglesI am a beast turned drab driven in from the far country to scavenge in dustbinsand basement entriestainted by offal and old bonesMy lack of conditionmy dullness is protective colouration for missionthe noblest drive of my kind to survive, depraved appetiteThis pencil and papermy belling bark that shouldfly meadows and pierce woods pitched off monstrous buildings in the streets of languageVAs a boy I was one learning to be moreOne with the pigs in their pen far inland chucking the/ acorns from a holed bucket., -the sea a dream of passionOne with my sisters’boys little man among little men One with my aunt in town in my white stiff thingsOne for my first communionOne for the party, party-manIn London now I am legion Legion for we are manyI would invite my pigs here for my first communion - they would rush outwards in all directionsAnd every English shore they dashed themselves over trotters gashing own throats would wash with their goreI would be oneI have learned to be more
￼VIVThe pigs stay at homeI wade the English shores where burns and becks empty with great sewers called riversOr I dive in the deep waters —one of my elements— rouse oysters from their beds like drowned corroded fruitThey are hard nuts to crack with crabbed brown hands and a stainless knife’ssharp point, broad haftI unhinge and chuck hundreds the years, a stinking middenthe pearls, mostly small and grey I send home to the pigsVIIBeneath that heap of shells my father points downriver to tell me that it runs through another country all the way to the seaThe sea trips off his tonguelike gossip—he has not seen it but knows it’s worth talking about —it is salty he saysand larger than all the landI lie dreaming of itits smell comes up through / cracks in the floorboardsfrom bacon curing underrafters under my bedW ith cows on the riverbank I sniff for it but turnto face the mountainsNothing, not thunder, not flood nor cataract prepared mefor the raw deep voice of it under the deck, the lullabyof her who bore me on her breastYears dulled that wonderthe shells a heap of deaf ears.Now I sift through their clatter clutching them at my head listening for the voice of my father
￼VIIII creep nearer and nearer —my sisters hide their faces even safe inside the house - the nuzzled ground slavers and sucks at my shoesI creep close to my father and his friend G***and the pale pig standing bound between them'its father shaving _j| throatA quick sliced stab and blood —though I know it trickledI see it spurt in an arca thick monotonous rainbow caught in a crockThe arc of the pig’s scream stopped in my ears—ten minutes before silence trotters trying to flail blond eyelashes stillOnly when the blood stopsat last 1 start to crya complicated wailingfather reproves with his glareto my sisters’ scorn I creep awayIXThat was the first timeI approached slow death under a waxing moonFather’s apprentice, I know the pig’s swan-song well never two the sameI know it well, I feel it coming from the throatthe beast’s strain in my handsMy hands shake as I write I can’t translate, in English I cannot make you hear it
￼My m other’s stitcheryby oil-light, bright needle pricking linen with petals taut as a tambourine beneath tight black eyesCome quick, my father calls come do something useful. She anchors the skeinwho never did anythingThey kneel down togetherin the sty by oil-lightthe feverish sow between them a small sister, brown hands travelling her white lardYour mother was beautiful father tells me one day.It is a strange saying.His eyes that have known more than mine seem to see lessThat fine work by oil-lighthe tells her, wrinkles your eyes but occasions for itdon’t stop, nor she, save to suck new silk for the needle’s eyenot useful, but thisAll her care is dispersed now, given or gone away under some several roofs my sisters and Iall her useless stitchery
￼I have a piece here in London made of stitches I cannot name in English, let alone mj/tongueA blue bird perched'on a green branch among red blooms but faded, old linen yellowed at every foldIt is like my heaVt, packed, unpacked furled and unfurled in foreign rooms hid in the luggage of my limbsOn my table in this blafdc bookI trace the profile of the that heart with pencil, rubber and no artIn this ageing and English lightXII have a piece here in Londonmade of stitches I cannot name /Tn English, let alone my tongueA blue bird perched on a green branch among red blooms but faded, old linen yellowed at every foldIt is like my heart, packed, unpacked furled and unfurled in foreign rooms hid in the luggage of my limbsOn my table in this blank book I trace the profile of that heart with pencil, rubber and no artIn this ageing and English light it’s hard to read, too dark at times to write, seeing no litde rhymesOr too much chimes unjustly -were they all silken lies she toldthat are now mellowed and grown oldThis one, hung in my tall white room stretched again, gilt-framed and fading dimmed by the light I see it inthe light I work by, pencil stitched and smudged across a grubby page dazzles my eyes with the heart’s rage
￼XIIAnd each plough-time the heavy horse leans at unbroken ground, the share burnished of rust at the first turnfirst furrow, the year’s paradigmThe soil’s breath breaks intact from itand birds hang on its lips, I passen route for school and my returnsees father’s warp stretched hedge to hedgeI learn my letters, figures toohe broadcasts over harrowed landI weave between the feint ruled lines his testament, my exerciseAt home my head buried in books The first cuckoo! my father calls Can you hear it? O f course I canI do not know why I say noI am bored with the grand routine that feeds me, the man who works it. My hunger is for print; his, cornin stitch, wreather’s embroideryHis labour is all harvestedsewing unpicked, all the seasonsgone for which he, his weathered face upturned, gathered intelligenceXIIIThere is one place I know where the street smells right in Soho, a cafe where I go sometimes, where they sell the right sort of breadand where they speak my tongue among themselves. I listenwith the other foreignersthe English men, I sinkand roll it on my tongue how sourdough sweetens! and swallow it hardmy teeth in the bread
￼XIVThe priest throws back his head under the uptilted chaliceUnder the black of his beard his supple throat pumpsAs if he emptied the domeof the psalms lapping its brimAnd on my tongue dissolution of wafer and high seriousnessThe creed’s sumptuous chant strangely bland but indigestibleBecause I think I could not give all my juices to it; flatusIn the bowel lent a pained smile to the practice of holinessTo him whose racked form rode the tree into whose death I could not donateSuffering so framed with pomp but I see now in retrospectNot wholly corrupt, a memory a drinking to certain hopeThe priest’s voluptuous throat throbbing with joyous guffawsCelebrating a death and again roaring at the death of deathr
￼XVThen I was consecrated to correct economicsI was a bright pupilNow with a dull eyeI look out from London across foothills of brickDomes and spires diminished douched by a cataractof glass, architect’s visionI had it, I saw manpinned on the drawing board in plan and elevationMy tall head built of panes tears of glass sizzledon the dome of my heartTheoretical pityfor the man I had seen not for me, not for meI had not yet learned that. I was a bright pupil.Now with a dull eyeI creep through porticoes pitiful, not a cubitadded to my statureXVI(Is it worth it this dredging up memories ofthe future that is long gone and that never was?W orth anything to think of the position towhich ambition raised me, me and all of mankindit imagined? Since I have been put in my placeprobably itis worthless but it is costly)/
￼XVIII was a saint, for loveof country I left it - frontiers as are well known are imaginaryand bloody—my idealsin the safe custodyof trustworthy comradesLike a child who’s lent toys to fickle friendsI fear to returnWhat of my toys amongst the pieces they picked up the imaginaryand ransacked nursery pieced together again piecemeal, beloved country ramshackle in my headI want to visitbut I hesitateto go back, for goodXVIIIThe ship I came on passport to mission iron link with home (the farewell handprint of my dead fatheron its starboard rail) the subtle groundswell sickness at parting embarking upon something• When I heard (from fellow-exilesI can’t call comrades^ that the Vessel C*** survivor of-warby accident, hadlong been broken up steep deck, raucous plates all scrap, in a gustold salt stung my eyes
￼\ vvctors \ CXXIXIn my countrywe look into each other’s eyes freedom has been wonThe vigors have given it to us —if freedom is everything that is what we owe themWhen a man dies his son eats the bacon that cures under the dead m an’s raftersThe chandelier’s contagion inherited by blood: the victors’ heirspreserve our freedom, salt it downW e are hungrythe flesh of our house whole but divided in spiritWe look into each other’s eyes first one way and then another first one way and then anotherXXXI am a puppeton very long stringslength gives a certain elasticityOrI am a part ofa ventriloquist’s actI sit very stilland keep my mouth shutI am a dummy on the knee of acadaver
￼XIXMy sentimentality appals methen consoles; emotions still, but sudden I butter-fingered drop them and mis-feelI was a hard nut in my prime to cracka mind and body bedded snugly inwell knitted joints, nothing rotten or looseBut then a place grew softly where they met back of the throat, perhaps, above the heart grew large and liquid, a soft centre, sacWhose juice digests my thick skin from within and now I think my insides are all slops contained tears pent up in a fragile shellI am a hard man before breaking out I shall, if I hole myself, leak away.I am appalled, to hatch now is to dieXXI do not listen muchto fellow-exiles’ talesof home, they must believe they are better off here since they cannot returnI do not listen much because I can, but one such bitter recital nestles deep in my ear like a worm, a tale ofimaginative torture -a troublesome priest penned in B*** prison, at length exhorted by a spikered hot steel up his arseon his knees to say mass over shit and pissthough ordure and urine were the words the man used who told the tale, shakingI don’t know if I should take his words for gospel his imaginationor my lack of it, factFacts are made up. To know from far, to rememberis to daydream. Bread. Shit. To see straight in close-up an imaginative actit is best to forget
￼XXII have nothing to say in return missionary without a gospellamp hid under a bushel me in this airless room!you think I’ve escaped to thisfrom the pig-pen, my trampled countryor am expatriate on greener grass mixing my hopes and fears with yoursmy conversation is a charadeI watch from under word-coverwhen I re-enter my homeland I shall shout hopes out loudI’m no exile banished from my soil exile is my missionpatriot, servant, soon I shall return till then this pencil is bluntedre-sharpened, otherwise never share my fears with anyone, anywhereXXIIMy parents’business always was well-known in the next villagebefore ours becauseour clear-eyed neighbour silent M other K***had a garruloussister living thereto whom each Sunday she’d carefully walkwith white eggs and take brandy in returnretracing her stepswith a happilyempty basket justas her darling hens were cackling over their darling white eggs
￼Prayer was often difficultthe confessional was an easy routeto God’s ear—it was his eyeI feared glinting through lattice-workThe presumptive photo of mewas taken before my first communion crisp and black and white—his eyean open shutter between prayerssnapping at each new secret sina series of mug-shots falling away from the primal image—Itried to surprise myself in mirrorsto find out if anything showedthe complexion of my soul seeping through an aperture—that his eyewould scan, find wanting and write downI could not find words for my sinsI repented of faith in forgiveness penance mere punishment—Ifeared passing of notes and whisperingXXIVThe hospital —me a boyi n a m e n ’s w a r d — I love the whole the real worldStethoscopes read universal tremors world of diagnoses screens dragged around trivial atrocitiesand unlikely cures starched sheets and disinfectant covering upI love it allthe noise of life silence of death orchestrated out of controlDoctors bending over listening withtheir instruments their smiles andfor corruptiontheir knowledgeor what is not worse ignoranceI love it alla museumof living sicknesses as I love England
￼XXVIn the England I love I am visitorI am listenerand collectorI step out stooping from the sick-room the confessional and the hen-coopW ith my stethoscope my white coatand a notebookfull of symptomsWith my micro-camera under my cassockwith white eggs cradled in my smockXXVIW hen the air though cold hung heavily in the trees I heard a pig’s screamand looked out—an arena at the forest’s edgewhere a desperate dog-wolf chased one of our youngA piglet runs like a cat ears flat, stops so fast with all its trotters dug in grinning in its fearthat the grey beast overruns and snarling turns backon the pale scampering thingThen it seems successturns the pig’s head from terror to playfulness tillits squealing is with laughter and the dog-wolf toorelaxes despite hungerfangs sure then of lardWhether or not I dreamt this or saw in the fleshcircus at the forest’s edge when the air though cold hung heavily in the treesI heard the pig’s scream bubble softly and turn red
￼XXVIIWhat I am does not add up then I thinkthat always there’s a big bomb in the airPlane circling abov^ england on alertready to head east before you can blinkAll is in order up there precisiondouble-checked triple-fail-safe on targetAbove smiling diplomats governmentsand people making mistakes making loveI think of just one of themjust one crewmade one through harsh discipline conditionedMade interrogation-proofby torturedependable tools put through my pacesI am of their brotherhood I encodethe world’s everyday chaos my coverWhen I wonder what I amI think ofthis life of ours, men plus bombs I add upXXVIIII am not Samson pillars and porticoes do not give wayat my weightI am not blindI watch the faceslisten to gossip corridors and closets whispers of free speech this democracyA house divided against itself—eyes alreadyclogged with coin— does not need Samson
￼XXXIMy face a professional dissident I stretch to fit the maskMy heart a muscle-knotcan’t afford feelingacts by the method—empathy disallowed—objective performancehappy when the audienceturns away, coughs behind its handMy head a cabinetof files each labelledFaces, Names and Places Technical Detail, Plans Political Praxis, Miscellaneous classified according topriority and secrecyW atch, listen to the audience collatedesignatetransmitadrenalininstinctthe head gathers intelligenceThe face knows nothingthe heart knows something else
￼XXXIIW hat does the heart know it is not certainthe heart is in exile and not from its soilVoltaire’s tragic figure the faithless priestthe heart thought it escaped God and his trappingsleft home for the night like my grown sisterscarrying their smart shoes as far as the roadlodging boots in the hedge against their returnthe heart has grown up twice faithless atheistMaterialism & History are not enoughI want more I want more the hungry heartI know about hunger when there is no foodbut no, not when there is no such thing as food
￼XXXIIILately, perhaps because I soon shall cross it for the last time, I have been trippingto the seaAnd what seems like a mote troubles my eye a man’s head floating far out, fightingwith the seaImaginary and bloody frontier -stones, fine red fronds like hands’veins in the seaUnaccounted-for corpuscles per cubic metreand only great mammals warming the dilute blood of the seaI pick up soft pebbles of chalk, sculpture burrowed-in, bored-through, dense with the dead of the seaMy size is embarrassing suddenly, my pride - what do I know of the creaturely galaxiesin the seaAnd what of the man I imaginefar out, trampled in the waves’charge, drowning in the seaI know nothing, I turn back to the low cliffs their dirty-red and grey houses blindly looking out to seaAnd I think I throw my shoes off and dive in a good socialist or a bourgeois heroby the seaMy victim does not appreciate the difference I buoy him up, he cries Save me, save me from the sea
￼XXXIVSoon I shall board a plane and fly from one language to another. It willtake a part of a dayI shall fly from English even from these poems back to my tongue. I still think of it in that wayAll my intelligenceflew that route under wraps and waits for me. There I’ll be day by day by dayTransmitted, translated back in time to the tongue I was taught in. The thrill of seeing, then, one wayBefore that, older gamesof dreams and sense and faith long forgotten. My skillwith each word a new toyI’ll think of my poems this intelligence inmy other tongue. I will not be a sad old boy
￼XXXVI am flying to my homeland I will not be a sad old boyMy father is long deadI will not be a sad old boyMy mother is dead alsoI will not be a sad old boyMy sisters are still aliveI will not be a sad old boyMy wife is not any moreI will not be a sad old boyMy work is over and done with I will not be a sad old boyMy time is up it is too late I will not be a sad old boyMy time is my ownI will not be a sad old boyWhat time?I will not be a sad old boyI’ve been saying it over and over like a charm, a strong charm repeated under a waxing moon or litany, endless litanychanted to ward off the devil or a prayer, a heart-felt prayer a begging letterXXXVI(Fortunately froman objective viewpoint I am unimportantI serve the state a people’s monk an eye on a stalkmy feelings and my fate the last thingsI should think aboutI look out for the rest why worry themwith my hope and guiltI am unimportantit takes so many m e’s to make a mass)
￼XXXVHI have not mentioned it yet—a man in my positionhas to be discreet with women— but since I left my wife behinda succession of at bestbrief happinesses has dogged meI think of my mother and father.My eyes have known more than theirs but seem to see less. I do notwonder at my heaviness. Eyes’saturated humoursprecipitate a callus on the nervethat only tears can solve.However tenderly it was doneit has all been snatched and stashedin the memory. Nothing was made. Now I want to make it upwith somebody, in my tongue, at homeXXXVIIIW hat shall I say now with this English tongue cut out of my head(M*** whom we though lost came back from the dead from the fascists’ handsHe had lost his tongue. They had translated him into a foolforgetting how well fools are listened to, his eloquent handsmuscles at his tongue’s root fought with the air in his open moutha crock at the endof an arc of blood. We cried out for him)I have not suffered not really, I amit seems in one pieceand if we’re careful my friend, professor at S***, will translateall this, this false start back into my tongue. I may find my tongue
￼XXXIXDuring the war— men at men’s throats —how we trusted our poor neighbours we thought we knew wrho our friends wereSo I’ll proposea special voteof thanks to friends here in Englandfor trusting me— here’s to neighbours!Do not disturbwas my watchword— if he’ll forgivea spy’s foiblesI’ll forgive the drunkard next doorLeave him in peaceXLOn leaving shall I pronounce as retiring episkopos benediction on my diocese?Shall I quote Jesus, My peaceI leave with you? I would not bequeath my whatever it is to a dogIn peace is passive enough,your choice. Peace does not belong to me I am going home to look for itShall I quote the prodigal,Father I have sinned? I cannot tellif I’m moving to or from the pig-penBecause I’m taking myself with me I’m taking myself to the banquetI shall say gracer-