￼3*&••Eyes wide with the moon* ^bo^NEyes wide with the moonlie speaks in a tangle of words Mow cold her hair waslie would have me imagine the moon The briars the bedded leavesA place out of the cold#The cold shines into meThe bright face takes my breath Withers my warm replyHe will have warmed her handsA tree he says the branches her cold hair Among the embracing roots#She will have been drawn into The moon in his eyes her tongueInto his mouth . ..’as our bloods separate’As our bloods separate the clock resumes^I hear the wind again as our hearts quieten. We were a ring: the clock ticked round us For that time and the wind was deflected.The clock pecks everything to the bone. The wind enters through the broken eyes Of houses and through their wide mouths And scatters the ashes from the hearth.*Sleep. Do not let go my hand.I'bot boUAV' Ci ?O n rU V idDAVID CONSTANTINE —^ (ht_2.rr\rv^*v:X emS"ChiA rvjl£•
￼Most are sleeping, someHave waited hopelessly for mercy. Others even by this will not be stayed. But we who have not slept for quantity Of happiness have heardThe dawn precipitate in songLike dcwfall.We think our common road a choir of trees•Daffodils in vases’Daffodils in vases, watch them daily For the first touch of dying, evenThe blossom you came carryingOf cherry and almond I will raise The (ire with tonight to seeYou naked by, only the tulipsWider and wider leave them opening Until their petals fallIn gouts on the marble hearth.'But most you are like'But most you are likeThe helpless singing of birdsTo whom the light happensOn whom it fallsAnd at whose purity of voiceThe skies weep and there is a pauseIn all the world before beginning And before the ending.
￼one.Locus /\moenusOne read of the place where the covert mound rose lanked by slopes, and clear waterissued below for thirst and the excited mind nd the senses equally were delighted.One read of that pleasant place in the writers of pastoral -■And imagined its charms scattered over an earthLess than so beautiful, and thinking never to come there Did: and found it surpassed their praises.Musee du LouvreThese courtiers in a wood have come upon her Rising before them moonlike in a clearing.She strikes their eyes, their hands are all upraised At the light she sheds upon them from her scallop. Ear inland henceforth, deep in the heart's covert, Closing their eyes they will always hear the sea.It#3 # — e?SomeQone at least reading about beauty in a roomAbove the city has turned from the lamp once having heard her step behind him on the creaking board and until Morning then and until, close in the eaves, birds wokeHe was allowed to lie on the narrow bed with herunder the maps that papered the sloped ceilingEmbracing her freely and planning with her journeys.
￼They saw the figures of Fugitive Love and supposed them Wrought to the condition of subtilityBy one another's hands: she streams away□And the soul may be seen, playing upon her limbs,xhe hotel bed was bordered with a mirror where they reviewed those figures, curiousWhat novel disposition of themselves N'iQWould lend their evanescence form.3^ — ^Chartres and AvignonOne could not look through it nor did the light From outside enter as light of dayBut passed inward in the form of a persuasion □■That love hungers and will be filled byNo dexterity. That was the window of Mary, □Of post coitum tristis. WakingIn Avignon he saw her beside him sleeping with □The sheet thrown off, arms and throat>7Already burned from travelling. The dirty,pane □Showed a blueness under which the townWith sprinkled gutters foretasted the dust □Und thin shade under walls at noon.Reading that in the depiction of the female bodyNorth and south of the Alps there were two traditions By stages night after night in disreputable hotels North and south of the Alps he examined whetherShe approached more nearly the Gothic or the Classical Bearing in mind from Paris a certain YenusAs far as Florence where a lascivious EveDisplayed her teeth-marks in the bitten apple.
￼46IffDavid Constantine'The mind then'&The mind then seems to become the burning point ^-^jjOf the other senses, when by dayArches are seen and one's delight converges At their tips and down the aisles, and whenIn darkness are corresponded all parts having stiffness □Actual or potential, likewiseAll declivities and entrances and more are devised 3t3And the mind then is the glass, burning.Upon his dictum 'Dessiner c'est connaltre1 JJGossip put a lewd connotationSaying that master of the essence and forms of women‘"|t" . •-»(Entered the place his pencil had depicted. .fc’pn \ I'Oh do not leave it to gossip lewdly to imply |Our certainty that through the foolish penis\ Exact and loving knowledge comes. To that point TUThe cognisance of all the senses runs.He answered: 'With my penis.' Let us not Imagining the inconveniences Oi palate and easelAnd dismissing Bullhead as an unmanageable tool ^SJJump to the conclusion that he meant it figuratively.\odfn(3>| PA(r\t_ t.NC>Si