￼Attila 22-37 18/9/92 12:29 am Page 32,csCanvey Island Zen Stalinist Theme Gulag 12 June 2018Dear Darren,Been here nearly three months now, ever since the United Com­munist bastards stopped my car at the Hertfordshire border check­ point ^ n d fojjnd that old Madonna tape and the copies of the Underground Sun I was trying to smuggle through. I reckon I’d have made it if it wasn’t for that bastard sunstrip - no one told me they had been made illegal under that poxy new Articulacy Act and I hadn’t bothered to take it off, which was a dead giveaway. I was shitting myself when I got here, what with all the rumours about those Red bastards torturing people with books and chess sets and copies of the Guardian and so on, but, believe it or not, I’m having a great time! Yeah, straight up!Didn’t look good to begin with though. When they checked us through the perimeter gates things were really grim. The whole of the camp is surrounded by this huge moat full of what looks like soya milk, and it’s guarded by loads of pit bull terriers with really fierce lesbians on long leads - even if you get through them, there are two huge barbed wire perimeter fences that really rip your clothes, with an illuminated strip in the middle covered in that really thick motor oil that absolutely ruins your trainers. Anyone who did manage to get out would be looking at well over a grand for a completely new set of gear, at least. And the illuminated oil strip is kept under constant surveillance by hundreds of teachers and social workers who watch your every movement from massive ivory towers. It was well scary, I can tell you!But when we got inside...wow! First of all, we were met by these really nice birds who gave us all ‘Canvey Island Zen Stalinist Theme Gulag’ baseball caps, and then the camp commander - an old geezer called Billy something who seems alright, as it goes - gave us a welcoming speech in which he told us not to worry, the external security system was not at all representative of life inside, and as long as we didn’t try to escape we’d all have a whale of a time since the theme of this particular gulag was Saturday Night in August on the Costa del Sol, 24 hours a day, 365 days a year! And then the welcoming party started...At first we couldn’t believe it at all. After all, this was supposed 323' The Gulag Archipelago-^ro
￼^ vT-A *JcAttila 22-37 18/9/92 12:30 am Page 33,—to be the Reds’ most notorious prison camp, the one no one had ever escaped from - but when they turned on the lager fountain and brought out the paella and the disco began I thought hey, why would anyone WANT to escape? If you lot in the Tory Resistance knew what was going on here you’d tear up your membership cards and start fighting the pit bulls and lesbians to try and get IN!It’s officially called a work camp, but there’s hardly any work to do cos everything we need is flown in from your side - volun­ teers go down to the airstrip once a week to unload the food and videos and lager off the supply planes, and yours truly always volunteers of course,'cos it means I get to “lose” some of the stuff on the way back, if you get my drift, though there isn’t much point actually since everything’s free anyway. Old habits die hard, eh? But the rest of the time - party! Unlimited free condoms! Un­ limited booze! We’ve got cable TV with 215 channels, and we’ve even got our own camp newspaper, run by the bloke who owned that Sunday Sport before the revolution - so you guessed it. PHWOAR! None of that boring news stuff at all! Though I hear rumours that things are pretty bad outside - apparently the Reds have renationalised the air industry now. Bloody Commie bastards! You know what we used to say in the good old days - there’s no such thing as a free breath!All in all, what with their bloody Articulacy Act and the raising of the school leaving age to 20 and all that socialism and national­ isation and health service nonsense (whoever thought we’d be hear­ ing that rubbish again, I thought the 1990s killed it off for good!) I reckon I’m better off in here!Although I must tell you that there’s one thing here that really worries me. Some of the people here, most of them actually, believe it or not, started to get bored with all the non-stop partying and discos and booze and sex and videos after a couple of months and they’re going quite voluntarily into this big building marked REHABILITATION where all they do is sit around reading books and talking! Every day loads of teachers and social workers come down from their ivory towers on the camp boundary to take part in discussion groups and sometimes people don’t come out of there for days - there’s plenty of sleeping accommodation, and it’s tucked away in a corner of the camp, and they just stay there!And when they do come out...well, I can tell you, sometimes it’s horrible. One of my best mates from the Resistance, an old / bloke eaUed Garry-who used to be quite a famous Sun journalist before the Reds rounded them up after the Battle of Wapping and33
￼Attila 22-37 18/9/92 12:30 am Page 34,stuck them in here, spent two whole weeks in rehabilitation and when he came out he started talking about Zen Stalinism and the United Communists’ education programme and the bloody Artic­ ulacy Act and - get this - how the global AIDS plague wasn’t the homosexuals’ fault at all! He called me a neanderthal - I had to ask one of the teachers to tell me what it meant - and he even tried to get me to go to rehabilitation! I mean, what a traitor! I was going to get a few of the old gang together (though most of them are in rehabilitation too now, I’m sad to say) and give him a right old kicking, but the next thing I knew - he’d gone! ‘I’ve gone over to the other side’, the note read, ‘to help supervise the returning of the United Kingdom’s air supply to its proper place in the pub­ lic domain!’ Wanker!Wey-hey! I’ve just seen the latest issue of the Gulag Grope, our paper! Talk about jugs! And I’ve got to go cos the curries are here, and there’s another party starting in a couple of minutes. PARTYYYYY!! Hope you manage to destroy those new hospitals and schools the Reds are building - SMASH THE ARTICULACY ACT and GOD SAVE THE KING!! My so-called mates might be going soft but me - never! I reckon I might just pop down to rehabilitation tomorrow, though; just to check out the birds, like, not cos Zen Stalinism means anything to me, no way...Rule Britannia!Yours,J-efEN-'34
￼VegetablesNo agony, no ecstasy, no pleasure and no pain -so exquisitely uninteresting you drive your wife insaneThe TV is your oracle, the newspapers your guideand your shiny little vehicle is your passion and your pride You’ve done the same things every day for nigh on forty years and in your ludicrous routines you hide your worthless fears On the blandest boat in Boredom you are captain of the crew - and every time I eat vegetables it makes me think of you...You died the day that you were born, and now you sit and rotan empty-headed dinosaur in the pond that time forgotYour image is respectable, there’s nothing underneathand the whole thing is as surely false as nine-tenths of your teeth'I %o\it views are carbon copies of the rubbish that you read and you swallow every morsel Rupert Murdoch seeks to feed"/you go to bed at ten because you’ve nothing else to do - and every time I eat vegetables it makes me think of you./^Your sex life is a catalogue of your poor wife’s frustrations -like thousands of Red Indians, she has her reservations A,«nd so she took a lover; of course, you’ll never know -the last time you made love to her was many years ago ynd if you had some spirit then it wouldn’t be so bad:it’s your awesome anonymity which makes me get so mad"f yt)ur brain stem is a nether world where bored trainspotters queueand every time I eat vegetables it makes me think of you.You’re a cabbage in a pickle and your brain has sprung a leek so lettuce keep our distance ’cos I vomit when you speakI’ll always do a runner so I’m going where you’ve bean’cos to see you chills my marrow and turns my tomatoes green''f .you’re an eighteen carrot cretin with a dandelion whine - so stick to your herbaceous border and I’ll stick to minej\ #nd although this verse is corny, it’s amaizing but it’s true that every time I eat vegetables it makes me think of you!