￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:01 pm P,asp 30The Significance of SignificanceL , W ■ T')(rrG*Xv)She was worried he couldn’t be happy just loafing about by the river,like she liked doing.Plans, and plans about plans, and sex, was his idea of happiness.He wore a floppy hat. She felt so lonely!Another thing, she couldn’t spell.Laborinth. Itiniry. Elann.She cooked him cocklesin a thick orange sauce,and bought him a suitcase - ‘for the Great Man’.They sat on a rocky mountain dressed in leather.Sardines and beer.Parois vertigineuses.Their children were his books. She understood that.0 Significado De Significado, lecture notes.‘The blissfully well-run nursing-home’ is now public knowledge -her little lump, like longing,prized from her oesophagus;her crawling from the hut on her knees.A tortoise-shell comb, embroidery,The Crack.A lovely moth.‘The nurse is a crashing bore’ ...poking about among her mysteries. God bless you, Patty.30
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:01 pm Page 31QueenioSand the risen peach, swollen with lust, introduce a finger-nail tentativelyunder its congested lip;the juice will coil down her wristsand lonely open hips, restless,engorged with maggots. Please come home.Lust has turned her hidden milk to bone. Peach-blossoms stiffen,goat-thick orchards sink,eyed beetles wink and push like hounds against her skin; peach-girl, don’t go. Shaky, untouchable, defiled by desire,she casts around for somewhere soft to lie. Come here. The knee-deep fruit play Queenie with her loving soul, stripped cleanand tranquil by the coloured mouthsof peaches soft as eiderdowns.They whisper Queenio. I said Come here.31
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:01 pm RajP 32PeggyHe loved the sunlight —this was in New Mexico -he loved the sunlight,and he used to go for long walks with the llama, Peggy;and when his mother died,one night in June,he brought the llama with himto the funeral:standing like a queen in the mist,batting herjjig'eye-lashes like cream.His mother diedto get away from them! She suffered terribly.He used to be a tailorlike his father -pricking his pot-belly with the pins and sucking the red-currantsthat he made.^/His mother was a gold statuette.^ He wanted so much love,that was the trouble,yet, if you tried to smile,he looked away.The llama called himChocolate Eyes.She said, Don’t cry. She was the only thing he wanted in the end.f32-e-
￼Hill Trembling 25-58 3/2/94 1:01 pm Rage 33Natural WondersIThe lovely boywashes himself all overin a ski-hut. His mother sends a new suit every year.‘He only cares about his mathematics.’IIHe’s tired.He hates the snow.He can’t stop masturbating.Each little death,each floating point cries Heaven, where are you now?IllThe handsome mountain-dwelling monk lies dead. Something is wrong with the electric fan.His secret love-affair exceeds his wildest dreams,while here on earththe other monks are lapsing.NOTE: In the technical term ‘decimalfloating point', the sequence 2658 13, for example, would be used to represent the number 7.658 x 1013, or 26580000000000.