￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:21 pm Page 9.Burying the elephantWhat a grave it took to dig,burying the elephant,his shadow lengthened and grew dark, his shadow rolled over and was gone. 0 shock of the spirit whengreat things go down.He was caught in the sun’s net,the sun brought him crashing down, elephant spirit meeting the ground;blue eyes muddied with a failure to rise, earth’s yawn m ust bury him now.The elephant was heavy-blooded, stone full, slow with time;we all came to bury him,our blue eyes lit with ivoryand a kind of grief;1 had my own pit dug/$\feet up, my animal kickedwith stiff limbs; in my hidemy shadow rolled on the grass and groaned, my spirit grew dark and gave;elephant trum pet bellowed in the the forest sank to its knees,the forest rose and swayed.W hat a grave it tookto bury my animal’s meat.I turned his spirit out and now the darkness is complete.trees,
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:01 pm Page 5.Man chopping woodMan chopping woodlooks up to seethe helmeted boys go over,he can hardly believe -men in their khaki fatigues, running hard across the no-m an’s-land of his back yard.The whistles are screaming,he drops his axe; the wood smells warm, sweet, as it should;the men going overthrow up their arms as they did on the old news reels,just as he had always pictured Great Uncle Johnwho was lost on the Somme.He thought it was allblack and white in the war,all hands on hearts, flags in the breeze, he’s never seen men sink to their knees he’s never seen them torn limb from limb he was justgetting the woodpile in.His wife’s in the kitchen, baking pies,his kid’s on the greenplaying football with the neighbours’ kids, he tries to screambut his voice won’t comeand quick as they came, they’re gone,it’s quiet again,smell of new wood and raw airand no knowing if history was playedor statistics made, if pain was realor death hardin the no-man’s-land of his back yard.se- 58e
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:08 pm Page 9,UndertowI was not gently ledinto that inner room.From where I lay, it alwaysseemed another room away,and feeling the wall for a doorI felt the cries of all those girls before being drawn, drowned,prom ised and offered and ledto the very core, and whether willing or in dread, allswooping low and followingthe flow and irresistable tideknowing the undertowwas where they always died, abandoningevery distinguishing sign,mole, tilt and curl,number and name,until they were allthe same and it fellcold as a cave in the room,they stood holding the spent flame, wanting to put it down,bury it now it was doneand move with the ease of girlswho know themselves,into a different room.Once their soundturned down, my handsbegan to burnfrom holding m em ory’s hand.I laid them flat on the cool sheetand turned my other cheek,lying easy in a white bed, wondering when would I be given upfor dead.90e
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:07 pm Page 8,A week leftIt is clean inside my head,there’s been a storm; things leap there, up the salmon-falls the sun leaps,the brightness,the good feel of the day.A m oth goes flutteringinto the blue candle of the past;for miles both waysthe road is the same; the houses,the gates; only the peopleback in my room the belongings squat,soon they will huddle, sad and packed away. My fists grow small.There’s a week left.I want to think only of good times -I am sixteen and tannedand my fringe is too long;I am thirteen and playing kid,the round heart of sunlightis almost at my fingertips,the house opens like a flower,doors are flung wide;or I am nine and in a new dress,it ripples and creases dark and light,but there’s a week left,and I feel stones inside.I will open my eyes wide,I will open my ears, I will tryto call some colour to my smile;the days form a ring,they have numbers pinned to their backsthe weight is doubling them,their grim dance shakes me from limb to limb there are seven of them.87
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:01 pm Page 6,Everyone’s coldHe woke in the dark, blind, still inside the close nature he would like tokick off in the grass and walk from. Sun came up, but he never saw.He was trying to fathom the time by the depth of his fearhe felt it was light on the street why was it so heavy in here?He got up, pulled the shutters across.The wind looked dull against the thick glass.He rode the bus to her housestorm tide sucked his heart dryand flooded it full,the extra sounds kicked in, the tightness came,he reached for her throat, to him this violence felt like love turned backwards,he waited for time to beginfor sun to blow the earth out,for cracks to show.‘Everyone’s cold!’ he cried, but she reminded him of love, the circle and fall,and what she saidshe said so simply that it broke him down,he spread till he wasthin on the groundhis snakeskin spirit dreamed in the grassthe quiet went deep, she made him promiseto let go his anger at lastand bury his fear in sleep.61
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:21 pm Page 9,After the factThen I lay down.The train moved and I was tryingnot to fall back frightened.W estminster rose cold between the trees;I waited for Battersea, the satisfying way the four white towers would hold me still, a pillar at either shoulder,a pillar at either heel.W hen the desert arose,that cup of mine began to thirst for rain. I lay between two juniper treesand when the trouble came,it was quick as steel,I loosed myself to meet it.Down England’s spine towards the tailof Brighton, dogs on the sand, Lowry peoplearm in Sunday arm along the pier.There is a wayto grow into my life, to pass a handover the damaged face without unreasonable fear. I walk the planks, beyond^candy floss and beer.It is all sea to the end of the seafrom here.96
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:21 pm Page 9,EvidenceThey came to the end of them, nettles took hold, the roof fell, thistles grew right down their hall; she listened to his doubtful thoughts, gathering evidence.Into other people’s homeshe made his solitary way,left his bones in their cold stone jars,put his hot cheek to their flagstone floors, heard only echoes there.She lay under a mountain ashkeeping count of the seconds that passed; with her free hand she traced a root, circled and circled the heavy doubt,cut his name in the dark.Didn’t he see the end of time chasing minutes across the face? The heavy cast of early Junefell too smartly on her pain, would she ever be safe?She lay counting them to a close, in her vessel was bitter blood, truth flooded her deepest canals, truth found its own level,close to the bone.This evidence bore down,her heart felt the gavel’s rap;where he WTlaid her she didn’t sleep, the silent jury kept her awake,she would never be safe.She turned on her side, he knelt in his dark, kissing the life from her every joint;she counted elephants, one to ten,he said her name a final time,it was over then.56.93
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:21 pm Page!The man I knewHe climbed on his life,hands ragged, winter-blown eyes; space revolved around his world,a million lights were lost in thought - it wasn’t the dark that mattered.The man I knewthrew his life in the water;the man I knew surfaced and gasped, he was survivor, kicking the boards of the boardwalk, grabbing the rails for a long haulback to the real world.His colours came through. In his single roomno one held him as he wept and he was glad of no one.W ithout sight, he wasready for life; kicked dust at the stars, swung with a measure of hope,made no bones of it.All that winterhis letters fluttered to m y letterbox; although I broke the hold, I turned aside, and read them all, and cried.On goesthe hungry scissors up our paper lives. The whole splits, the halvesroll back alone. High on his life something else, different and good,can begin. Across his skya million lights go on,his palm ghosts the back of my neck, his memories reach out and back,he is travelling light.95
￼Berkeley 55-96 19/8/94 5:01 pm Page 6,Near the end of blue Tuesdayhe wrote himself a noteabout how miserable he felt;put on clean socks, laced his boots, went out to face the weather.He sat on his step in the sun until the fog rolled in;fat fog rolls sat on the hills and blew across his road.He went inside, turned the wind down and knelt by his life, blowing for a spark.When it grew dark,he crouched in the dark, fiddling with the dials listening to the voices fade in and outspreading the weather.But news on the hour increased the interference , the hair on his neck rosehe turned from the news through a snatch of songs, liquorice tunes he once whistled to.He rocked and rocked in his white board house head in his knees, casting around for himself.It came unexpectedly, like the truthright at the end^r a silence that stilled his hand - he passed through every station on earthand in the end, face down, head first,the hissing silence held him.-e-60/