￼VEILS AND MASKSBortom era ord anade jag era ansikten.De ansikten ni bar ar inte era verkeliga. Ni var fSrkladda maskerade beslbjade.Era obesldyade ansikten ar vakrare...Beyond your words I sensed your faces.The faces you beaiy are not your real ones. You were disguised masked veiled.Your unveiled faces are more beautiful...Mirjam Tuominen (Translation: David McDuff)Xi
￼Intz'usionThe glaze of loved and lover, our amorous self-containment, concentric and utterly present to the other. Sweetest hour.But what if between our gazes shadows of the stricken fall,the stares p/e seem to veil keep on commanding us?Our two-ness is never alone. Whose is that intrusive face that looms unseen between us condemning all we haven 't done?The eclipsed. The destitute.O sly worm of dominance coiling its own discountenance, our masks and blottings out.Is love a threadbare blindfold? 'Yes, ' say our shadows, 'unless you turn to face the faceless '.Who '11 re-envisge the world?2. 2-
￼How?When the time comes, how will we have been: giver or hoarder, sharers or sleek gringos'? Children of the barrio, how can I explain?Silk I love: fall and flow and cocoon,the worm's sheen, desire clinging and loose. When the time comes, how will we have been?And fruits: plums, tangerines, seedy moon of a kiwi, yellow-orange flesh of mangos, children of the barrio, how can I explain?Or cheeses skinned with peppers, a stiltonwaxy, wrinkle-rinded, my blue-veined Gorgonzolas. When the time comes, how will we have been?Morning curtains, towels lilac and greenin the light, the pile of a rug scuffing toes, children of the barrio, how can I explain?Something cries its grievance. A false coinis spinning: heads I win, tails you lose.\When the time comes, how will we have been? Children of the barrio, how can I explain?2*
￼OutsiderA sheltered arch or where underground kitchens of an inn sentthrough grids of pavement gratingthe warmth of the ass's breath -Where did last night's Christ lie down?Every morning for months I watched a man I might have been,about my age and bearded too,his face blotched crimsonwith cheap wine and sleeping rough.He walked the far side of the street always hurrying somewhere;a father who couldn't praise, I wondered, or what had blurred his star?For months our eyes never met,though the street between us was narrow, until that eve he crossed."Some help', he said, but it must have been my double's eyes that askedwhere would He lie down tomorrow?/
￼An old outsider within me winced, shook him off and fled;that street between was so narrow - I chose the inn and was afraid.I'm sure I've never seen him since -but tomorrow when caraffes go rounda lone presence will passtremors through our frail togetherness again those eyes will askwhere did last night's Christ lie down
￼Tables1'You know yourself, nothing but money counts.' I try my best to smile my knowing smile.Nods to an age's spirit, a self-effacement.So often he's the enabler, a hidden hand lent. 'On bread alone?' But any doubt is scandal.I swallow mutinous words as the tables turn.What did I ever know of deprivation? His scorn whips me: shame, insecurity, angst that haunts a body all its life. Nothing. I know nothing.Self-made, yet so many taken under his wing. Even innocence must sometimes wear a mask.'That's talk for acsetics or the too well-off!'2An ascetic? No. A mortal who loves to eat sharon fruits, blancmange, to sip iced rose or feel warm sand on the arches of his feet.Young Keats dressed and quiffed for his table. I bath early, grooming and scenting myself; silked and rakish, I'm ready to love invisible
￼muses. Then everything cloys except the journey. Endless desert. I feed on some hump of memory and expectation. Ecstasy moving and stationary,a delight fuelling itself. Unlimited supply and demand. The end of desire is more desire. My camel soul must travel the needle's eye.3He's sleeping rough. There but for a woman's praise assuaging my temperament. (Who'll shelter my double I tuck my knee-caps into the hollows of her knees.And still he haunts me, my vagabond counterpart. I know Thomas More brought beggars to his table. Every loop of the mind I try keeps falling short.So much dereliction I know I can't countenance. Justice is a faceless scales. Tell me who'll bethe rich man sighting that prodigal in the distanceto fall on his neck and kiss him? The love cup raised in celebration of a father's huge abandon; the art of giving, the art of never giving up.
￼HostelStation of ease for the broken or frail. A tear in an ocean. And yet that welcome At face value, a roof and warmth, a meal. Vague signals of angeldom.So little. So short of grand revolution We'll always want to dream of.If only dreams could scoop or fill an ocean.... Thimbled gestures of a love,Some gift of falling for endless tasksBerth this moment's care;The scarred visage of a down-and-out who asksIf an ocean starts with a tear?Patient logs of strays and have-nots.A youth stubborn and hurtUproots and wanders. No-one knows his whereabouts, Nomad and introvert.Long headstrong years on the loose;Now shattered and underfedA quarrelsome body yields nightly to delicious Mercies of bath and bed.Z.-S'
￼One evening and again he's goneWithout trace. No mendings. No rebirth.Tiny alleviations, something beautiful done. A caress on the face of the earth.t>7
￼Theft.Another wired photograph of an African woman Holding a small girl with a pear-shaped head And a shrivelled crowfooted face. Has someone Thieved a child, left her this elf instead?Drought. Failed crops. And the rains too late. Hollows of famine rumble the bowels of the earth. Look long and deep. Unable to clean forget,I begin my day, busy in the lap of the north.Little knoweth the fat what the lean doth mean.I can't ghost-write a suffering. Only my guess And leap, flickers of memory or the unforeseen.I know how easily a world unsheathes my tinyness.But nothing appeases her stare. Again I'll pore Over this image of hunger. Is compassion a guilty Fear of there but for fortune or is there more? It's as though something in her gaze commands me.A look both rapt and implacable. There's no wool To pull over these eyes. Look long. Look deeper. Cycles of dominance; a hemisphere's rise and fall. She stares and stares. Am I my sister's keeper?
￼Two After Dark1I tuned in that night to a man's ageing voice:'I'm fancy-free. I could have had my pick of them.'An eavesdropper, had I already begun to pity him?'Maybe if you're tethered young, you get used to it. All you needed was the gab and a good way with you.On the dance-floor I was as smart as any on my feet.'Out there with a steady, if I saw a handsomer woman I'd watch my chance. But haven 't you a girl with you? It's you I want, I'd say, and sure don't, wind anyone'.I stare at a wireless trying to envisage his face. 'And I did a great trade in women from far and near.'An old notched gun smoking stubbornly in the corner.2I remembered sitting in half-light with an old friend stitching years we'd missed. But as night came onI knew I'd heard her hearing my unasked question.'I waited', she laughed, 'for a prince to come riding on a white horse'. Always one of us, she'd refusedto flatter or fawn; confidante and equal in everything.
￼A nature that had to give all. Why anything less?She used to say 'Wait till I'm minister for fairness!' Just wait. That was a time when we owned the world.Men. Where will they all fade with their giddiness? No prince. She rose, making her way across the dark to a lamp, luminous and surefooted in her apartness.
￼Rowing BackIf she broached him near the bone, like his father He'd abscond, then, reappear in his boat to pout For hours on end in the bay, sitting it outTill she came beckoning guiltily from the shore.I see him there shamefaced, glad of a let-out.As hunching on his oars he turned and backtracked. Sullen but somehow holding his maleness intact, Frail dignity balanced on the keel of a boat.Come clean. What is it we've been so afraid of?A fear of what we couldn't tame, wild otherness Wobbling and ungraspable, a sway and completeness. We row an unfathomable sea. Comber and trough.Tumble and come-back. A filling tide's actionAnd passivity, slow logic of retreats and charges. As wave into wave keeps gaining on itself, surges Beyond our control and so full of direction.But something in her expression is veiled and denied. Those old patterns of huff, guilt and climb-down.The ghosts of so many women are standing aloneWaving to an oarsman brooding on his phantom pride.
￼Is the boat in the b>aay cradling a dread of failure A bravado trying to face up to its loss of face?
￼At the Hairdresser'sMy neck on the porcelain rim, a tautness unbends Backwards into suds and rushes and squirts of water.A teenage girl (she could easily be my daughter) Gentles my head. Surely a world is safe in her hands? Through the steamy towels and scissorings a radio Blurts news from the East. Some million men dug in.Our sly litany, old stealthy dream of domination: Silkworm, jaguar, tomcat, hawkeye, sea-sparrow.Her thumbs spiral deep into a skull of memory.Sully's and Quinner's gangs fight for a school fort With hedge cuttings bound into whips. Lash and hurtAnd threat of 'sissy' or 'coward'. Above all, don't cry My clogged maleness loosens in her determined fingers. Those helmeted faces so boyish with their unspilt tears