￼There is a distinction between Yeats's 'Sing whatever is well made' - with all its attendant disorder and disturbance - and the gentility-principle condemned by A. Alvarez. MacNeice sounded the true note of Anglo-Irish impatience with England when he said: 'what distinguishes the 'Movement' as a group from a poet like Robert Graves is that the latter's neatness is always a means to an end'.36 (MacNeice exempted Larkin from this critique.) Northern Irish formal concentration - still evident in its testing by the supposedly freer younger generation of poets - has origins which are neither single nor simple. But they certainly include the fact that the English lyric had already mutated under high pressure in Anglo-Ireland. To stress this bit of Irish literary history is not to wax sentimental over Ascendancy residues or make a sectarian point. It is to notice how the state-ideologies of the Republic and Northern Ireland have suppressed cultural strands which yet declare themselves creatively. Pre-partition Ireland has been a long time a-dying. It may yet help a new Ireland to be born.IIIField Day and the CanonYeats's pessimism after the Easter Rising included fears for literature and literary criticism:18
￼At the moment I feel that all the work of years has been overturned, all the bringing together of classes, all the freeing of Irish literature and criticism from politics.37Here, addressing Lady Gregory, Yeats does not so much disown politics as fear polarisation, a squeeze on pluralism, and what might happen to the inside of his own head. He was not always to be so pessimistic, but these fears were realised in his lifetime(see 'Defending Ireland's Soul') and since 1969 the North has renewed their prophetic force.As if under orders from historical necessity, the 1970s introduced a political strain into Northern Irish writing - especially its critical wing. By 1980 one group of writers^ (Seamus Deane, Brian Friel, Seamus Heaney, Tom Paulin), three of them also academics, had espoused an explicit and interventionist cultural politics behind the banner of the Field Day Theatre Company. Besides its annual touring play, the company has produced fifteen pamphlets - the majority by literary critics - and now the key to all its mythologies: the Field Day Anthology of Irish Writing (1991). The anthology has received a bad press, particularly in the Republic, for an under-representation of women all the more striking in a compilation that suspects the aesthetic and favours the political. But this cock-up should not just be put down to general-purpose patriarchy. Its sources lie in Field Day's ideological direction since their first pamphlet- series. In an essay, 'Poetry and Politics in NortherninIreland'38, and/the pamphlet From Cathleen to Anorexia (reprintedhere) I questioned the Field Day agenda. This was on two main grounds: firstly, that their chosen political model appeared to19
￼tosimplify the state of literary playthe cultural negotiations particularly at work in poetry from the North^the new politics they might symbolise; secondly, that a distinctively Northern Nationalist formation was claiming wider validity than it had earned, not only with respect to the North but to the whole island.In overall design, if not in every sub-section, the Field Day Anthology confirms my earlier diagnosis. It would be churlish to deny the anthology's grand sweep, its valuable collation of out-of-print materials, the many contextual insights into the eighteenth and nineteenth-centuries provided by W.J. McCormack, Seamus Deane and other editors. Nor am I either anxious or eguipped to offer a critigue from 600 AD onwards.What concerns me is how the twentieth century, above all the last twenty-three years, looms over the entire enterprise. In one'sense this is inevitable, in another deliberate. Although Kevin Barry has praised 'the promiscuity of what is made available'39(showing that post-modernism is indeed in the eye of the beholder), the anthology is no do-it-yourself pick 'n' mix or harmless baggy monster, but a directive encyclopaedia: an Interpretative Centre packaged and signposted - especially for consumption abroad. Over half the first print-run was destinedfor the USA. The texts are ornately framed by introductions, headnotes, footnotes, categories. Seamus Deane, the General Editor, also edits or co-edits eleven sections - among them, the20
￼two sections of 'Political Speeches and Writings'. His insistent presence does much to freight the ship with Nationalist assumptions and priorities.Before discussing the Field Day Anthology as a symptomatic yoking of 'Irish literature' to Nationalism, I should indicate the longer-term context. Field Day, responses to Field Day (and much that goes on outside this little orbit) continue a debate about culture and identity which has taken various forms, some of them literary, since the 1830s when Catholic emancipation began to alter Irish power-dynamics. The anthology rehearses earlier phases of that debate, not only in an analytical spirit but in furtherance of its own hegemonic ambitions. Three volumes, four thousand double-column pages and fifteen hundred years make a heavy gun-enplacement on the Kulturkampf cheerfully heralded by'Head' in Samuel Ferguson's 'Dialogue between the Head and Heart of an Irish Protestant' (1833):We must fight our battle now with a handful of types and a composing- stick, pages like this our field, and the reading public our arbiter of war.40fToday's textual battles are more often joined betweenNationalists and 'revisionists' than between Catholic andProtestant Ireland as such. Northern Unionism/as a defender of jL A*the status quo, has only patchily developed the kind ofs,-*self-validating discourse long practised by Irish separation? andwith which, or in which, Southern Protestants have more readily0l\O£cIenjoyod. John Wilson Foster is one of the few literary critics21
￼who remedies 'the voicelessness of Ulster Unionist culture7, although historians are thicker on the fround. Hence, perhaps, the tendency for revisionism and the Irish Literary Revival to serve, in Nationalist intellectual quarters, as proxi^fe or scapegoats for Unionism. For example, Tom Paulin in the preface to his Faber Book of Political Verse refers to Yeats7£'muscle-flexing Protestant triumphalism7 - presumably completetoeswith union-jack tatfesr=s. More seriously, the genesis of the Field Day Anthology invoked the Revival as anti-self. In his pamphlet Heroic Styles: the tradition of an idea (1984) Deane floated 'a comprehensive [sic] anthology7 chiefly to counter the Celticism which Yeats absorbed from Matthew Arnold, and expose:the fact that the myth of Irishness, the notions surrounding Irish eloquence, are all political themes upon which the literature has fastened toan extreme degree since the nineteenth century when the idea of national character was invented. The Irish national character .... has been received as the verdict passed upon the Celtic personality. That stereotyping has caused a long colonial concussion.41It is unclear that literature should bear all the blame for these notions, even if these notions should bear all the blame. Nineteenth and early twentieth-century literary images deserve to be treated with some historical distance and caution. Deane often responds to the Revival in a curiously foreshortened way,22
￼was though it were breathing do^n his neck. The stereotypes thatpervade the contemporary political arena have various sources,Sand, as John Wilson Foster argued, may equally invest Ulster Protestants with 'a negative mystique(;© i2 Better to be'eloquent7 tha^: 'boot-faced7, as Declan calls them in one Field Day pamphlet/3 And, aside from a glancing reference to'the spiritual heroics of a Yeats or a Pearse7, Deane does not target Irish Ireland7s contribution to heroic rhetorics and to the essentialist 'mystique of Irishness7 he so depplores.44 Indeed, Heroic Styles ends by reconceiving D. P. Moran7s cultural separatism in sophisticated terms: 'Everything, including our politics and our literature has to be re-written - i.e. re-read. That will enable new writing, new politics, unblemished by© Irishness, but securely Irisb^45 Deane7s criticism frequently travels in a whereby he first seeks to disprove 'such a thing as an Irish national character or an Irish fate or an Irish destiny7, but then reverts to Nationalist language: 'it is indeed true that we have in this island, over a very long time, produced a literature or a form of writing which is unique to us746 (my italics). Deane7sotherIcc<?,orcontrarygyre, istoresistthe'promiscuous embrace of pluralim7, even while 'words like "tradition", "identity" and their sVckj swarm of relatives7.47 'Destiny7 and 'promiscuity7 seem to be >the horns of binary dilemma^: the former may make you (or Ireland) a character in somebody else7s fiction; the latter may deprive you of any character at all.23
￼This split, as in the case of Irish-Ireland thinking, fuels an intensive drive towards integration. For D. P. Moran, the-gerarl had to be 'the element that absorbs'. For Deane, re-readingwill at least erase the Celtic 'blemish'. But 'the Celt' isultimately code for Protestant as well as English versions ofCIreland. John Wilson Foster comments: The battle with Yeats isAbeginning to resemble The Everlasting Fight. He is thenationalist [some] Irish critics want and the upper-classProtestant they don't want.48 In certain lights, the Field DayTheatre Company look like an attempt to replace the allegedcultural power of the Revival with their own myths and rhetorics. 01The novelist Colm Topbin has said:Each artist in the great Irish tradition hasartinvented eur Ireland. Each has done so in order5to survive. Yeati's Protestant ascendancy, BrianFriel's history lessons, Seamus Heaney's Catholic Derry childhood ... In the Field Day enterprise itself, however, such manoeu-^erings for the sake of art have been stripped of their origin in/ artistic necessity and presented to as a politicalmanifesto, the political truth. A number of menhave come to believe in their own dreams.49However, in the anthology as wehave it, counter-revivalism has merged or developed into counter-revisionism. Promiscuity now seems a greater threat than national-t±rg£~Qaittrr-as-destiny. In an earlier Field Day publication Deane credited (discredited) Irish historians with a 'polemical ambition' to 'demolish the24
￼nationalist mythology that had been in place for over fifty years', and stated categorically: 'Field Day regards this new orthodoxy with disfavour7.50 The anthology more elaborately challenges the extent to which 're-reading7 Ireland has been the prerogative of historians. In one sense this is no bad thing as we move into a more inter-disciplinary age. However, Deane's General Introduction harbours its own polemical ambition while pretending to philosophical relativism. He outflanks both revivalists and revisionists by offering not so much literary history as a historicisation of writing. Writing demotes'literature7, ties it to the other texts of Irish history and turns Irish history into texts. This leads Deane (in a manner that would have alarmed George Orwell) to question not only the objectivity of certain historians, but objective history itself:Historians of limited philosophical resource still long to answer the question, 'What really happened then?7 More modestly, this anthology asks the longer, less abrasive question; 'How, in the light of what is happening now, can we re-present what was, then and/since, believed to have been the significance of whatreally happened?7 ...It is part of the received wisdom that the Irish past has been (mis) interpreted by [Nationalist] historians who had a cause to plead and an axe to grind. It is equally the case that this anthology, like the works it presents to thereader, is at the mercy of the present moment and, also like them, derives its authority (such as it is)25., .rii
￼from that moment.50By inviting readers onto purely textural ground, and loadingthe text, Deane tries to have his Nationalist history and eat it,to deconstruct and canonise in the same gesture. There areQmScontradictions between -the hostility towards revisionism, evident nostalgia for the old grand narrative, and tie-breaking proposal to make reader-receptions 'our arbiter of war'. Without empirical checks, without argument over the relative persuasiveness of historical hypotheses, the authority of the present movement tends to favour the sharpest axe rather than the sharpest eye. Perhaps some Nationalists now regard 'history' as a long-standing ally who has inexplicably defected. Hence their occasional exaltation of Folk-memory over 'scientific' history. Hence, too, this grasping at theoretical straws. I find SabinabLoviband's ideas pertinent to Deane's sniper attacks onIempericism and to the whole Kulturkampf opened up by Field Day.oLoviband argues that the 'doctrine of the autonomy of the logos' can dangerously detach language from being 'answerable torreality', because: 'From one point of view ..., it encourages a vision of language as a medium of play and trickery rather than of communication ... from another (related) point of view, it desplays language as a battleground where speakers struggle for mastery'.51t C.26
￼In practice, the Field Day Anthology establishes its own master-version of history quite conventionsally. It abounds in chronologies, periodisation and judgement^/ as to 'what really happened'. Sections are headed: 'The Famine and Young Ireland',n/6'/'The Intellectual Revise 1830-1850', 'Poetry and Song 1800-1890'.Tom Dunne points out that 'Deane's introduction to the particular sections he edits - presumably written earlier' do not reflect'the reservations of [his] General Introduction'.52 Rather thanliberating history into fiction, the anthology pegs literature toidate, fact, event. Competition with historography, obsessionAwith politics, and the chimera of secure Irishness determine the dreading emphasis. For example, a hitherto unpublished tale byRo\j/an Sheehan occupies fourteen pages of 'Irish Fiction 1965-1990' because it supposedly constitutes a 'brillianti^ metaphor of Anglo-Irish relations'. Meanwhile John McGatern getsthree pages. However, Declan Kiberd, charged with editing 'Contemporary Irish Poetry', found himself in difficulties sincemost contemporary Irish poets are not coming up with the right metaphors. They have, he laments, 'remarkably little to say'fabout politics 'in the past quarter century'.53 This mayi simplymean that they don't say what Kiberd wants to hear. Many would,Tagree that Paul Duhcan is the Republic's most conspicuously'political' poet. However, the tendency of his poetry can benend-termed 'revisionist'. Kiberd includes more of Duncan's politicala/vi,poemslin a rare fit of aesthe(^ticism, he calls Duncan's style'loose to the point of garrulity'.5427
￼Irish history emerges as the author of Irish writing, rather than vice versa, whether vice versa signifies the aesthetic or the post-structuralist. Further, history itself is construed within a specific historical stand of Nationalist discourse - Republican as opposed to Home Rule. Thus Deane introduces the Irish grand narrative as an unvarying tale of conquest, from the Stone Age to the Northern Ireland office:The island was conquered by pre-Christian invaders, Christian missionaries, the Normans, the pre-Reformation English, the Elizabethans, Cromwellians and by the Williamites. It was dominated by imperial Englandand it r€ivu.ii*i£ , to the present day, in Tfr/z-ll ^'economic andpolitical that affect the United Kingdom in its troubledpost-imperial decline.55By the same token, 'writing' turns out to be as selective acategory as 'literature' ever was. Indeed, the anthology'soriginality, perhaps its raison d'etre, is that it highlights notlost literary gems but discursive texts: texts which themselveshighlight politics, philosophy, culture. As history of ideasr(mainly ideas about Ireland), some sections work very well. Yet, to admit this principle is to multiply the difficulty of representing constituencies, women being the most obvious case.'Anthology' becomes an even more magnetic field^medium as well as metaphor^for the selectivities of Irish pc(i/icC . Not every section takes a political line, but counter-revisionist polemice.iV c zig-zags through the/fabric.28v c'
￼iitiTiitrnniVi'TiiTi miI•. •.** «v,*•(»> ,1, . ,,?;v•!>W:'fcW*•->■V^iTS.VlEarly on, the presence of Spenser, other 'Early planters', and Cromwell signals anti-colonial intent. As we have seen,Deane reads all Irish history up to and back from the present movement as 'a long colonial concussion'. He has said: 'Field Day's analysis of the situation derives from the conviction that it is, above all, a colonial crisi^^56 (True to his rejectionof empiricism, the conviction does not derive from the analysis)^ That statement came from Deane's introduction to three Field Day pamphlets by Terry Eagleton, Fredric Jameson and Edward Said. It must be admitted that all critics involved in the Irish(rKd.faction-fight tend to call upon^theoretical support which suitsr\their book - whether feminis^, deconstruction, or a moreddrtraditional Marxism. Field Day unstandably favour theorists whomight help to insert Northern Ireland/Ireland into the colonial/post-colonial frame. At the same time, the theorists in question could have been productively exposed to empirical data about Ireland since the era of Yeats and Joyce. Strange collusions are taking place: intellectual ^ in aToepost-colonial never-never land. See Lee's of how theRepublic has treated socio-economic ideas from abroad also applies to those who throw theory at Ireland, hoping that bits of it will stick. Lee asks: 'Did they conceive of imported ideas as raw materials, as intermediate goods, or as finished products?'57Jameson's pamphlet Modernism and Imperialism probes the 'third world' features of Joyce's Dublin without recourse tocomparative European economic contexts. The latter might also>am29
￼make Dublin pub-culture look less weird to Jameson, on whose1^ ...criteri^f should not have outlived British rule; 'the very fact ofthe pub itself, of public space in which you meet and talk, is itself a happy survival of an older urban life^" which will have no equivalent in metropolitan literature .../5S Edward Said, although more friendly towards Yeats's 'nativism' or essentialism than is Deane in Heroic Styles, fails to grasp the shifting sands of his position as a Protestant Nationalist. Thus he misreads Yeats's 'Fisherman' as exemplifying 'an anonymous man of thepeople, who in his strength and loneliness is also a muteexpression of the people'.59 In fact, the poem marks extremedisaffection from 'the people'. Terry Eagleton, also author ofthe collusive Field Day play Saint Oscar, takes an anglo-centricor "tack when he warns Irish critics against prematiwely pluralisinginyidentity or falL fcor the 'liberal humanist notion of culture\[which] was constituted, among other things, to marginalise such peoples as the Irish'.60 If Arnold flattered and colonised the3CCelt in one way, Eagleton may do in other. He assumes (liket*Said) a homogenous, unproblematic Irish people. Nor does hefdistinguish between cultural norms in Ireland and those obtaining somewhere called 'Britain' but evidently signifying Southern England/. Liberal humanism may have been tried on Ireland, but has scarcely been tried in it, any more than have the politics of pluralism. Irish liberals tensed between powerful opposites -iwitness Sean O'Faolain or Hubert Butler - irthabiiZ a verydifferent context to that of historical English liberalism. Hence, for instance, Butler's doubts about the seriousness ofu -C -30
￼liberal English liberati like Graham Greene and Stephen Spender: 'Their art and their reputation would not, I think, surviveareal Kulturkampf in which first principles were not only invoked but appliedl^60 Cultural differences should, more broadly, undermine 'liberal humanist' as a totalising reflex sneer- With regard to Saint Oscar, and to Eagleton's co-option by Field Day, the playwright Robin Glendenning protests:Apparently the Nobel prize-winning Wole Soyinka ismuch criticisedtroubles of hison its colonialdanger of Fieldtheir Irish audience, or of providing their English audience with anything too complicated to understand...I did think that Field Day's raison d'etre was that the language of Irish politics had petrified, and that the language of drama had therefore a vital and radical responsibility. If one of these petrified languages is Irish Nationalism, surely a radical responsibility goes beyond finding novel ways of saying the same damned things? And surely inviting English left-wing intellectuals to use the petrified language in their own quarrel with their own establishment is also evading that responsibility.61 Although the term 'colonial' can of course be appliedtoIrish experience, most historians would qualify or specifyits31in Nigeria these days for blaming thecountry on his own countrymen and not legacy. There does not seem to be much Day falling into the trap of unsettling
￼uses and dispute the one-size-fits-all zeal of most theorists.For instance, internal European colonialism, might constitute anapter (if not necessarily happier) model than those elaborated bydFanpn or Said. In the earlier period, the degree of parallelismbetween Irish and New World 'colonies' is the subject ofcontinuing debate.62 Also, political scientists tend to pointout that if situation X resembles situation Y in one respect, itneed not do so in all. Frank Wright's Northern Ireland: AComparative Analysis, which compares the North with several-\r s'ccic.Tici'fontier-soutos' across the globe, lists specific ways in which dit does not resemble Algeria.63 At the same time, the horrors in former Yugoslavia have brought a particular range of unhappyEuropean parallels to the fore. Again, John Whyte's compendium c<--s overview of the social-science literature, Interpreting Northern Ireland. concludes that 'internal conflict models' are close to becoming 'the dominant paradigm'.64 Is it revisionist to suggest that there may be no dominant paradigm: that colonial readings might be usefully spliced with approaches which showIreland/Irish writing in other lights? Deane's resort to thercolonial/third-world paradigm owes something to the persistent Nationalist belief in Irish exceptionalism (echoed by Jameson's reference to 'the uniqueness of the Irish situation'65). It is not necessari-dry the case that: 'The failure of... cultural versions to achieve hegemony is more remarkable in a European country than it would be in those parts of the world which has been subject to European dominationVi6632
￼j-aOne result of looking no further (or nearer) than 'colonialism' is to fudge the role of religion - supposed toi-jitt\ tK-c <Xciuf-vt-e/}~consistently blames colonial false consciousness fori/'sectarianism' and th^s leaves the latter term unexamined too.For instance, his introduction to the section on Joyce/’mentions 'the dual British-Roman Catholic spiritual monarchy', and hisgeneral Introduction refers to 'a society sectarianised by the * "x*Williamite confiscations and the Penal Laws'.67 TheseEuropean churches themselves. Ireland was not the only corner of Europe where the Reformation - and Counter-Reformation - had divisive consequences^ and it was always unclear whether ones- c m -) eventual Irish state was to be for the church or the Church ©nos for the state. Hubert Butler produced the following argument against Brian Inglis when Inglis maintained that the Penal Laws made it impossible for an Irish Protestant to criticise the status quo in the Republic:The Catholic Church prides itself on its universalitylocal activities. Why not say that the Penal Laws started not in Ireland in 1688 but rather in France three years earlier, when after the Recreation of the Edict of Nantes several hundred thousand lost sheep were bayoneted back into the Fold*.68fkvX'V h frt^cLfsuyb t m Kiaj33u.c,.
￼Tom Paulin deserves credit for featuring religion in a section called 'Northern Protestant Writing and Oratory 1791-1985'. But Paulin (perhaps inventing his own Ireland) tends to package Protestant orators - who include Ian Paisley and Paisley's nineteenth-century predecessor Henry Cooke - as marginal and doomed exotics from 'a solipsistic unwise gnawed ati/its edges by anger and incoherence', 69 and this removed fromthe intense theological - political dialectics that moved through the Irish nineteenth-century and beyond. In fact, the Hound of Heaven who fails to bark in this anthology, except courtesy of literature, is the Catholic Church. Where, for instance, is Archbishop John Charles McQuaid and his nineteenth-century predecessor Cardinal Cullen? Balance(as well as information, requires a section with some such title as 'Catholic Apologeticsfrom 1850 to the l^-~^)Divorce Referendum'.If Protestantism looms larger theologically, Nationalismlooms larger politically. Unionism, lumped in with Paulin'sPresbyterian orators and thereby dehistoricised, consists of thetUlster Covenant, a patriotic speech from James Craig in 1940, and two speeches made in political defeat by Edward Carson (not a Northerner) and the late Harold McCusker. Neither nineteenth-century Ulster liberalism nor twentieth-century Ulster socialism gets a look-in. Deane's 'political' sections (and Luke Gibbons's cultural counterparts) overwhelmingly stress varieties of Nationalism (some varieties more than others). Thus2'Political Speeches and Writing 1900-1988 ends with a flourish of34
￼Charles Haughey, John Hume, Sean McBride and Gerry Adams. The introduction to this section itself reads like a political speech, particularly its eulogy of ex-Taoiseach Charles Haughey:Charles Haughey, perhaps the most resourcefulpolitician in Ireland, has repeatedly calledNorthern Ireland 'a failed entity' and seekso-1<«-f"10.1recognition about its future on that basis.There is, in his policy, and in the attitudesof his party, Fianna Fail, a recognition thata political crisis is not susceptible to genialgestures like those of [Garret] Fitzgerald. Itis a matter of interest and power, and most ofthe power is in the hands of the British. Haugheyhas still to show that he knows where the Britishsee their interest to lie. Best, in the interval,he skilfully combines de Valera's meticulouslycrafted republicanism with Sean Lemass's bestpossible blend of cosmopolitan modernity andancestral loyalty for present-day Ireland.70rHere Deane nails his colours, his authority to as General Editor, and 'Irish writing' to the Fianna Fail mast - or, at least, to its Republican grain. Despite saluting Sean Lemass, he does not document Lemass's reforms of the late 1950s: reforms which, in steering the Republic away from economic protectionism,
￼betokened the end of culture protectionism too and laid the fireJfor contraversies - abortion, divorce, - now ablaze in the political foreground.Church-state politics also bring feminism into the foreground, since control over women's minds and bodies is central to the argument. (Meanwhile, the Pope has intervened on the other side). In excluding women's politics and politicaluwomen, of whatever stripe, in landing Haughey but not MaryacRobinson's libertarian crusijzades, in overlooking contempory Irish feminism and its foremothers, in minimising the politics of the Catholic Church, the Field Day Anthology locates its own political heart North of the Border. It thus reflects the increasing tension between Northern Nationalism and Revisionistprocesses - or social change - in the Republic (see From Cathleen to Anorexia). A recent and symbolic case in point was Bernadette/(Devlin) McAliskey's attack on blase Southerners for 'laughing at grandmother's bare feet'. North-South differences within broadly Nationalist Ireland extend to the greater conservatien of the Catholic Church in the North. Radical nuns and priests are thinner on the ground there; the laity, though with some middle-class reservations^ a?e obedient. In other words, Northern Catholics, for purposes of cultural defence and communal cohesion, still abide by the contract negotiated between Catholic^and Nationalist during the nineteenth- century. That ambiguous bargain has not yet come unstuck, as it has in the,CRepublic (hence Hierarchial hostility to the North's small band36
￼of integrated schools). The Northern Nationalist newspaper, the Irish News, retains pro fide et patria in its masthead. If, inwest Belfast, Republicans sometimes clash with the Church, that too reproduces a nineteenth-century pattern. ^And Gerry Adams took care to attend the funeral of the Catholic Primate Cardinal 0'Fiaichj(. So it was always on the cards that, wittingly or unwittingly, whether impelled by conscious programme orprogrammed unconscious, Field Day would collide with progressive%forces in the Republic. Colm Tofbin said in his review of the anthology:Unreconstructed Irish Nationalists have always had real difficulty with the 26 counties. The 26 counties are limbo, they believe, waiting for the day when our island will be united and the British will leave. This leaves out any idea that Southern Ireland has been forming iiis own habits and going its own way.71Shocked, by the reaction from women, into recognising the/Irish Republic, Field Day have embarked upon a damage-limitationexercise. To atone for their all-male directorate, and Deane's all-male editorial team, they now plan a fourth volume edited by women writers, critics and historians. Perhaps this afterthoughtfirc,wmight be called - Field Day's viewpoint - ‘The Mad Women in theAnnex'. Nor should annexes be attached to flawed structures. /\Such a volume under such auspices, however powerful its own feminist critique, would tie women to a totalising text whose37
￼patriarchal and Nationalist compulsions are not easy to disentangle. One commentator who condemned the anthology from a feminist angle, also asked how Seamus Deane, 'a hero of mine', could do this. She might have noted the blend of sectarianism, anti-Englishness and dismissive attitudes to women writers in Deane's of George Eliot's 'evangelical female puritan spirit' in his Celtic revivals (1985).72 But the centripetal cultural norms laid down by Catholicism/Nationalism encourageinheroes and heroines to kiss and --wake up when it comes to thecrunch. Conversely, as a revisionist woman critic of Field Day, I may have given double offence. (It is an odd state of affairswhen writers and critics are deemed beyond criticism^ Yet the anthology's sins of omission support the question-marks which'From Cathleen to Anorexia' raised over the synchronisation of Nationalist and Feminist objectives. When Terry Eagleton's Field Day pamphlet compares Nationalism with feminism, and urges bothd. to resist premature deconstruction,73 he implicitly fears thatlatter's potential to deconstruct the former: partly through its subversion of absolutes, partly through its reinstatement of trans-cultural values. Sabina Levibc.iU makes feminism the test-case when she argues that values assigned by cultures andA<>'groups might be 'seen so answerable to a universal org^end-universal standard that would identify some discursiveJregimes, but not others as tolerable.74 In the Irish Republicfeminist universals have proved indispensable. Francis Gardner's study, 'The Unfinished Resolution', shows that - until recently - women have been less politically ative there than in other38
￼Northern European countries. This is because 'a budding feminist consciousness was subsumed by Nationalist hegemony,75 itself%subsumed by Catholic hegemony. Gardner says:It has been noted that, following enfranchisement, women's political activity often seemed to recede,as pf the effort of getting the vote had left suffragists temporarily exhausted. But in many countries, within a matter of decades, remobilisation occurred. This contrasted with the Irish experience,where women appeared to losjt motivation to reinstate feminist concerns on the political agenda, or toparticipate in shaping the new state.76i —-Women were allow^no voice in drafting de Valera's 1937constitution which upheld Catholic social teaching by recognising '^he Family' as 'the natural primary and fundamental unit ofSociety' and desiring women to concentrate on 'their duties in the home'.Like the 1937 Constitution, the Field Day Anthology tries torplace itself above argument. On the one hand, Deane's General Introduction uses theoretical relativism to discredit'revisionist' critiques: 'The political animus informing... non-nationalist groups was concealed as much as possible, and the most frequently worn disguise was, in history, the pretence to"objectivity" and in literature the claim to "autonomy"'.77 On39
￼the other hand, he throws theory to the winds and advertises the anthology itself as transcending context, and as not merely an overview of texts but a unitary island-story:There is a story here, a meta-narrative, which is, we believe, hospitable to all the micro-narrative 5' that, from time to time, have achieved prominence as the official version of the true history, political and literary, of the island's past and present.78At this stage I need not dwell on the ironies of 'hospitable'. However, 'meta-narrative' might be exposed tobroader debates about canons and history. I find Anne Rigney's The Rhetoric of Historical Representation (1991) and Jan Gorak's The Making of the Modern Canon ( ) relevant to the Irish interface between anthology and historiaproply.e-Rigney examines three historias of the French Revolutionwritten at roughly the same distance from the event as Irishnhistorians now are from the upheavals of the 1920s. She showsir* Athat while historiafs need to accept the theorists's point (i.e.Ithat they are engaged in representation as well reproduction),their house-style is neither as unphilosophical or unself-conscious as Deane makes out. Historical narratives function within an 'intellectual antagonism', and historias are/\constrained 'by the nature of their historographical role and the anature of the raw material with which they are dealing; the fact that they are not free to produce whatever many they choose; the fact that unlike fiction-writers they are not free to invent'.7940
￼Michael Laffan, in 'Insular Attitudes: The Revisionists and their5.Critics', points out that change^m Irish historiographicalpractices since the 1960s were not simply dictated by newIpolitical exigencies (or 'political animus') but by the opening-up of crucial archives. Laffan also insists that 'in looking critically at the past, in stressing complexity and ambivalence... Irish historians... have simply applied, in the Irish context, the same approaches and methods as are taken for granted by their counterparts in other countries'.80 Nationalisthistory, resistant to the democracy of interT-Ckt*.^! antagonism', desires to cast 'revisionism' in its own monolithic mould. Laffan remarks:Those historians who mince the wrath of radicalor hyper-sensitive nationalists are a diverse bunchof people: by nationality they are Irish, Britishand American; by political inclination they areconservative, liberal, radical and even (on rareoccasions) Marxist... They disagree vehemently amongthemselves on many questions and some of them wouldbe inclined to repudiate the label 'revisionist' notmerely because it is a label but because of thecompany they would be presumed to keep as members ofany such group or faction.81 .V LiHra f3It is equally tendentious to identify a homogenous faction who hide 'non-nationalist' politics behind doctrines of artisticautonomy. No Irish writer or critic can be so 1 as to divorce literature from context along the lines suggested by Tom41
￼\v*Paulin's Anglo-centric contention that;'We have been taught, many of us, to believe that art and politics are separated by the thickest and most enduring of partition^-rj’2 The argument does not turn on whether to link literature and history, or literature and politics, but on how\ ,Although Deane stresses 'the extent to which, in Irish conditions, canonical forms have not been established',83 canons have been floating and floated for some time. How they relate to'English' canons is another matter, to which I will return, andwhich I see as a more complex affair than 'repossessing some ofthe standard "English" names - Swift or Sterne, Burke orWilde'.84 In fact, the Irish canon has not always claimed thesenames. Yeats excluded the Anglo-Irish eighteenth century - tof) c i ^ ^ £v Doiidaft^-s- protests - when he was canon-building in the 1890s. So,. . o/l<aO later, did Daniel Corkery when canon-building on behalf of Irish>^0 r-Ireland. Indeed, Corkey went further and employed Yeats,htogether with much of the Revival. This obliged Yeats to rethinkhis own Irish canon, to reinforce the Revival with the eighteenthoM. vcentury, rebuild his Protestant literacy 'ancestral stair' -c') Goldsmith and the Dean, Berkeley and Burke have travelled there(j'Blood and the Moonjj. Deane has himself ridiculed Yeats'sconstruction of the eighteenth century, and described hislove-hate relationship with Spenser and Blake as 'the pathologycof literary unionism'.85 Suc?i shifts bear out G^arak's conclusion that 'the canon' is neither single nor simple but the product of continual contentation:42