￼FARM IN PENNSYLVANIA-fNear the flat of the valleywhere the slope bottoms out,the farm buildings, small houseand big barn, hold onto their space.Above, the woods have the lookof something pushed back, held, waiting to drop down and overwhelm the skylit clearings. Up there the deer will be watching, slithering through the birches.The fields in cultivation stay near to home, asway with a~dpift of cattle, or nodding with corn. Alongside the house, close,lie the strict vegetable rows, and a twisted orchard^struggles^ behind the barn.L^I^vJvsjl|pver a wallis a smaller field with the one certainharvest, perhaps a dozen grey-white headstones, where the graves are,\lhk