￼2X<- S|2 —es>*+00^))We hear you spoken of as a dead manAnd where you were there is new growth of obituaries. Someone has met an eyewitness from Darlington—A liar, it is true. We had thought this wasOnly the interruption of one of your storiesAnd you were working slowly on a smokeAnd, tilting your indoor trilby, would appearThrough clouds soon and would broachYour silence waiting like an untouched beerFor a man back from the gents. Remember the bloke$kSo bent with arthuritis that for his wakeThey tied him to a board and in the small hours Some joker cut his cords and, with a creak,He sat up grinning? In a digger's jawsRising in a shroud of snow at bitter daybreakAYou cleared a building-site; the mortuary men, Summoned to shift you, dewy, from the roadHave brought their breakfasts up and dropped their load When you op4ened an eye. Time and againFrom under newspaper we fetched you in,A foetal stiff. Around the cup you setYour fingers like a broken basketAnd thawing your nose in tea began to tellThe story of a man from MotherwellWho swallowed three hundred goldfish for a betAnd lived. You lived the part: the Indian doctor Offering to amputate; nice Ronnie KrayVisiting his mam; Lord LondonderryAddressing your father like the man next door,ou hooked yourself a stooge when necessary.if the liar from Darlington was right then now The devil is leaning on his fork and youAre keeping him waiting while you toast your bumAnd roll a smoke for what is still to come^ — Ahput a man you met in Eccles who...( f 3&2eTMs 1----------------------- — --------------------------------------—f
￼‘Many meanwhile’Many meanwhile are turning on cruel wheelsIn the pit of indifference fretting to engender firesAnd only bruise and ever from the hub fall as flesh falls From the bone and gnaw in the night on a shroud of fears.Under the wheels, under the crosses of stars stretched out On gaps of darkness they cover themselves and tryWith a little rod to strike life that will rootAnd long on the sun’s axis to turn securely.Closing in sleep under one mantle, in the earsO f sleep our breathing quieter than a murmur o f sea in shells, We think of them under their draughty lattice of starsAnd dust going helter-skelter round the stuck poles.24y
￼SwansNot many see the white swans. Vagrants at road-ends haveOr, waiting for shift-end, Machine-minders staringAt dereliction through the blank panes.Not many hear them. Soiled Drunks have whom the cold wakes Early lying curled;Or, nearly sleeping, the innocent Lovers. After birdsongThat is the kindest light.Through silver grey, through rose Across our malignant cityThe heavy birds strainIn this season, about this hour .Little above roof-topsRapid, whistling, intent, Steadily clouting the air.Pity them should they flag For where is there a meadowOr any habitable waterAnd where, landing or falling, When the day hardens and we Come down the roads will they Avoid our fatal notice?
￼Watching for DolphinsIn the summer months on every crossing to Piraeus One noticed that certain passengers soon roseFrom seats injt he packed saloon and with serious Looks and no acknowledgement of a common purpose Passed forward through the small door into the bows To watch for dolphins. One saw them loseEvery other wish. Even the loversTurned their desires on the sea, and a fat manHung with equipment to photograph the occasion Stared like a saint, through sad bi-focals; others, Hopeless themselves, looked to the children for they Would see dolphins if anyone would. Day after dayOr on their last opportunity all gazedUndecided whether a flat calm were favourableOr a sea the sun and the wind between them raisedTo a likeness of dolphins. Were gulls a sign, that fell Screeching from the sky or over.an unremarkable place Sat in a silent school? Every faceAfter its character implored the sea.All, unaccustomed, wanted epiphany,Praying the sky would clang and the abused Aegean Reverberate with cymbal, gong and drum.We could not imagine more prayer, and had they then On the waves, on the climax of our longing comeSmiling, snub-nosed, domed like satyrs, ohWe should have laughed and lifted the children up , Stranger to stranger, pointing how with a leapThey left their element, three or four times, centered On grace, and heavily and warm re-entered,Looping the keel. We should have felt them go
￼Further and further into the deep parts. But soon We were among the great tankers, under their chains In black water. We had not seen the dolphinsBut woke, blinking. Eyes cast downWith no admission of disappointment the company Dispersed and prepared to land in the city.27
￼/ I 'j\1‘- ) 1 /„ -ISLANDS1. BrackenThere were sheep then, they pastured on the little islands, We took them there by boat. But the grass has goneAnd the fold my father’s father built with his bare handsHere at high water has also gone. One by oneAll his fields have gone under the f^hs againAnd now it is hard for you to see how it was then.Bitter, unharvested, deeper than children, Theferns risefrom high water over the wall. Thefields drown; the swinging gate isfallenAndferns break round theposts that stand as tall As men. Butfrom the spring you clinibed this way After the spilling water-carts on a hot day.You would not think we had any open ground,But we did. We called it Plains. There was spaceFor all the island to be sitting roundWatching the tennis or the cricket. Our playing-place Has gone the way of the fields and I shouldn’t know Where to look for the pitch and the court now.Sunk flourishing in depths o f hitter greenThe little islands are lost to us already.We watch from boats the rats going hungry between Waste and waste. Rememberfo r our sakes quickly Where the sweet water places were and whenAnd by whom thefields werefirst rid oftheir bracken.Sometimes in summer we made ourselves a bedUnder the ferns, where we should never be found,And looked up through the lovely green at the sky and said That we were at the bottom of the sea and drowned.I believe sometimes we slept, but the afternoonWhen we woke again was still no further gone.28
￼QtcUu -toesOUOWelie ontheharbourwallandpeeringdown Where the wrack heaves and hideous clawsfeel Afterfood, we see the clouds that do not drownIn pathless water with all ofour things lost but sail Untouched through the coral and the saltflowers Through the places o f this island that once were ours./29
￼SS•^ Qj2.At blown cockcrow, hearing the driven sea,You remember the rattling sash, starlight Surviving faintly on the looking-glassAnd the islands troubled with a ceaseless crying.Scheria, kind to strangers, wept for her shipSunk by God/unjustly; for the Schiller'sMore than three hundred souls there were many in Two continents weeping; and everywhereFor the sailors of our wars, numberless Mothers’ sons who have rolled in without faces. Indifferent Hermes conducted them all.The sea turns and its creatures hunger. SoonEverything lies under the mercy of day.The surface flickers with scared pilchards. Light, above all the light. And the sea comes, At sunny tide-flow the plucked, the smitten seaComes running. The wind then, high-ridden by One nonchalant gull, batters the openingEyes of the sun with water. Far-reaching, Iridescent, the white surf comes and comes.Children are playing under a rainbowOn Pool Green; or behind Innisvouls, Delighted in a rocking boat, they stand Out/staring the ancient quizziness of seals.30
￼3.Our child when we came looking and calling after herAnd had come through marram and sea-holly to the dunes’ crest When we stood crushing in our fingers plucked samphire Looking still further and calling and saw her at lastShe was remote and small on an almost islandAnd turned away, at tide-flow, but our fear was less Of the sea already parting the cord of sandThan that she was so small and averted from us.We ran heavily, the white sand sank us in,But through the neck of the place stole then like bird-stalkers Over the flat wrack that popped and stank in the sun Towards her kneeling before big granite chairsGently stroking for shells. When she turned and looked up And showed us wordless in her palm the fissured cowrie The spiralling white horn of wentletrapAnd scallops smaller than her smallest nail then weWith our looks put upon her the fear of deathAnd the ownership of love. Between our tall shadows She walked to the safe beach down the snake path Already sunk over ankles in warm shallows.Gratefully then the weed rose in the sunny waterAnd swirled as it liked and flowed and the bright shell Hoardsfbefore the thrones Sparkled)without herWho stood between us watching, waiting for tide-fall.Hoards sparkled bej&re. 'the "thrtne^ wt+hiaot her31