￼FROM A NEW COLLECTION BYSARA BERKELEYTo be published in 1993/94 byNew Island Books, Dub1in .
￼Man In BalloonHe was what he wasHe dreamed it was more.Some said his spirit kindled at his throat.He stamped it out.He kept his emotions at bay. One dayFinding them wrung, he weighted and drowned them One by one. Pity sank without trace.Fear sank, then Love. Setting his face,He held his great anger downAnd saw it drown.He felt so empty then. The reservoir was low, The ducts were dry, the blood was cold.He could not find his feet, his head was light, Like an air balloon -He clambered aboardAnd rose.Bottomless the sky; looking down He saw the cloth of the earth unfold, The pattern of river and town, Snake of a track, quilt of cloud. When would the secret be told?All day it was light, the night Kept him afloat. At dawnHe felt wings. He knew flight. He soared.
￼Facts About WaterBe ready for the flood, they said.I gathered my skirts. No flood came.Beware the danger that comes with a man, They said. I waited for the fall.In blinding lightA man came stumbling to us from the stones. Was this the man? He fell at our feet,Fire, famine, flood.Give him his name, they said.I was drawn to the man, I told himThis is your name, and then he was all I saw, The first I knew of endless, immeasurable calm, The whole struggle over and done.I had expected pain, insteadHe treated me with care, folding and wrapping, I had never been given before.He gave me to myself, said without sayingLove if you will, but be warned,I have very little.Here was a manWithout the anchor of dreams.He blinked in the sun, he hardly seemed At home in his set of bones.1 felt his uncontrolReined in with a shaky hand. I said,If you need me in the nightCall out. Trains run beneath my house. His flame flickered, but did not go out,I conjured a green field to steady him, No gate, no way in or out,But a cool mile of young grassAnd four spare dry stone wallsTo hold him in.I had never held anyone in before.In return, he brought me to his shore, He wrote in the sandFacts about water.Minim, fathom, barrel, cord. Magnum, gallon, jeroboam. He said When you wake far out,Dream a boat, and with these things Make good your return, and he wrote: Sextant, compass, dipstick, dial, Plumb, octant, nautical mile.He left me sleeping,I woke without fear,In a rigged vessel, sails and mast,
￼1dreamed my way to dry land, Acre, arpent, section, square, League, light-year, township, are.
￼FallWe sit over Indian bones And over the silent, Sitting up,Buried ones.Bob Hass laughs about Dickinson And tells us it isOkay to be slowAnd confusion is all part of what is Meant to be.I finger the silence that followsA poem's end.It is the soundOf having been there, the hard despair That followsPain getting wordsAnd after rainYou can hear the dropsStaying in the trees.Sometimes the day tumbles earlyBut coming up from the Mining Circle The grass yearns downTo the figure of a girlIn bronzeGreen as rain, and such bewilderment Is part of what isMeant to be.t
￼He Isn’t ThereShe is a single note of the song Without him; she gets it wrong, The blood stops going to her head, She sees stars.She almost gets run overWithout him; into rush-hour's cars She steps out, thinking ofHis forearm's blond hairs,His slenderness.Everything has a ghostEvery spirit has a doubleHer lost half cries out for itsLost other. She senses troubleAt the source, tries to block outThe wrong sounds, the noise, the noise,Was that his quiet voice? She opens her mouth But without him no sound comes out.She stands in the trafficCrying in cold air her single noteAnd he isn't there.
￼Heartbreak HourHis flat is allOasis, warmth of books.He gives me teaAnd offers the missing piece Ofa picture:Low skies and a lake iced-over, I tell him aboutLove's quavering note,He says there will always beA man's hand cupping my chin, Look to the light, he says,All ice is thin.Leaving there at four, heartbreak hour, The air is freezing overAnd the blind animalsFretting in the small of my heartAre begging meTo write the stories of ice and fire. The journal of leaving behind Oases, and facingThe solid grey doorAnd my own walls, my silences.
￼In his roomInside his room, life wasA balancing of weightsIt was a memorable sight -All that man,Contained,And those who called him madTrawled that word from their shallow hearts, Yet, spine-arched, their napes tooWere resting lightly on the truth.I first saw him as I swam up-streamHe burned bridgesHis face took the river coloursHe was one who lived perpetual spring, When he turned after rain,When he let the leaves be blown,That was unknowing,And I too lost time, growing with him, Became a changeless thing.Like smoked-out rabbits,Ears back,We fled the turns,Of tide, of season, of the day;And could I have knownThat so much fright would fall upon the warren, On the riversideAnd on his spring,I might have found the perfect height And flung my spirit down.
￼Letter (on a beach)Down to cold stoneTo whet my heart. It is not long,The letter with the burning lines.Hearts are sore, mine singsA mournful tuneI have to listen to. The beach is raw,White waves crashing down on sin,Sky washed and the water in,Coke can in the undertow,A gull runs shakily at the edge.Wave after waveAnd the foam climbing up the dark Underbelly. The dark could punishBut it comes too late - gull takes fright.A tightness climbs my throatMy wings are trembling,White envelope,The end, the wrapper, the crumbs, the dregs. The weekend falls back like a medium weight. The letter walls me out, I feelNothingAnd nothing is better.
￼LoomOur house standsQuite alone on the roadIt darkens and darkens,The doorbell rings into the gloom, We cannot let light in,We are seldom home.The house is many-corneredIt has an angular voiceIts spirit is noosed;Light from the streetsMakes frosted squares on wallpaper there The drive lights make more squares; Shadowy paintings, blurred booksJigsaw the dark.These pieces make memory up.We are kept tight within our bonesBy places, names, and childhood happenings; Meals that have been taken there;People wearing faces they will cast away,Sun shining through the rooms,Getting lost somehow.No need to shape the tones,The house spins its own,That frail loom the builders raised in days. They put the wires inThat hum and sing in spinning outThe crazy, half-heard tunesThat make the spaces at my fingertips Vibrate, as though sentThrough a different element.
￼MistThe singing goes on, lonely, in the mist Long after dark. Up on my second floor I follow the score.On the window faceA clammy smile, spreading, white, Nothing behind the eyes,The chilled limbs invading my few rooms. I turn to find at home,Comfortable in my easy chair,Body without bone,Whispering with the books.Sweating the air, exchanging looksWith the family photographs,Billowing secrets under its breath.The kitchen cradles the dark,The fridge has started quietly to humTo my foggy guest, the phoneShrillyFails to ring. If it would only rainAnd damp down my unwelcome friend, Or I could make the move to fire,And paint my home
￼PaddingtonThe taxis line up in the sooty air,I wait for a later train.Above us all a net is cast in the gloomIt hangs above the clocks you can hardly see For grime. They have given up the struggle, They wander in time as the platforms thicken And grow lean,I wish I were not this faint dishevelled me With the stoppable heart, always an eye out For the leap of light,The shaft of yellow I turn from,Healed for a spell. The sun is red,The ordinary livesAre running out on narrow rails,The engine growls at the rear, I stop my ears, I turn from the snub end of the beast, Ashamed that the soundCan so dismantle my peace of mind.I look to the three arches for black grace,A sense of light coming apartAnd coming together, up in the birdnote rafters The organ-music heights; I thinkI have to climb down, get on a train,And sit tight.
￼PatienceA game of patienceThe cards tap on the flatTable-top; it is late,I keep my letters tuckedDown between the flower potAnd night; marry the gentlemanYou met in the gallery, they say,Live like we do, be happy,And write back without delay.I shuffle the cards,Life is not dealt straight,The King has left his Queen -He poured the fire that lit her crown And when he left she let herself go out. She sat down.Memory pulls on its chains,I find a placeNear the end, my wishes are weightless, I lay the cardsOn the rough table-top, they stir dust. The motes set up a thin cry.Her kingdom in flamesBy her red King the Queen is laid, Heart, heart, diamond, spade.
￼Polesthe mind runs north to souththe weirs in the river thought turn round the rivers in the heart's valley turn; heading westi lose my sense of self,of home, and how the land lies.the bus groans as though in pain against livid barriers; prevailing windsfold their gags into my mouth,the land lies north to southher waters turn to follow the moon,the cold lies flat along the ground,frosts calm the earth's trouble,she is black and white from pole to pole, the great whites, north and south,the snow wastes and ice caps,and then the deeper blackswhere space roars, way beyond,as though out thereall darkness found a voice.
￼Potsdamer Platz, BerlinThe comers of the world moved close After the wallFell and was flattened and filled. People dared to walkIn the wide streets and the empty places. Potsdamer, where an old man stumbled to a seat In the weeds, Potsdamer Platz where they will Build and lose a world.Point by point a shape emerges,The blocky offices, flawless, linear,Behind the old memorial church with its Bombed spireThat I admire because itFails to please,Because it hangs out human memoryIn the breeze,Because it grieves.Clean glass heals the open stone,The markets drip jewellery,Silver bands and candles, hats,And over Spandauer StrasseThe statues standing out against the duskSing of the wide streets and empty places,O f Potsdamer Platz where they will build,Two years after the wallFell and was lifted and filled,With hardly a scar, the tar tissue knitted so well, I stand for the last time in a placeWide as the space a man's life takes to fill.
￼ReflexShe crouched in the corner of her head The ache of sanity passedThe bricks of the wall held her there, Eyes quenched,Darkness about the mouthHer back to the words.She was a crafterMoulding her absence with bare hands, Dovetailing silences,Learning and learning, blind and divining The age of shadows, their grainy touch, The lie of them.We brought her shelter:A cardigan of words she would seldom wear; The nouns she devoured,Survival balanced, melting, on the tongue; But the verbs, tensed in their paradigms,She had no purpose for, And cast away.
￼ShippedLife stretches far, many things come right, The sea yawns crisply to the ship's stern. Tonight I am possessedBy reaches dark and out of sight, Unexpressed wishes race us out of port, Heads high, sailorcapped,They cheer briefly as we wheel, and clap Against the pier one last timeAs the land pencils to a foreign line. The wind chokes, fouled in the spume, There are wind-spirits out tonightOur trail is knuckle-whiteHard bone under little flesh.I will wake in waves, wondering Was this where I drowned last night?
￼Sung through fireI put a match to music Up came this soft drum Those plaintive flames Those strings.Fire came down upon my house Many things were lostThe sun came down.My children, playing with water. Did not bum.My fatherToying with wordsCould turn a phrase to burn my ears But chose insteadLove's gentle word.When I was a child, I fell asleepTo my mother's songTo the light under the doorThe muffled mysteries of the adult world. Sometimes I recall that songI am almost child againAnd to my childrenSing lullabies through fireWatching their faces in the red light. Most of knowingIs not knowing but a guess; Rage at the signs of nothingness Fury and fearDisappointment, disillusionment And in the endAmong the ashesLove.
￼The SwimmerInto the risky waters of another month Bottle and paddle, milk-crate raft,I swim against the small choppy waves. The children shout from the beach.I am fighting my reluctance,Almost dread, to take the water on,I would rather swimIn lakes that make the bodyYellow green, and where there is no bed; I wear a fluid dress,A thing of grace then, the swimmers are A family of slender girls.I swam like thatOn the last day, on the first beach, Exulting inThe sweet milk of being alone in it; And when the water calledFor a change of element,I breathed it inAnd thatWas easily done.