￼/
￼O
￼Q— TUe our credit, we’ll offer you moreBut now all the chickens have come home to roost There are men in grey minds at the doorYou were top of the tree in the eightieswhen the plastic explosion held sway- "Y-you bought crap on a whim now you’re out on a limbrepossessed by the Devil todayIn the London hotels where the suits go to lunch if you beg your way into the feastyou’ll see Major, the Devil’s trainspotter_ ancj I ^ m o m ^ * neighbour of the beast making jokes with their friends in the Citywhose promises put you in hockand talking of regenerationwhile the bailiffs are changing the lock—^ B u t again you believed what they told you on your hand-picked excursion to Hell‘Ah, it’s better the Devil you know, mate!’ Now you’ve got to know him far too well...11Attila 11-21 18/9/92 12:10 am Page 1t i p p tc f Va CC-*~-Repossessed by the DevilIn the days of the old never-neverwhen your house rose in price with each day in a right to buy giveaway con-trickto make millions vote Margaret’s wayyou mortgaged your income to SatanDoctor Faustus of Shoreham-by-Seasaw the homeless in the bed & breakfasts and thought how the hell can that beso* you borrowed the earth in the eightieswhen the plastic explosion held sway'ty o u r repayments are late so this is your fate -repossessed by the Devil todayNow you used to be prudent and thrifty till Satan’s slaves took you in handYou are what you buy was the corporate cry in a don’t pay till next year landNo matter you’re stretched to the limitCUw(dlof,
￼Attila 11-21 18/9/92 12:10 am Page 12,A man was beaten to death in August 1992 at a burger stall in Kingston-upon-Thames by-»e«©pbeb4e4©ealthtt«9-because, though English, he was speaking in French to his female companions...Language Barrier‘Oi, you!Whaddya talking foreign for?You’re English like us, aintcha?So whaddya talking foreign for?Nice birds though, ya done alright there, mateBut watcha talking like that for?Oh, they don’t speak English, don’t they?Well, whyya bovvering with them Froggie slags then?Talking never did any good anyway - give us ’em over ’ere, they cantalk to our meat, that’s Esperanto, innit?Watcha sayin to em? Oi, cunt, watcha sayin to ’em?Talkin bahrt us, are ya?Fuckin wankerBet ya think yer really clever-clever, dontcha,talking foreign so we can’t understand yatrying to impress those birds with yer fancy lingo -fucking university wankerHey, Del boy, shall we TALK to ’im, eh?Poncy cunt - let’s teach him a REAL lesson, eh?Oh, not so mouthy now, are we, wanker?Well, it’s too late - we’re gonna kick some good British sense intoyer, aren’t we, lads?No use begging now, ya student tosser!’and the boots went inthe fists went inand he went downthe boots went in againthe fists went in againand the lights went out on a lifedestroyed in a blind moment of hatredby the psychopathic flotsam of Thatcherism’s own - and let’s have no excuses,no bullshit sociology,12
￼Attila 11-21 18/9/92 12:10 am Page 13,no talk of deprivation, of mitigating circumstances - Kingston-on-Thames?No, these were just mean-spirited scum,celebrating the values of the last thirteen years -the values of crass ignorance selfishnessviolenceand of course‘pride in being British’.Was it for this, the 1944 Education Act?People are murdered every day, of course- in this nasty, brutish zit of a country,often for even more unbelievably banal reasons -so why this poem?Simply that I remembera visit to a pubmy own bilingual conversation(it’s a skill, you know, you learn it, like medicine or carpentry - a skill that most Europeans take for granted)and the broken beer glassand the contorted face of the thugwhen I replied to his insult in his own tongue -For me it ended differentlybut when I saw that story in the papera shiver ran down my spineI remembered that evening in the puband the impotent anger swelled uncontrollably in my guts...One final thought;I bet THIS senseless murderdidn’t make the tabloid headlines:After all,The Paper That Supports Our Boys wouldn’t want to alienate its readership, would it?13
￼ACtila 11-21 18/9/92 12:10 am Page 14,In the vanguard of the stultifying wave of social and political apathy currently festering across our nation we find The Kids. Their immediate forebears were radical hippies and wild-eyed punk rockers who rioted, vomited, went on demonstrations and generally stood up and spat. This bunch —who’ve actually got far more to he angry about than the last couple of generations -- .seenwaw happier with a sensible haircut, a nice cup of cocoa and a _ Chris Rea LP........— The Blank Generation)^(A new slant on an age-old theme)The youth of today don’t know they’re born ...at the age of five, they’re mowing the lawn— Sdfy the time they’re eight, their golden dream is a foolproof, high-yield pension schemeAs puberty strikes, know where they are? Out there on Sundays, washing the carBirthdays and Christmas, the same old cry: ‘Please, please, Mum, can I have a new tie?’Games: ‘You be a company director, I’ll be the local tax inspector.’Teenage rebellion: ‘Grow up, Dad, and buy a suit, you look real sad!’Music: Doors and Rolling Stones (!) and bleepy acid monotones*(*though some arereally daring creatures - — they like Blur and Manic Street Preachers)APolitics: Grey. A tinge of greenfrom time to time, to suit the scene.14