￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 12:45 am Page 38,CanadaI am playing at a plush, antiseptic businessman’s dinner and dance establishment called the Norwood Hotel; it’s my first gig in Win­ nipeg, and it seems completely self-evident that no one round here has the faintest idea what Attila the Stockbroker is. The gig has been organised at very short notice by the Winnipeg Folk Festival; as far as I can tell, the publicity consists of a box ad in the hotel restaurant menu and a couple of leaflets shoved between the Grate­ ful Dead albums in the local second-hand record store. There is a two-dollar admission charge, waived for anyone staying at or enter­ taining in the hotel.The majority of the audience consists of businessmen; corporate males, each with one of those little cardboard identification badges which middle-aged executives wear in lieu of personalities when they go to business functions in hotels. They are all rather drunk, and obviously under the impression that Attila the Stockbroker is some kind of country and western act.There’s a smattering of Folk Club regulars, mostly Woodstock survivors and Man sweater victims, and, to my pleasure and sur­ prise, a group of ten or so who look like punks and show every sign of interest - in fact virtually all of them come up to me individually during the course of the evening and ask me why the hell Pm play­ ing at a country and western club instead of the local anarcho-veggie commune, and will I come and play for them there after Pve been booed off?At the appointed hour I take the stage. Directly front of me, and seemingly obliviousJSrmy presence, four gentlenyftt of the wrist talk corporate gunk - their lapel badges indicating an umbilical allegiance to a local computer firm. Summoning up all my consider­ able energy reserves, I launch into an extra loud, extra fast version of ‘Libyan Students From Hell’ and await the onslaught.An hour and a half and three encores later, I leave the stage - very worried.38
￼Attila 3 -47 18/9/92 12:46 am Page 39.eAustraliaI’m not much one for snapshots, though the world is now my oyster I chronicle my wanderings in poem and in songBut when I went Down Under, I brought along my camerato photograph the wildlife, that rich and teeming throngOn my first few days in Oz, I wasn’t sure that they existed -those strange, exotic species, they mostly hide away$ >ut on the way to Melbourne the truth became apparent;if you want to see some wildlife, then take the motorway...There are wallabies and wombats, there are possums, birds and lizards and kangaroos of all sorts, yes, even a big redand all these different species have one quality in commonyes, each of them is wonderfully, spectacularly dead...There are lots of flies in Oz, and now I know where they all come fromfor there were lots of maggots in the creatures that I sawyes, every little corpsie was a blowfly kindergarten -more wrigglers and more squirmers than I’ve ever seen beforeNj?fow I’ve made my contribution to Australian natural history and it’s by way of a tribute that I decomposed this songbut one word of advice to all you wild death photographers: stay inside the car because the bastards don’t half pong!39checklist fry n€<-J
￼eXenophobia(a satirical look at the English attitude to Europe —strange how the xenophobic attitude of ‘our’ football thugs is mirrored, albeit in a slightly more subtle way, by the Conservative Government, and in a slightly less subtle way (!) by the tabloids)THE DUTCH the Dutch they’re much too much we’re gonna kick them in the crutch flick bogies at the slimy wogs and trip them up with their own clogs we’ll twist their ears and break their glasses stick their tulips up their arses^foul their windmills with our bowels and vomit into their canals^K?DANES the Danes we’ll bash their brains and wire their willies to the mains boycott their bacon and their prawns and go and piss over their lawns the scabby Scandin­ avian scum got scrotal scabies of the bum thevhve on fish heads and weak tea their lager tastes like canine pee mcSWISS the Swiss they stink of piss no race more tedious than this with cuckoo clocks and huge amounts of money in their bank accounts they may be rich but we don’t care we’ll shave off all their pubic hair and make therp live in Belgium - that’s the right place for the boring prats •SreFRENCH the French they smell like tench we’ll chase them all into a trench get loads of garlic on our breath and suffocate them all to death we don’t like onions snails or Proust so smeg off Frogs we rule the roost you,may be existentialists but we’re dead hard and we get pissed ukTCZECHS the Czechs they’re scared of sex they’ve all got crabs and skinny necks their cars are shit their beer’s too strong we’re not gonna stay there for long there’s absolutely zilch to do there’s no Black Label and no glue so we’ll just wrepk the place and go and leave them to their queues and snow the FINNS the Finns live out of tins they all look like the Cocteau Twins their scenery’s not very nice ’cos most of it’s a mass of ice so don’t go there it’s much too chilly you’ll end up with a frozen willy it’s a godforsaken hole obscenely close to the north pole KRAUTS the Krauts they think they’re louts but I’ve seen nastier Brussels sprouts they strut around like football yobs but they’re all talk and cheesy knobs they live on pickled vegetation what a fucking stupid nation alltheir nipples are bright green the strangest folk I’ve ever seen me SWEDES the Swedes well they’re all weeds and all their cities look like Leeds they walk around with plastic bags and noses stuck in porno mags they live on fish just like the Danes but they’ve got even smaller brains their language sounds40Attila 38-47 18/9/92 12:46 am Page 40,
￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 12:51 am Page 4like double dutch their land smells like a llama’s crutch jbe GREEKS the Greeks those fucking geeks we’ll lock ’em up in bogs for weeks puke in their restaurants and bars and write rude slogans on their cars we’ll get a load of herpes scabs and stick ’em all in their kebabs, and write a note - in puke - to say ‘CLUB 18-30 RULE OK! POLES the Poles eat toilet rolls their underpants are full of holes they have to queue over an hour to get a mouldy cauliflower they whine and whinge and gripe and moan and play the hairy pink trombone thev’pe always wanking in the loo there’s fuck all else for them to do ffteYANKS the Yanks der, many thanks for -brmg--ing-ift-your bombs and tanks protecting us from Arab hordes and bringing herpes and skateboards you’re foreigners but you’re alright— lU W ’cos you speak English and you fight or so it tells me in THE SUN- ...Oi! Being a moron is such fun!
￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 12:52 am Page 42Four Song Lyrics1. The Pen and the Sword(for Salman Rushdie)You never thought that it would come to this they took your freedomnow they want your lifeHere’s to you in your distressPoet on the run to a safe addressMan of words in the shadow of the knifeYou told of life in an inhospitable land of a satiristand a city made of sandYou wrote it for your brothersand they burned it in the streetand the Union Jack said ‘send them back’ ...to make the irony completeA refugee from another century where the world is absoluteand words queue up to die— l/^^here the page is a flameand the truth has a single name— jwhere womanhood is crushed to the sound of an anguished cryThey say the pen is mightier than the sword The poet will never call the tyrant lordBut when the sword is raised what can you do when all you’ve got is a penand they’re coming after you...?When they were brownshirtsthey were soon abusedBut a new disguise leaves some people confused But if we won’t stand up and be counted -well, it happened once before__ Remember Pastor Niem'oller as you hide behind the door42
￼Attila i8-47 18/9/92 12:54 am Page 43,A refugee from another century where the world is absoluteand words queue up to diel/^ where the page is a flameand the truth has a single namel/J .where womanhood is crushed to the sound of an anguished cry to the sound of an anguished cryin the name of an ancient lie...You never thought that it would come to this they took your freedomnow they want your life■H there’s to you in your distressf ,poet on the run to a safe addressH pian of words in the shadow of the knife43
￼e2. This Is Free EuropeDead of night in Carpentrasbrings the ghosts from the days of Vichy Broken windows in the high street Swastikas in the cemeteryBlond young men on a Rostock evening Beer and loathing on their breathTen to one like their cowardly fathers Arms outstretched in the sign of deathCHORUSIf it takes a voice then shout the truthIf it takes a hand then hold them backIf it takes a fist then strike them downFrom Cable Street to I-IoyerswerdaPamyat, Schonhuber and Le Pen -THIS IS FREE EUROPE...NEVER AGAIN!Afternoon in a Soviet cityNow they don’t even need to hideBlue shirted thugs advertise their pogroms None are arrested, none are tried‘Pamyat’ means ‘a memory’ -What memories for these Russian Nazis? Children killed in front of their mothers Human skin turned into lampshadesCHORUSOnce more we see the darkness in the European soul As the chains fall there comes an awful beastHis eyes are staring, and there is hell upon his brow - Oscar, Francois, Gregor, Tanya listen to me now... I’m a Jew in CarpentrasI’m a Jew in that Soviet cityI’m an Asian in the East EndI’m a Cuban in East Germany Don’t tell me it doesn’t concern us It’s not something to ignoreThey are feeding on our apathy - That’s how it began before...Actila 38-47 18/9/92 12:54 am Page 44cMLus44
￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 1:04 am Page 45This is for Jorg Wolter and all my friends in East Germany^t>0>3. Market Sector One (Summer 1990)Another new year and too much beer and goodbye to the Wall But now there’s only disappointment, nothing left at allThe dreams we marched and fought for have faded and turned sour The cabbage is a king now,* it’s Helmut’s finest hourand on the streets the people want it ‘as seen on TV’ and a big bunch of bananas is a sign that you are free It’s just begun -Market Sector OneAs in the East they talk about a future bold and newa thousand Western businessmen are celebrating too ~T/the vultures are all circling ’cos there’s money to be madea multinational carve - up, a bank to be obeyed/\ /tfnd now the old, rich foreigners make claims on every hand'i ^you’re living in my house, mein Herr, you’re farming on my land’ It’s time to run -Market Sector OneIs that all that we were fighting for? Landlords and sex shops, nothing more? Welcome to the Western dream Welcome to the cheap labour schemeThe whole of Europe’s changing - Big Brother’s on the run It could just be a brand new age of freedom has begunBut freedom doesn’t bow its head to some financier’s will And Europe is our common home - not some gigantic till So send the moneygrabbers riding off into the sunAnd take your assets in your own hands, answerable to none Then we’ll have funAnd justice will be done...* ‘Kohl’ is German for ‘cabbage’45&
￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 12:54 am Page 46,—— —4. Tyler Smiles422/urmti)( IS'joJ)Here’s to you, the sceptic fewin the dark old days of ’82when a thousand corpses stoked an awful pyreHere’s to ’84 and ’5when all our dreams took another divemidst the jeers of Mammon and the howls of the Digger’s choir There were times I really thoughtthey’d all been conned and all been bought-d.G>&V -—(jasV ^) - I t—/T>oo much Chingford on the brain and never going to think againj? /but it’s a taxing time for Essex now...And Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson an angry crowd stretching miles and miles^ix hundred years but the lesson wasn’t learned And Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesthrough a hail of bricks and stones and tilesafow history rolls back, the worm has turned, retribution earned.Tell me why it took so longall these years we’ve sung this songand will the spectre ever go away?A hundred thousand garden gnomes outside a hundred thousand homes areCfctanding on their own two feel®today No strident tones now, just a whinea hand-picked bank clerk holds the line The same song with a few new chordsfor Albion’s user-friendly hordesA thornless rose is bending in the breezeAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesthrough the acid rain and the sheepdog trials P perhaps he never really went awayAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson the village greens and the seven dials - there’s still a bit of fight in us today! Tyler smiles.46
￼Attila 38-47 18/9/92 1:01 am Page 47And if it’s really over, and the swords turn into ploughshares She’ll go to Eastern Europe, oh they really love her there The fool Walesa and the iron curseAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smilesas Labour’s leaders close their fileson ‘Wat’s his name’ from their own historyAnd Tyler smiles, Tyler smileson that angry crowd stretching miles and miles - ‘Hey - Gotcha, lady! Gotcha, finally...’Tyler smiles.Written a few days after the fa ll o f Margaret ThatcherTHE NEIGHBOURS RETURNEO HIS LRWNMOWER WITH BITS OF DAMP GRASS STUCK TOTHE INSIDEOF THE BLADES .THEY PUSHED HIM TOO FAR. NOW HE'S OUT FOR REVENGE, HE'S A ONE MANARMY ANDTHISTIMEIT’SREALLYPERSONAL,ETC. FROM THE HAVERS OF XIWTA TRAIUSpflTTERS..• •47-e-T