￼A Reader’s NoteCall him anything, call him Jim . At any road a Scottish male of a certain agestands hopeful, hesitating, lost.He scuffs the dust, unable to go on or back.I want to see him on the rack.Compressed or stretched, the heresies will show. And mock him carefully, you who goto govern or deplore, judgingor not judging, in all events undone.The riders of our times left notes behindof intrigues high and low; one sings of love, another of the shredding of a document...He scans these tales of power - screwed up, corrupt, infolded, though I would not have it so.bc>V6 v.ttV-&s
￼MazedIt was the things the women saidfair mazed our Jim ; contrary shockscrazed him as they do with rats.First they taught him sensitivity, to choponions very fine and cry, prioritisethe lady of his life. He got the knack.Applause! Then she whose absence still definesthese screwey situations, left to flame itwith his pal Bill. Live for friends, get in touchwith your distress. But soon enoughhis distresses got in touch with him -a right good kicking filled him in.His bruises were stupendous; in diverse bedshe was rewarded, sundry titbits showered on him.Then Jenny came from Aberdeen to sayEnough. Binge-time is over, the cheese is moved. Work, discipline, avoiding dread diseaseswill be the key-notes o f the 90s. Without political understanding thereisonlypain- gosniffitout.Certitude of the educators, high groundof the women, tests of the high heid yins! Quivering, ardent - a rapier, a whippet,as easily broken - she raps him on the chest: Nowyou mustforgetyourfeelings.Sod this for a game of mazes. He resigns.On his back for days, pinky feet in the air.What you doing, Jim? Minding the ceiling, and its bars...
￼ShetlandHe sailed for Shetland, very near the edge, to bog & cliff & a celibate friend.She did her helpless best by him.He climbed all day and failed to fall.Light-hoarding stars above her bed,a full moon on the wall - he wanted to be dead, and badly. A mortal sin, she said, I tried it.Well, she was Catholic but that stuck.No way out but up. At the c r u ^he clutched into the chimney’s heart an eaved...He taped his knuckles, she poured the wine.Only reflected light this tenderness, but stillthat night they lay like pardoned thieves - baffled, eased, beside her moon, beneath her paper stars.24
￼About TessShe cocks her head, considersanother country, you. Smoke infiltrates your throat. The rasp that says you’re not dead yetis the trigger of seductions.‘And do you eveil^she enquires,‘act on your irresolution?’The bar’s de-stabilised, you colonize each other as folkies sing of Nicaragua.‘All right,’ one hand on hers, the other grips your car keys, ‘Why not?’There are reasons, but they melt like wax.Relax. Tonight you cross the border.You cast huge shadows as you get into the car.
￼Tess, in TunisiaReleased,she tilts over on her side.‘The Fall is only that,’ she says shaking sand from her hair, ‘when yoiAvish returnsto Paradise. Go on, forget her.’She says we are inventingnew ways of shipping men and women and all her art is aiming fora raft that swimmers reach and share.She says this that it may be so.You did not worry as you laybeached together through a starless night; an obscured moon still pulls the tidesof billow-talk and pillow-friends.These words comefrom Proverbs, Tess, and the Koran; dogs bark above our heads and yet the caravan moves on.
￼Love-Torn Squaddie in Rannoch TormentBeing, show me your ground.Only the moor and a keepof castellated cloud and the wind moving on as she did, snagged enough to make roots whinelike children left behind.He waits for his heart to stop but it won’t.That’s all the ground there is, soldier, it’s all ground, even the airy-fairy cloud-castle on the hill, eventhe shrilling in your chest.Being torn between moving on and being left behind, he wavers shredded among heather.