￼But, of course, not all rappers conform to this crude stereotype! MC Trainspotter, the world's first rapping trainspotter, certainly doesn't....He knows you don't have to be really tough and live somewhere dangerous and have a gun and a big penis to be a rapper!BOYS IN THE HOOD (Trainspotter Rap)MC Trainspotter, yeah, that's me- and this is my homeboy,Nice-T!Now some people think that trainspotting's rot.... but me and ray posse, we sayIT'S NOT!All you need is a camera, notebook and penyou write down a number, then you write one down again We're ignored by the nation, we go down the stationand we've got another hobby -masturbationhey, don't walk away, 'cos I'm talking to youyou know what they call us -Tire Platform 2 Live Crew!Now me & my homeboys work inand at the weekendwe go to the libraryon Saturday roomings we likeand then we go.amateur league groundhopp§ing ^I nearly caught pneumonia at Billingham SynthoniaWanna know the layout of the ground? *I'll phone ya!And at half time I've got everything I needa nice telephone directoryto readMC Trainspotter in the houseI've got the suss, and I've got the nous^I don't live in a ghetto like those rappers in the States I like the policeyes, they're my best mates...I've never been arrested(that goes without saying)I've reported lots of people I've seentravelling without payingand here's what I say to every other rapping crew - well, I'm OK at rappingbut I'rn not as good as you!But I do thinkyou spend far too much on your gearI could save you some moneyso please listen here:My trainers are from Qxfam and they cost 50p>My anorak's ray mum's and the carrier bag was free!I wouldn't like a gold chain - somebody might mug me and I don't want a baseball cap - they really bug me!a bankshopping
￼Me and rny posse we're the 'boys in the hood' and it keeps out the rain - now isn't that good? and if you want informationdown at the stationjust ask me, it'll fill me with elation!MC Trainspotter - yeah, that's meYo i there, horneboy!Want a cup of tea?
￼For Clive Ponting, Sarah Tisdall, and all those who follow in their footsteps....RAPPING MOLEI'm Rapping Mole from Leahy Hole, who I am you'll never guess -Got a secret code on an angry road to an underground addressI'm a real cool cat with a photostat of a secret documentAnd when I leak it brings a shriek from government!Cos I'm Rapping Mole from Leaky Hole and I'm driving the politicians up the poleBelgrano or the missile bases, Ministers all get red facesAt my desk behind the scenes, I bin the lies and spill the beansWith a rap rap rap I cut the crap and tell my tales to magazines!Kim Philby was my hero - he showed me how it's doneAnd Tony Blunt's a clever bloke - he really had some funUs funky moles get everywhere - this cat can surely rock it AndI'vegotrqyfunkyblackmailcheque right here in my back pocketMy eyes are sharp, ray member huge - I'm the hip- hop priest of subterfuge fThis mole's got soul, he knows his role - this mole's got style, he make^you smileolaeuik&dThe Sieve-all Service is named well - it's like a sieve, it leaks like hellso bang bang bang come join the gang, let's freak and leak and do our thang!lA /\ oDon't worry Mr. Minister - don't freak and make a fussJust leave your file with a happy smile - your secret's safe with usOh, naughty Mr. Minister - this cover-up won't do Your wife, mistress and hamster would all be ashamed of youSo while you sleep I creep, creep, creep to a photostat machineand soon your lies are on their way to a left- wing magazinerfW
￼and then the feline is among the pigeons, that's for sure -your secret's out, so scream and shout, you bottom-faced old bore....'Cos I'm Rapping Mole from Leaky Hole and I'm driving the politicians up the poleGot a secret code on an angry road - gonna spill the beans and shoot my load!I'm a real cool cat with a photostat - I'm a fruit bat wombat acrobat!And when I leak the pinstripes freak so watch out, geek, your future's bleak!Said 1,2,1,2,3 - spying for the CND!4,5,4,5,6 - we know all of Whitehall's tricks! 7,8,7,8,9 - spill the beans and watch 'em whine! 9,10,9,10,11 - all good rappers go to heaven!Got soul, little doll, I know my role, I'm top of the poll - I'm RAPPING MOLE!
￼GydW -uOv &a1/'^ P ^ H-jl_r,_r-,-iv.c. -,-,-,~i !,:^i|-,n^t Park Mix? 1 K ft*** nzvzLu^ti^'j a/Ve^JLi,with absolutely no apoTogies lo Paul Hardcastle's appalling 1980s disco hit 'N-n-n-nineteen'Tuesday September 12 1989 began like any other day in the footballing calendar, with newly- discovered Team of the 80s, Crystal Palace, travelling to Anfield to test their Colditz-like defensive qualities and mesmerising attacking skills against the sacrificial learnings of Liverpool. Now football is a funny game, as the uterly retarded cliche goes, and on this particular evening it proved to be a very funny game indeed, in fact a positively hilarious and side-splittingly humourous one, even more mirth- inducing than Princess Diana trying to define existentialism or William Waldegrave having sex with a paper-shredding machine. For while Palace's much-feared rivals Brighton & Hove Albion were slaughtering Wolverhampton Wanderers 4-2, at Anfield the final score was Liverpool 9, Crystal Palace 0. Liverpool 9, Crystal Palace nil. N-n-n-nine nil, nine nil. N-n-n-nine nil, nine nil. And following those fateful n-n-n- ninety minutes on that hilarious Tuesday night the hapless halibuts from Selhurst Park were subjected to fierce and merciless ridicule from the rest of the football world and many of them are still living out their experiences to this day. Even now the South London branch of the Samaritans are receiving streams of mysterious phone calls where the only audible sounds are donkey-like voices braying bewilderedly 'Nine- nil. N-n-n-nine nil. Ee-aw! Nine nil. N-n-n-nine nil. Ee-aw!' And when the Palace players got home, obviously in need of moral support and counselling following their torrid n-n-n-nine nil experience, none of them received a hero's welcome. None of them. None of them received a hero's welcome. N-n-n-none of them. The long-term effects of such an unbelievable n-n-n-ninenil stonking are hard to predict, but it seems likely that many of the Crystal Palace squad may be so demoralised that they may be forced to leave professional football and sign on. S-s-s- sign on. Sign on. S-s-s-sign on. S-s-s-sign on, sign on. S-s-s-sign on, sign on. A worse fate even than this may well befall the Palace goalkeeper Perry Suckling, a man who, rather like the Queen Mother, wears gloves for no apparent reason, for his intense feelings of humiliationl4JfA. ■*P^a<'Lj-(J'rf'/b-ftf/utee,
￼may well lead him to sign on in Vietnam. V-v-v- Vietnam. S-s-s-sign on. V-v-v-Vietnam. S-s-s- sign on. V-v-v-Vietnam. S-s-s-sign on (repeat ad nauseam)