￼( It)ol-J•"cuIJ, CfiArf^U, Scrrict.**4± .Su.nj %7* £< u/t. /tv-^. Ax ^/?oca •I5-T it* *CJVKlcZi/cj ♦ Ltsr^£ TU l/ii. f" 'y< frt.hS'tl•A^_f^7 /•*<J Oii/lUrjly)-^- ’Vr^t^yjr^ f ytt* (k*iljX // £VZ»wA) ,>£ /\r^jl'-^\ ’ X ,£K ,$X /y A/p/- •AT /$*7^ //j^S (Vt^r l/J./<«*•Vr /J bt*>\J.or^ / ^/<//rwC^vfotf^ fvhCtnij Lk*Ly^i0 ^^ • 2«> Uj/- l/xAiss/i't/j *.i/•%\A^V'2j
￼The Way of EddiePurity comes easier to the devil, Eddie You're the patron saint of Nervous Wrecks, you're the Godfather of pervert sex& cheap pornographySo what's brought this sudden uplift, Eddie,this space face & feeling of supreme well-being? Are you laced up with Cough Mixture again?Is this some new Designer Natural High?& what's all this balls & baloney, Eddieabout Karma & the river's eternal flow?D'ye take me for a complete Buck Ejit?So now you're in tune with the infinite,in rhythm, Ed, with your aura & the spheres'& every blade of Shitgrass is fantastic, looks so majestic' i hear you pray,'all moves with sychronicity & is divine, see the bees guzzling down their pollen& the bush in its joyous blossom'Sure you don't know the trees names', Eddie &birds to you are just cartoon furry friends. Where's your Observer book of plants, Eddie? What's this flower called then, eh?Christ! You're sin advert for Lobotomy, Eddie & ok the Way of Zen is an honourable path but not for the like of youwith your liquid lunches & yellow toungeyou can't stand upright on this lino, Eddie, never mind walk steadfast on the astral plane, You can't negotiate the corner shop, Eddie’let alonei*suffering of the Holy Grail.You're about as mystical as a cabbage, Eddie as enlightened as a dollop of cementEverytime i clock you, Eddiei think,'how profoundly sad ah such fodder for my tears'.’'there's poor Eddie'i thinkdoesn't he strive & try hardbut with his face like Circusboy, old twister, he's away with the mixerpoor Eddie's lights are always onbut there's never anyone in.................,P\/£. f-Ooif^PoCSI^J
￼Meter ReadingsEddie, if you have the fearor a doze of the noiaor the crawling heebie-geebies don't blame metrace back in the infantrycount them all, Eddiethose you've slept with ,/ since 1973every blow-outevery quick blow-job, Eddieit's time to have them analysedsuddenly there is bad blood between us& when you kissedMiranda Churchill Londerry Smith in the bog endof the bike shelterdid you have a mouth ulcer?have you slipped the hand hound something rotten once too oftenhave you finally disposed of tenderness? will there be true romance leftwhen you live in spooky quarantine?,have you any wits in storeto have about you, Eddiewhen the radio spells it out & you contort your furry faceWELCOME PEOLE TO THE FINISHING POST PEOPLE OF THE HUMAN RACE..............
￼Prayer for the barely standingsuch a hideoas waste, Eddieyour illegal smile wearing thin ashtrays & hubbly-bubbly pipes haunting the smell of your deathbed when you end up wired up to machinestubes up your nose, Eddiethat'll spoil your cute kisser charts & graphs on downward slopes & your pickled lungs held aloftas reminders to the lily-whitesthe Big C, Eddie, discuss.& your liver will be shredded too cancelling all its devilry outin a whirling drvish.of Special Brew& you were never really at the ballgame out to lunch you were never there climbing the ornate wallhangingsstill comotose in your chair& on the barstool you preach on, Eddie many wee blighters called tumourshave sprouted as you've speeledso keep on playing the wurlitzer, Eddie sing along with all the loony tunestalk more gibberish to the opticscos just for now your song plays onas the old ticker disintegrates& the scratchy needle scrapes .across the plastic of your hoursso you've learnt a few new songs, Eddie?'” very good, how about a few?how about 'ONE DAY AT A TIMEg, SWEET JESUS THat's ALL I'M ASKING OF YOU'...............
￼Return of Sensitive Eddiewelcome back from the health farm, Eddie you're looking well, are you sick?after all that fresh air &herb tealay off the auld Clandew, Eddielay off the auld Scotsmacor next month you'll just be back propping up the wine bar alterrambling & gambling & shambling, Eddie your crooked wee eyes cockedat any tight skirt in sightwas not meditation blissful, Eddie? was not brown rice beneficial?so don't end up back in bedlum, Ed up to your oxters in shiteno more wacky backy, stay steady, Eddie keep your zipper in it's clipperno more pervy polarmids eitheror horsing back the jungle juicethat sends you, Ed, all of a ditherSOBER SOBRIETYthere, i've said it, Eddie now that was fairly painlessnot a bit of wonder, Eddieas in the good old fruity daysJour covering your ears with your paws & sprawling about on the stormy seaof your bed-settee-put-me-uplike Caligula on a bad day, Eddiei hate to see you suffer like this, Ed, here, have a blast of this...*.*.I
￼Coke, but no Sympathyimpressed Eddie? y<xsfd . how could i fail not to be? top salesman of the yearagain & again infinitumwhat delectable picturesin all those luscious brochuresbut i just can't help from mentionin' Edders, old flying kite,for a high power tychoonyou do a fierce ammount of snifflingwhat's with all the paper hankies? & the dribblin' snotall down your Filofax?am i supposed to be impressed when this immodesty hurts me so? all this fastspeak & speedabout Time Share Apartmentsetc etc etc etc& i know if you really tried, Eddie you'd sell sand back to the desertbut you've had your expensive breakfast off the mirror again, haven't youEddie Murdoch?& in all this canned laughter ,your mail order voice attacks methis canned laughter is deafening so reach for the blade, Eddiefor the rolled up 5 quid noteup your nose, up your nose, Eddie that's where all the money goes..*..
￼Pooh-^oohsure we should have known you'd be out of your dome on solvents, Eddie, glueis there no noble causes left to catch a feeble grip of?lighter fuel won't make you cool if you igniteits gentle barbarismwill trail you offstage early blithering & babbling& Evostick just drives you screwy, Ed fierce stuff altogether the auld glueyou'll wander through this riot footage, Eddie like a headless horse in a cartoonlik e the legendary Mr Magooyou'll glide blithely through Jhe murders through the gutted polling booths& when it all goes dangerously askew amid the sizzling barricadesin the heavt trucheon chargethere will only be hypermarkets, Eddie belonging to zipperheads & sharks& you'll end up hyperventilatingliving in the doorway of Marks & Sparks&your face will stick to lamp-posts, Eddie it's sticky gunge of tearscome out of this lustrelet me soothe your crazy fearsJUST SAY NO & crawl back to bed , why not wait for the state, Eddieto kill you off instead.*....,
￼Lounge Lizards0k Eddie if you really insisther name, my little milksop,is Felicity Montague Python Smith daughter to the wayward daughter of the country squire& i can't for the meagre life of mefor the meat, the murder or the life of me work out what she's doing here!this is Slumsville Ed, the pits& his nibs in the manor would do his nut if he saw her here scooping pints down or firing back wee onesamid these plastic flowersSTAY BACK, EDDIEDown sniffer, down!you horny wee gett, Eddie quit gawkingit would serve you right, Eddieif she hit you a smack in the bake stop cruisin' the distant highway of her ragged crimson hairstop tracing her shape in the airshe's out of your league, Eddiethe Python Smith's have servantswho have servants themselves, so there she's not in your league, Edwardwhich looking at your bellyas you burp & inflate yourself|s the 4th division, Eddiesomewhere near the bottom end...*