￼VShe thinks she can crack admittance Through my glacial film.She thinks nothing moves in me But senility.But my eyes slitherTo take inThat she herself is not young Or pretty.She sees something in me.I see her children.Little girls in petals.I slip them onto my knee.That’s all I need of Kate Greenaway.All the words and sounds ever uttered, all and flame, or crystal, are utterly powei you, in the smallest point, what love m mirror can.Omvt. Pussy in the WellThis creature yawns^rfnd invites me To putmy head jn its mouth.Looking dowi ( its throat I see A nether world, another world.delations of cloud They cannot tell Only the broken4 \kRandall 37-end 20/3/93 12:23 am Page 4 Kate GreenawayDrink of yourself.60
￼Randall 37-end 20/3/93 12:23 am Page 4tIts fertile walls hold favours, They are soft and green and \y£t.The kiss is deepThere’s something in the ttfater.Pulls,Deeper than the man, i The boy,Deeper than the boy^ The baby,Deeper than the l/aby, Liquor...O r\ \*And very sooiy you’re through the mirror,Through tha/sucking woundTo darknesClosing oil that baby, boy and man.There’y something in the water Pulls,;ind,you are out.-e-The Ice HouseDark ages wear white eyes,I want herWho disturbed me like ice and fire.A roundhouse surrounds a sad spell. The sorrow is palpable,It freezes doves in their tracks.This was our dovecote,A keep for the parts of us too tender To venture in the world.61
￼Randall 37-end 20/3/93 12:23 am PageI stand at the centreAs the drum revolvesHer song from the heart’s chamber.We were born dead.To mine the ice from our eyes.TurneresqueThrow open all the windows then Where genius painted glassAnd mortals may walk through Without receivingA shard to the heart.The dainty white glove Has arrested the organ And doves dip their wings Strike out at canvass.Down fuels usAnd then the angels Who touch men Make them mad.Or yearn for the moment Between contractionAnd expulsionWhen the feathers weep.Drop beauty on the cataract Restore vision soThe eye shallMove the heart.62
￼Randall 37-end 20/3/93 12:23 am Page 0- You Do Not Know My LifeThe abomination is, to have made this woman from her image. How my eyes herded her three times a week for years.For years she brought my watercress and lettersAnd only here and now I ponderBecause the snow has pinched her tattered cheeks And sucked the ancient blood she neededTo get her up the lane in winter,How she had to tread cut glass to water,Spoke to me from duty, never pleasure.Here is the old woman who brings my watercress and letters Three times a week, three miles through sun or snow Invisible and unremarked for years.The shepherdess, her lambs long gone for slaughter. No complaint on her cracked lips which are a wound Wearing salt, the things she could say and doesn’t.My salads sprout out of her fist and she transfers them Tenderly,She struggles home in sackcloth,I watch her crook the snow by the neck, unpile it From her path.And then I don’t think of her again.But she brought to mind a waterfall once seen Falling upwards by force of unnatural weather. It peeled off in violent geysers of rainbow hue Defying every assumption of how, and where, Water should fall.SnowdropHe sentencedaiie to be a man. I searchejHor a manBut ferfind a flower.63R e *-o rvYY e n
￼Randall 37-end 20/3/93 12:23 am PageHe wanted me to be a boy. I wanted to be a girl.He made my life a misery UntilI acquired genius beyond gender.But I wanted him dead./I wanted him plantedJm the ground.I was innocent.Now I am old.Now I am innocent again.And he is planted in the ground Like a flower.I pardo/l him.He pardons me with a drop of snow.Harknow3 Uwns a girl and a flower^ doesn’t matter.e nVIV- A.o-eSnVBitler RedThe decades steep in red. Icicles bleed.The garden waits After the eviction.Stalactite meets stalagmite While waiting.Time has no saviour. The garden gives over.64G-fonl «>r-r 'VV-e r> •doe-snVor