￼Garrett 29/7/91 10:02 am Page 17Pont Au Change: Two ViewsUnder the bridge or overWe are many maters, one river; Over the bridge or under, Many currencies, one money.And she: explaining in her cleanFrench, in a creaking room of the musee Carnavalet, that in those daysThere were two currencies: one for ParisAnd another for France (which is to sayNot Paris) and these two were exchanged Under this table on that bridge over the filthy Seine - which one could see had not changed...And I: grappling with rates of conversion In broken English, picture the bridgeAt Naunton, sucking this smoothGift of green and gold into its mouth, And the slipping sky, to spew it back Out the other side in rucked blackAnd silver - consider this a fair Exchange, but hardly the same river.e/17