￼h e thing that worries me about T the kind of people to whomTHE EUMENIDESthe really terrible, o-so-shuddering things happen, likegetting electrocuted in the bath or haplessly plummeting off an Atlantic cliff(reaching right over for the lastblackberry)four hundred feet falling falling onto spiny uprushing rocks- or having one’s child raped and murdered in a wood,isthat in their firm-built houses theyspent similarly pleasant dullish evenings reading aboutthe kind of people to whomthe really terrible things happen,likceancer of the bowels,a sliced off face in a machine,finding one’s child raped and slaughtered in a wood.27 /
￼From Sonoran PoemsI descend I enter youa diplomat sick of negotiations choosing to be hijackedby a blue stewardesswith a gun instead of champagnein the midst of a ghost-town in the midst of a desertto restto forget time and the six directions to be forgottenLike a kachina-maskyou wear your beauty like a kachina-maskyour beautythe minute you are gone desert rainredmariposa lilies astonished mariposa liliesFrom desert scrub the lord’s candles glimmer a wind shivers and I am changedwithout knowing it yet without holding it yet mistaking it for joyI become goodI become loyal to myself
￼moment by moment new stars madeO Mother of TonantsinO Our Lady of GuadalupeThe bulb-light flickers figures are there searching combing the ghost-townYou stand with blue lips back to the dooralien and fanatic covering meBut how can love recedebut how can love recedethose slit domesthrough which the night keeps pouringIt is my kachina-maskit is my kachina-maskinstead of patched jeansyou come to me dressedas the traditional spyand seducer quelling your nature it is my birthday you saylong black gloves garterbelt and stockings tense as a strung bow
￼I fuck it as I pretend it is you I fuckit is the fetish I fuck it is the godthe mountain around which everything moves it is hereand here and herein these fulcra of greatest anguishI adore the oppugnant stressesagent and double agent and triple agentwearing my kachina-mask I will betray anything wearing my kachina-maskYouthe songbring a smile to my lips I cannot silenceMuse you are deadwhy do you walk along my dreamsmy dry veinshunting your murdered childrenand wailing and scratching huge rentsin the backs of lost travellerslike the ghost-woman of the sandflats of the Santa CruzI am tired of facesthat shine next to me as close
￼as a filling station the other side a motorway softly shiningat nightLet the downpour be storedMy soul is very lonelyblind he has touched your face he sends me to be a go-between to beg you to comebring a flower of the saguaro cactus to cure my friendThe Indian cemetery at Xan Xavier square and facing easttheir white and nameless crossesyour hand gently enchaining meand your eyes with love releasing meit is not of death I thinkon this happy daybut as if the whole universe moves towards the eastr25
￼Your hairblack, black as the dead, wrong side of the moon,comet tresses,if my lips dare probe them, electrically alive as a storm of meteors, and as mortal to my peace of mind,elipsed by darkness, the whites of your eyes gleam at me like the coronae of a binary eclipse,the cold, still chastity of your thighs where my teeth wander is the Milky Way, galactic whirlpool and forgewhich comes to us as cold, still, chaste light;the constellations crazy,their patterns haywire;in the space of a weekyou have flared from nothing into a supernova.
￼I watch you, glacial in mink, enter on the arm of your husband, imperious through the sighsof your fans, the autographs. Haughty, you take your seat; your arm shrinks from his hand;I whisper into your ear,I am still crazy for you.He is still crazy for you.He watches you, late, uncombed, with lateness on your mindstraight from your doctor’s room, enter the cinema’s darkafternoon, sit straight by him. Neither yet flickers a sign.You brush your hair from your eyes.Mink is as tender as steel in alphaville.Hair is as molten as steel in alphaville.He watches you watching the screen W ith never a glance at him.He watches him loving you,je t’aime je t’aime je t’aimehe whispers, now as then.He is still crazy for you.Your hands touch on the sheet, like pack-ice, split again.Days are as cool as steel in alphaville.Love is a cutting-room, all images equally true,I mix them all up in you, au revoir becomes je t’aime in the crystal at your ear, as I direct your handto stretch for husband, lover; the camera is crazy for you.A film can be cut like steel in alphaville.
￼Your hands in the pit of your back, steel grapples to eyes of steel; your breasts on hoardings star; swiftly you brush your hair;your husband is crazy for you.Our son must be fetched from school. Blinds of the late afternoonare falling one by one.Light opens on the steel evening of alphaville.You are the bathroom-scale’sbland mutability;the steel tape whips aroundyour breasts, your waist, your thighs, imexorably as lovers;the tape is crazy for you, erecting your rasped nipples; it hugs you into despair.You ghost into the steel slimlines of alphaville.When, next autumn, next spring, the houselights go down on this film, who will be crazy for you, whisperingjet'aime je t’aime?I whisper this in your ear:stretch out your hand to him,but remember our mountain-cabin; preserve it in snow of your tear;converse on what is real in alphaville.You are light falling on breasts, you are a stocking’s stretch, you are the heel of a shoe,you are a brush through hair, you are a collar turned up,you are the leaves you crunch, you are the wheel of a car, life is in love with you;you are the sad, steel thrill that steals through alphaville.
￼'> ’ ' 'V ' V.*, ,v,;. ■ -S-.-.V•■wwwr