￼Below the SurfaceThis is reparation for something imperfectly remembered, but rooted here. The lolling willows,the silver shadows, all formed a part of it.I look up. The water boatmen scurry round the lilies.There is the meniscus, echoing the curve of the eyeball; also the curve to the horizon.Under my back, the river gravel, my bed and board and shelf life; and here am I, victimof my average weekly yearnings, so peaceful now as all the curves darken, one by one, in harmony.68
￼CENTRAL RESERVATIONS
￼DAILY ROUND
￼Clay PipesHere is the box with the pieces of clay pipe, stems like twigs, bowls swagged and ribbed, all cracked and chipped; but neatly docketed in your schoolboy hand.They were difficult to spot on the river bank amongst the pebbles. We spent hoursbent over like ancients, quartering the ground (you in your first adolescence, me in my second).The Thames mud smelled of beer from the brewery; fishermen stood peacefully in their waders,while we scrunched and scraped and pouncedwith nervous absorption.When two pieces jigsawed together you gave your special, satisfied frown.AddictionsW e’re all hooked on something: gold or pinchbeck;solitude; a particular pain,the soft optionor something harder.Kick one habit and,as you stand quietly at the window, another will dust down that empty chair and settle in.72
￼BedIn this store window, a vast bed,radiant white in satin, lace and crystals, embowered, flounced and veiled: a Swan Lake — an iced cake of a bed; unsullied, intacta.It knows nothing of body fluids, amorous heats, night sweats, births-, couplings, dyings -such leaky businesses.By this bed, a lover would kneel, slender as a freesia, his samite cuff trailing the floor. Could you relish so immaculate a conception?Central ReservationsI’ve just been taught another damn lesson. Is there no end to them?It’s still all life tests,crossroad decisions, multiple choices.Even last words may be subject to assessment: but do we have faith in the examiner?As I ponder this, a voice issuesfrom clouds looming above the window:Trust me, it booms, we know what I am doing.73
￼August in the OfficesThe small divorces of the summer offices relieve the year, let in the air.Absentees sun themselves by succulent hedgerows or sit in rain-soaked reveries on river banks -but their desks gather accretions; the names on their doors have a distant, commemorative look.Territories suffer encroachment, feuds and flirtations lose their fine balance; but in September -the canvas shoes flung to the back of the cupboard - flocks of fresh memos gather for the winter.The ClaimantThere’s no reasoning with gloom:it breaks out from below the pavementinto your head, into the corners of the room.Supposing you trace its lineage. What’s the point? Name it; it merely answersYou 're the one I want.74
￼One’s CorrespondenceI wrote to you to say that I’d be there but lost the letter giving your address and now I cannot find it anywhere.Although I’ve searched until I’m in despair, what’s worrying me most is, I confess,I wrote to you to say that I’d be there.It came first thing on Tuesday (to be fair the breakfast table was in quite a mess) and now I cannot find it anywhere.I think you said you lived in Berkeley Square or did you say you’d moved to Inverness?I wrote to you to say that I’d be there.Where parties are concerned, you have a flair. The letter said: ‘Please come in fancy dress,’ and now I cannot find it anywhere.I’m sure I wrote a note but couldn’t swear to posting it: this is an S.O.S. -I wrote to you to say that I’d be thereand now I cannot find it anywhere.
￼CompassionWaiting in the supermarket queue with my mange-tout and steak,I gazed abstractedlyat the shoes of the woman in front -plastic and misshapen, sticking plaster where one rubbed at the instep.In her basket (her hands grey and knucklv) some small bony meat.She look^ so illimitably patient and hopelessthat the easy tears blurred my eyes at the cash desk. But then I went home again,and I was so busy with my dinner party, you see.ConfessionOne day, she told a stranger on a train everything. After twenty yearsshe didn’t find it easy to begin,but then, encouraged by his faint, grey nods,she fitted words together:explanations, revelations, vindications -the relief was enormous.She touched her face with cambric, feeling shriven.At the next station he rose, creakingly, ‘So very' nice to chat with you, but I fear the conversation was a shade one-sided. This wretched deafness...’
￼Problem OneAfter a wedding, ten people stay the night in a house which has one W.C.At 9 a.m. the hostess administers 150 ml. tea to each person,and all sip at the rate of 50 ml. per minute.90% of the guests then fall to planninga furtive sortie to the W.C. - not wishing to attempt fur-tongued, half naked pleasantries en route.The protagonists crouch anxiously behind their door-jambs, like characters in an early French cine-melodrama,struggling to interpretthe creak of the floorboards, the click of a door-catch.Suddenly, a youth downstairs staggers from a sofa, pulls on jeans, plods up the stairs to the W.C.and locks himself in. He takes from his pocket a copy of Camus’ The Plague, and settles down for a good read.
￼Ladies at LunchDo you remember his hand was shaking like this? Mine too, Elena,but you were always p f brave.‘You first Maria,’ he said to me,and I held the needle over the flame.I don’t think we tried to sterilise the cork.What innocents we were. How deliciouslyhe shocked us: ‘Of course this is only a metaphor for sexual penetration.’He kept stroking the cat absent-mindedly and having to wash his hands all over again. I thought we’d be there all night.‘Let’s get on with it,’ I said,‘or my parents will be back.’I lay back in the chair and clamped my eyes shut.W hen 1 bled all over two linen napkins he went very white. He was much keener on sex than on ear piercingbut he hoped that one thing would lead to the other. Which in time it did,in that bed-sit of his - so bohemian,all lino and frayed edges.We were both foolish, Elena,but at least I didn’t let him marry me.78
￼Heaven on EarthThe loveliest times in all my lifemymothertoldme- neartheendofit-mere when I used to go to the Caledonian Market on Tuesday mornings. I remembered her coming home on those Tuesdays,ruffled, animated, as from an assignationor triumph. Once she brought back a clockwork canary in a wire cage which sang on two notes and gyrated like a tiny feather duster.W hen it dropped off its perchshe took it back to the stall quivering with delicious indignation and had it put miraculously right. In those days, she sighed,anything could be made better.MonochromeI want so much to find this empty room;the quiet light striking the bed into eminence against the shadowed walls.No view. No one calls.It is a retreat. Yet I would not pray therebut lie between cool sheetswatching the reflection of flowers,pale in their white jar.
￼DiversionsIn old age, confined to bed,my mother developed a keen obsession.Lorryjack-knifedontheM4, she would cry as you skirted the commode to greet her:They '11have to leave at Exit 2and go round here - she had a mapon her bedside table: her thin finger quivered.Our small talk, our flowers and chocolates washed up against a tideof burst water mains, spillages, contraflows. We nodded solemnly.She’d gained a nourishing rapportwith all the road junctions in the country.Areyou sorryyou never travelled?I asked her. She shook her headat my stupidity. Every day, every night, she travelled.80
￼Trouble AheadIn the taxi, in a sweating, staticjam, you check your watch again.Your train! You’re bound to miss it. And what about the strangerwho is meeting you? Troubled scenarios blossom and race through your head.Someone leans on his horn, and the hooting spreads, like an animal crythrough a herd. A bearded manstrides back angrily from some crisis point ahead. Christ, can’tyou wait afew minutes. Someone's dead.all fall silentbut it’s an exasperated silence. Death buggers up the traffic no end. People should die in bed.ChoiceYou’re the one I boned up mah jongg for You’re the one I bought the chaise longue for You’re the one I yearn to go wrong for.You’re the one I’ll garden my plot with You’re the one I’ll throwifin my lot with You’re the one I’ll find my G spot with.You’re the one I’ve had my teeth capped for You’re the one my scruples were scrapped for You’re the one I get all unwrapped for:You’re the one.
￼Don’t Look NowToday, I have been seeingstairparts. It is bestnot to look directlyat the heavy duty fixers,the two-gang pattresses (japannedand countersunk) or the sinisterly named door knob set with escutcheons.The togglers, with their rising buttsand easy-on hinges, were hanging around as usual, waiting for straight couplings and high performance cavity screws;but the white-faced hardboard lay motionless and epoxy: it wassashlocked to the roundheads.EntrailsI am cum ina'il that digestion is the great secret o f life -REV. SYDNEY SMITHTwenty-two feet of wondersTwenty-two feet of woes:Why we’re obliged to have so many yards of them Nobody really knows.Sometimes they lie retentive,Sometimes they’re wild and free,Sometimes they writhe and get madly expulsive The moment you’re out to tea.82
￼Entrails don’t care for travel,Entrails don’t care for stress:Entrails are better kept folded inside you For outside, they make a mess.Entrails put hara-kiriHigh on their list of hates:Also they loathe being spread on the carpet While someone haruspicates.Twenty-two feet of wondersTwenty-two feet of woes:Why we’re obligj/ied to have so many yards of them Nobody really knows.Moscow SpringIn the Kuskova gardens workmen lift the wooden boxes from the delicate statues.Tender bushes are unwrapped from their overcoats; twigs unbend in the melting light.The men warm to their work; hang their fur hatsin a row on the fence.r83
￼GamesA rat with his head in a tinenjoys low tide. The river has exposed its flanks of mud and shingle:tusks of wood at the water’s edgespeak of mammoths or great amphibians but here on the path we pick our waythrough artefacts - expanded polystyrene chunky as peppermint toffee; string elaborately knotted; an old baldbroom. Joggers thud past miming all degrees of anguish; but the gulls have landed in a drift on the waterand are rocking in a trance up and down, up and down, on the washfrom the pleasure steamer.84
￼FaidageryThree men in camel overcoats - coarse, moon-faced, slicked-back hair - are sitting in the front rowof an audience.They mutter to each other disapprovingly then rise, button their coatsand ostentatiously leave, saying:‘I can’t stand to see women committing Faidagery.’It’s not in the dictionary: I look for it when I wake up. But it might be in some arcane tome or medical compendium.One could be committing Faidagery in all innocence.there is always something you do which annoys somebody.m
￼Jessie’s BakeryThis shop, something o f a cult with local inhabitants for its delicious hot bread, was closed by the healthauthorities on thegrounds that theflour wasfull ofmoths.Blindfold, you could find it by the reekof stale cats. Big Jessie queens it here, her grey hair dollied up in yellow curls, six days a week.It takes her years to talk your loaf into a bag. The weather never tires of hearing about itself. Flour stirs and setdes; hours lag.In fact, time stops. Flies, as if in amber, stiffen in syrup tarts. Sultanas scabthe shelves; the customers half rememberthe world, in its complexity and pain; and, like the lotus eaters, grow averse to facing it again.86
￼Frank’s Journal, December 1878That morning, it was wonderfully cold. I put a bowl of water on the silland in an hour it froze. So far, so good.The dog-cart picked me up at half past eight, then we collected Willie, Jack and Fredand up we went to Earith. By the timewe started off for Welney, it was ten.My first long run on skates. They went ahead while I got in my stride with less despatch. My face ached from the wind: I had to rest by Bedford’s, but I soon warmed to my work and got to Welch’s Dam by halfpast twelve: the last six miles took only half an hour.The Welney skaters - fastest in the world -were marvellous to watch, and there were crowds to cheer them on. The low rays of the sunstruck sparks of fiery light from skates and ice.At the Blue Boar we ate a pigeon pieand, taking biscuits and a flask of tea,we turned for home again, against the wind.We ran eight miles and rested by the Dam, then down the counter wash, across the bank and round by Hundred Foot, where just before a lad had drowned (but no) one that we knew).We passed the Dinsdale boys on Bun' Fen... and after that I slowed, and lagged behind. My legs were made of lead, my hands of ice; the sun had disappeared, the sky was dark;I prayed for strength to make myself keep on.I can’t remember how 1reached my goalbut Lansdowne James was standing on the bank./87
￼He pulled me from the ice, but I could move no more: my skates were frozen to my feet completely, so he took me on his backand carried me to shelter. Such a day!I offered prayers of thanks, and was so bold as to petition that the ice should hold.WantsLike yours, my wants are simple: security with the window ajar,the battle without the spilt guts; the family to throw offand rediscover: a magical bed-postand Life Everlasting, with my own teeth.
￼THE STRONGER SEXf
￼The Badminton GameThat morning, I awoke and went downjust as I was, in my green slippers,to look at the hydrangea mariesii -the only flower Clifton allows in the garden, for he must have his trees and shrubs.Out I crept, my slippers darkening in the dew, and hearing a movement beside meI turned and found Ruth. She was carrying the racquets; and so - smiling, not speaking - we ran between the great bushes to the net,and there we played (quietly, of course,so that Uncle Edward might not hear)until the breakfast gong recalled us.We ran up the backstairs en deshabille,and down the front ones, tardy though decorous,and kissed Uncle Edward; but I took careto embrace him as he likes best, to forestall reproof. Colour rose up behind his moustache and his face worked silently, but then he vanished as usual, behind The Times.She’s Nothing But TroubleIf she smiles, don’t smile back.But of course you will, like an electrician taking chances with the wiringon a dull Tuesday afternoon.
￼Albert MemorialPassing the Albert MemorialI remember our night of love, so-called, which started with a concert, and went onto the expensive hotel where we ate our supper too much, too rich, too noisy -the violinist, with his pander leerfingering and bowing over the stuffed avocado^ and I, like (but unlike) a Vestal Virginwishing I were home at my sacred hearth.Courage! Courage! This is what is called Life. Put down the hermit’s dish and tacklethis hunk of meat - so vigorousit nearly leaps out of its sea of sauce.At last we are in the lift which elevatesfrom Gluttony to Lust. The corridors stretchinto infinity; such luxurious cellsand here by the bed is a Gideon Bible.I open it, keen for guidance or diversion.Too late! You bend over me,tall as the Albert Memorial, or a tree,take the book and tidy it away,bored with the prologue and ready for the play.