￼MOSCOW SPRINGIn the Kuskova gardens workmen lift the wooden boxes from the delicate statues.Tender bushes are unwrappedfrom their overcoats; twigs unbend in the melting light.The men warm to their work; hang their fur hatsin a row on the fence.New Statesman
￼THE BADMINTON GAMEThat morning, I awoke and went downjust as I was, in my green slippers,to look at the hydrangea mariesii -the only flower Clifton allows in the garden, for he must have his trees and shrubs.Out I crept, my slippers darkening in the dew, and hearing a movement beside meI turned and found Ruth. She was carryingthe racquets; and so - smiling, not speaking - we ran between the great bushes to the net,and there we played (quietly, of course,so that Uncle Edward might not hear)until the breakfast gong recalled us.We ran up the back stairs en deshabille,and down the front ones, tardy though decorous,and kissed Uncle Edward; but I took careto embrace him as he likes best, to forestall reproof. Colour rose up behind his moustacheand his face worked silently, but then he vanished, as usual, behind The Times.
￼DIVERSIONSIn old age, confined to bed,my mother developed a keen obsession.Lorry jack-knifed on the M4, she would cry as you skirted the commode to greet her:They'll have to leave at Exit 2 and go round here - she had a mapon her bedside table:her thin finger quivered.Our small talk, our flowers and chocolates washed up against a tideof burst water mains, spillages, contraflows. We nodded solemnly.She'd gained a nourishing rapportwith all the road junctions in the country.Are you sorry you never travelled? I asked her. She shook her headat my stupidity. Every day, every night, she travelled.r