￼Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:40 pm Page 51The Silent Woman1It accrues, the silence,as papier-mache does - postage-stamp-sized square upon postage-stamp-sized square, and again, again, into a gummy carapace, drying.Once it was only one layer thick,almost transparent; once, before, it was not there at all - the very air was garrulous and her lips kissed that, breathing, speech, embraces barely differentiated.But she can hardly remember then:memory too must push through silence and may be discouraged in the dense maze of gum, the thorn thicket keeping familiar princes back and away from kissing.2The child shielded the doll’s head with one hand from the rain, though the hood of her own mackintosh was still flatupon her shoulder-blades. They had steppedfrom the greengrocer’s doorway into a downpour likeglass curtain behind glass curtain over and over.‘Oh,’ she cried, and ‘oh’ again, while her sister danced with covered hair under the falling water.‘It’s Christmas and weddings and silver paper suddenly, but I think my doll will melt in all this wetness.’Her mother said, ‘Don’t talk nonsense!’ and the littler girl turned round and round with her feet in dazzling puddles. The child in question started to apply the paper silence.3/‘We slung a curtain on a string across the roomto achieve some privacy for each of us.I would sit sealed-off and try to hear her reading,to listen to her sewing with silent thread and needle.51
￼‘Her quiet tantalised - though surely not on purpose - until the whole of my existence in that placewas waiting for a movement’s rustle, watchingthe dark for light strained through hung fabric.‘I grew to want her for the shadow that she made upon my mind, the faintest she-suggesting staining of the air in front of me, wherever I might look; my marriage, in the end, was to such ghostliness.’4In fact she spoke a good deal within the sounding-box of her skull; she recognised her own real accentsin the soft contralto retailing judgements whilethe face she assumed hung expressionless over the table like the Baptist’s head offered on a platter to them all... and he kissed it as Salome nuzzled those cooling lips, thinking something had been attained by decapitation.Inside, her voice buried deeper as the wormor mole does, leaving a smaller and smaller echo to surface for a cast of earth at the backof her eyes. She doubted any change was noticed in the glazed gaze on the dish pushed to one side.5The doll her daughters played with - putting it to bedin the pram, taking it out to have its clothes changed, showing it the garden, an^so on - had grownnear faceless with this use, eyebrow and mouth paint gone.She hated it, without reasons she could speak -little homunculus, grey-pink foetus - pulled the quiltup and up to cover its forehead, obtrusive in the nursery cot, her look drawn there despite the other tumbling toys around.And when they paraded it in a new dress for her,she could not praise, but turned away to book or needle, erecting a thorn thicket of interlacing branches,a curtain to withhold and hide even her children.
￼Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:40 pm Page 536What gets left behind is often not intended to be found; despite the old wives’ saws, clean underwear is not donnedfor every fresh foray into the streets of traffijrt'. The moment itself selects the meal in preparation, what half-written letter is there lying on the desk.q ^I h ic l o 5 cIn her case it was the doll-sized babies’ bones,wrapped-up in layers of paper and stowed in a chest,that remained after she withdrew her quiet intothe absolute silence. It rained again that day,and they could not understand what they had found. Without her heard interpretation, everything was conjecture, all metaphors of gum and princes, melting, a severed head.53f
￼-e-Pen and PaperBefore the ladder to the platform closed in by fleering voices, the tying of the feet, the laying on the tilted board face down but with no place for cheek or lip to rest on,before the oblique blade, the bloody basket;arrived at the foot of the scaffold, Madame Roland asked that she might have pen and paper to record‘the strange thoughts rising in her’.Request refused, as if it were some clever-dick trick of postponement;the page remaining at the stationers, the quill untrimmed, the strange thoughts in the skull as in a vasethat spj^fJ; them quite illegibly under the guillotinea moment later.A fate she knew could not be much delayed, she would not read her own words back to herat leisure after, what she felt urged to keepcould not be kept by her more than a minute’s space; but nonetheless she wanted pen and paper, meantto snatch out of the blood-stained air those phrasesthat would cage the strangeness lifting through her now.For only words could net and hold the foreign birdslong enough in her sight for naming, recognitionunder the single lightning-flash that time had left her;only with pen and paper could she possess her death,the momentary owner of a basket loud with wingsthat the imminent blow would knock from her hands and scatter.Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:40 pm Page 5454/
￼Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:40 pm Page 55‘They Say the Owl was a Baker’s Daughter’'And thorns shall come up in her palaces, nettles and bramblesin the fortresses thereof; and it shall be an habitation o f dragons, anda courtfor owls.’isaiah, 34,v.131An empty bakehouse like a weekday church,as chill to the touch as a milkchurn,with the same bluish shadows as skimmed milk, an echo as of a tin cup tapped by a spoon;yet furred throughout with flour, blurredas a breathed-on mirror, a steamed-up window:the setting for the owl -itself a slowed white flicker, some shadow’s reversed image on a spiral of unexposed film.It is night. The lighthas drained into metal vessels:lean over that great mixerto catch its dying gleam —some fallen star goingwiddershins down the black plughole.The owl wakes in its ruin,the broken bakehouse wall,where the window that waspeeled back, fraying bricks,its whitewash dropped dunes of new flour; the whole of the dark flooded in.There are black loaves bakingin the ovens’ doorless caves.The owl attends them, busybetween this slab and space,its white flight-feathers quiveringlike the shapes in antique moviesrecovered just in time, their silver edges eaten.(?)&55
￼-^3“Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:40 pm Page 562When I was ten or somy best friend was a baker’s daughter;she nibbled raw pastry for pleasure.We played in the vacant bakehouse in the afternoons, riding down chutes meant for loaves, or rollingin the loft’s fat waves of flour-bloomed sacks.She wanted to be a ballet-dancer -might have been,but for the off-white filaments of doughthat bound her, hand and foot,to the little shop with their home stuck to it and the big, low bakehouse,like a grounded ship behind.The abattoir-keeper’s daughter made a third - with no similar skein of flesh to hold her.She was the first vegetarian I knew;Orv\.<* b r 1through her skin shrunk back white on her bones (,o'e,u’t w^en she told us, how market-gardeners and farmersfed their land with the slaughter-house blood. She disliked owls, for their killing,the carrion smell of their nests.And I was a grocer’s child, a grocer’s grand-daughter. Our shop was across the road from the startof a wood, where the jays laughed by dayand owls screeched and hollered throughout the night. It was down the hill to the bakehousewith pavements, roads and dwellings all around;there the birds’ dawn chorus was thin at best...In the end that daughter had to go to bakers’ college.3Walls beyond walls all around; and men and women, children strategically placed, observing or turned away from the owlin a cage in the pet department.56e