￼New LitaniesBecause I know that I shall turn again Pray, please, Paul £luardBecause I know I will be bored again Pray for us, BaudelaireBecause I know I’ll spit in spite again Sharpen my tongue, M r PopeAnd let me take with it a little more water Mr Cole PorterBecause I am a vieux marcheurStumbling up the flighty stairsMM Laforgue and Corbiere(And to hell with Yves Bonnefoy).From purgatory, Auden, where you must beI pray for you,Kindly reciprocate(And we'll hang the Golden Fleece upon a sour apple tree) And take that grin off your face, Max Jacob.Against LiesItisnottrue- IamfreeFrom all this Xtian stuff-One is still in the nineteen-twenties When occasionally an aeroplane Would punctuateExtraordinarilyVarious dull cloudsOne still agrees with H.G.Wells, Bernard Shaw, AndreBreton, Picasso, Aragon, £luard, All that lot. Even Andre Gide, Who slinks in, in the last line.203
￼Inertia (Spleen)Our faces, hopeless, Melting like blancmange Tell their own story.Numbness soarsOver the campusHands,T en idiot fingersPlaying shadows behind churches.NeverthelessWhen you smileThe street is flooded.What goldsmith did you employ T o set the trees as gems?HereColdness and spleen are married. O.K., the ship will arriveAt noon precisely.I will get a big hugFrom my big brotherAt twelve o’clock.204
￼About Sociology ._—V7.)I have, Goa help us, taught the eleven-plus. By the /Headmaster1s secret instructions Between four fifteen and four thirty I Taught intelligence tests.#I have heard well-salaried bourgeois parents Offering to pay for evening instructionOr threatening to complain to the Wead.1 have seen the complacent faces of inspectors of EducationAi have seen rebellious hairy studentsDrop out and drop back into themselvesLooking for a barber beforeAnswering advertisements and filling in forms of application ,I have heard plump nail-filed charge-nurses With motor-cars and mortgages Endlessly'“urging IK recalcitrant alcoholics To lower their sightsAnd be content* to conform to the norm.1 have heard/greasy bossy nursepScreeching like a school teacherMagging and threatening old men and old women As if they were backward infants.^ 2cSt