￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:41 pm Page 5DMici/lion, epwraph qr bhmkMielide!f
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:42 pm Page 6AcknowledgementsThis book includes poems selected from Sara Berkeley’s collections Penn (1986) and Home Movie Nights (1989), both published by Raven Arts Press in Ireland and by Thistledown Press in Canada.For the new poems in Facts About Water, acknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publications in which some of those poems first appeared:Sara: please list any magazines and anthologies here, including the names of the publishers of the anthologies and their year of publicationN e il-ortly <e.(£>(ds<%pOhlicahoASthivewas ptfbhsned by Tfie newStatesivtcM. \a \°\°iO] "A iMeek left* appealed tiA Age/ida iA Ja/wa/\j 1^ 1; a poeM app&v'fid iVt tk\c T ls tia (i c<mtfigMeMb&r uhit.1^ pc>e/v\) - o/ie or two poeMS (agcu/t, I ca^-rtr teoAetAoW' wvtvdnores,) a p p e a l iV\ TVjsm i<a .Atdfbologies:K/ildiSH TPjiVtOs , ed. Ailbbe Swyfia, Attic Pfess,FoetYv) liitvt aA Edge, ed. Meil Astley, blood 6ooks( I'll5.t^ Oephcwt4
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:41 pm Page 3SARA BERKELEYFacts AboutWaterNEW & SELECTED POEMSB1Q0DAX6 BQDK5—f-SUbstifdte "T^eRoodsfs"-fibf"0dhtfoQStow"?
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:48 pm Page 4&Copyright © Sara Berkeley 1986, 1989, 1994ISBN: 1 85224 2922 Bloodaxe Books (UK)1874597 04 1895449 28First published 1994in Great Britain byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN,in Ireland byNew Island Books Ltd, 2 Brookside,Dundrum Road, Dundrum,Dublin 14.9 New Island Books (Ireland) 6 Thistledown Press (Canada)Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.Thistledown Press Ltd acknowledges the assistance of The Canada Council and the Saskatchewan Arts Board.LEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. No part of this book may bereproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without prior written permission from Bloodaxe Books Ltd. Requests to publish work from this book must be sent to Bloodaxe Books Ltd for the UK and all other countries except Ireland and Canada, for which applications should be madeto New Island Books and Thistledown Press respectively.CANADIAN CATALOGUING IN PUBLICATION DATABerkeley, Sara, 1967- Facts About WaterPoems.ISBN 1-895449-28-6I. Title.PR6052.E57F3 1994 82P.914 C94-920199-5Cover printing by J. Thomson Colour Printers Ltd, Glasgow.Printed in Great Britain byBell & Bain Limited, Glasgow, Scotland.in Canada byThistledown Press Ltd, 668 East Place, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan,S7J 2Z5.
￼Berkeley 1-9 10/9/94 12:24 pm Page 4Copyright © Sara Berkeley 1986, 1989, 1994ISBN: 1 85224 2922 Bloodaxe Books (UK)1874597 04 1895449 28First published 1994in Great Britain byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN,in Ireland byNew Island Books Ltd, 2 Brookside,Dundrum Road, Dundrum,Dublin 14.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.I?HERNrtf9 New Island Books (Ireland) 6 Thistledown Press (Canada)Thistledown Press Ltd acknowledges the assistanceof The Canada Council and the Saskatchewan Arts Board.New Island Books receives financial assistance from The Arts Council (An Chomhairle Ealaion).LEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. No part of this book may bereproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without prior written permission from Bloodaxe Books Ltd. Requests to publish work from this book must be sent to Bloodaxe Books Ltd for the UK and all other countries except Ireland and Canada, for which applications should be madeto New Island Books and Thistledown Press respectively.CANADIAN CATALOGUING IN PUBLICATION DATABerkeley, Sara, 1967- Facts About WaterPoems.ISBN 1-895449-28-6I. Title.PR6052.E57F3 1994 821'.914 C94-920199-5Cover printing by J. Thomson Colour Printers Ltd, Glasgow.Printed in Great Britain byBell & Bain Limited, Glasgow, Scotland.in Canada byThistledown Press Ltd, 668 East Place, Saskatoon, Saskatchewan,S7J 2Z5.
￼Berkeley 1-9 10/9/94 12:24 pm Page 5SFor Michael
￼AcknowledgementsThis book includes poems selected from Sara Berkeley’s collections Penn (1986) and Home Movie Nights (1989), both published by Raven Arts Press in Ireland and by Thistledown Press in Canada.For the new poems in Facts About Water, acknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publications in which some of those poems first appeared: Agenda, New Statesman (5 Society, Poetry with an Edge (Bloodaxe Books, new edition, 1993), Prism, Times Literary Supplement, and Wildish Things (Attic Press, 1989).
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:43 pm Page 733 34 35 36C. 37 J8 2- 39 403. 41 6. 42 R. 43 II- 44 *3- 4546 /?- 47R- 48 49The hung manDeath of a red flower Do you?Maker of rainLittle riverHome movie nightsJust don’t walk out in front of my bike Less than a hundred hoursScarecrowI don’t want his name in hereClosed outPole-bound LaunderetteA study of us together A time of drought The figures in the rain W interingContentsFROM PENN (1986)13 14 15 16 17 18 192021222324252627282930Everything green furious pfeorge1.£ •PennOut in the storm BrainburstRevival nightChrysalisIn St Etheldreda’sUnseenComing to ^The Judas /lowerHe drew back always SongDeath in a stranger’s head Cycling backOrangesHejiraThe partingFROM HOME MOVIE NIGHTS (1989)
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:43 pm Page50 51 52 53ConvalescentThe swingThe courage gathererTenFACTS ABOUT WATER (1994)56 Man in balloonMan in flight& Man chopping wood& After the story brokeMan by his life-to Everyone’s cold&& The drowning#5 Sung through fire<?p Zoo Gardens, Berlin& Potsdamer Platz, BerlinFacts about water PaddingtonFallHe isn’t there1* Heartbreak hour71 The road to the interior % Patiencef#WJK&7*In his room 16 FamineT*> A letteryiLoom Mist PolesnV& AirportReflex&z Sea-borne8t Uncle8u* TightropeV&86The waking WaspA week left Slender girls At the railsm&98 Undertow91 Fault92 ValleyTcJ&Sola'
￼Berkeley 1-10 19/8/94 6:43 pm Page 995J# 9?T 9ftEvidenceBurying the elephant The man I knew After the fact