￼Garrett 29/7/91 10:03 am Page 20Nilak i.The sky began as a blue bowl scoopedAnd rimmed by the eye’s orbit. Lilac was there, Still and circumscribed as in lalique,To fill a bowl’s ache.The mind would hold things in little, Like itself, to grasp a lifetime’s Breath, a place in emptiness.This is no blindness,But still the smaller part of seeing.Worlds spill slowly outward from their centre, The eye’s bowl fills and overflowsAnd even air must move.Wind blows. Blue on Persian blue, nflak, A sea where crests of lilac breakTo foam; and in their leaves, the soft Lallation of the waves.20e/
￼Garrett 29/7/91 10:03 am Page 21Tyranny of the SpectrumWhat shall we makeO f our days, when colour, Or memory, lackAll integrity, beckoning All ways to some thing Just out of the picture?Painting by numbers,The mind selectsNot what the soul’s Compound eye reflects,But only the coloured pencils The heart allows.A child’s calendar: What could be simpler Or less refutableThan the seven bright Weathers of the week - Or more immutable?Let’s say: It was so. Doubt not the snow’s Whiteness, the window’s Bland transparenciesNor the seven certainties O f the rainbow.Call it a grey day:In a thousand lit rooms, Children, furiousWith the snickersnackO f scissors, shatter rainbows, Make snow paradisiac.21
￼Wedding BreakfastA table in the sunlight;Two cups of black coffeeAgainst the cloth’s impossible white, And a basket piled with cherries.How constancy dazzles with its white Lies! The shadows dark as coffee, Two cups of tricked light,A new moon rising on each cherry.Still life: you can’t. Even the lightIs mortal. Death is the bride in white ^sting first fruits of loss; the slow Ripening of cherries, blood-bright.
￼Degas’ EcoliereIt is not every day, on meeting Someone new, we have the chanceTo size them up as they advanceAnd know ourselves in their retreating.Not one foot high, and a littleLarger than life, your body’s simpleIn its bronze motion; straw hat tiltedA candid angle, chin lifted (perhapsA touch too high), your bag in hand, on hip, Above a thigh that flexes as you step Forward to part the air that holds you up.And I would think you less than woman Were it not for the fact that, openAs your free approach may be(Breasts rounded as two firm tokensOf maturity), still you haveSome small thing to hide. Oh Eve,Is it an apple you hold behind your back?As she retreats, her posture alters:Not her step, but the eye that falters Seeing sameness so utterly unlike.A girl’s thin shoulders, a satchelIn one hand, and in the other, crooked Up to grasp the free end of her plait, Nothing withheld - but a holding back.We are authorised to trespass.And we do. A terracotta headThat has no life behind its earsIs not a head, until we make it so.I did not ask to see this lastIntensely private hanging-on to Childhood, but sought it nonetheless.
￼29/7/91 10:04 am Page 24And the World in a Bowl of PorridgeThe barbed hand stops punishing.Plaited and pig-tailed, obedient as dolls, we wait, Our scored scalps tinglingWhere the comb had raked.Porridge steams in the breakfast bowls.Then the steady hand pouring; from jug to dish The twisted ribbon of milk;Round^d| bouldered shores the white silk slips And laps the island in.Slowly the world revolves.Then the skilled hand spooning; In one long viscous dripThat measures centuriesA stalactite of golden-syrup drools And spills away.Once there was an island; long agoAn atoll dwindled to a scattered archipelago. In another world, on the rim of a spoon, The snail retracts its golden horn.
￼Garrett 30/7/91 5:50 pm Page 25Moules a la MariniereWe scoured the secret places of the creek, Parting blistered fronds ofTo find the concupiscent clusters, rockedIn their granite creche. Jack-knives prised The molluscs out. Slick blue-blacks bruised Slowly dull; and the sea expunged our tracks.Bouquet of Muscadet, bouquet garni recall The tuck and chuckle of mussels in a bucket Behind the door. Damp and aromatic,Steam insinuates itself into allThe kitchen clefts, and clings in briny beads Above the flame where mussels chirp and wheeze.I pour on wine; it seems they beg for more,The beaked shells yearning wide as if in song - Yet dumb - and lewdly lolling parrot-tongues. Cream licks the back of a spoon and drawls a slur O f unctuous benediction for this feast.We smooth our cassocks; bow our heads; and eat.It rained all night as though to wash awayA brininess that tanged the atmosphere:Dreams - of forbidden fruit, offruits de merW renched from their secret beds, of tastes that lay Like sea’s after-sting on the tongue. Still lingersA trace of guilt. I wash my salty fingers.et25