￼TREMBLING HEARTS IN THE BODIES OF DOGSThis selection includes work from Selima Hill’s collections Saying Hello at the Station (1984) and My Darling Camel (1988), as well as the whole of The Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness (1989) and a new collection, Aeroplanes o f the World (1994).It does not include any poems from her recent collection A Little Book of Meat (1993)which is available separately from Bloodaxe.
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 4:28 pm Pa"0Contentsf r o m Saying Hello at the Station (1984)12 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21Questioning Mr BonnetBelow HeklaThe Fowlers of the Marshes Dewpond and Black Drain-pipes Elegy for the Bee-godThe RamThe FlowersTy-CochChicken Feathersfrom My Darling Camel (1988)26 The Sea-Water Hall -28 The Holidaymakers’ Daughter30 T h e Significance o f Significance31 Queenio32 Peggy33 Natural Wonders34 Lotty35 Lucy36 Benjamin37 A Skiing Accident38 The Seashore House40 Early Nights41 The Unsuccessful Wedding-Night42 Crepusculo - Ibiza , o~4r~44 T h e Ptarmigan Hunter46 The Bath47 Eating Chocolates in the Dark ^48 Mother Stone49 Noone50 Not all the Women of England52 Ouarzazate N53 Jacko’s Girl54 Visiting the Zoo55 The Small-Mammal House56 Parrots57 Looking for Camels58 DevotionO-cc^zU-^-<,^0^
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 4:23 pm Pa'The Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness (1989) 61 The Accumulation of Small Acts of KindnessAeroplanes o f the World (1994)96 Beethoven’s Mother97 Lilies of the Valley- Ot^-t99 Tomato Soup Cs-tI b w T i B</tV y V ^ 5 *i^ C /V\IJfcv First Bra 102 MaryloufrJT103 _Snow Babi.es .104 /M y Darling Reindeer105 ^The Hare106 /W hat Happens in the Present 107-^:Sugared Almonds__108/The Villa109 /The Dog-Man111 / m aisie112* -Molly114^ Brueghel’s Helicopter115 •''Abstract Expressionism116 ./Eating Lychees in South Kensington 117 /Being a Wife118/Amelia Milkypi/C-j127 128129 130 131 132 133 134 135 136 137ASelima SelimaJoseph Beuys, Yul Brynner, Sigmund Freud, Gorbachev,Freya Stark and Me J/The Veil * ^TifiJjhlecloth^T^l^ /tarnationsLondon's Countryside by Greenline Bus c~A /Voices of Bulgaria/Margueritet/The Birds ) ------ ^ /Orchids/The WaspsCAa •'‘ • '- A lj (kXvJCrv*^sThe End of the Roap c <~'r i /hundreds of Letters to Hundreds of Naked MenlAy/yV119120121122123124125126' Crocuses • c ~ tj /KMftj iJ hnfcFC.Deep in the Scented House . Three Sisters'The Marble Quarry /A Cup of Kindness/Our Lady ofSnow
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 3/2/94 4:23 pm Pa138 ✓'Sips139 ✓Albert ('140 ✓How To Be Happy —142^Biscuits-.* 1UJv*143 ✓The Island144 ✓The Man Man «*✓<.145 /Standing Here Beside You 146 Comfort -fr-T147 ✓'Wolves148 Silence149 -/The Journey 150 • Boatingp>Q-hlh Citytfir ^p\~v*\t’CjjLjL1 JI ptfU-CcsiJez
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 19/5/94 1:08 pm PiThe Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness (1989) 61 The Accumulation of Small Acts of KindnessAeroplanes o f the World (1994)BeingaWife D"1 The Wasps \(The Man ManflM^V (My First Bra) Io * The Dog-Man l o 3 Selima Selima IT"7✓My Life with Men Three Sister£^“0Joseph Beuys tK 1?2> (Standing Here Beside You) I'-iS Milky H*kM a i s i e 111y Potato CityBeethoven’s Mother 9 (>✓*The Toe The Birds/Brides with Songbirds Tangled in Their Veils SilenceCarnations 17»IyEvelynMarguerite 13>H-TheHaff lO^Voices of BulgariaMary/Lou IMy Darling Reindeer IC>"FHundreds of Letters to Hundreds of Naked Men 12jo Sparkle IS2-/The VoiceofBoboAbstract Expressionism 'Sips \V2Night Night (was The Journey) 1+-^ Wolves 1The Island I'A'i(Heatwave) (was Marble Quarry) 1'L-1 What Happens in the Present l o tHow To Be Happy l"4-0Boating iSOEating Lychees in South Kensington 111S A Nightdress Sprinkled with Fish Scales-e-e-l’S ‘1
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 19/5/94 1:08 pm00The Postman Like a Bunch ^of Flowers vAlirabelle (was Albert)(The Veil) a ?Brueghel’s Helicopter (l>+' A Cup of Kindness 11/L OurLadyofSnow |IS The Villa IOrchids Ufc,The RunwayCutting (first to be cut) MollyBiscuitsSugared Almonds (was Hank) My First Bra96 Beethoven’s Mother97 Lilies of the Valley99 Tomato Soup101 My First Bra102 Marylou103 Snow Babies104 M y Darling Reindeer105 The Hare106 What Happens in the Present107 Sugared Almonds108 The Villa109 The Dog-Man111 Maisie112 Molly114 Brueghel’s Helicopter115 Abstract Expressionism116 Eating Lychees in South Kensington117 Being a Wife118 Amelia119 The End of the Road120 Hundreds of Letters to Hundreds of Naked Men121 The Marble Quarry122 A Cup of Kindness123 Deep in the Scented House124 Three Sisters125 Our Lady of Snow-0
￼Hill Trembling 1-9 19/5/94 1:09 pm Pag^lO126 127 128129 130 131 132 133 134 135 136 137 138 139 140 141 142 143 144 145 146 147 148 149 150 151 152Crocuses Selima SelimaJoseph Beuys, Yul Brynner, Sigmund Freud, Gorbachev, Freya Stark and MeThe VeilThe TableclothsCarnationsLondon’s Countryside by Greenline Bus Voices o f BulgariaMargueriteThe BirdsOrchidsThe WaspsSipsAlbertHow To Be HappyThe Climbing AccidentBiscuitsThe IslandThe Man ManStanding Here Beside YouComfortWolvesSilenceThe JourneyBoatingEverything Is WonderfulSparkle10e
￼Dogs 1- LO 22/12/93 3:21 pm Page 7Contentsf r o mSaying Hello at the Station (1984)Questioning Mr BonnetBelow HeklaThe Fowlers of the Marshes Dewpond and Black Drain-pipes Elegy for the Bee-godThe RamThe FlowersTy-CochChicken Feathersfrom My Darling Camel (1988)The Sea-water HallThe Holidaymakers’ Daughter The Significance of Significance QueenioPeggyNatural WondersLottyLucyBenjaminA Skiing AccidentThe Seashore HouseThe Unsuccessful Wedding-Night Crepusculo - IbizaThe Ptarmigan HunterThe BathEating Chocolates in the Dark Mpther Stone {%talltheWomenotEngland OuarzazateJacko’s GirlVisiting the ZooThe Small-Mammal HouseDevoHon ”Cl Of\t-'The Accumulation o f Sm all Acts o f Kindness (1989) The Accumulation of Small Acts of Kindness
￼Dogs 1-10 22/12/93 3:21 pm PageAeroplanes o f the World (1994)tBfeethoven’s Mother---------------------------Lilies of the Valley cot <’ I’AtYln C/\im ' Tomato Soup ^My First BraGr \ T l r n - l t T i T i i r l M j a L*' Marylou t'^vA'ifc ^ u i v t t -Night Night S n o ^ j ^?aai3A.d,-My Darling ReindeerThe Hare — 'g.v Op-oo ver-Y&vst>*°\ What Happens in the Present'"1Iarrk Al<vu>i.dS. — ^v/b>s TheVilla~SrcYra<\p« zr&\HB*The Dog-Man '-•DA Message for theWorld^MollyBrueghel’s HelicopterAbstract ExpressionismEating Lychees in South Kensington Being a WifeMinor Lapses ArvtCr^i _ .Ov Hundreds of Letters to Hundreds of Naked Men_ -Mothec €tOm ('T HViSl KSSXAHeatwave- ^ T h t TY|&cMje_ A Cup of KindnessDeep in the scented hous$^ Three Sister?'Our Lady of Snow CrocusesSelima SelimaQ>vfOrVvA' ‘,f ~’moPna\SAfc-CtnH-^Joseph Beuys, Yul Brynner, Sigmund Fre/dVFreya StarkC>a/usfc 't o Cl^-f V<LTN>_C>-'\ O.and Me■M y PrivaTG=feafe _tOC^o VXTkwewell~ ivJH<The Veil ?The Tablecloths—Carnations C_J London’s Countryside by Greenline Bus Voices of BulgariaMargueritet o
￼Dogs 1-10 22/12/93 3:21 pm Page 9The BirdsOrchids ..The WaspsI SipsHnway'tii AlbertHow To Be Happy The Climbing Accident—ThtrHarp— TheIslandr1)(Vl3nWxr\ —zS^ J*\\u -—'2&c\Wblv/CL^ooKb\-^34tsW/frnS&^A - -xcM^ “"xdc*— SvlW itVUt*(t3rCry £t*«*2-2*SpO tffl?rc-o sftJ9-0-
￼Ot.33^3_ip ye7,tc
￼DrZK-J' ^Das LebenDas Leben der Huhner ist rot.Das Beben der nachstenliebe ist rot.Das leben ist schon.Beben der Herzen im Leibe der Hunde. Das Leben der Herzen ist lieb.Das Leben macht den Himmel heer. Das Leben mochte langer sein. langsamer es Lebe die Liebe.langsames Leben ist lang.
￼''Yvv€ ic>^ a
￼Questioning Mr BonnetM r Bonnet, the helpful Egyptologist, explains the strange cosmologyin his Reallexikon der agypschen Religionsgeschichte that he wrote when he was dying in Berlin:Horns, the god of light, hid his semenin a dish of chopped lettuce leaves,and greedy Seth, the god of darkness, pig-headed, metal-boned, swallowed it, and so, by trickery, the moon was bom: Thoth, on a lotus flower, the blue baboon!He crosses the celestial oceanas helmsman of the world,called Aah, the vizier of Ra, the sun.He loads the gleaming boatwith palm leaves which recordthe days and nights in notches,for he is the measurer of time,and he invented writing.He carries an ivory writing palettein his long black fingers, to instructthe scribes who squat before him on the sand.And he helps them on their later journey through the Night Of A Million Years as Thoth, the protector of the dead:he takes them kindly by the handand guides them through the underworld; his nine baboon musicians finethe long bank where the travellerspass on their way to Osiris,dreaming of playing draughts
￼with the gods and dancing with them in the Field Of Reeds.Mr Bonnet, did you meet him, and will I, when I step on board the silver barque? Will he be saying Pleased to meet you, Mrs Hill, and how’s the writing going} as we descend the corridors of nightinto the Judgment Hall. Will he pat me on the shoulder with his cracked avuncular hand and, tucking my book inside his sky-blue cape, will he wink before he picks his tail up and climbs onto his special perch above the scales?
￼Below HeklaI appear like a bird from nowhere.I have a new name.I am as dean as a whistle.I beat the buttermilk in big white bowls until it is smooth.I wash the pearly plates under the tap, and fifty canvas bumpers and fifty socks. They drip in the sunbelow grey mountains like the moon’s.Each night I lift the children in their sleep and hold out the china pot for them: Wilt jpu pissa, elskan,pissa, pissa I whisperas I tiptoe from bed to bed . . . Around mid-night,I go to the geyser below Hekla and bathe in the warm water.I am a short fat English girl.I am twenty-five mothers.I lead my children in a line across the heather to the church. The father watches mefrom his dark door.He shakes his head,and takes me by the hand: Blessa ini, elskan, blessa pii!And now, September,dust is flying: the bus is here. I am ready.I am on my way to Reykjavik,
￼Leith, Liverpool. . . The children of theare running to the Good-bye,give our love to12t
￼The Fowlers of the MarshesThree thousand years agothey were fowling in the marshesaround Thebes —men in knotted skirtsand tiered faience collars,who avoided the brown crocodile,and loved the ibis, which they stalkedwith long striped cats on strings,under the eye of Nut, the goddess of the sky.My mother’s hushed peculiar world’s the same: she haunts it like the fowlers of the marshes, tiptoeing gaily into history, sustained by gods as strange to me as Lady Nut, and Anubis,the oracular, the jackal-masked. When I meet her at the station, I say Hello, Mum! and think Hello, Thoth, This is the Weighing ofthe Heart.
￼Dewpond and Black Drain-pipesIn order to distract me, my mother sent me on an Archaeology Week. We lived in tents on the downs, and walked over to the siteevery morning. It was an old dewpond.There was a boy there called Charlie. He was the first boy I had really met. Iwas too shy to go to the pub,but I hung around the camp every night waiting for him to come back.He took no notice of me at first, but one night the two of uswere on Washing-Up together.I was dressed in a black jerseyand black drain-pipes, I remember.You in mourning? he said. He didn’t know I wasone of the first beatniks.He put a drying-up cloth over my head and kissed methrough the linen Breeds Of Dogs.I love you, Charlie I said.Later, my mother blamed herselffor what had happened. The Romans didn’t even interest her, she said.
￼Elegy for the Bee-godStingless beeswere bred in tree hollowsfor beeswax and honey. Every year, in the month called Tzec, the bee-keepers played their raspadoresand danced across the fields with bells and ribbonsround their feet, to honour the fat bee-god, who buzzed in the heated airto their music.He lived in a gold housein the hotlands, and drank cocoa sweetened with honey.All’s quiet now, it’s June, and he’s not here, the late, the long-forgotten bee-god, who sped on zig-zag wings across the sky to the faithful. Cross-eyed, bejewelledand tattooed, drumminghis fluffy yellow feeton the tree hollows,he gave the bees new hope,and cocoa sweetened with honey.If ever I find him —thin, justly offended, deadin the dry chaparral -I will put jade beadsand honey on his tongue, and wrap him in a shroud
￼of wings, and loop his neck with pearls from Guatemala;I will light him candlesof beeswax, bringing sleep, and he will rest in the shadeof the First Tree,and wait for me there - humming a tune, and drinking cocoa sweetened with honey.
￼The RamHe jangles his keys in the rainand I follow like a lamb.His house is as smoky as a dive.We go straight downstairs to his room.I lie on his bed and watch him undress. His orange baseball jacket, all the way from Ontario, dropstothefloor—the ram s,infelt,arched across the hunky back.He unzips his calf-lengthStar-walkers, his damp black Levi’s,and adjusts his loaded modelling-pouch:he stands before me in his socks — as white as bridesmaids,little daisies, driven snow.John <5J{^ain)watches from the wallbeside a shelf-ful of pistols. Well, he says, d ’you like itfAll I can think of is Granny, how she used to shake her head,when I stood by her bed on Sundays, f so proud in my soap-smellingspecial frock, and say Ah,Bless your little cotton socks!