￼INTRODUCTORY ESSAY Revising 'Irish Literature'Fifty years ago, Louis MacNeice summed up the reading- difficulties where Ireland is concerned:Most Irish people cannot see Ireland clearly because they are busy grinding axes. Many English people cannot see her clearly because she gives them a tear in the eye.1Misty eyed Americans add to the confusion. Complicity between Irish axes and foreign tears compounds it. As for seeing Irish literature steadily and seeing it whole, such an enterprise faces institutional, constitutional and theoretical obstacles. The latter surfaced when post-structuralism turned our quaking sod into a quaking text. And above (or beneath) all, the slow Northern Irish civil war has exposed fault-lines half-buried for half a century.Nevertheless, critics persist - and should persist - in trying to read how Irish literature reads Ireland. The essays collected here were written in the belief that literature, both as cultural artefact and cultural criticism, can help us to interpret Irish culture. My second belief is that any interpretive activity which involves literature should take into account its formal and aesthetic dimensions. Techniques, conventions, 'mechanisms of tradition' bear witness to context, while to exclude value-judgements is to exclude the cultural information offered by what works, what doesn't work and why.£<gJi\:s/Lau{?A
￼Revisionism is a shorthand and sometimes abusive term for historical studies held to be at odds with the founding ideology'n'Ooof the Irish Free State ^Republic since 1948). Whether historians have indeed caused subsidence under the Nationalist grand narrative, or whether its foundations have always quaked, my upbringing took place in one of the cracks that are now highly visible. Therefore, autobiography will colour the historical perspective in which I initially want to set current debates about literature and culture.My father T.S. Broderick, Professor of Pure Mathematics at Trinity College Dublin (1944-1962), was a Catholic teaching at a university whose history epitomises Irish sectarian differences. As James Lydon explains:From the very beginning Trinity was alienated from the vast majority of the catholic people of Ireland. Founded at a time when everywhere in Europe, and indeed overseas with colonial powers, religious conformity was being demanded as the norm in most states, the college from the start assumed openly a sectarian character. The English government was determined that converting the Irish to the reformed religion was a necessary part of the wider policy of teaching them civility, so that they could become fullsubjects of the king. Ireland must be ruled as England was and therefore the same penal laws which governed catholics in England must be applied also to Ireland. The Irish, and also the Old English, catholics must be converted, by force if necessary. But education would also have a vital role to play. Ironically, the protestant establishment believed every bit as strongly as did the catholic bishops in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries that education must befirmly based on, and generally informed by, orthodox religious beliefs.2However, there were respites in the polarisation whereby Anglicans began by excluding Catholics (and Ulster dissenters)from Trinity, and Catholics finished by excluding themselves. At the end of the eighteenth century, with progress towards Catholic3
￼emancipation, Catholics could and did enter Trinity. They included Thomas Moore, the sons of Daniel O'Connell, and 'nearly all Catholics of eminence in Ireland in the first half of the nineteenth century'.3 Indeed, the cross-sectarian Young Irelandmovement of the 1840s, according to its founder Thomas Davis, was 'made in the Historical Societies of Dublin, and belong[ed] toTrinity College Protestants and a few Roman Catholics inPerhaps political or literary advance in Ireland often belongs to some such cross-sectarian moment. But after 1850 the Irish Catholic Hierarchy, worried by secularising treats, insisted that Catholics must be educated by Catholic institutions. In Lydon's words: 'Keeping Irish Catholicism pure meant a minimum of contact between catholics and protestants.'5 This slowed, to its continuing crawl, the task which Samuel Ferguson defined as being'to make the people of Ireland better acquainted with one another'.6Cardinal Paul Cullen, chief aborter of this incipientpluralism, had a twentieth-century counterpart in John Charles McQuaid, Archbishop of Dublin from 1940 to 19 . McQuaid's / regime intensified and formalised the an' on Catholicsattending TCD, and in a notorious Lenten pastoral of 1961 heforbade his flock 'under pain of mortal sin ... to frequent that college'. Two decades earlier the Church's attitude had inducedmy father to leave the Church rather than Trinity. Since mymother, also a mathematician, came from a Scots Presbyterianfamily, my sister and I, though baptised Catholics, were brought up within the Anglican compromise (the Church of Ireland).4
￼\«\^> °Hubert Butler's essays, first collected in Escape from the Anthill (1985), helped me to make sense of my sequestered childhood among the Southern Protestant minority. During the 1940fs and 1950^, though imbued with protestant-Nationalistidealism, Butler challenged both the confessional nation-stateand the minority's refusal of critical participation. His£SSaywritings (discussed irr/'Defending Ireland's Soul') interpret the processes which made mid-century Southern Protestantism so inward-looking, self-protective, embalmed in genial euphemism, and fearful of guilt by association with the North. When I was growing up, all Protestant social life, as well as education, revolved around Church of Ireland parishes. The Ne Temere decree(1907) , enjoining the Catholic partner in a mixed marriage to bring up the children as Catholics (a decree my father disobeyed), aggravated fears that the Protestant community would dwindle still further if it did not keep itself to itself. Religious apartheid operated just as firmly in the Republic as in Northern Ireland. Hence Paul Durcan's satire 'What is aProtestant, Daddy?'Protestants were MartiansLight-years more weirdThan zoological creatures;But soon they would all go awayFor as a species they were dying out,Soon there would be no more Protestants ... 0 Yea, 0 Lord,1 was a proper little Irish Catholic boy Back in the 1950's.7Circa 1958 I took part in a Church Ireland Jfouth club debate on the proposition:'That the minority do not play their full part in the affairs of the Republic of Ireland'. A few months ago I5
￼found my paper for this debate - I was glad to see that it blamed both the minority and the Republic - inside an old copy of the Bell (June 1944), which someone must have put into my hands. The issue features an emblematic dispute between the editor, Sean O'Faolain, and W.B. Stanford: Stanford's polemic, 'Protestantism Since the Treatyhaving provokee. a riposte from O'Faolain called 'Toryism in Trinity'. Stanford, who died in 1984, was Professor of Greek at Trinity College, a well-known Homeric scholar, and a prominent Church of Ireland layman. His article, reprinted from a pamphlet, objects to 'symptoms of a pressure based on ecclesiastical policy'8, including: difficulties about land-purchase, lack of Protestant access to public jobs and offices, the contention 'that to be a true Irishman one must be a Roman Catholic', and 'banning all literature which criticises the Roman church and encouraging that which criticises any form of Protestantism'.9 Although himself the sharpest critic of retrogressive Nationalism (see 'Progressive Bookmen') O'Faolain takes a tough line with this whining, on the grounds that: 'any Catholic knows more about grievances, ancient and modern, than all the Anglicans of Britain and Ireland put together'.10Perhaps his reaction marks some kind of boundary between a liberal Catholic Nationalist and a liberal Protestant Nationalist, such as Hubert Butler.That even the liberal O'Faolain should 'resent' Stanford's raising of the religious question says much about its repression within Irish Nationalism:6
￼Conversely, the most explicit writings need not be the most revealing. The matter of Ireland sets traps for critic and artist alike, unless they look to manner as well.In this preliminary essay I want to challenge some concepts which have shaped the profile of 'Irish literature'. Seamus Deane and others insist that perceptions of Ireland are unduly determined by stereotypical literary representations, by the afterglow of Matthew Arnold's broodings on the Celt. But it may also be the case that perceptions of Irish literature are unduly determined by assumptions - mainly Nationalist assumptions - about Ireland. If one reading produces too many peasants in the twilight, another may produce too many colonisers in the text. So whereas the Field Day Anthology of Irish Writing (1991) sets out to reclaim its contents from the colonising forces of Eng. Lit., I would argue that Irish canons have been equallyA rough-hewn by indigenous axes. And, since much Modernist<£>Vthinking rests on literary events in Ireland at the turn of the century, to revise Irish literary history might lead to other revisions.IIIn a MinorityMy own critical approach owes something, though I hope not everything, to a particular background. Autobiographical mediations of history seem as inescapable in Irish criticism as in Irish literature. So a few years ago, like the man who suddenly discovered that he had been speaking prose all his life, I realised that I might be a 'revisionist' literary critic.2