￼Still LifeConsider die solidity of a pear,tear-drop in ij* bulbous ambergravity-downdrawn stretched from its stalk weight hangingdown out of clusters of leavesflower-end star measuring the dive to ground.Take note of the taut skin-stretchthe about-to-break-out white pushing behind itthe sweet wait for time or wind to bringthe severancethe drop.It is all a vast expectancy, promise, hope,fear.