￼High Street, SouthamptonMean enough now, re-built, street I once knew, And tame and bright and tight and wide enough Now, neat toy-town blocks of boxes, Noddy shops With plastics wrapped in cellophane for sale.A shiny hum of traffic with no pulse Along the concrete now. Time to un-pin Bravado, unfreeze tears, feel pain.We missed the mac of excitementIn the old High treet, when it burned: Twenty-two years led up to this, a loss. Nineteen Eighteen, Armistice DayWaves of excitement thundered round my pram, The crowded skyline bristled in relief,Shops packed in narrow cliffs rang joy.But found no Ali Baba word to openThe caves to small boys’ lust, each heaven cut off - (A crimson wedge of steak, coffee to rape a nose, Vast scented lilies, lobsters, brandy-balls,Spectrum of ties from which to choose a week -) The angel plate-glass scolded lack of means, Banished a school-boy home - tea, homework, bed.So Speech Day willed a jeering oil to blisterForty distinguished Old Boys: the Mayor to be strung up. Militant ARMS FOR SPAIN boards down the High Street, And DAILY WORKER outside cinemas.(A fat old bald man sighed, ‘Ah! Propaganda!’And livid neon smirked back from his brow.And all the Fifty-Shilling Tailors’ dummies sneered).And after Munich put us into heat,We went on talking, walking up and down,A Saturday addiction, dear Unreal City!And ettfin Betjeman’s slim volume cameTo prove to us we loved, about to lose;In small beer, posthumous, glowed wonted fires,Rake’s progress to armed forces of the crown.75
￼Not there, then, in the blast, when flames were eating. (My parents started walking out o f town.)Came back on leave, amazed, it was all gone,Nothing was where it was and all was wrong,And everywhere looked through to green of park, Vistas to statues or to distant spires.And scuttled, numb, to pubs still left.Bar Gate survived, as usual, with its airO f being left over from some other pageant, Waiting to be relieved by Ham the Fifth.Apres la guerre, the G.I. saw a slum,And wished himself in Naples or Berlin. We met again and told old stories, hastily Beat it for London, looked for jobs.It’s rough that there’s no moral comes from this, Only excuse for lack of roots.Where is the Phoenix? Surely there was burning. With more bravado still, some extra tears,We just accentuate a usual gap.Old stories for old friends, then shy away And pick up, elsewhere, what we can.76r
￼Three DaysA pleasant way to finish the war offAt the convalescent Depot at Salerno,Scrounging, on the Education Staff -Run Quiz, Tombola, Brains’ Trust in the NAAFI, Give left-wing lectures on the post-war world.Plenty of cheap, good, spirits in the Sergeants’ Mess, And sea and time enough to swim off hangovers.Armistice, Italy, was a fine, fine day.We were awed and excited, suddenly free.Finito Tedesci. Finito Bourn Bourn. And no fear nowTo be sent up through squalid transit-campsTo front-line mountains, snow and mud and bang.San^ the RED FLAG again, several times this time -Alex had brought it off before Montgomery -And a muscular Glaswegian R.S.M .Thumped on the bar and glinted through black brows:‘It’s victorry for the lads. I’m glad. I’m gladIt’s victorry for the worrkers back at home.’We left the mess and went swimming, drunk in the moonlight.V.E. Day was a different matter, stale.Started drinking in the morning, went on all day, We’d expected this so long, and O.K. this was it,We were rancid with expectation.And Churchill wireless-spoke, fatigued. What was it? Submarine bases, Ireland? What about demobilisation? And a red-cap sergeant, who nobody trusted,Lay groaning under a table: ‘Four bleeding years! Churchill! Four bastard years and a half!.Churchill! etc., etc., etc.,’True but tedious, we thought.Next day got up with brass-sick mouth. We went about our duties, sullenly.V.J. Day I spent in Halifax, Yorks., Wilfrid Pickles’ home-town, R.E. Depot. They had the gall to get us on parade
￼778For a major to tell us the war was over.It wasn’t we weren’t pleased the new inventionHad finally finished things off. And no fear now etc.But there wasn’t much celebration, there wasn’t much beer in thetown,And the locals wouldn’t have a lot to do with us.They’d had time to get used to soldiers, all through the war.
￼Bell’s ElegyThe Bomb’s been dropped again, in style, and how! Fat clouds are worried over the debris.A patch of blue sky stares. What happens now? Angels weeping, of course. Mainly for me.
￼Ode to PsychoanalysisII said to Doctor Hackenbush During abortive analysis,‘I hate the word, Love.’I meant parents’ unhelpful concern, I meant they had to bring me upTo work hard and do without money Just as they had:I had to be neat and industrious And flatter any bosses around With my modest ability to cope.IIMy penis was dangerous, dangerous, dangerous, Messy and dangerous,In danger o f being cut off.(My God, the ducks were quacking for it,And cocks ran round and round without their heads, My grandmother’s cat chased a rabbit’s tail on a string.)My bladder was sadder and madder and badder When I used to wet the bed.I remember a cold rubber sheet underneath. (Dear waters, please, bring back the Flood).My bowels were a sheer embarrassment, Holding back in white-faced spite,And then erupting generosity,A richness on a social afternoon...80
￼I didn’t get very far, acting it out With Doctor Hackenbush.I developed, he said,‘A massive negative transference,’ So the analysis was cut offAfter I hadn’t paid himFor over two months -He took two-fifths of my wages.(His name wasn’t Hackenbush anyway). I still wanted to kill StalinAfter that. But I felt I’d let Freud down. The cook would not run the State,And the State wouldn’t wither away, And psycho-analysisWas very expensive indeed:Postpone, for the time being,The New Jerusalem.IVSo here I am, in the middle of several paths, More or less where I’ve always beenHaving survived war and intensive masturbation Getting away with murder, maybeBut suffering Hell because I’m always overdrawn At the bank whose manager hoversClacking revengeful shears.Hey there! Nobbdaddy! That’s my flaming sword...
￼ManicureEach fingernail, ugly again,Must be clipped to a crisp moon.Ten homy wedges,A city’s dirt under the edges,Could sharpen to ten weapons,Razors, flick-knives - mustn’t happen.An urbane law,Not red in tooth and claw,Says what nails are for:Combing the eyebrows neady,Scratching the skin discreedy,Squeezing blackheads, scraping corns from toes, And picking one’s nose.82
￼I didn’t get very far, acting it out With Doctor Hackenbush.I developed, he said,‘A massive negative transference,’ So the analysis was cut offAfter I hadn’t paid himFor over two months -He took two-fifths of my wages.(His name wasn’t Hackenbush anyway). I still wanted to kill StalinAfter that. But I felt I’d let Freud down. The cook would not run the State,And the State wouldn’t wither away, And psycho-analysisWas very expensive indeed:Postpone, for the time being,The New Jerusalem.IVSo here I am, in the middle of several paths, More or less where I’ve always beenHaving survived war and intensive masturbation Getting away with murder, maybeBut suffering Hell because I’m always overdrawn At the bank whose manager hoversClacking revengeful shears.Hey there! Nob^daddy! That’s my flaming sword...
￼ManicureEach fingernail, ugly again,Must be clipped to a crisp moon.Ten homy wedges,A city’s dirt under the edges,Could sharpen to ten weapons,Razors, flick-knives - mustn’t happen.An urbane law,Not red in tooth and claw,Says what nails are for:Combing the eyebrows neady,Scratching the skin discreedy,Squeezing blackheads, scraping corns from toes, And picking one’s nose.82/