￼Hill Trembling 95-123 3/2/94 12:32 pm Oge 115 Abstract ExpressionismShe had this huge dog -a mastiff, I think it was,that her father had bought herwhen the doctor-said having a dog might help -and she walked very fast on her spindly legs beside him, trying to keep up; she’d come up alongside him finally, and he’d stare into her eyeslike Wittgenstein.It was snowing - the sort of weather,the harbour-master said,one minute you were wishing you were dying,the next minute you were wishing that you weren’t;and the girl with the big dog laughed,although she didn’t understand him,and she was only wearing a cardigan,so she must have been terribly cold.Then the harbour-masterinvited her into his little office,where two German tourists,looking very much at home, were painting the sea.Was it you who was saying, the bigger one said,Ad Reinhardt went all the way round the worldand took 5000 photographs - or was it 50,000? -and not a single one of a human,not a single one!Her partner nodded, and gave the dog a sandwich,and then looked up at the owner,who got one too.,115—
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:02 pm^Bage 138SipsThey come from certain over-heated quarries that operate illicitly, in relays,for those who are attracted to the flowers that grow gigantic in the noonday sun.And then they come on here and pester me - sort of pester, sort of guide my lipsuntil, like them, I learn to sip the flowers that grow so big they block the daylight out,and people are condemned to live in darkness; and, such is their confusion, every daymen with yellow dogs patrol the rocksand kill and quarter anything that moves.138e
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:04 pm 0ge 149 -VOvejAVrTheTmjrneyI met him on the stairs quite unexpectedly,and there and then I left the little hospitaland, trusting him as much, or more, than humans, followed him, without a word - to you.Some of you, I know, have been expecting us, have waited years, in fact, for our arrival,so can I take this opportunityof thanking you for your encouragement?Your country, as you know, is not well liked,and anyone who comes, must come alone.We have to make our way across the mountainsby intuition, some would say mistake,not really knowing why we started out,or who we are, or what we’re looking for.It’s like the special side-room at the hospitalthat patients other patients were unsettled by, patients needing quiet, used to sleep in.And people loathed it. Anything but that!Why? Because it’s up a little stair,and looking out on nothing but the moors.But once they did, and this applied to everyone,a subtle transformation would come over them.
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:03 pm0ge 147W olvesNormally a rather timid man,he knew exactly what he had to do -find a wolf, and, watching every movement, kneel down before her in the darknesswhere endless little bands of beady nightlife stream like gold across the forest flooras if there’s been some terrible mistakethat only they are able to correct,only they and those like them who know. Most of all, he needed to kneel down - something not encouraged in an office.Offices are not the place for tiptoeing,gazing, kneeling, anything like that.Offices are not the place for wolves,or anyone involved with them, or night. Offices are meant for office-workers.Anybody else will be removedand flattened out in basements by machines. Nothing is the name they’ll be remembered by, lots of it, as ordered, nice and flat.
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:02 pm 0ge 143 The IslandMen want to understand, and think they do, and maybe if they don’t it’s not their fault, but basically this place belongs to us.We like to organise ourselves ourselves.And anyway, anyone can visit -brothers, fathers, lovers, anyone.My son comes often; or I visit him.You ask us if we miss them. Not at all.We don’t use cars, or electricity,and men especially seem to find that hard. Another thing - we feel healthier.We work the horses; bear much fewer children; and eat and dress and live very simply.We shepherd sheep. We scale trees for fruit. We abseil cliffs for samphire and fresh eggs; and some of us, as you have pointed out, migrating to the cities, abseil glass.
￼Hill Trembling 95-123 3/2/94 12:33 pmge 121&HtstAwwvi_JEke-Marble Quarry(for Heywood and fenny)Only the movement of the occasional rabbit or the drifting shadow of a distant crow f disturbed the stillness of the marble quarrry, and it must have been nearly an hour,>'he told me later,before$he noticed there was someone there -white as fish-bones,white as sun-bleached eye-lashes,white as the elongated mother-of-pearl lozengescunningly inlaid in the musical cigarette-boxof her second home,white as the hands of the man who delivers her anthracite beans.
￼Trembling 95-123 3/2/94 12:29 pm/Page 106What Happens in the PresentWhy do they have to have their fried eggs and black coffee and tame maidsand an urgent phone-call to make,and not enough time to time time?And are their holidays really relaxed enough? And are the shops near enough?And the car servile enough?And is the moment following the moment following the moment fast enough?so they never get touched by the present’s immediate present - where women walk to beaches with white skin;where the beach-chalets’ very decaylends them an air of sanctity we feel at home in;where salt smells of salt;where silk feels like topspin;where people we pass belong to the same side as we do, where everyone does;where a briefcase sits alone in a locked officeas its owner comes crawling along a narrow ledge five storeys upto get it back, and carry it home through the streets to his strip-lit bed where bagfuls of kittens mew from nightbound skips;where someone like me - for the sake of the way things are,for the sake of the present,for the sake of its calm, enigmatic compassion -will die for someone like you.
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:02 prrw-Page 140How To Be HappyIn the crowded hold of someone’s boat,chocolate sauce is being poured on pearsthat shudder as the chocolate coats their shoulders and spreads its lip across each tilted plate,across the laps of guests, the rubber floor,till everything is sunk in utter darkness,and no one speaks, and no one even moves.Years go by; then someone’s eyes make outthe polished surface of a chocolate seawhere tiny golden boats are busy fishing.140
￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:04 pm ge 150BoatingFew, if any, went to bed that night,and in the morning rescue teams set out.Only those too weak to help remained -the little man, the children, three small hens. They waited in the house for what seemed days until a river made of melting snowcarried them away towards the sea -everyone, that is, except the man,who had a boat, and rowed upstairs to bed,but even that, his fifty-year-old bed;slipped away as he approached, like sand,and the house itself was washed away,and he was left to roam the world alone,rowing through the treetops in his nightshirt,or sometimes rowing, sometimes simply drifting, feeling too relaxed to really think;but once he saws,or-thetigh-t-he--saw^.a woman* waving from the rail of a liner;but when he called, she didn’t answer him -as if to stop him calling out like thatand spoiling the whole joy of the occasion.ivTxiAC.150-e-