￼proletarian writers to mobilise, with the Hewitt who tried to enthuse Ulster Young Farmers about their poetic heritage in a journal otherwise devoted to flax policy. Behind both incarnations lurks Alexander Irvine, the Antrim-born preacher, social-reformer and writer. Irvine, in Hewitt's words, 'had exposed the outrages of the chain-gang in the Southern States[and] ... stood shoulder to shoulder with Jack London'.55 Hewitt in the early 1930s was inspired first by a sermon of Irvinethen by a controversial speech at the Labour Hall celebrated 'the agitator Christ, and the communism of the early disciples'.56 Then there was a private occasion when Irvine told him that inUlster 'Someone was needed to say the unpopular things, to maintain the imperilled values'.57 Hewitt turned this episodeinto a short story called 'The Laying on of Hands'.From the mid 1940s a small number of cultural missionarieswere at work in various savage quarters - for instance,Sam Hanna Bell and John Boyd in the BBC. Although Hewitt later abandoned regionalism as a coherent theory, it served or caught its time. My Introductory Essay indicates some artistic and intellectual continuities, including Seamus Heaney's attention to the regionalist era. When Hewitt reviewed Heaney's Death of a Naturalist in 1966, he employed the value- terms of his regionalist aesthetic:Lrm...spare', andrelated Heaney to Ulster writers like Michael McLaverty andPeadar O'Donnell who 'inhabit the same region of our national feeling' .5829
￼At this point MacNeice may seem to have fallen out of the frame. Indeed, his flat Autumn Sequel (1954) contrasts with the evangelical conviction of 'Freehold'. Both these long poems celebrate friends and creative spirits, but the former fails to locate any larger 'knowable community'. What Hewitt criticised as MacNeice's lack of 'roots' may finally show in his inability to reanimate the unifying impulse of Autumn Journal or hiswartime poetry. Yet MacNeice's legacy to his Northern Irish successors had not become wholly aesthetic in that the Kafka-esgue world of his last dark parables reflects the politics of the BBC in London and Belfast. MacNeice took a hand in the three-year fight to get Sam Thompson's Over the Bridge on to the stage: a juncture where culture and politics effectively reunited and won a famous victory over the Unionist establishment which had attempted to suppress the play. Thompson, the working- class socialist who shattered Unionist censorship in a way from which it never quite recovered, was encouraged (to write for the BBC) by Sam Hanna Bell. He was also guided by Bell's friend the literary lawyer and socialist Martin McBirney, later to be assassinated by the IRA. John Hewitt had taught Thompson in a WEA Class. It was MacNeice who had recruited Bell for the BBC. MacNeice consistently used his own clout in the London Features Department to fortify Bell and Boyd in their constructive subversion of Unionist hegemony in BBC Northern Ireland. Douglas Carson has said of these two producers: 'together they democratised local radio'.59 Over the Bridge, which could not have existed without this left-wing literary milieu, without the30
￼Progressive Bookshop and all that, was used by Unionists opposed to Lord Brookeborough (whom the scandal weakened) in their campaign to replace him with Terence O'Neill. And we know what that led to.Douglas Carson, in a lecture partly based on talks with Sam Hanna Bell, has shown how MacNeice's support for Over the Bridge preceded the review in which he greeted it as a revival of the thirties spirit: 'a play about something. Social consciousness seems to have become, among the younger generation, a dirty phrase [so] it is very refreshing to encounter a work such as this which reaffirms the eternal commonplaces of the misery - and the dignity - of man'.60 Over the Bridge, originally scheduled for production at the Belfast Group Theatre in 1957, was dropped when a member of the theatre's board of management set the alarm bells ringing at Stormont. The same man was Head of Programmes at BBC Northern Ireland. In Carson's words:The result was the famous battle which lasted three years. Most of the Group company resigned. Thompson sued the management. They settled out of court, but controversy raged in the press and at Stormont.Behind the scenes Sam Hanna Bell was working for Thompson. MacNeice was less inhibited and took Thompson's side openly. /The BBC was not well pleased ...61Unlike MacNeice, Hewitt lived to rethink his politics andcultural politics in the context of Northern Ireland after October 1968. 'The Coasters', written in 1969 and published in An Ulster Reckoning (1971), has unique authority to tell the
￼Now the fever is high and raging;who would have guessed it, coasting along? The ignorant-sick thresh about in delirium and tear at the scabs with dirty fingernails. The cloud of infection hangs over the city,a quick change of wind and itmight spill over the leafy suburbs.You coasted too long.ere, too, a characteristic trope of the 1930s - metaphors of physical and psychic illness - finds a belated occasion. In 1986 Hewitt published Freehold and Other Poems. This collection reprinted (for the first time in book-form) both 'The Bloody Brae', product of the pessimistically political 1930s, and the title-poem, product of the optimistically cultural 1940s. In his preface to An Ulster Reckoning Hewitt ruefully recalls 'an apparent softening of the hard lines and a growing tolerance between the two historic communities'. Freehold also juxtaposes two poems which sugggest how cultural visions must accept the reality and challenge of political forces. 'Ulster Names', written in 1950, proclaims the regionalist spirit: 'I take my stand by the Ulster names,/each clean hard name like a weathered stone'. Its dark twin, 'Postscript, 1984' lists:Banbridge, Ballykelly, Darkley, Crossmaglen, summoning pity, anger and despair,by grief of kin, by hate of murderous mentill the whole tarnished map is stained and torn, not to be read as pastoral again.Two complementary poems by Hewitt and MacNeice can be interpreted as epitaphs or elegies for their own literary- political endeavours, and for the utopianism of a generation.32
￼Hewitt's 'A Local Poet' (1975), which again revises and darkens an earlier text, measures the distance between ambition and achievement:He followed their lilting stanzasthrough a thousand columns or more,and scratched for the splintered couplets in the cracks on the cottage floor,for his Rhyming weavers fell silentwhen they flocked through the factory door.Besides regretting the failure of literature to unite weavers,factory-workers and the 'mannerly' middle-class poet, the poem —Hf itl CPiAt h i’s -registers the obduracy of the political 'problems andcleavages'62 wh-is-h had been Hewitt-'-s starting-point:He'd imagined a highway of heroesand stepped aside on the grassto let Cuchullain^'s chariot through,^ and the Starry Ploughmen pass; but he met the Travelling Gunmaninstead of the Galloglass.MacNeice's 'Epitaph for Liberal Poets' (1942) foresees the obsolescence of free thought, the death of the individual and the poet, the triumph of 'Those who shall supersede us and cannot need us - /The tight-lipped technocratic Conquisitadores'. Yet MacNeice did not cease to question the Conquistadores any more than Hewitt ever relinquished his local burdens.33
￼Ulster, considered as a region and not as the symbol of any particular creed, can, I believe, command the loyalty of every one of its inhabitants. For regional identity does not preclude, rather it reguires, membership of a larger association. And, whether that association be, as I hope, of a federated British Isles, or a federal Ireland, out of that loyalty to our own place, rooted in honest history, in familiar folkways and knowledge, phrased in our own dialect, there should emerge a culture and an attitude individual and distinctive, a fine contribution to the European inheritance and no mere echo of the thought and imagination of another people and another land.53But in 1953 Hewitt missed an important chance to implement his vision when Unionist intrigue denied him the directorship of the museum. In the same year he wrote 'The Colony', which translates his cultural meditations into his most sophisticated poetic model of Ulster politics. The poem permits itself one utopian simile:'as goat and ox may graze in the same field/and each gain something from proximity'.Regionalism, the guest for 'a native mode', certainly improved on textbook socialism as a stimulus to Hewitt's poetry. But he had never been only a man of the Left, - hence, perhaps,John Wilson Foster's remark about conservatism - always evincing the holistic ambition of Belfast's Victorian polymaths. Hewitt refers to 'my thought' as to something more organic and moral than theoretical. His copiousness and didacticism smack of the nineteenth century as well as the 1930s. To the detriment of art, he generally had something to say. As Foster shows,54 another ancestral prompter must be Methodism. Vivian Mercier has analysed the evangelical origins of the Irish Literary Revival, and a similar missionary spirit links the Hewitt who urged28