￼T\tjo pAcec-fefXUc _L_SffiTKRTBOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDHafiway\upYhe remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is a lor§walii66poBshed plaster, with mysterious golden women paj*ed;bn the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the cloads. Tiwnty of these frescoes have survived since the endof the fifth century.TheStfirrorWall is covered with graffiti: hundreds of songs nfating.to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, mediants;-,travellersandBuddhistmonksduringtheeighth, nintianditenth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, prolably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath thqgortraits, where the words were written on the wall: love pcmns;. satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebationsof beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes painfulexperiences.Rhfiard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the Minor Wall. Some keep close to the intricate forms andmeaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they are freeuersions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modern voices or combining several songs.2nx &>acX &XHXI The MirrorPOETRY BOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDHalf way up the remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is a long wall of polished plaster, with mysterious golden women painted on the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these frescoes have sur­ vived since the end of the fifth century.The Mirror Wall is covered with graffiti: hun­ dreds of songs relating to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, merchants, travellers and Buddhist monks during the eighth, ninth and tenth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, probably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath the portraits, where the words were written on the wall: love poems, satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebrations of beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes pain­ful experiences.Richard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the Mirror Wall. Some keep close to the intricate forms and meaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they are free versions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modem voices or combin­ ing several songs.za 0 86327 221 5 k/l\m§ ! JSj s Wall O& >$r 1 r0 r1 ►n1 O CRICHARD MURPHYfh
￼
￼"1%BIQ0DAX6 BQd:ISBN 1-85224-093-8 \            9781852240936781852 240936£4.9.p vKL*C ONTO VJW vT’O1N85224 093 81 85224 092 X£10.95POETRY BOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDHalf way up the remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is a long wall of polished plaster, with mysterious golden women painted on the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these frescoes have survived since the end of the fifth century.The Mirror Wall is covered with graffiti: hundreds of songs relating to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, merchants, travellers and Buddhist monks during the eighth, ninth and tenth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, probably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath the portraits, where the words were written on the wall: love poems, satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebrations of beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes painful experiences.Richard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the Mirror Wall. Some keep close to the intricate forms andmeaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they are free versions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modern voices or combining several songs.POETRY BOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDHalf way up the remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is a long wall of polished plaster, with mysterious golden women painted on the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these frescoes have sur­ vived since the end of the fifth century.The Mirror Wall is covered with graffiti: hun­ dreds of songs relating to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, merchants, travellers and Buddhist monks during the eighth, ninth and tenth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, probably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath the portraits, where the words were written on the wall: love poems, satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebrations of beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes pain­ ful experiences.Richard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the Mirror Wall. Some keep close to the intricate forms and meaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they are free versions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modern voices or combin­ ing several songs.r1QDDAX6BQDK3L^00% tAlNL&ICOPAcjcCL P7YPQX\^/YO<^j _____L/RICHARD MURPHY
￼2)2 '''v'/7u|«c<?<°. - A*~v\ ?r\2* v^ vCV?rr fMse ^r
￼nsx> Half way up the remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is aPOETRY BOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDPOETRY BOOK SOCIETY TRANSLATION AWARDHalf way up the remote fortress of Sigiriya in Sri Lanka is a long wall of polished plaster, with mysterious golden women painted on the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these frescoes have sur­ vived since the end of the fifth century.The Mirror Wall is covered with graffiti: hun­ dreds of songs relating to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, merchants, travellers and Buddhist monks during the eighth, ninth and tenth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, probably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath the portraits, where the words were written on the wall: love poems, satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebrations of beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes pain­ful experiences.Richard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the Mirror Wall. Some keep close to the intricate forms and meaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they are free versions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modern voices or combin­ ing several songs.long wall of polished plaster, with mysterious golden women painted on the rock above, who seem to be dancing in the clouds. Twenty of these frescoes have survived since the end of the fifth century.O c£&£The Mirror Wall is covered with graffiti: hundreds of songs relating to these cloud nymphs, composed by nobles, merchants, travellers and Buddhist monks during the eighth,TheMirror Wallninth, and terrth centuries. These songs or lyrics were sung, H probably with vina, flute and drums, in the gallery beneath X the portraits, where the words were written on the wall: love cnpoems, satires and curses; happy, witty, ironical and sad celebrations of beautiful, erotic, festive and sometimes painful experiences.X5SJ Richard Murphy's poems were inspired by the songs of the OMirror Wall. Some keep dose to the intricate forms and >$X meaning of their Old Sinhala originals. More often they arefree versions, elaborating particular images and ideas, bringing in modern voices or combining several songs.r1 rB1Q0DAX6 BQDK5ISBN 1-“85224-092-X > „            9781852240929X9 781852 240929CP§f1TiRICHARD MURPHY/0 <AViB1QDDAX6 BQDK51 85224 092 X £10.95ia '938 v(Z,P /V K .'CH ^ 2 .I3-■-i