￼The trees here, though the wind leave off, never unbend. Likewise when he sat the stick retainedThe shape of the sixty years he had limped and leaned. He would haul from under the bed with the crook-endHis bundle of photographs and the soldier’s pay-book, The usual service medals and a card o/two in silk.The marriage bed was draped to the floor like a catafalque And he hauled the War from under it. And when he spokeOf the craters at Ypres he used the pool on Pool GreenAs measure, and the island’s entablement of brambles when He spoke of the wire. He rose, drinking gin,Massive, straighter than his stick, and boys were shownAt the hoisting of his trouser up the sunless calfA place that shrank like Lazarus from being raised, A flesh the iron seemed only lately to have bruised. And if one, being bidden and not in disbelief,Put in the hand to prove him right whoThat he was past hurt there—probingIn that still weeping place the fingers Wondering between them an angle of iron grit.For year by year his flesh, till he was dead,Evicted its shrapnel, as the living groundPuts out for the Parson or the Schoolmaster to find, Scouring at leisure, another arrow head.
￼6. Spring TideThe summer moon was terrible. It beamedLike Christ on Lazarus. Nobody now,In daylight, can distinguish what he dreamed/ And what he saw, in night-clothes at the window.It was like All Souls when everything lostAnd the smothered dead struggle to rise. Around Midnight the moon hauled hand over fist £^sheet by sheet the waters were unwound.But nothing was recovered. Still the sand,That we saw white and phosphorescent, levels The slopes and pleasant laps of landAnd stops the doorways and the fires and wells.The curlews cried like springs starting to run. Then sleep began to fill us and we feltA weeping rise and flow. Now in the sunThe sea is brimful and our cheeks are wet and salt.34
￼w/c®® o(7.Sheer nowhere: the landEnds, the rocks pile dufnbly where they fell, And hold for any life nearer to ours than lichen There is none; the usefulWood of wrecks whitens beyond our reach.Rain passes, rain on the sea, and sweetensW ith all its copious fallby not one measurable jot the expanse of salt. Clinging to islands weCamping with our dead around a sunken plainSuch as we are, late on,Want above all things passage to one another, Aid and the sharing of wellsAnd not to swell our bitterness beyondThe normal allocation of tears^ .35