￼XVI.^Plaudit humus Boree ^ugijim ridens exulis.Pullulant arboreenodis come patulis. Gaudet Rea coronarinovis frontem flosculis, olim gemens carcerari nivis sevis vinculis.Felix morbus, qui sanari nescit sine morbo pari.Ethera Favoniusinduit a vinculis.Ornat mundum Cyprius sacris dive copulis.Castra Venus renovari novis ovat populiset tenellas copulari blandis mentes stimulis.Felix morbus, qui sanari nescit sine morbo pari.(Tuum, Venus, haurio venis ignem bibulis. Tuis, Flora, sicio favum de labellulis.Flora, flore singulari preminens puellulis,solum sola me solari soles in periculis.Felix morbus, qui sanari nescit sine morbo pari.66
￼pPeter's lament(People celebrate, at easenow that winter's driven out; on the newly verdant trees frilly knobs of blossom sprout.Earth's bedecked with cheerful frondage, waving wreaths of buds about,^after lying long in bondage chained by winter's icy drought.Love's infection fimth its healing m a fellow-sufferer's feeling.i ,, / ( —-(fihter now the western breeze, putting mist and clouds to flight; enter Venus, who decreesall her creatures should unite,male with female, in communion, following their appetite;people, too, are linked in union, urged by her to love's delight.Love's mfectuni firttb its healing }n'a felloiv-sufferer's feeling..Through my veins I feel the hot funnels of divine desire;Flora's mouth's the honey-pot which alone can quench my fire.Flora, flower of uniqueness, perfect pattern all admire,only you can salve my weakness with the succour I require.Love's infection finds its healing (X .in a felloiv-sufferer's feeling.K u/Ck,C^CCj leJOU-v w - X £ e d S, pjX H67
￼Rapit nobis ludere dictis livor emulis.Nos obliquis ledere gaudens lingue iaculis.Nolo volens absentari, votis uror pendulis. Fugi, timens te notarinigris fame titulis.Felix morbus, qui sanari nescit sine morbo pari.In discessu dulcibus non fruebar osculis. Salutabas nutibus pene loquens garrulis.Fas non erat pauca fari. Fuere pro verbulis, quas, heu, vidi dirivarilacrimas ex oculis.Felix morbus, qui sanari nescit sine morbo pari.
￼Envy with its bilious tongue drove us from our tender play; hypocrites and gossips flung cutting weapons at their prey.Now we burn in separation; all my being longed to stay,but to save your reputation I was forced to go away.Love's s its healing i*r a fellow-sufferer's feeling.Rather anything than partwith no kiss; but it was so: what was in your silent heart(L^ QODAVCcUfluids￼only gestures dared to show.Words were banned; but your revealingeyes and features let me know all the pain you were concealingwhen your tears began to flow.Love's infection finds its healing j ) t a felloiv-sufferer's feeling.69
￼XVII.Dum iuventus floruit, licuit et libuit facere, quod placuit,iuxta voluntatem currere, peragere carnis voluptatem.Amodo sic agere, vivere tam libere, talem vitam ducereviri vetat etas, perimit et eximitleges assuetas.Etas ilia monuit, docuit, consuluit, sic et etas annuit:'Nichil est exclusum Omnia cum veniacontulit ad usum.Volo resipiscere, linquere, corrigere quod commisi temere;deinceps intendam seriis, pro vitiisvirtutes rependam.70
￼A new leafWhile my youth was fresh and green my routine was quite serene:all was pleasure; 1 was keenon the scent of action,quick to chase and then embracecarnal satisfaction.Now my age begins to tell: raising hell 's all very well, but the middle years compelsober introspection;then a man will try to planchanges of direction.Youth advised me to be free — actively encouraged me; when I ventured on a spreethere was no restriction:'Go ahead,' my conscience said,with its benediction.Now it's time for penitence, continence and abstinence; now I want to learn some sense;henceforth I'll be graver:I'll go straight, and cultivateways to Heaven's favour.