￼Natural WondersiThe lovely boywashes himself all overin a ski-hut. His mother sends a new suit every year.‘He only cares about his mathematics.’iiHe’s tired.He hates the snow.He can’t stop masturbating.Each little death,each floating point cries Heaven, where are you nou/fiiiThe handsome mountain-dwelling monk lies dead. Something is wrong with the electric fan.His secret love-affair exceeds his wildest dreams,while here on earththe other monks are lapsing.Note: In the technical term ‘decimal floating point’, the sequence 2658 13, for example, would be used to represent the number 2.658 x io 13, or 26580000000000.
￼LottyA white South African depressiveis kneeling on the veldt in Waterberg training the beam of an electric torchonto a little garden, where a king and queen in white are watering their fungi-beds.Baby soldiers wriggle on the paths,and lift their heads from time to timeto suck the lovely globules formingon the queen’s black jaws . . .He kneels by the nursery all night.It’s true he isn’t well.His wife died, and he lived alonewith Tame Toktokkie X and Tame Toktokkie Y. His six-inch mother scorpion,who carried sixteen babies on her backin pairs, died recently as well.He used to call her Lotty, or Carlotta,his mother’s and his grandmother’s name,
￼LucyThey lie down naked in the spider room where legs are ears. They listen as they spin.Then Lucy takes him for a walk. My dear, in half an hour, she is in love with him.Ulrike Meinhof, sing angelically; Mongol invaders, bathe in padded light;it is the Buddha passing on his elephant. Lucy, take your love and follow him.BenjaminI am so closeI could kiss you, Benjamin.(Our eyes never meet.) Do you remember slicing shins like fruit?Do you remember stepping through the snow with nothing on?(I’m pulling off your jeans. I’m very close.)You dance and hideand live on peaslike necklaces.(She wishes you would smile, but you don’t.)You’re sleeping on the floorbeside your rawhere crow-black songsrevolve, revolve, revolve.(Your mummy thinks you are a sort of ghost.)
￼A Skiving AccidentEven the humble moledreams while he sleeps,a little man as clean as a tomato.Lives in hills, dreaming of a beetle coming ’The presidentsdream of the presidents,breaking their hearts on the piste. Pineapple Lip Balm. Blood on her mitts.