￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:43 pm Page 23.Hera’s Spring'Nothing mill be left o f Jeserac but a galaxy o f electrons frozen in the heart o f a crystal. I shall sleep, and without dreams. Then one day, perhaps a hundred thousand years from now, I shallfind myselfin a new body, meeting those who have chosen to be my guardians..A t first I will know nothing of Diaspar and will have no memories of what I was before. Those memories will slowly return, at the end ofmy infancy, and I will build upon them as I movefor­ward into my new cycle o f existence. ’ ARTHUR C. CLARKEjThe City and the StarsMissing his noisy play around thehouse, and remembering the time was nodoubt near, she hurried out, unkempt asshe was, andfound him at last, pale-facedand tearstained, hunched on the weir bank - nofishing-rod in sight - plunged in himself, his pain. With a motherly tendernessshe wiped his eyes with her skirt-hem; she knew; she gently questioned him; and said:Believe me, dear, though it will seem strange to you, I have wept too for all thesethings you mention - and others that may­ be have not yet started to haunt youagain. Do you recall, for instance,the dark coppery flowers on the lowtrees? the waterfalls, or methane-falls- call them what you like - leaping off cliffs? the strong, live winds, and violet skyflashing with great clouds? And I expectyou have walked many a time with your husband on those mountain-slopes as bright as metal, with thunder laughing inthe ground, and clear red flame exploding above you? I know / have —though with,as it happens, a wife beside me- a dear woman...I too have been there,Jeserac; a terribly long timeago, but it’s still precious to me.23
￼-0 - lio'bToday isn’t the time to convinceyou that these eroded hills, blue sky,green woods, not to mention the speckled fish you like catching, are themselves not unbeautiful...this first day, you’ve aright to feel desperate. I recallmyself (though how many others in between!) writhing in the ammonia-snow I’d always thought of as home, and was to again - tormented by theglobe your mind is filled with, shrieking at my sisters to leave me in peace! Poor mites, they ran off and told everyonethat a yanu was inside me! - This,darling, was near Procyon, the lightyour father taught you to find last night.- Oh, don’t think I don’t understand; it’s the beings you gave yourself in loveto - not moons or cliffs! And the dull ache of this you must expect never towholly leave you. How often one finds oneself wondering - and the worst of it’s being completely unable toshare your dark thoughts with anyone else -I where is, say, Kersti? - a granddaughter I once had somewhere in Boo|-«H*)tes; in which of the far-flung micro-filesof our cosmic city Diasparis that beloved pattern crystallised;and where will she —or he- emerge again? Yet one knows there can be no answer. Only the dumb Selector knows that.Still, it’s the way of Hera’s Spring; we have to count our blessings. —I see that too hasn’t come back yet, dear! It would soon, so I may as well remind you.Ages and ages ago, on thisvery planet (in re-emerginghere, we’ve come home, in the deepest sense), men, who had previously ‘died’, as24Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:43 pm Page 24,
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:43 pm Page 25e,though they were cattle or sheep, found out the secret of immortality....Still doesn’t bring it back? - Just vaguely! Well, anyway, after they’d finishedrejoicing, they found that, after all,the threatening shears were things they couldn’t do without. It’s said the daffodilswithered in the poets’ verses; nothingseemed beautiful when nothing would pass away! - in fact, they found the prospectsso deadly they clamoured for death tobe restored. Instead, their scientiststhought up a middle way, called Hera’s »Spring, (I don’t know who gave it that name). But it came from the way Hera, ‘queenof the heavens’ (you’ve heard of her inthis world) renewed her virginity,that is her purity, each year, by bathing in the spring of Canathos.It fits. The spring we step into isthe frozen heart of a crystal, from which we emerge, having just held our breaths, maybe a million years later.This first time is the worst, Jeseracdear - your homesickness, if you like, is focused, not radiated. When youhave had, like me, almost as manyparents alone as there are stars outon these sharp, moonless nights - in fact, when I look up, to whatever point inthe sky, I know I’ll face a dozenable to pierce through me, hazy orbright, each with a dozen bereavements -you’ll find the ache is a thing you can’tdo without either, in some queer way...But here I am, talking as if I’mantique, instead of being quite ayoungster in the city, not all thatmuch older or wiser than your smallbrother Helderr, whose first world this25
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:43 pm Page 26,?is! - and who, if I know anything,has woken up howling for my milkby this time! You stay here, Jeserac; come home to us when you feel ready, or hungry!PomegranateEach year more clearly you can see her dark flowers wither to the sick light, or crush to our tighter embrace,as she picks up her bag and her coat, drifts out to facethe statutory six-months with her mother.She turns to my heart’s cog; rounded, no longer the child the courts shared between us, as a pomegranate cleft: small need any more for the fury who would have leftme nothing...though God knows I have never reviledher. ‘Be good to her,’ I say, this morning; ‘give hermy —®(I cannot finish). ‘And - forget me while you’re there.’ ‘You both say that!’ She flicks her eyes...‘Father, must I go?’My green shoot, Kore, dawdles now at the brightening river’s ferry - waves once - head bent, March uncabling her hair - then shoulders her bag, full of books I’ll expect her to know.26/
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:43 pm Page 27.Cygnus ARemoving hairgrips, nail-varnish, pensively brushing Black hair down to the blackBra, scattering a thick perfume on the night,You’ve time to read me pointed textsFrom the Gideons’ Bible propped by the red-stained kleenex Till I must shut my eyes tightWhile you slipOff (still that ludicrous reserve)Your diaphanous half-slip.But I prefer to gaze over the dark rooftopsAnd talk to you over my shoulder.Somewhere out there, love, near-neighbour Rigel Winks its white Chaucerian lightFrom Orion’s heel; taking its petty flight From the peaks of the EagleBurning throughHitler, by Deneb and Altair,Falls Vega’s vulturous blue;Cambering Perseus covers half the sky,His spring from the weeping, huddled sisters, To see if he can reach AndromedaBefore the formless monster lands - Cassiopeia stretches out her hands;And out there too’s the glareO f yellow CapellaAnd red, bull-eyed Aldebaran.Yet since, sweet, all my stellarFriends are in fact outshone and liquidatedBy the sun streaming from the green shade Suspended on this window over flickers of you, I let myself go on and onPast Deneb, into the dark breast of the Swan Where only the radio-T elescope,Picking up its grating noisesHas any real hope27
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:44 pm Page 28/Of finding out that such a thing exists - To a celestial catastropheGreater than most at various times enacted In this Trust House - a cataclysm Unforeseeable by their worst pessimism- T o two galaxies attractedInto each otherAt a slow thousand miles a second Transformed to a smotherWhich astronomers cannot untangle; Cygnus A....So girlish, now that your hollow mouthhas shed its lipstick flavour, you hold my hand Preventively, I kiss h!ack\hair,Your eyes shut tight in pseudo-tragic prayer,Your weekend penates andMy cupidonClutter the bedside-table besideThe white text ofStJohn.What must it be to have been born inside Such a fantastic complication -To pull aside a Cygnian tryst-house curtain And watch the overwhelming mergeAs whistling suns and planets all converge! For a moment to feel uncertainIf one’s discreteGalaxy will ever emergeWith all its stars complete,But only for a moment - the chances are That not two single stars will getToo entangled, as the run-through takes its course In the next millenium; no glacialFate is ready, sweet, to quench an outer-spatial Swan-light, though scoresO f spheres sail byEach second - blues, golds and reds In a greased, fabulous sky.28
￼1 10/11/92 2:44 pm Page 29,We’re sure to see two ‘silver plates’ unpair Round the Year of our Lord 90,000 -Though, really, five hundred million years ago These ‘lovers’ fled away, despiteCuriosity at Jodrell Bank tonight; No doubt by this time snowHas covered overHas heard the excuse of lovers:‘But that was in another galaxy,And besides, the star is dead!’While on live red-dwarfs, other will see St John Shine in your eyes, an aeon hence,Recording, with their brilliant instruments, That the red-shift heaven’s undergoneSo shyly, doesn’t veilCompletely the Magellanic Cloud,Though all the space-trips fail./29
￼I3(£> /Requiem for AberfanOn 21 October in the Welsh coal-mining village ofAberfan, Tip number 7, containing waste or slurry from the mine, slipped and overwhelmed Pantglas Junior School. Twenty-eight adults and 116 children were killed: a generation.Magnates whose sweated legions crucifiedThe valleys, washed their soft white hands, although The children died before they died.Brethren who rode their God in on the tideO f weeping, hawk this good comfort, that we owe Our deaths to One on green hill crucified.The child whose dream, the child whose drawing tried To tell somebody that the hill would flow,Knew that they died before they died.Workmen who chose and staked this mountainside, Their ankles lush with streams, a school below, Learn on what green hill they were crucified.Sleepers who from their sheets saw the coal slide And bury, seven nights before it happened, know The children died before they died.Mothers, whose off-to-death sharp voices denied Fevers and fancies, following at each cock-crow The road they drove them to be crucified,Die on the ninth-hour before they died.30Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:45 pm Page 30,
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:47 pm Page_31^^_II.There was no keeping out, that day, or keeping inEither. They set up roadblocks, but you couldn’t stopAll Britain pitching in and trying to help.Or gawp. I stopped one car myself, a whole family,From the Midlands, ‘Is this the place where all those kidsAre buried?’ he said. But mostly they wanted to help,Anything they could do. Which wasn’t much.They didn’t have a chance, you see, didn’t have a chance...Yet, you couldn’t seem to keep them in. The children.Not all that lot could. My missus and me, we saw DavidA score of times, I suppose, that Friday. He was everywhere! Running up to the front-door, about to bang it shut,About to turn the corner. Always about to, always three of us,In the road, in the crowd. Once, I still swear I did see him,In Moy Road, then he vanished. There were the rumours, you see, Of some being found alive. The whole terrace was like that,Full of them. No, you couldn’t shut them in. It was likeHoles in the slurry you couldn’t see. There wereMore kids about the place than normal, I’d say.Funny, it was the same even when I’d found DavidIn Bethania. Not a mark on him, there wasn’t. Like a doll.We still hoped. It hadn’t happened, do you know?III. The FatherThe day, you came, I felt her turn from me. Absence, fullbreasted, coasting at my side, Straining for different hungers - rightfully.With no regrets, my pit-black spirit died And rose like waste through galleries of you. Cast like a tip, I saw and sang my pride,The first-born, inexhaustible, the newSeam, richer, deeper than all Rhondda. A man Gets born again out of his wife, I knew,31
￼Thomas 11-51 10/11/92 2:47 pm Page 32,eWhat did it matter that the more you ranInto your mother’s heart, the closer I felt iTo an eighth spewed cone outtopping Aberfan?With no regrets. And yet have I not knelt Begging God that His curse should overwhelm Me also, so confirmed was I in guiltAt having willed this on you, in some dreamI had forgotten maybe. When, as the arc-Lights flickered on the ant-hill, I heard your screamRise faintly from a desk, miles deep, the black Slurry was in myself. Why did we pause?Now, when the shuddering cage transports us backTo that rise up to hell - untold, we knew — Always, I hear, faintly, unreachably,You cry where my own evil fell on you.IV. The BrotherI steal into his room, with my pack of cards, A. And play\^ patience under his photo,Hoping to tempt him.I get tired of it. It never comes out.So I go to the mountain, quite a lot.I remember we had a story onceAbout how somebody led these children into the mountain, And there was a lame boy who couldn’t go.Mummy doesn’t know, but they have parties in the grave. Last night, in my sleep, I heard it.I was in disgrace for telling on them, but I didn’t.Robert called me, Sissy.The terrace is empty. All summer it’s Sunday.If I showed him my cards, offered to let him win Only so he would play with me, play,Would he let me in?32