￼Kafka’s FuneralIt should have been raining leadthat Prague June.More probably, though, the sun shone instead. The sky would have beenvery indifferent.It was not a large gathering bunched at the graveside, silent. Max Brod, humped and intent, gave the one speech, a lament,a claim, an honouring.The box was ready to go, Kafka Iat last/becominglthe molehe always felt he was, to stealalong the winding tunnels of his secret castle,or to burrow as he used to, furledunder his sick man’s bedclothes, still and safe, and see himself sailhis books away adventuring into the realand difficult world.The distraction when it cameam o Pe-rccame from that world, a woman, dark,^Cl11 1 1 Ulll llldL uUllUj a YVUlliCllI, UdlIYjV twenj^sh, who brokedecorum, and in the shocky / 'yof a moment’s numbsurprise, flung hair,arms, body and passionate wailing in a wild restrainingstruggle over the gapingtrench. Kafka’s father38fr$&ee«»vu*v<;} <
￼turned his wide back.Someone or other helped her, bent to her trembling shoulders, lent her a kind of calm, and the spenttears dried on her cheek.The itch of them she would winceaway from even when her small name slid from sight, and her rich hair paled,and the man that she thought she heldhers only was everyone’s.These two had fused and faded. Soon his dark books would glow in a space whirling at some indefinite distance from that agonised, now more or lessirrelevant, Prague afternoon.