￼Atlantis(for Lotte and Hugh Shankland)It dies hard, the notion of a just people;The wish that there should have been once mutual aidDies very hard. Through fire, through ghastly ash and any Smothering weight of water still we imagineA life courteous and joyful; see them lightly clad Loving the sun, the vine and the grey olive.Over the water, from trading, they come home winged With sails, their guide and harbinger the white dove.CHRONICLE IThe sea suddenly stood up vertical, sky-high,Bristling with the planks of their peaceful ships.The earth roared like a bull. They said Poseidon, Breaker of lintels, was shaking them. There was fire too Glaring like a red eye. But the unkindestWas of all the four elements the purestAnd to breathing man his being: the airClagged and precipitated in cankers of pumiceAnd thereafter for weeks in a fine dust.Wherever the living air was welcome nowAsh entered and the hearts of houses ceased;Their eyes, hurt by blows, were quite extinguished;Their mouths, agape, were stopped. Ash filledAnd softly embedded household pots, shroudedFrescoes of air-beafing dolphins. Who survivedWhen the sun had*wept and blinked its eyesight clear Lame in the lungs saw only dustLying now quiet as snow. One inch of such -That is from nail-end to the knuckle of the thumb -Will render infertile the fruitful, the man-nurturing earth For perhaps ten years. To them now kneeling on rock Who had salted no fields, burned no olive grovesAnd poisoned nobody’s wells, there remained no rodTo sound the ells, the fathoms, the generations of ash.----44
￼vK-The cinder. On Santorini the common people,Scratching a living in the old ash and pumice,remembered Kalliste and watched and prayed. But a scholar, A believer in Atlantis, when the steam had thinnedPulled out alone in a small boat. How greatMust have been his disappointment if he thoughtSome glimmer of Atlantis might be vouchsafed himncrea^e toCHRONICLE IIHow deep below? None of the warring nations Had length of chain to fathom at what depth Atlantis lay. Nobody anchored there. But then - In the days of death by impalement or the ganch When Christian citizens of Candia ateThe besieging Turk—with a roar, witnesses say, Like innumerable bulls, the sea, or the earth Under the waters, rendered up to the surfaceA new island, called nowadays Kaimeni,noespectf(jywho had doneGiltlheir lost lovingkindness and wisdom: he saw Only black smoking slag and ash, and smelled An intimation of Christian Hell. AlsoThe hot sea soon uncaulked his punt and rowing Desperately heavily for home he sankIn depths well known to be unfathomable.ke koped Tor Siroe however ckm treturnatW<2-hvoteA"twoI m e - S r h e A :(Wh© had done ao eipeoa.1 wr©r\& wickedkoj^d Scmt) kowzoeu Atm lo t<mact\or>45
￼ChronicleScabby with salt the shipwreck wonderingUpon what shore, among what manner of savagesHe was tossed up, found himself receivedWith a courtesy near to veneration. LiesWere ready on his tongue but he foundHis rescuers, his hosts, discreet or indifferentAnd asking nothing. Only once he was bathedAnd dressed in clothes held by for the occasionThere was a pause, a silence, and his fear returned Imagining sacrifice. Solemnly, deferring,They led him into the church. The congregationWas the island’s marriageable girls. He must choose, They said, one for his bride. Any strangerShowing himself indignant or lasciviousHeard behind him the whetting of knives. The wise man Walked modestly two or three timesThe length of the aisle and among the girls afterThe heart’s true inclination made his choice.A priest of the church married them there and then.Next morning early with a harder courtesyHe was fetched aboard a manned ship and soPassed back into the sea-lanes. Some thus restoredPut off the escapade, some boasted and someWandered thereafter for the one bride. SheAccording to the custom of the island was courted by the best And if she were seen to have taken the stranger’s seedThen by the very best, and married in her third month.IThe second husbands shone like full moonsIn reflected sun, their stepchildrenWere called ‘the strangers’ and enjoyedLove and privileges above the rest. The boysGrew proficient with boats, eyed the horizonsAnd one morning departed, courting shipwreck. The girls Excited a restlessness but themselvesWaited, knowing they were most likely to be chosen When out of the sea one morning a salt man crawled.46/
￼(T. "JV.et'e. The sorv /SuniumDawns may be rose and dove-grey Evenings blue-black like Persephone Lovely. But the culmination at noon At sheer midsummerThat is incomparable.Remember the bay, the water clear As nectar in a calyx,'«nd-hew-the-son Brought our perception of carnal life To the burning point.Then the horizons had no attractionThere was no drowsiness, we watchedAnd bathed and sweetened the mouth with fruit.Where promontories embrace an arena of sea At noon the bivalve openedThe mollusc wingsThe lips.