￼DAVID CONSTANTINEDear Mrs Thatcher,OxfordjfJ)ear ,C o ^ ld VK>0 ry\fc Wva(ettfcrt/ ht.d ICv-<t»S p«.ac:vl\Gd to «v\ vKjyjr l^JsT'b v /t 2_\r-2^vW\ r\A>^>G6 'I’Vvfcyv't oJt IMost people never wanted you. Fewer and fewer want you now. Riots, mass disaffection, beggars on the streets, many thousands sleeping out, a fifth of the nation stuck in poverty, a large increase in public ugliness...Will you be handing it on soon to a successor? To Mr Tebbit, he is the fit person. You made him possible, he ought to inherit.I teach. You don’t like teachers. I teach in a university. You like them least of all. But here I shan’t be repeating our professional grievances. I want you to know about something positive you have done. There is a lot of talk about the demoralisation of teachers, so perhaps you will be pleased to learn that, as a teacher, I do not feel at all demoralised and I have many colleagues in the universities and many good friends in our maligned public sector schools who do not feel in the least demoralised either. On the contrary, we owe to you a very clear sense of purpose and responsibility. You are that against which I have defined my job as a teacher. By ‘you’ I meanyour convictions, the policies ensuing out of them, your practice and your tone, and not just yours but alsoyour government’s - Mr Tebbit’s Weitqnjchauung, say, and the voice ofyour little gedly-Mr- Gammer-- and not iust theirs but your voters’too, the triumphant spirit that was among them when you were riding highest. Teaching, for eleven years now, has been an act of contradiction.It* \ ca.n3>Enei sp-io at,"to'?)ireVTAj wtcij NcTlas."tht bfeirnrvHft. |hSok0 in,Don’t get me wrong. I don’t teach sociology, nor even history (in which you have been showing some interest of late) I only teach literature, poetry especially, and don’t be thinking your name is forever on my lips, it isn’t, the contradiction I am speaking o f is nota matter of daily dispute, it is fundamental, it is my basis and my inspiration. A teacher’s subject need not be one easily “politicised”for his or her teaching to be an act of opposition to you and all your convictions and all your works. Tke-»tery premisc„qf-teaehtng—is-^ \ ) contrary to~yattr-gove.-nmetr,r. 'Should a government be judged according to the idea it holds of what a human being is or might be and of what human society is and might become? We shall do best, I am sure, not to ask for_o,>/\jetu louaA
￼DAVID CONSTANTINE 53anything very special in that way from the governments we elect: something modest, neutral, not too lofty, not too low either. But you and your Tory Party have gone abysmally beneath even so modest a hope or expectation. I wonder when there was last a British Government whose idea of the human being and of human society was as low as yours has been. Perhaps in your history syllabus such questions will be addressed. For what goals and ideals have you put to the people in these eleven years? The lowest, the most selfish, the narrowest, the merely mercantile. You have consistendy brought out the worst in people and given it your blessing. We have seen in public office figures and behaviour that previous administrations, Labour or Toty, would have blushed to acknowledge —and seen them cocksure and triumphant. You pitched the message very low, you sanctioned desires and tendencies that people, rightly, used to feel ashamed of.& nd so we *,have a nation known abroad for the Falklands War, for connivance / in apartheid and-tiw-hiimbiiiM nfT.ihva, and fin' pnllnlinn And at / C honie,Jjastcad of society,~we have division and self-interest, y — •Teaching literature I am bound to believe that human beings in Britain now are capable of reading things more humane and imaginative and intellectually challenging than the Sun. That is why, whatever texts I teach and without ever mentioning you andyour colleagues by name, my teaching is necessarily an act of opposition. Education altogether is total and fierce resistance to the notion that fit reading for millions of British people is the Sun. Since you have done nothing yourself to counter that notion, and a great deal to encourage it, all teachers as teachers, engaged in the education of young people, are yonr.opposition.Afld-your ethic, if I can call it that: your-view ofvalue only as monetary, yew—■view—efi enterprise only as solitaiy and self- interested,-yow-view-of aspiration only as materialistic, your view of poverty as dese|yed and contemptible, ycw vtew ofwealth as proof ofvirility, your view of the Kingdom of Heaven as power to dole out charity from on higl^- nobody can teach literature and not be, in the whole undertaking, your flat contradiction. Literature widens the imagination and the understanding, it extends compassion, it raises the level of aspiration in personal and social living. Literature, and the teaching of it, become not specifically (about specific issues) ideological, but wholly and intrinsically so by virtue of the ideological context (of your making) in which as teachers we must operate. That is particularly the case in the reading and teaching of poetry. Poetry is, in its very nature, resistant toY<SVJ I/UIY-tcs caj.V5.<sha_ll — fexi i(ooa.o& u ielY C.zlltrd 'THx\xYvCrlSf'V\ 'TkcJ
￼54 DAVID CONSTANTIN1Cacquisitive reading, resistant to acquisitiveness; it is the anti­ commodity, that which refuses to be bought and sold. Poets, when they write, necessarily believe that there is more to life than beggaring their neighbours and brawling for shares in British Gas. Literature denies and opposes you - and again, by ‘you’ I mean the sort of government you have given your name to and the view of people and society you have done your propaganda for.And, finally, teaching, whatever the subject, fosters the spirit of criticism. I had a teacher who used to say that the purpose of education is to increase sales-resistance. That will do well enough as a working motto. You have been remarkable chiefly for your unwillingness to tolerate other opinions. To other opinions, when you could not eradicate them, you have offered contempt or, at best, condescension. Necessarily then, in teaching young people to think for themselves, we a^e peaching a fundamental opposition. What bullies,. -liars and -sleazy' salesmen have appeared on our television screens in your name! Criticism is a social duty, never more so than in these last eleven years. That is why teachers, however contemptuously you treat them, know that their job is an honourable and necessary one.I said I was not demoralised, and I’m not. Still, I concede that the drift has been your way for quite some time. Your market ethic is ftieely ensconced- in the universities now. You have got us evaluating our subjects and our courses in terms of earning power. More graduates go where the money is as quickly as possible. Fewer go into the professions where the money isn’t. I concede all that, but emphasise, as contradiction, what has been equally and even more so my experience: the alertness of young people, their geneiosiiy, thei. sense of justice, and their conviction too that the collaborative venture of teaching and learning is, almost by definition, an act of resistance to your divisive and -mercantile assault. >I always believed that sooner or later a moral revulsion against you would set in. It is happening now. True, some of the outcry is only from people disappointed in the very mean expectations you encouraged them to have. You are failing now even on the level you were aiming at. But more than that I truly believe the revulsion is coming on. Government such as yours is really a belittling of the human being. The idea you represented has been an ignoble one. People are more generous, less selfish, more imaginative, more capable of a just society than you ever gave them credit for. How sad and bitter and poor your decade is beginning to look.Yours sincerely,DAVID CONSTANTINE.David C onstantine is a poet, writer, and Fellow in German at the Queen’s College, Oxford. He has published a novel, Davies, and three poetry collections, including Watchingfor Dolphins (Alice Hunt Bartlett Award) and Madder (Poetry Book Society Recommendation and Southern Arts Literature Prize). Ilis Selected Poems of Friedrich H olderlin appeared this year.. OHVE w o (2 - 01wovjuD wwe /s urttIP'T W Owvoow rv\v>/€lS uF*L-\ T H O sJT OC v /Tpro— ----------------