￼title? AT MADAME TUSSAUD'SorHOME TRUTHS
￼AT MADAME TUSSAUD'SSeeing you in wax is a shock.I hadn't realised you were here.You stare glassily North-West, with a slight curl of the lip.The hand is excellently done, it reminds me of certain intimacies, certain afternoonsin that room with the faulty light switch and the purple sheets. We closed the blindsand locked the doors. Love is so athletic - a wine glass toppled in some amorous antic.Afterwards there were drab days:counsellors, consolers, a cold decline from your sun.Here in wax you are all dignity and tailoring. Thoughtfully I lean forward and startto undress you, hardly noticing the faces swivelling towards me. I work my waythrough garment after garment, like a doctor . whose patient cannot help himself.
￼PONDThe fish have got too big for the pond: first the moorhens disappearedthen the ducks (corner-of-the-eye stuff, nothing strictly attributable).The Canada Geese stayed, but looked as if they knew something they'd rather not think about.A goat on the village green went mad overnight. Then pensioners living nearbystarted to peg out: heart attacks mostlyand always at Meals-on-Wheels time(the body on the rug, the cartons emptied). Alice Weevil went missing altogether.A youth up a ladder, on his mobiledidn't at first hear the flub of something working its way up the rungs to his ankles.'Shit Kev', were his last words, 'What was in that stuff you sold me?I'm seeing something unbelievable - a huge -'\f
￼EMPERORI rise at six, clean my teethwith paste and then powdered coral,scrape my tongue, and rinse my mouth with brandy and water.An hour is spent in the bath,while my papers are read aloud to me.I shave with a razor from Britain;Eau de Cologne is brushed into my chestand then I am dressed. My boots are broken in by my valet, who must always be chosenwith this in mind. I take my snuff boxand my handkerchief, and am at my desk by nine.My troops wait in their bivouacs. Maps unfurl their contours, and all Europe is under my hand.
￼THE MELON SELLERThis man has been standing by his melonsfor hours. He hefts one like a hand grenade,looks mournful. Something is wrong with his salesmanship.Round him, crowds swirl up from the underground. They look through him, as he lollsby his stall, his throat worn out by bawling.Short skirts, brown legs brush past him. He wants to be squeezed, nuzzled, nibbled by mellifluous lemon-scented lovers.He scowls at his golden spoiling fruits, longsto drown them, imagines their fair little heads bobbing down to the sea, leaving him unburdened, footloose, free.Connie Bensley49 Westfields Avenue Barnes, London SW13 OAT
￼BONUSIn the first warm sun of the year,to raise my spiritsfrom zero,I get in my car anddrive to the garden centre and there, pushing a trolleylike an ordinary person,is a Famous Actor.Is it? Yes it is. I hear hisvoice, low but unmistakeable,asking about potting compost.His chestnut hair, his leather jacket gleam. He doesn't lookat the price of anything.I choose Heartsease, while he musesover something more flamboyant.The darkness of his glasses! The brightnessof his signet ring! I turn away,but by chance we pass and repassalong the leafy arboursSBlossom rains down on usfestive as a wedding.At the checkout, our trolleys touchbut I do not speak, except to murmur sorry when his his- Garrya Ellipticafalls on top of my Maidenhair Fern.