￼Kites. Jill maughanThey've lectured him, made him watch the video, read their book-lets, given him a 'talking to'.Approached the solvent abuse people, let the other kids have a go,grown finally despondantfaced with their own failure.The boy knows howto climb ten miles high and hang there like a magnificent coloured kite,he's ridden the blue air waves and slid down the sunsblazing shafts^ helda paradisaic summer in his hands.So what would they swop the glue for? It's been sixteen years of neglect, of a Mam who just stopped caringand a Dad who passed onnothing but his shop lifting skills. Strange, how everyone screamsof Graig's dying but him.He's almost sorryfor the fuss he's in. "It's not death I chase up there", he tries to reassure them but explaining doesn't come easily/without laying some blame, soinstead he insists it's safe,as if convincing them that kites never, never could, fall-out of the sky...
￼Survive. Jill Maughan.Fix rvew lead slates on this roof, put new wood where the old has rotted, replace the leaking framesput in the weather proofed door.We are going to survive.Burst open the window locks^let the breeze blow the dust from around us,rip up the plumbinglay down the floor,we are going to survive.Buy mouse traps for the rodents paint the walls - a hint of hope, fill dustbins with old weeping and throw in the memories too for we are going to survive.
￼rChance.If I leave you in the morning,your hair untidy against the North wind and the onslaught of this rainey seasonand good-bye. If I never come back the same as I am tonight, having followed the headiest route that ledaway, away, forgive me. Blamethe sunlight fidgeting on the pine trees,the call of the mocking bird in the dawnsomewhere else. It's chance that chatters on my shoulder, points out the roadswhich may lead me to forget,and urges me 'go'. How long could we have stayed like this? And why does my whole heart cry, forever..