￼Name1) Nomad2) Everything Ends in Ice3) The Heavy PettingZoo4) Zaghruda5) Burn Brighter6) The Bridesmaid7) The Butcher's Cat8) Keyf9) Attempt at a Beautiful Poem10) Valentine11) Dream of Explosions12) Angel Song13) Registering her Complaint14) Breakfast Poem15) A Friday Night at the End of theMillenium16) Surrender17) Light Entertainment 18) Bangkok19) Losing Control20) Still Life21) Delay22) Butterfly Collector23) Two Attempts to Join the LightVerse Bandwagon: i) Abracadabra ii) Love Yourself24) Fresher25) Poem for my Future Love 26) Hara-kiri27) The Last Love PoemSaved UnderNomad IcePetYed Burn Bride Butcher Rox Attempt Vale Explosio Angel Reg BreakMilleniuSurrender God Bangkok Lost Still Face ButterAbra Love FresherFuture Hari Last
￼1) Nomad2) Everything Ends in Ice3) The Heavy Petting Zoo4) Zaghruda5) Burn Brighter6) The Bridesmaid7) The Butcher's Cat8) Keyf9) Attempt at a Beautiful Poem10) Valentine11) Dream of Explosions12) Angel Song13) Registering her Complaint14) Breakfast Poem15) A Friday Night at the End of the Millennium 16) Surrender17) Light Entertainment18) Bangkok19) Losing Control20) Still Life21) Delay22) Butterfly Collector^il_-<Affe>atrJudabTa--^24) Fresher25) Poem for my Future Love 26) Hara-kiri27) The Last Love Poem
￼Bury me .in desert where sand sweeps A single magnificent gesture;Where there are no trivialities or Tangles, no sticky knots of feelingOr tear-damp patches, human things. It is impossible to harm dunes,Or bruise winds, or burn sun. Desert air is thick with mirage,So the Bedouin breathe dreams andMove, keep moving, not letting home, That heavy hooked numbness, catch them. And the stars? The stars in the desertAre utterly indifferent to me -So much so that I think I may fall In love with stars, those cold-eyed Maps which guide me towards newness.Do not need me, I need youTo leave my body untended,My skin naked and unkissed Beneath the dry, valueless gold.NomadClare foUcxnl.I
￼Everything Ends in IceThe day that I met youWas the first day of sun. I was shiny and new.You thawed me in an hour; Made me mute as a flower - All good clean fun.As I bit through peach fur My longing for you grew. Always knew you loved her, Yet got grazed climbing trees As you swarmed me like bees. I sweated you.Starved of sun, nothing grows, And rain was all I got. Watched my dreams decompose, And lit trees doused in fuel. You were Halloween-cruel.You let me rot.Now, I'm cold as a corpse.My heart is blank with frost. Skies are bleak as my thoughts; And this numbness could slice As I swallow the iceAnd I am lost.CLoje. PoUcvd.2
￼The Heavy-Petting ZooIt's your best friend's 16th birthday party.That's 8 hamster lives, and yet she still wasn't wise enough To realise it would turn into a heavy-petting zoo.Let's put it this way - you wouldn't bring the family,And there's an awful lot of stroking going on.The lounge crawls with muzzy, fuzzy pubic mice.You want to hibernate, but every bedroom is locked.(That soft-haired girl from the Shetlands is offering rides.)You could have been a part of it -For a small price at the door you could havehad them Eating out of your hand by now,Felt that breathy, hot nuzzle-lick,But instead you're floundering in your own sour Vinegar juices, like an ill terrapin.The other girls are beautiful and brittle chicks,Eggs precarious and smashable in the cups of theirbras, And he's with her somewhere.They're probably mewling cutely at each other, Or else she's stripped and pink as a piglet And they're at it like rabbits.It's sickeningly bestial.You hope they get myxomatosis.Yet in your small child's heart you knowThat if he'd called you, you'd have followed him as she did.As a lamb does, whitely and without question.
￼ZaghrudaI try not to recall the darkest timesFor fear that hate will rot away my womb Khun mae mon Soeur daughterYes - we touch long desire feel ache also Yet you branded us whores hurenIn the brothel the Harem (Skirts up round our thighs) We lay back and thought ofKuche - centre of our worldJollof rice dumplings hamii nam lasagna basturma At the suk we purchased food for you with given coinsSari izar veil tarhaThey smothered us We saw but were not seen Invisible people devoured by nightI heard of one Asian who killed herselfWhen you laughed and laughed at the meadowsOf soft dark hair on her limbsWe pasted lead on our skin to make us bleich for you You liked us cripples our feet golden liliesNo ambitions but for you masterWhilst you said come on darling sweetheart kitten Dog querida sweet potato pieIn Borneo menstruating women mustSit on the roof for 3 daysDefloration may involve a sharp stoneOr a fist wrapped in clothAnd of course we love the stink of baby crap!We want to pluck our brows until we weepYou sucked our milk then spat it inour facesThe other week Iran was on the newsMen mutilated their own flesh for Islam / At first I cried with joy to seeThey had caused themselves to suffer also Hallelujah! Fierce sang rouge drippingYed maeOnly then I saw their wounds were as deep as oursSaw the pained desperate smiles as they tried to be strong Three men died that dayOh brother padre We anoint your cutsForgiveness is easyTake our hand and we'll love you Poor sad Don JuanI know we can survive this togethersohn loverwith yaah sanehthrough choicebetween equalsCfare Pollo«l.
￼Poets construct huge firesSo that God may see them from above. The tongue is a flame,And everything fuel for it.They pile on the rotten, dull, broken, And pull off charred skeletons of things Horror burnt off the black bones;Almost bearable.Sometimes love is a casualty, Caught in white heat, left raw, Its dark sticky skinToo painful to be touched -But it is worth it for the blast,The melt, the seconds of brightness. The poet is an alchemist -Even the most sordid and hopeless hurtsCan be licked a scalding gold. Can combust into a momentOf blistering beauty - Sustenance for these cold months.Burn Brighter
￼The BridesmaidI trail behind the bride, watch the dip of the lace At her waist; a brail I could trace with my thumb. The bouquets, which smell as the skin at the back Of her neck must, are beautifully done.Violets for violence. Her gentlest touchCan bruise me, as I cannot stop my bloodFrom racing to meet her, clamouring to pressAgainst the merest brush of sleeve in a tender flood.Her ivory straps are biting her back and I long To slip fingers between her body and them.I have to clutch hard on the flowers to stop myself reaching And slice up my lovesick hands on rose stems.Roses for the razor she shaved her calves withThis morning; as I watched blossoms she dripped in the sink Through steam, as I painted my nails, she talked about love How much she was in it, and him, and what did I think?And the hand which slips a ring on her is not even shaking. It sickens with anger, this body which has obeyedLove now for a year, which knows every colour her hairCan turn in the light, and is achingly always her maid.dcue Policed
￼Butcher, butcherThe Butcher's CatHack me some meat.Our poor cat is weak and needs the blood;For you've drained him, drained him,Neutered and tamed him,Fed him with scraps and with saucers of milk.Yes, you stroke him with affectionate fingers; But he saw you SAW that cowIn two.He's seen what you doTo the other animals, butcher-man.On some hot nights he's watched you tip-toe in Fresh from the slaughter-house -Stinking of iron,An anaemic's wet-dream;With your blood-drenched boots squealing on the tiles.He saw the way you fed that hen with best corn, Gave it a name, and thenWrung it's neck, as though it hadCalled your Mother a slut.Butcher, butcherI am sick, real sickOf the obscure cuts you bring me - heart, tongue, sweetmeats;And that stripy apron that you wear,And the way you like your steak so rare.I get MAD when I peer through the grime of your windows And see the naked limbs -Like fragments of disembodied porn-stars.And I feel the same fear as our dear pet, For at night in our big white bed,Stuffed to sickness with sausage;I have noticed you feel my breast as though It were a pound ofGood turkey. Measuring its leanness.Valuing the meat.One day soon I will pick up my cat and run,From you, butcher-man, and your mince. Your stun-gun. Oh, you say that you would never EAT us -But I have heard that in FranceThey eat Horse.You pimp death.Glare Pollard."7
￼Beside the menagerie, Amongst roses and jasmine Nude women play tag.Skin is yoghurt, Arms marrows, Breasts eggplants.A pearl, a ruby -These things mean nothing. Are a singleDive through blue Beneath the whetted eye Of a Sultan.It is the scraps that obsess their hearts - A match;A pepper-corn;A slice of pear.These mean a lovethat must be silent. Not his sort of love -A love you shareWith those sticky sweet things - Lips of the beauty;Ladies' thighs;Woman's navel.The ice in their delicate sherbetsHas come seventy miles, , And is mixed withpansies,violets.And is mixed withmusk toSmother the stink of nothing.They no more speak truthThan the guard with his slit tongue.The difference is that their tongues glitter With crushed lapis lazuli;Pulverized pearl.Kismet is cured with a little yellow pill. Opiates gild their fates -It is said those poppiesAre white as each faceThey blanch with almond paste; Corrode with smoothing arsenic.Keyf"I tumble onto my divan and am soon fast asleep, worn out with the exertion I have not even made."Halide Edip.
￼And in the end, sisters? In the end even love ends With a slice of a scimitar,Or getting stuffed in a sack.Their veils are an act!Pretending they have something to hideWhen their lives are Gazing through windows Then bathing off sky.There's always hope of course. Did you hear about the eunuch Who found it had grown back?The magic here is black;'They'd train macaws to cackle lies To be mistress of robes,The keeper of the baths.Each coffee could be poison.In cliques, they plot their silent war
￼Attempt at a Beautiful PoemI wanted this poem to be beautiful for you. Longed madly to say pretty things,But from this cafe window I can only see Neon shop signs that hum like migraines, And people sagged beneath them,hunched from carrying Broken plastic bags full of whisky, beans,Toilet tissue and tinned ravioli.Those chip-trays could be said to dance like butterflies, But the bitter milk oozing from crushed dandelions, However hard I try, can only make me think of pus.Women tread delicately round dog-shit, weeping Black tears for their fetid thighs,And because "Soldier, Soldier," was somoving last night.I could pretend the rain was glistening quick-silver, But it beats rotting chips to a greasy pulp.Pummels the man'spasty flesh to bruisesLike those on the peaches that roll off market stallsAnd decay on the drenched, dark tar-mac;Until it would not surprise anyone to see A maggot squirm out of his shin.I so wanted to give you a poem that was beautiful, But somehow I know that promises oflicking you calmAs a sleep-deep ocean, and sap-sticky kisses in forests,And fists full of starsAre not going to work this time.C Io jcPollcwd.3
￼We always come, dumb with longing. We come in our thousands - Dressed in pink for shame;Slow-dancing in same-Sex couples.We are not the broken hearted -That's the worst of it.No excuse but our inadequacy, As we choke on ginseng, honey,The stinking trufflesMadame de Pompadour swore by. Paper hearts flap in the draught.Body language, rose quartz,Spells, charms, laughingAt every fucking thing that he saysAll false hope,Like the card your Mother posts you I cannot bear this stenchOf tuberose, Pheromones, Fingers.To want somethingIs to know I cannot have it. February leaks its gluey juices;Bleeds over everything.Valentine
￼Dream of ExplosionsThis is not feverish flamenco fire Devouring my home like a loaf -This is a margarine candle flame. Enough light to read by.This is not a black hole. Nothingness So intense it thirsts for me -This is a vacuum flask Full of tea for two.This is not drowning. Becoming a terrible bird As the ocean vomits into me -This is a soothing lukewarm bathTo cure my aching joints.This is not an earthquake. The world's old wounds Torn open again, like a bad case of scurvy -This is the peel torn from a tangerine.A good dose of vitamin C.I am the cat that got the milk.Woman who awoke in a warm bedOn a black-ice morning, and never got up again. My life is nice. I raise a mild smile.Yes, I dream of explosions That shake my bones loose,But what if this is the most violent? What if this is it, my childhood dream?I cannot let it go for a whiff of gunpowder. If I stand in a lonely, open fieldTrying to catch lightning bolts,Perhaps I'll only catch my death of cold.Oh, but if I caught that bolt r And sparked the world bulb bright!Should I settle for this currentThat keeps my TV running, but little more?CXo-re foLUxrdII
￼Angel SongThis fir-tree point could impale.I balance on it, praying for still skies. Fingertip bulbs in cracked coloured cases Fuse, and threaten to burn my skirts.Shiny, red apples decompose on nooses.Pine cones are sprayed with crunched-mirror glitter. Sometimes it is thrilling.This sparkle, this lack of roots.Only the others hate me. Cry outThat I am no better than them,It's just my wings are sprayed old goldAnd a halo on a pin skewered through my scalp.But I earned that jet of golden paint!I suffered as the pin pierced my soft plastic head, And unlike them, I cannot make mistakes.An imperfection and I will be torn from this tree.I cannot be bitter like a gift of myrrh,Or they'll say: "Who does she think she is? Tied to the spike as if it is a crucifixion." I am a seasonal decoration,Pretty - but I will not bring salvation. Tinsel is not real silver, you know, Just foil that moults off strips;And nobody can join me up here.What am I but a detail in this small beige room? An afterthought in an outfit made ofSomeone's old wedding dress. These needles Bring not sleep, just little hurts.0, to have a Bethlehem to go to.To be deep filled, like a mince pie.Father Christmas, give me wings that work.I am so tired of trying to rival snowflakes.
￼Registering her ComplaintA dream holiday, the brochure said,But in her dreams the toilet flushes. She's irritable as a QueenWhose gown is made of mosquitoes.An unripe gecko scurries from her wrath.The brochure, she is almost sure, did not Inform her it was monsoon season,The dark trees strung up with liquid fairy-lights,And though it did not say what sort of breakfast was included, What sort of breakfast is dribbling chunks of violet melon, Mango, papaya, fresh lychees like turtle eggs?English people expect an English breakfast -Fat streaked bacon. Scraping filled sausages. Tea.Today she was hoping to lie on the beach, Aphrodite in nylon knickers, her sweating breasts Strawberry mousses, offending the natives. Instead they are registering her complaint.Butterflies huge as bats flap clumsily Past the foyer, as the ceiling fan lazilyThumps the still air. There was a snake In that bottle of wine, she tells Them,And in another a rat-foetus - she had nightmares.The receptionist thinks of his two mud rooms,The way his daughter begged a biroOff a stranger, and sleeps clutching it.Arranges for this woman to transfer out of Paradise.The heat sucks on her like a cigarette.Her dull eyes dismissing the orchids that are exploding Like invulnerable fireworks in the damp air,She informs a fellow white there is pressure -A storm tonight. This at least is something.
￼Breakfast PoemI am egg-shell fragile and grapefruit sour.My face blotchy; eyes raisins soaked in booze. I stench of night-sweat, am too tired to shower,To scrub off each ingrained mascara bruise. Memories slice up my still-sleeping head, The morning paper does not bring good news .I'm strawberry-jam sickly; I'm bacon dead. It's always morning when the ghosts appear - They haunt my toaster and they burn my bread,They say I stink as stale as last night's beer. They laugh with glee to .know I burned inside, Once aware that your skin was tasting-near.I had no resistance; I had no pride.Confessed my love, then watched you turn to run. Now my egg tastes salt from tears I've cried,My soldiers are charred black. No war is won. I try to weigh my loss against my gain:I have lost uncertainty, face and sun-Rise. I've gained a hangover; a dull pain. We're out of milk. My party dress is stained./
￼A Friday Night at the End of a MillenniumOn the first of January In the year 2000I will be twenty one. Yes, I am a womanOf the next millennium; Star on the clean black. Our hope for the future. But I don't give a fuckAs I check my pocket:Purse, lipstick, rape alarm;And I'm out for the night in a town Where only rain glitters.Air slits up my wrists As I head for the pub. Tottering on thin heels, A cripple.We get a seat by the TV screen.Neck squirming-sour vodka and tonics;Pose with Budweiser bottles.Soon we are watching Casualty with no sound on.I get cheese and onion crisps.We gossip to convince our veins They are not stagnant with boredom. The room looks like our lounge;Oak beams and a mock-Turkish carpet.It is full of men who look as though they'd Play dominoes given half a chance.One winks at me -And I sneer the sneer of the young and slim. He could cut his fist on me.The week's blunt miseryDissolves with the salt off the peanuts.My mate's called KerryAnd she's game for anything.Slept with three Ouzo-slick Greeks On holiday this Summer -Sticky one night stands,And she's not ashamed.No, she's proud as can be, Flashing blurred pictures ofHer topless. Him fumblingIn his pocket for a spare condom. At ten we head for the club.It's symbolically underground.
￼I order a pint for a pound,Sit on a cracked back chair andBegin to get intoxicated. My ex is here Selling cannabis to pre-pubescentGirls with ultra-bras, Pierced noses, plum hair And nicotine gilded fingers. He is beautiful,An angel in some lights.He laughs at everyone,And is too clever for this world;Fingers greasy with lightly salted puppy fat.He sweats; snorts vodka •Until his nose bleeds prettily. Laughs some more, thenMakes a pass at me on the stairs.Shit, he is beautiful,But he only wants meTo prove he gets what he wants - So I push him away.The only boy I ever liked to kiss. It makes me sad but proud.I have won.I will learn to live withoutHis static lips,The warm dark sparksThat danced softly off his Fingers down my spine.Dizzy with the punch of winning, I dance.Jump up and downLike I'm tied to this rotten ceiling with elastic. I swing my hips,And lick my lips -They are dry with cider, Flavoured salt and Hard-jawed smiles.I enjoy dancing.There is a kind of freedom in it, Energy pounding out of my Hunched-up joints.From the floor I watchA boy who told me he thinksI am very attractive -But he's sleeping with her now.The big commitment -Get them in bedAnd they're caged. Hooked.
￼Can't wriggle free.His hair is chilli-red,His eyes fish scales,His smile a small boy's.I used to get giddy when I saw him -Now I just feel weighted.Tired. My bones will shatterLike peanut brittle or barley sugar Or some other crap sweet.Another pint, and they chargeMe two pounds this time -They must have seen me staggering, But I'm too drunk to care.Alcohol goes straight through me. The girls' loos are fullOf lads smoking joints,So I have to piss quietly,Hovering over the bowlAs though I'm a hummingbird In order to avoid diseases. Stale urine.Someone's bloody tampon goads me redly I read the sign on the toilet door, Itsays: "AvoidunwantedPregnancy - use a telephone."Oh, that used to make us laughWhen this bitter-dark club seemed new; When this tongue-moist airDidn't catch in my throatLikeawishbone. IalwayswishFor something utterly impossible: Lager that hasn't been watered down, A star, him.The poor wish fairies -I am expecting miracles!It isn't fair on them.This bad luck is my own responsibilityIt is my own fault,I take all the blame.I vow to aim lower and stop thinking I'm the fucking second coming,Then pull up my silk copping knickers. Stumble out, eyes greyedBy a gauze of yeast.Mirror, mirror on the wall,Says I'm the biggest dog of all.
￼My flaws glow vivid.Nuclear white light strips my skin off And leaves the true-me clean.A regular ugly sister.Leaves me like a plucked turkey; Face withered and swollen with heat, Lips just a parched outline.My arms are gorilla hairy in the brightness.My lip is bald, because I scorched off the hair Before I came out,With a cream that claimed to be roseBut stank of shit.My armpits are stubbly jutting caves. I put deodorant on after shavingAnd they stung as though waspsHad built nests in the covesOf dark, moist calcium.I have a good itch of my bikini line, Readjust my hair - it's sucked sweet sticky.One lad is trying on his girlfriend's eyeshadow. Having a good laugh.It makes me sick-greenTo see them crackling with happiness;To see their reflections -Quivering jelly-fish with hysterics. He suits it - it is glossy purple,A pair of artfully blackened eyes.I watch my nails as I wash my hands.See I've chipped the "Madly Midnight" polish, And it sounded so exciting too!I try to say "Hi" to someone on the stairs,/ Only to find my pickled tongue snow-numb.I cannot speak, mind bleakAs a figureless, hospital-white Winter horizon.Sitting by the slot machine That says "Win! Win! Win!" In the hope its optimism Might rub off,I listen to:"I'm Only happy When it Rains."Lose me in empty Diamond White bottles. Watch others dance,Limbs flying as though They are epileptic.All want to pullBut many are too scared.
￼(What if something falls off?)Stickily laughing,I worry about smeared makeup, taxi-fares, My omnipresent virginity - the usual.Then the inevitable accident - Sweet, sweet cider downMy new blue dress.I drip like an icicle -Force a smile when a man In skin-tight army pants Offers to lick it all off Of me for free.Looking down, I notice .My thighs are exposed.Our skirts get shorter every week. My knickers playing hide and seek!A boy approaches, he is unremarkable, But at least I feel no nausea.I may go with him to enhanceMy pitiful total of boys kissed so far.Only I've done that before - And it leaves me soiled.The sickening unfamiliarity Of strange tongues;Moist muscle choking you. A heaving of fleshWith a bruised bud texture That tastes of vinegarOr, worse, tea time hot pot. Dead meat or applesThat have browned for months. And it either chokes you -Suffocates as though you've swallowed an Asda bag;Or they're gentle and sloppy - Slobbering dog-likeOver your chin, your neck, Your upper lip.Giving you a wet moustache. Snail slime slipperyAnd filling your throatWith its unknown glue-juiceUntil you want to hideSlug pellets behind your lower teeth.If you're lucky they'll just Move their tongue in circles - As though they are drawing
￼Balloons or coins with it.The monotony dulls your senses And loosens your jaw.You want to eat him -Not through lust butFor the thrill of his head in your gullet.Blood spurting brightly from his warm neck vein, And you'd swallow it like medicine.At least then it would be over.Their stubble grazes your chin,Until it feels as your knees didWhen you fell on stony ground as a child. And if you open your eyes - ugh!Lids curtain-closed with blissAs though they're on a train to Paradise, When you're feeling queasyAnd are itching to get free.Their indignity is distasteful,Their knowledge of your precious mouth. You want to slap them.Burn all official records of their being.Their pleasure and shut-eyed fun is a sick joke - They think you like them!It is at times like thatI realise what an ugly word 'snogging' is.Sometimes, I find myselfLooking around - that’s the killer. Suddenly, you care what everyone thinks; Blush rare-beef pink.Roast hotly with the realisation He is not cool, or handsome,And his character is dubious - This boy who has hisSalivary glands pumping for you.Who you are sharing spit with.And you cringe, wince,Try to arrange your hair differentlySo nobody will recognise you. You and this grotesque, Macabre, bladdered freak.The one with his handsOn your thighs, your back, The nape of your neck.He even tries to cop a good Feel up your top -The nerve of him to think
￼You are in his league.On his level.Not too special to touch.Anyway, I decide not to go withhim.Laugh for a while as a blonde,gay Goliath Licks a hard stripe downMy homophobic male mate's cheek.My ex reappears,Now vitriolic and revenge-bent; Picks on my sparkly shoes,And the way I've mislaid- my purse.Flirts violently withOther lager blondesBefore my same stale face, Trying to make me cry boozily,How little he knows meII never break,But am strong as cartilage.Look, my legs flex as though made of it.Lights flutter like dying butterflies In the hot whisky crush.I am no one, smudged.A happy blur."Are you okay?" Some one asks, And I nod cow-like.Look at my watchBut see no time, no movement.Kerry's in the cornerFumbling jumpily with a lad, Legs clenched tightly round him. People stare a bit, giggling,Then give her a round of applause When she comes up for air.She reddens, but not much, For she loves attention.Adores a starring role. Oh, she is a wild-child! I look shocked, forIt pays to humour her.See, even drunk I am condescending! People stomp on my feet.Rip my tights with careless, Skeletal fingers.They are trying to destroy me! I thumb the holeUntil it gapes.A moon made of
￼Lightly downed thigh flesh.The gold of the hairs shimmers. Magic dust. Then theyStand erect like little warriors,And I feel like a hermaphrodite, And cover it guiltilyAs though it is a ripped hymen. It is cold in here.So cold I would gasp, Had I the will power Or the energy.A consuming coldness.I am a dead foetusDunked in a lab-jar of ice water. Exposed and raw,And I can't feel my pulse,Just the throbbingOf a headache coming on. Oh, it hurts -And they've started playingThat terrible Prodigy song, You know, the one that goes:"I've got the remedy," butOnly makes me long for paracetamol.My stomach churns -That last pint tipped me over. My mouth is dryAs a burnt moth.I perch on the radiator. Watch my hand clenchingAnd opening in the darkness: A sea anenome.Watch all the people. The ones who willDance into the glorious Sunrise with me.The ones who will kick-startA new, shining era.The leaders of menWho will gush like fresh bloodInto the next century. Sacrificial lambs. The whitest of white; The brightest flames.They are joking about blow jobs. They are inventing nastyNames for one another -
￼Like "Trout eyes."They are spilling Newcastle Brown Down their Adidas three stripe tops And beckoning peopleWho scare them in broad daylight.Adjusting spiked hairAnd gold hooped eyebrows In the mirrors of dull Alcoholic lemonade bottles.Andkissing. Fingeringeachothers1 Writhing maggot bodiesAs though they are cut-glassOr braille or made of flowers.They are glugging down doublesWith competitive grins.Shimmying round the shattered shards Of smashed pint mugsThat blossom. An ice web. They are vomiting a cocktail Of bitter and bileOn the threadbare stairs.So many people and they all Only want to be loved. Funny isn't it?How all could love fiercelyIf they only got the chance, Buttheywon't. It'ssad. Like spilt lager.Like the taxi ride home.
￼SurrenderSometimes you are so raw -Salted eyes crackling; heart bruised to a huge Rotten plum; your back flayed as a galley-slave's - That you have to stop the slow dance and sit down.Sometimes you have to acceptThat you've been months now underwater, And no one is going to press their mouth Against your mouth, and halt the airless Agony of your collapsed lungs.You say you must try, or can't wake and feel alive, But there are other, quieter ways of living -Some Buddhist monks can .so slowDown their hearts that they almost seem dead.They claim to be content.Sometimes you have to wave somethingWhite; resisting the temptation to useA bra, or other underclothes, orA freshly laundered strait-jacket,And instead choosing something quite serious:A square with no yielding curves, clothCut from the blanket you bought for the bridal bed.And that delicious moment when your mind,Muddled from sleeplessness, drink or swellingCaused by beating your desperate head against walls, Desks, the bathroom tiles, thinks for a second, Perhaps maybe they might be possibly yours -There comes a time when the scarsThat cover your body in a web of startling pain Distract you too much for even this to be a pleasure.There is no redemption, or balm, or daylight.Sometimes you must just be grateful for a resolution.Do not look on it as giving up, for there 'is nothingTo give up. Sometimes the story does end with two people In separate rooms, and one not even realising this matters.
￼Light EntertainmentCommissioning a sit-com an awful lot of work,So God created me instead - What a sadistic jerk!Right now he's sat in Heaven 'vnOn a fluffy white bean-bag,With cans of beer and kettle-chips, And probably a fag,Tears rolling down his long beard As his belly shakes with mirth. Laughing his huge heart outAt the joke I've been from birth.A classic episode last night -I was having a wee,When my Dad's friend walked in the room. There goes my dignity!I spilt my drink, I burnt the eggs, I found I'd a verruca.Forgot to set the videoFor 'Friends,' and lost at snooker.And the delicious irony When I got shot by cupid!I thought perhaps my luck had changed - How comically stupid.That stale old joke: I fail with bloke! This show has lost its spark.These same sick gags are wearing thin. God's humour's just too dark.tn
￼Thousands of monksLike burning clementines Heads smooth and shiny As mud puddles.Thousands of male tarts, Slender and painted -With eyelashes to Make me envious.Thousands of people on Bicycles. Tricycles. Mopeds and tuk-tuks. Cars and taxis. Riding on elephants. Travelling by foot.BangkokPouring out of incense-heavy buildings Like a fleshy discharge.Clotting up the crossroads and the Junctions like scabs.Even on the murky mushroom river With its glorious stink,They pile onto the ferry boatsUntil they look like they will sink. Heaving. Breathing.Yards of skin that smells of lemongrass.Once, led past the small, hot stalls - Full of steaming satay and coconut milk - I was taken to a temple made ofMarble, gold and jade;Within which, in sticky coolness,They laid deep pink lotus flowers, , Uniform as folded linen napkinsAt the altar as gifts.Smiling, our guide said:"Thereare no individuals in this world.We are all part of the same great spirit.When you can accept this and become part of everything - Then you will reach Nirvana."But I screamed: "No!I am an individual.No one else thinks these thoughts I have. No body looks just like I look.Separate and removed - I am no part of you! I am special.I am different.I am me! Me! Me!"Apparently, I fainted then.They brought me round with tiger-balm/8
￼And curries so hot I wept,But their kindness no longer seemed so selfless.Drug-happy on the morphine Of Buddha's fat smile,They did not understand when I begged for solitude.When I told them I would rather be The only orchid in this city,Than a wet, pink cellInside the cheek of a goddess./
￼The bank is all sluggish veined marble, Silence and grandeur, a horrible church."Are you saying your cash-card is stolen?" Eyes grey as incinerated five-pound notes Gaze on me in disappointment. "No, lost," I confess, a sinner, through the glass.It seems I lose everything these days - Keys, dignity, pool games, nerve,The ring my Grandmother left me.The staff are bowed and hushed before Computer screens as thou-gh in prayer.I am passive as a two pence piece, passed Around, dull from fingers. I have lostControl. Hunched over the toiletAs though sheltering from a holocaust, I dribbled sick, that sweet yolk,Down my chin and blouse last night."Name?" My dry lips clamp on absence. Footsteps are gunshots through pillows. I am suddenly six again, bawlingRedly, alone in the supermarket.And the people who are queuing to receive Coins like Communion wafers, stare greedily"Name?" Through hallowed quiet her voice Echoes like the tannoy did that day:"We have a small, frightened blonde girl Here, can someone please come to claim her.Losing Control
￼Still LifeI have taken up painting since I fell in love with you, As my hands are quite desperate for something to do.Still lifes mainly, as it makes me impossibly grateful To gaze on something beautiful until my eyes are full -You always run from me whilst I'm still hungry to stare. It's a common misconception that there’s just fruit there;No, my canvases are laden with longing and lust.Desire aches a gloss of sweat into the oil-paint crust.At first, plums were nipples full of gold milk; ripe and ready, My apples were firm and smooth, that headyFertiliser taste clutching their skin, sour and strong - As chemical as my make-up would taste to your tongue.Oranges promised a sharp, delicious biteAnd then juice gushing out like a cry in the night.When you started dating her I drew spat-out pips, The poisonous berries that grew around her hips.I daubed maggots in the core of each pink cherry, They squirmed out from the heart of every strawberry.In art class I was told I'd lost all sense of perspective; My slit-split skinned pears were no longer objective.I stopped sleeping, began to sit up all night and paint My fetid black bananas, melons swollen and faint,And those peeled grapes, silver as your blind eyes. Are you allergic? Am I crawling with fruit fly?Without even tasting me, how is it fair to refuse?Did nobody tell you that once you've inflicted a bruise,All the flesh around the hurt goes rotten brown?Cloie Policed.
￼Business men are eating pre-packed sandwiches; They smile, as though awareI can't really afford the fare to London.My face is licked on the pane with a milky tongue.The anaemic countenanceHaunts rivers, office-blocks, mills - Ghost of those who drowned internally, Damning up dreams until canalsOf stagnant water carried their corpses Out of those industrial towns.On one eye is a statue of Mary and child; On one eye is a supermarket;Her tongue is weighted withA cathedral,A town hall;Her mouth is the scar of a derelict roadGlittering with wasted streetlights. They never apologised for the delay; Although inside she screamed like the Brakes when they said:"You must disembark, miss, the line goes no further," My reflection moistens her lips, my lips,Ready to bite down on some city, to tear itWith our teeth, and swallow it entirely.Delay
￼Butterfly CollectorThe lake skin was the skinOf a corpse, grazed by the wind,And the rank grasses caressed his shins, Juices bleeding and soaking.He observed butterflies,Those gaudy icari,Dumbly fluttering.Vowed to protect them from the drip-drip, The terrible dark plunge.The first that he caught was a Painted Lady,Her tawny orange silks convulsing beneathHis thick-fingered hand, spasms melting to calm.Later, he learnt to make a net from nylon Curtain fabric, a hoop from clothes line. Used ammonia to poisonSoftly as backhanded compliments.Recently he has been murdering the rainbow - He has a Red Admiral,An Orange Tip,A Green Hairstreak.Desperately, he aches for the Pale Clouded Yellow Dreams every night of its buttery wingsBeating against his face like eyelashes.It isstillthepaintedladyheadoresthough.He didn't mean to break her antennaethat time. Stuck them back on with a tear-dropOf seccotine applied tothe head.You wouldn't know there'd been any damage./ Even at work, he finds himself imaginingThey are in some garden together.He is an Adonis Blue. The flutter of her wings Mirrors his heart.Somedays he plucks out the setting needle, Gestures for her to fly, free, luxuriating In his own benevolence. She does not move.The caterpillars writhe amongst thistles, nettles Their flesh breeding dark hairs like pubis.Each time the needle plunges back in deeper.
￼2Love YourselfThe virtue of humility is hopelessly outdated -Darling, don't you know? These days it's self-esteem that's rated!All the magazines inform us: if you do not love yourself Then what can you expect but to be left upon the shelf? Life's a self-fulfilling prophecy, and you make your own luck, So must be gutsy, cock-sure, don't-give-a-fuck.'Virgin' Mary's humble sentiments were probably heart-felt - But today that meek and mild act would earn psychiatric help. (All that turn the other cheek is for the weak, it's dead and gone,Let's grow up, and not pretend we don't look out for number one.)When this century has ended, then its epitaph will be: "I was selfish, I was heartless, but at least I was me!"Clare Polloud.
￼FresherIt was to be a whole new chapterIn the grim little pamphlet of his life,David became Dave, owner of Diesel jeans and obedient hair. His record collection was pared down brutally.He had anticipated girls with nipples Big as the bottoms of beer-bottles,Their smiles white as vacant signs on toilet cubicles, There would be drunken sex on someone else's beanbags, Sneaking from curry-houses stinking of unpaid-for Vindaloo, Blowing each day's budget on lager and a twenty deck.He'd make mates who could supply him with quality gear, Scrape illicit powders to lines with his student union card.Yet here he is, in his bedroom at half past one, Soberly wanking to distant techno beats,A stale taste in his mouth. His head swimsWith the short girl from geography who blanks him.And lying by the papery wall that his groansOf reciprocated pleasure were to cause disturbance through, He can hear someone pissing. Nothing is new,It is all just the same but more impersonal.
￼Poem for mv Future LoveI do not want a settle for second best love. A mundane grow-to-love-himCosy little rut love.A pizza and a videoHolding hands and making plans romance.I do notwant to be able to look at him without crying. I do notwant to be able to eat in his presence.I do notwant to be fond of his little waysOr to have fun ever when he is not there.I do not want our meeting to be a cuteAnecdote to tell our children,Or to buy him aftershave for ChristmasAnd receive French knickers in return.To go to the cinema with him and kissMildly on the second to back row.I do not want to fall in love by halves.A dilute milk-trayAnd two dozen red roses love.A maybe-this-is-itSlow dancing and fancying romance.Iwant tofall inlove sohard itbruises. Iwant tofall inlove sohard itscars. Iwant tofall inlove sohard itfractures, And cuts my knees and slices up my arms.I want to fall in love so badly I cough up blood. So madly I would confess to murder.So terribly I would gouge out my eyes.So painfully I would gas myself.So utterly I would eat mud and bone.So crazily I would leap offTen storey buildings in the night.I want a love that chokes me. Blinds me. Stabs me. Shoots me. Rips and burns me. Tears and wounds me.Heals me like new skin. tIt will be a passionate stupid vengeful Breathless arrogant tender devouring Painful fiery dirty gentle fumbling Vicious beautiful glittering fatalPure love.It will be a complete and utter whole and total Everything and all love.A love that is blind to colour.A love thatis deaf to warnings.A love that does not feel the cold.A love that does not taste the blood.Not the kind of loveYou learn to take for granted,But the kind of love that makes you live in fear, And feel like you're only living when he's near. A love that will make breathing seem trivial. That will make time stop deadAnd the sun burn out.^5
￼When he touches me my skin will sing. I will become electrically charged.I will tremble and ache when he speaks. I will smile stupidly at his name.I will start crying for no reason.I will love the smell of his limbsAnd the taste of his tearsAnd the sweep of the curve of his back And the rhythm of his heartAnd the patterns of the pale blue veins on his wrists. I will onlybe able to sleep when he is holding me.I will talkto him even when he is not there.I will kisshim so hard my mouth will bleed.I will holdhim so hard even surgeons will Not be able to separate us,And for so long we will turn toAsh and crumble.I will love him so much it will be illegal. Dangerous.I might explode.I do not want a settle for second best love. A mundane grow-to-love-himCosy little rut love.A pizza and a videoHolding hands and making plans romance.I am waiting for the love that will renew meAnd send electric currents screaming through me. When I fall in love there will beThunder. Lightning. Fireworks.I am waiting for the love that I deserve.CLcne Policed.
￼Hara-KiriIt is as small, complex and compact As a microchip.(God must be Japanese.)They will hook it out limb by limb. Tough veined trout pink fleshAs raw as sushi.Nothing will remain of it but Bloodspots on her bright white sheets Like stubborn flags.If she let this grow it would Cripple both of them.Hearts mutated by the fall-out.It would want to die for her. Kamikaze pilot.A noble death.It's karaoke!Everybody in the ward sing:"Baby, where did our love go?"Career prospects and finances and practicality Are squatting like sumos on her mind,And this rising sun holds no promise,For she will attack at herself at dawn And there will beNo surrender.She will slit herself open.Watch it and her intestines slip outIn the light of a Samurai sword.
￼The Last Love PoemThis is the last love poem, there will be no more,I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, if ye find my beloved, that ye tell him, that I am sick of love.For two years, a doll of you rattled round my scratched, spluttering heart chambers, Last night I tore it out,wiped off the gunk, the bloody slobbers,found the petty limbs shoddily made. Did I say your eyes were kind skies? They were painted sticky chlorine. Did I call your mouth perfection?It was just a splintered jut,moles nestling below it like rooks,I take everything back,iiLove n, warm affection; sexual passion; wholehearted liking for something; beloved person.It was 2 am on their first date,He took her to the derelict hospital,its gutted wing was rain drenched; incurable,And she always knew he would never be her suitor, her cavaliere, wooer, amoroso, his tongueugly malt-sticky with Marlborough Lights,that thick Bolton accent pronouncing affairde coeur, grande passion, made her laugh,But oh, the way he jerked from her touch,as though she'd tried to slip ice-cubesdown his shirt, hurt like she was chewed up, bitten, smitten, spoony, her gut spooned out,iiiThe more you arch, the more access he has to your breasts and clitoris, and by being on top you have total control over how fast and how hard you want to go.If ever any beauty I did see,Which I desir'd, and got, t'was but a dreame of thee,The club flickers with the peach light of skin feigning arousal, the screens show thighs, ill- fitting uniforms, cheap off-white lace, bodies writhing in slicks of oil, like dying birds, She drinks the cocktails. Long slow screw.Multiple orgasm. Slippery nipple, The creamy green Shag. They are embarrassing to ask for,but she does, though her shy tonguen
￼would not dare articulate her real thirst,There is a scar on Beth's forehead,a small indentation made scratching at chicken-pox, I want to give her everything,Pamela Anderson fucks on a motorbike,ivHere love his golden shafts employs, here lights His constant lamp and waves his purple wings,Did I say how nice your mouth was? Did I say?There's something wrong, isn't there? Tell me what's wrong,These, lulled by nightingales, embracing slept,And on their naked limbs the flowery roof showered roses.There's something wrong. I'm paranoid, forgive me,Do you still love her? Tell me, There's something wrong,Know to know no more.vLove was invented by the churchto encourage monogamy and reduce illegitimate births. Love was invented by the capitaliststo ensure a system of patrilineal inheritance.Are you listening?It is a fake, whatever the hell you think you're feeling, It is socialisation, and wonder-bra adverts,and biological practicality, and the ruling elite.In most countries romance doesn't even exist.It's a big western lie.IT IS IN YOUR FUCKING HEAD.Some people say they are in love every week,some never say it, some say it once (but afterwards, finding red-eyed photographs or weeping over sliced onions, feel nothing but impotence), some feministsfeel in love is impossible in our oppressive society, some girls buy magazines for the front-page promises: how to catch your man, twenty ways to make him love you, some people will not change for love, some cannot,some look in the mirror and do not recognize their own breasts, or necks, kissed to cream and purring,Baby's good to me, you know, she's happy as can be, you know, she said so.Ironic, how the moon looks like a contraceptive pill. How love drenches the loved, whilst the loveless suck at the stems of roses, hoping for moisture, slicing up their mouths on the barbed wire stems,Am I bent?Yes.Will I ever be happy?
￼viCertain words belong in love poems:milk, sweat, swallow, cinnamon, jasmine, hummingbird, indigo, nectarine, salt, humid, cut,They mean nothing, but he likesto watch her mouth shape the sounds: scar, molasses, beloved person.vii..And to win tonight's big prize of eternal misery,you simply have to complete the sentence: Love is.. a) When you cannot see any flaws, orb) When you see all the flaws, and love each utterly. Answer it incorrectly,and you're suffering for NOTHING, you stupid bitch!Lucy loves Chris loves Sarahloves Karen loves John loves Anna.This worm eats heart-flesh, tongue-flesh, thigh-flesh.It is in the drinking water,the bedclothes, the loo-roll. WAKE UP! IT WILL EAT YOU ALIVE! RUN! HIDE!Anna loves Steve loves Kateloves Matt loves Tom loves Louise.This worm eats eye-jelly,ear-drums, crotch-meat.It is in your Beatles albums,your TV, your stockings.DON'TLOOK! ITWILLLEAVEYOUFORBLIND! RUN! HIDE!Lovelorn adj. forsaken by or pining for a lover.Comfort me with apples: for I am sick of love.viiiIn 1995, approximately 40 percentof marriages were found to end in divorce.Her love altered where it alteration found,so was not love, merely infatuation, a crush. But oh my God she was crushed utterly,and who can claim to know how love is measured? She cried into the bathroom carpet all Christmas day for that man, and did notcount the tears, but the wool was sodden,Her face took the texture of the weave.(Oh, but he will suffer, she tells herself. One day he will wake to find that loss has kidnapped him, and he is gagged and bound in a dark, rat-ridden cellar. One dayhe will realise the scale of her worth
￼and, awestruck, hack off those fingers which allowed her to slip through.)To know know know him is to love love love him and I do.ixBy night on my bed I sought him whom my soul loveth: I sought him, but I found him not.In your room, with its stained duvet, yourChe Guevara poster, the guitar which clings jealously to your fingerprints, do you dream about me ever, do you wake up touching yourself, the breeze flickering against your skinlike my eyelashes, seeing ghosts of my hair, my hip bones bruising your eyelids?Last night, every night, I dream of you,I dreamt I saw you across the still lake,and screamed at you for giving me this burden, this melancholy, this rotting smell,You looked up, your face a torn petalagainst the ache of the dark forest,and we two stood staring at each-other,my arms laden with feathers, flesh,and the stones which weighted me,a paper doll, to your awful silence.xEv'ry time we say goodbye, I cry a little.How the world was made, the afterlife, infinity, the soul, all the great questionsmean nothing, nothing at all, when she is close and can almost lick the raw, bitten down skinwhere he tore the fingernail off with his teeth.Whitethroat, skylark, goldfinch, they dipand soar, quite loveless, yet still alive.How can they not sink beneath the weight ofno breath on skin, no tongue, no I love you, ever?xiDid my heart love till now? Forswear it sight!So that is it? Just friends? I cannot bear it.For I ne'er saw true beauty till this night.Can't you see what you are doing? You will destroy me. Thus from my lips by thine my sin is purged.Talk to me. Say something, You will destroy me.Give me my sin again.
￼Shantihf shantih,Oh, but his mouth is the most beautiful thing,xiiThis was to be the last love poem,but I love him, and if I say it enough he might loveI will write other love poems - It is fucking degrading.Stars I have named after himgrind into my skin like crushed glass.