￼Hill Trembling 59-94 3/2/94 1:42 pm P* 62CHAPTER 1 BoySWhatever’s the point of writing it all in code? Supposing the coat is a monk,and the sofa’s a young horse;and supposing the photos are real?Darling, I love you.I want to stay here in the dark for ever. Everyone, don’t talk and move around.‘A strange lamented artist who loves dancing.’ Somebody’s clock. I hate her. Cold white lines. Cut light in concave triangles, the door,the side of the door, the panel’s lonely back.I think I am a sponge. I think I’m going. Or shall I write in code again? Who cares.She was descending like a boneless swan.I wish more people would descend like that.She knows I’m writing about her. Now she’s gone. Mr C. is calling. Here I am,hidden in my wooden hold of doors.Last night G. told me everything. It’s true:I will always remember you, G., I really will.I wanted to tell you about...I nearly did.She asked me if I masturbate. Wet grass. Hepburn - ‘fragile, feminine’ - please die. Rays of light returning on themselves. Glossy prints of Rudolf Nureyev.Taut purity of virgins in white landscapes, overwhelmed by tenderness.Don’t go.“Like drugfj,” he said, “the same basic principle.” ‘Rebellion itselfs a form of love.’Obsession with counting birds. My lips are aching.They have taken away my Lord. The Head is calling.
￼Hill Trembling 59-94 3/2/94 1:42 pm P0,23b 53 -Marine crustaceans’ seven leg-like mouths. Goodwin’s MOODS AND TENSES. Pipe tobacco. ‘Little did the author know.’Plisetskaya.I wonder if I’m good at telling lies.‘Un homme secret, il danse dans la rue.’I do not know the rules.Oh yes you do!“What’s she really like?”She is a virgin.Yellow parrots, lettuce, nylon wool.I went back to the study after supper.The bluebells are in session in the woods. Wearing dresses frightens me.Calves.Nipples.The teachers smell of beans and dressing-gowns.The dark proud gentleness of feathersreflected in the dancer’s famous face.Her hair is gold. She hates the other partner. Black satin, tinsel, armaments unfold.She didn’t know she made me cry. I told her. Broad hands. Dark blood. A little milk and rice. Down down down to the creatorof diamonds and coal and roots in silver tights. Beaten cut tormented killed and counter-killed. This isn’t what you think. It’s radioactive.Many men and unknown things go down there. Won’t write about the walk. Past. Frozen colour.Noises echo through the whitened squares. ‘Mauriac choisit Emmanuelle.’Hiding during meals - the seventh day.I won’t be watched so much by people later.‘Slowness Is Beauty’ - always at top speed.“I simply came to see if you’re alright...”‘Suppressed depression, iron will’ - that’s me!“You’ll burn your journal next year - DEFINITELY.” Her fatherland. Tormented hope. Horned tree.63