￼THA TUTAHKHAMUN. |VARIATI0N33 cUckbVL||fe spaced boVc^Botovl cx^ <J>rMe&
￼CARTER A t swaffham r> <■^orrV^We know him: it's the Carter lad who painted dear Lady Amherst's lap-dogand the Vicar's old bull-terrier, quite without schooling - son of our gamekeeper's son,And if his imagination pierces a tiny holein these venerable walls and holds a candlethrough to a room full of wonderful things but utterly foreign to a decorously mounted4*hunting party withits fine equipage,its whips and sticks and stuccoed wooden courtesy
￼then what is that to us? Tally-ho! and on towards the twentieth century: 1 the boy be contentA*with keeping trespassersfrom our noble pile;i.sor immortalize ourailing Golden RetrieverssV^lo^--------
￼CHORUS 6f NEWSMEN I Z-We are looking for a story.A running story, like the war. But not the war.An English story.Like Jack the Ripper.Like the Titanic.Like Scott of the Antarctic. We miss the hot leadWe used to catch.We miss those fat statisticsThat used to cover our front pages.We can do nothing with thisLatest dance, that latest creation.We are ready to jump into an aeroplane And leave for any part of the globe.(What is that Messenger carrying So swiftly from Dover?)We need a story.(Who is that recluse reminiscing Amid the cigar smoke?)We need a story.(And what is being unsealed?And why that smile?And whose are the words on that telegram We are looking for a storyFor the aristocracy at breakfast,For the middle classes on the train,For the working-man on the street corner
￼(And why has the Editor of the Times Gone to Newbury Races?)Something to do with money.One story that is a totalEclipse of the sun and will last Until the next war.Something to do with death.(And why has the Earl of Carnarvon Cancelled all his engagements?) Something to do with mystery.________ We are looking for a storyThat will set the peace ablaze. A story that is not a question. Not Irish.And not emancipated women.But which can be embroidered And photographed and sold.(Where is that young man hurrying With his notebook?)And not the civil war in China.(What is that noise in the telegraph wires?) And not the riots in Egypt.3' IZ3>Of7fvfr
￼^The landscape overhead will not be changed By flash-flood: it is a civilisation Bunkered securely in its desolation.More admirable, too, than this gold arranged About my sarcophagus - hanging its strange Treasures freely on view, a virgin cache Unnoticed by the lords whose liberationFrom dirty politics is a trenchIn the Kings' Valley. I warned them to keep Their distance from this entrance and its seal. Anubis is no god, but a dog asleep,So let him lie. Small punctures may healOnce you've unmuzzled him; but not (that steep Descent over) your mad desire to steal.^^ 13
￼THEODORE DAVIS 5 LAST SEASONI have dug for treasure the way I smoke without stopping, and obsessively.If I could have made my fortune like one Mr Standwood of Maine,&who imported mummies by the tonto turn into brown wrapping paper,then I would have saved myself twelve years of sweat. Or if I had been alive£the century before him, I should have ground up the flesh and sold itA:to the poor at an immense profit.But no one today is after mummy-powder.If I surrender this choice concession,then that pariah dog Carnarvon will be downAscratching where I've been, although he knows I have already published Touatankhamanou.*It's only this old seductress on my desk,this strange alluring figurine -
￼and when I hear her boyish voice, ^the best is yet...** I should know it's time to quit:she has promised me into too many darkand secret hollows, whispering ‘'intact''...4^I shall return to Florida, and make sureI die before she can call back: CSee? I promised!1*t
￼1972I am waiting, like all the others, waitingTo open the sacred seal and discoverMy future; and as I wait, this exhibition Snakes me through steel barriers to my golden Eighteenth year where I catch, amid the darknes That enfolds a teenage Pharaoh's history,Glimmerings of a more personal history,As if it had lain beneath the sand waiting For me to come and dig into its darknessIn search of the famous Mask but discover Only in each glass case my own face, golden. It is my coming-of-age exhibition.All aspects of me are in this exhibition:The child's chair and board-game are a history Of my early youth; my teens were that golden Dagger. This trumpet, this cow-bed are waiting For me to experiment, to discoverIn their cross-meshed passages of darkness,&yv>In sexual unity and divine darkness,The Goddess Hathor's milk-white exhibitionOf her transfiguring powers: discoverBetween her lyriform horns all history.The Necklace of the Rising Sun is waitingTo embrace us, its clasp is cool and golden...
￼Each morning my hopes shoot greener, but golden Futures only bloom after months in darkness, During nights of counting the weeks of waiting, And now at this jubilee exhibitionI am persuaded that time and historyAre relative. Come, UCCA! and discoverTo me the sacred light, let us discoverThe place where we are to spend our golden Prime and inscribe our names on history,As one young man did, emerging from darkness At eighteen to become this exhibition -The very thing for which we are all waiting./
￼cg= THE CEDARS |TIGHCLEREI see him in the distance. The stories he tells them waft across to me as I trim the lawns beneath his cedars.41He loves cedars: his father asked my father to put them in. The Egyptians made all their tables and chairs out of cedar,-4he told me once, were buried surrounded by it. Now he'salone on that fancy verandah, reading, or glancing up towards4these living crowns - always some fat volume open beside him. That's (he'd say) since forty days stuck out in the tropical seas4*with so little to do, between fighting off piratesand avoiding hurricanes, that he fell prey to the bookworm.But we know. In the old days he would never have stoppedstill long enough to have turned a leaf. If it wasn't the sea,it was the turf; if it wasn't the latest horseless carriage, it was some infernal air machine. Faster, always faster, until-4Trotman comes running to pluck him out from that blazing wreckin the Black Forest - head smashed, heart stopped.4-And all he wanted to know was had he killed anybody!Next thing, he is making Highclere a home for war-wounded, -4-young lads cowering behind this shadow-line: muttering, wide-eyed ghost battalions. M'lord was never one to let the grass grow.
￼Today he showed us another of his latest photographs - one ofa mummified cat, which wasn’t at all well received by his dog -4=nor by her Ladyship, for that matter. But then, we all have doubtsabout this digging up of times long gone. The papers make jokes 44about the thousands he has wasted (with 36,000 acreshere to keep) and to my own thinking, when there's talk of a curse44you think twice. He's already had a good nine lives - chased by a wild elephant in South Africa (more of an achievement44to have escaped than shot it, he said!), then only last week rushed to the hospital with three quarters of an hour to live.When he dies, it will be in a way nobody could have foreseen. £I don't think I've lost my nerve,*' he whispered, straight4" ,after that accident. And he won't let anyone wrap him upin bandages. ^1 want to be buried,* he laughs, fout in the open, -4high up on Beacon Hill, then - if you like — ^ to us, he calls us his garden angels! - ^plant one of de Havilland's DH9s44above me like a Pyramid; and make sure the grave is dug by a professional archaeologist!’' Tomorrow he's off outto the East again. The last season, he has announced.cIf the Pharaohs don't bite, the mosquitoes certainly will.*'13,+----------- 5b \7
￼CARTER BEGINS|—-y^----— ---------1'' 2-^lbThere is a language of rock that is notlike the language of diplomacyor newspapers or love. One must knowhow to read it, where to begin. None of ushas heard it spoken, though some taste the air into which its last words evaporated,a few have grovelled to wrench gold fillings from its mouth. There is a grammar of rock,but its secrets are guarded by aloof priestesses, their fingers to their lips as theyscald meaning from the bones. I will begin with a triangle I know to mean hope.Aboard the Champollion, steamingtowards the Pharos, unknown, unrecognised,49 pHI imagine steps that lead into chambers full of the poetry of this rock language.
￼The Valley in which we search fruitlessly is peaceful:we dream of gardens or ofa golden age, and our lookingis contented. If we knew what sentences of hard labourawait us the day we crack the dream, we would not knowrrtvfr 7this pleasure, sipping atperhaps and may, shiftingten thousand irritationsat a stroke. But the demonsof discovery are less considerate - they will block-book the hotels, and arrive each morning in dark glasses,-4ctpterattling metal plates, begging their thousand words.Vv^V\s-n
￼Down to bedrock now - but all we have to show isthirteen jars containing the remains of sweet oilsused to anoint the dead. Lady Carnarvon stoopsand for an instant glows pre-Raphaelite again:Miss Almina Wombwell delivering the firstflush of her youth into her lover's arms. Is thisa final remembranceof ^that night devotedto oils, when thou art re­ united with the earth^?Now she kneels to a lost fragrance, alabasterjars look pale disciples;and we - two wretched thievesmocked and left here to parch with a mystery king.— \°\
￼<z------ ENTR'ACTE ^Some friendships fell apart when they met our English damp. Some were toodelicate to have been carried out of the past. Perhaps others will be reclaimed and restored. Two sentinels remain standing:______ ___________Stuart,you were as watchful and all- seeing with your one eyeas Ra, ever-forgivingwhen we forgot and threwthe old washing-up sockfor you to catch; breakinginto your native Welsh inthe souk, or kick-startinga rustic Arabic which you had patched up until it coulddrive a class of sixty todrill out, ^11m-fine-thanks!^ to your every ftHow are you?3 And how you hated that head­ mistress of ours (whose name meant 'tin can', and whose face resembled one) for wagginga finger at you when you tried to "borrow" one of her clutch of Louis Quatorze to stockour chairless staff-room.
￼# i x y ^ 20You could bellow your own Son-et-Lumiere when you wanted to get things done your way;or simply sat with your shoe- soles turned insultinglyon your victim. fox!**as our idiom-proud Inspectorof English chuckled. Yes -and a superb actor to that last encore when you soliloquised draconian indignation before abaffled policeman. Scene: the Pyramids. To Be OrNot To Be arrested on yourlast day in Egypt. Always making new friends and taking uson sightseeing marathons through backstreet dust-bowls andopen sewers to try a glass of sugared tea and bassboussa -to meet Abdul Kareem, blackand glistening on the desert's rim in a mud-brick storage-heater, whose latrine ran cockroaches,and whose library lacked only Volume Two of Lives of the Poets to meet Mr Sami and his Violet, who fish-fed us and let usbloat on their privileged panorama of the Nile and Sadat being bulleted past, as they put in their requests for Macleans tooth­ paste, Marks & Spencer shirts... then merrily bolted the door
￼to show us the strength of their hospitality - Stuart,you tolerated it all, evenwhen Alan popped up, dear utterly-different-from-you old Alan, whose cracked earthenware humour could keep even his own temper cool. Who elsewould try to tell the joke about a whisky and a whitehorse called Eric to a room full of Moslem Brothers?Or endlessly repeat the story of how he slid down intothat camel's ball-cracking jaws such that I can still smell its eunuch-making snorts today?Alan, we miss you falling offyour bike, and holding forthon hieroglyphs and syntaxand black kites, or blunderinginto arguments with jumped-up officialdom and market-sharksand little horrors and big#wigsand Jane. Even Jane (like the frogs who used to rev-rev as you sang) misses your crooning choruses -'Beware of Long Lankin...'Beware all those unmarried girl students gazing at you from inside their Dalek costumes. ^Will you allow me to come in?^ you made them repeat if they were late. Task-master! And Asmi,Z
￼our old laundry man, he misses your Nile-smooth conversations up on that scorching roof abovethe domino slaps, sheeshafumes and warbling wailing casse drone of the cafe. And Ahmed, our Professor of Physics,misses those searching debates about the possibility and necessity of classrooms, about the ultimate origin ofour pay-packets...______ j Alan and Stuart, you weretwo golden companions during our year of prospecting for poverty, and still you are - despite that a-hundred-and- twenty-degree day out when you had cycled on ahead up the white mountain to reach the Valley of the Kingswell before us, unthinkingly bearing away the Greenings' unique and most precious yellow water bottle.# UptS