￼AT LES COLLETTES[for Serge Baudot]Scarcely any distance from the peopled plages extending their pebbled curve to Mentonand beyond, under the broiling Mediterranean sun, leave the boulevard and climb by the Passage Renoir to Les Collettes, built for my final years.In the hour before the house opens for the afternoon, stroll round the gardens, under those knotted olives, themselves a vast age before we came to occupy the place. Shade your eyes, as I had to, and look acrossthe chasm of light between here and the chateauatCagnes. Imagineme,beingwheeleddownthese paths in my wooden chair, or sitting hunched over that day's canvas, in my open-air studio. Then enter the house, and experience its coolness. Go up (as I could not, latterly, unaided)to the atelier on the first floor, and look down as I constantly did, on the powdery greenof the olive-trees. Consider them, if you with their gnarled contortions, a metaphor for my deformed hands' durability, through*Fortunately I had too much to keep me busyto worry about Cezanne and Matisse and thechanging the face of Art. As I gather turnedoutthecase. Ialwayskepttoasoledesign;whereas they saw from several vantage points, at once.Not only that, but they'd detect prismsand angles, where I'd see only smoothness.I sometimes wondered what chaos it could lead to - especially when that dark-eyed young fellow Picasso(born the year I did my 'Dejeuner des Canotiers')came bounding, like a goat, on the scene, promising to go further even than their extremes; painting what he thinks, not what he sees.One clear reason why, rather than contemplate the future, I was happy to remain in the present.care, pain.others
￼For all that I admit (in trust) to a desperation that once what is new has been supercededby the 'new' new, my early work, deridedat the time, may be seen in fairer perspective; it be conceded I opened shutters, let light in.*Sleepcomesoverme. Ihavebeentoomuchinthesun. And begin to be overtaken by some kind of delirium. Purveyor of order, resident in this rectilinear mansion, so meticulously terraced, I see myself at timesas comprising a geometry of my own: a sundialround whom revolve fragrances, subtleties of brightness and shade, which I transmute to canvas, in a process most easily attributed to sheer joie de vivre -if only to put the culture hounds off the scent.They could not comprehend, for instance, how Aline dictated her own style. Not least, through my delight in her rotundity: midway between fantasyand reality. More splendidly too, than with any other model, her skin responded to the light.Even that, now a secondary consideration.I miss her so much. Above all, the softnessof her fingers, as she wound the bandages on.This, among my memories, the one thing thatdullsthepain. Iwishshewerewithmeagain.
￼RENOIR IN ORKNEY[for George Mackay Brown]Monet might have made himself at home among these flat, green islands likegiantwaterlilies. Cezanneeven, with cliff-faces all cones and cylinders.Not that my vision is impaired. More a narrowing of the spectrum to a harmony of glistening silk,as though too much light were being let in -but without the embracing warmth towhichIamaccustomed: seascape and skyscape, a constant radiance. It would need the skin of the placeto burst a blood vessel, or myselfto stab at it with my palette knife:then there'd be something I could express. Only this morning, the world disappeared;the boat I was in surroundedby quicksilver; the bordering land erased in mist. Like a composer frantic for some variationbeyond a single high-pitched note sustained in his brain,I crave a cacophony of colour, before my mind disintegrates.At least with the fishermenIamathome. Theirtannedfeatures merit the mixing of pigments:my yellows and reds are in business again.As for the womenfolk, baiting the line has made their fingers like my own,and worse: knife-gashes, to the bone. Nudes are out. For one thing, their Kirkconcedes no such tradition.For another, contemplate the climate. Butsomethinginmebums. Imust startagain. Ihavefoundagirlwith skin like mother-of-pearl;am working on still lives of lobsters;and will distribute at the solsticecanvases of wild flowers, like mottled flame.
￼TRANSFORMATIONIt wasn't the Mediterranean, the yachts on the horizon,the bouillabaisse and cassis even, which completed our transformation:the ultimate confirmation that tout va bien came,after un bon repas,in the rue Pourquoi-pas.
￼FORT NAPOLEONWe sit entranced in the night air, watching a troupe of eight actresses alternate as Alice.The dew so heavy they slitheron the stage, till one goes barefoot, and the others follow suit. Finallythey vanish, leaving only the moon's refractions, and a filigreeof drenched prints, where they had been./
￼MILITARY MUSEUMToulonbasksbelow. Aredbox-kitestrains at its wire, a cliche of aspiration,giving song to the wind. On the summitof le Faron is a military museum, complete with simulations of the Allied landings inWorldWarTwo. Colouredbulbsflickeron a cartographic screen, at each site taken. On stereo speakers, crackly bombers roar.So many souls lost, but how few their number when set against a nuclear future.Covering the walls of the tower, these framed photographs, medals for valour, letters of condolence, regimental colours, are like the outmoded weapons ambiguous reminders of values valiantly fought for. Consider their selflessness, the readinessto sacrifice themselves, that their children might inherit a land free from war. For us: how preserve the pride nationhood engenders yet encompass the call for wider loyalties,thereby surmounting the barriers between men's minds? Such power, to decree not only what is butwhatwillonedaybe. Noranyassurance as to the outcome of human struggle: witnessthe sacking of Troy by deceitful Greece, lotsdrawnforprincessandqueen; themurder of Agamemnon, restoration of the old order; the founding of Rome. No place for arrogance, in history's progress: down the centuriesthe classic flaw for consecutive conquerors, to think their rule pre-ordained, or God-given who renege on their duty to their fellow men.