￼- 13 - FEETRoyal or common,Ugly or beautiful,Feet love the attention of lips Hands, eyes and moisturising lotion.Prehensile toesCan pick up any pinOff a floor and pinch like tweezers. The heel will always show its real age.The arch in the footOf a ballerinaIs a miniature Champs Elysees.Each arthritic bone has something to say.You may not like itSince what you hear may have Something to do with having had yours Beaten for what you wrote, said or did.Or worse for doingNothing at all when whatWas required of you was grace,Not turned-in or flat or calloused feet.
￼- 14 - PULSEIf I were a frozen lake,then the strumming would be loudest where the ice is thinnest and reveals what is most precious in that lake.A child is one thin sheet of icewith a faint pulse that can be located anywhere. As that child surfaces from sleep, or speeds/cross a room,or does something unexpected suddenly, the pulse trapped in the neck,just below the skin, unseen and unheard till now, flutters audibly.First it fades, like a voiceunder that ice, or an astonished face sliding from the thin, translucent surface that gave way to the body.When the noise finally ceases it’s the pulse retreated, retired to a part of the lake with ice that’s thick, obfuscated and lost.The prayer is for ice on a lake to keep, for the staggering pulse to remain,for ice to look its glassiest,most translucent and inviting always.
￼- XV - KNEESKnobbly and bony, they are maracas;broad and flat, landing pads for helicopters;in hot weather, pans for frying eggs; knees are often the only blemish on legs.Without them we’d star in The Wizard of Oz as the Tin Man, or a zombie in rigormortis.They crack and creak in someone else’s home, drawing stupid comments and flowering shame.If kept together they’re an effective contraceptive:"knees-up Mother Brown" doesn’t mean she has nice knees.They warn of cold spells, old age, flu;rub them down, oil them and they shine like new.Some people lose theirs for a debt;others wish they could lose the ones they’ve got.A frightened knee sounds like a woodpecker.A brave knee feels the way a frightened knee sounds.They are proud, strong men, two thirds high, bent at a coal face with miles of earth for sky;points of supplication; chivalrous courtship; bashers of groins; beggars for mercy; floor polishers; crawlers.Cathedral domes; twin vaults; skulls over delicate brains; bull-strong and bull-crazy; obedient and unquestioning;miracle carriers, I worship at your steps; knees, how can I serve you as you have served me?
￼- xvi - THIRTEEN VIEWS OF A PENIS-1-A Buddist demonstration of faith:how much drinking water (uncarbonated) can a monk draw up his untumid penis.-2-In an apartment on Manhattan’sUpper West Side a woman’s voice cries, "For God’s sake, don’t come!"-3-At a public congressional hearingthe prospective supreme court judgehas a boast about the size of his recounted.-4-In a house in East London in 1973 or 4,five brothers ages six to sixteen are circumcised on a table in a back room, consecutively.-5-The caption for a snap of a man whose penis is wrapped right around one thighreads, "He yanked it everyday for this."-6-All mothers in a certain tribe pop into their mouths the penis of crying babies to soothe them.-7-Needless to say it works everytime, unless there is somethingseriously wrong with the boy.
￼-8-A man who reached the North Pole desperately wanted to pee,despite a furious search he couldn’t find his.-9-Flaccid, boneless, chesspiece(a bishop), suspended upsidedown like a bat in a dark cave.- 10-Capable of growing up to thrice its resting size, when stimulated by touch or thought or praise.- 11-A blueprint for most weaponsof destruction: missiles, guns spears and sex without condoms.- 12-In old age, when all else fails,it may be the last thing leftto remind the old man of younger days.- 13 -We are living in the decline of the Penis Age. You can tell at a public urinal:a penis is always either too small or too large.
￼THE BODY IN QUESTION- 1 - EYEBROWSthat meet and merge bridge the left sideand right side of the brain.Bushy ones, thickones, are like hatspulled low over the eyes.They’re not sexythough the bearerof bushy eyebrows is oftenhighly sexed,and must pluck themto study and pass exams.Shave one or both entirely and your face becomes a big forehead;an assault zone,inviting slaps and jokes, that shines with anxiety.People who talkwith their eyebrowshave an extra dictionary;we’d be foolishto raise our own and not join them;especiallysince they may become Prime Minister one day.
￼- 2 - EYESThey lie. They don’t mean to.They twinkle. You can’t stop them.They water themselves, but only grow tired. They are most honest with their lids down. They beg to be robbed of sleep.They die on us long before the heart stops (when it decides it can’t afford to love). They die by losing their shine,by hiding their whites. Somehowthey are able to watch themselvesknowing full well they are quite dead.
￼- 3 - NOSTRILSHe cuts-back the hairspoking out two moist tunnelssneezing at the microscopic dustoff his Byron not opened since 1979 the year sweet Minnie Rippfeton died and he sneezed volleys as he criedin his stupid search of Don Juanfor a fitting line, just one.
￼- 4 - LIPSThermometers for love, lustand everything above or below them.Hold an ice cube to the lips; watch the whole body react;see it harvest a goosepimple crop long before the lips change from redto purple or if dark already, darker still, shrivellingto dried prunes as the bloodlips find so fattening is driven out.Don’t the toes and fingers curl, arch, stretch, shake, hypotherm?Isn’t the effect on the scrotumor labia exactly that of Joyce’s sea?r
￼- 5 - CLAVICLEIf water gathers there,then it must be becauseyou are caught in a downpour.If tears reach that far,then your grief is major, although you may not know it.If your lover can’t help showering there' with kisses, the blessing of such attentionwill turn sour. Test it.Try No, in your haughtiest Napoleonic grandeur.A perfect clavicleis a curse in disguise-is grief birthmarked- made flesh and bone./
￼- 6 - NIPPLESSafety pins or rings through them are acts of self-abuse;perfectly reasonable in a democracy and perfectly vulgar.If Jesus upset the moneymakersin the house of God, his fathers house, by pedalling faith, at least hiswere the goods of the soul.When nipples are attentive to the tongue, when they harden in concentration,they take on aspects of the mind;they relocate consciousnessfrom the head to the chest;they argue on our behalfthat faith has at least two sides none of which can be pinned down.