￼e3Copyright © David Constantine 1994 ISBN: 1 85224 299 XFirst published 1994 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.LEGAL NOTICEAll rights reserved. No part of this book may bereproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without prior written permission from Bloodaxe Books Ltd.Requests to publish work from this book must be sent to Bloodaxe Books Ltd.David Constantine has asserted his right underSection 77 of the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988 to be identified as the author of this work.ACKNOWLEDGEMENTSThis poem wasfirst published, in instalments, Ain P N was broadcast r|V \. on BBC Radioyrf^in 1994, and parts were read onRadio 4 by M arina W arner in her 1994 Reith Lectures. (LS\j CX -l*J C <7^-Caspar 1-8 5/7/94 6:53 pm Page 4Cover printing by J. Thomson Colour Printers Ltd, Glasgow.Printed in Great Britain byBell & Bain Limited, Glasgow, Scotland.
￼Caspar 1-8 5/7/94 6:54 pm Page 5Dedication or epigraph?Vywhu u^: //*. /e^v^Lj(~^ A^i IL ii .%