￼fleur adcock has published ten previous books o f poetry, and has edited several anthologies, including The Faber Book o f Twentieth Century Women’s Poetry. She has translated collections by tw o Romanian poets as well as a book of medieval Latin poems, The Virgin & the Nightingale (Bloodaxe). Fleur Adcock has rec­ eived several awards, including a Cholmondeley Award in 1976 and a New Zealand National Book Award in 1984, and she was given an OBE in 1996. She lives in London.AUTHOR PHOTOGRAPHISBfsl 1 -8 5 2 2 4 -5 3 0 -19781852245306COVER PAINTING & DETAILHans Holbein the Younger (i497/8-1543): A Lady with a Squirrel and a Starling© NATIONAL GALLERY, LONDONNEIL ASTLEY£ 10.959 78I852 245306Fleur Adcock is one of Britain’s most accomplished poets. Her poised, ironic poems are tense and tightly controlled as well as shrewdly laconic, and often chilling as she unmasks the deceptions of love or unravels family lives. Disarmingly conversational in style, they are remarkable for their psychological insight and their unsentimental, mischievously casual view of personal relationships.Born in New Zealand, she has explored questions of identity and rootedness throughout her work, both in relation to her personal allegiances to her native and adopted countries as well as her family history, whose long-dead characters she brings to life. She has also written movingly of birth, death and bereavement, and has tackled political issues with honest indignation and caustic wit.This first Collected edition of her poetry replaces her Selected Poems, with the addition of work from her later Oxford collections The Incident Book, Time-Zones and Looking Back. All her most celebrated poems are here, from the highly entertaining ‘Against Coupling’, ‘Smokers For Celibacy’ and T h e Prize-W inning Poem’ to modern classics such as T h e Ex-Queen Amongst the Astronomers’ and Things’ - as well as the notorious one about kissing John Prescott...‘Adcock has a deceptively laid-back tone, through which the sharper edge of her talent is encountered like a razor blade in a peach’- carol ann duffy, Guardian‘Adcock’s reputation has been founded on her spare, conversational poems, in which the style is deceptively simple, apparently translucent...a voice which teases both readerandsubject’- joshapcott,TLS‘Most of Fleur Adcock’s best poems have something to do with bed: she writes well about sex, very well about illness, and very well indeed about dream ing...Her imagination thrives on what threatens her peace of mind, and only when she is unguarded can these threats have their full creative effect...Throughout her writing life, she has made a fine art from holding on to principles of orderliness and good clear sense; but she has made an even finer one from loosening her grip on them ’ - ANDREW MOTION, TLS51Q0DAX6 BQDK5
￼Fleur AdcockP O E M S 1960-2000POETRY BOOK SOCIETY SPECIAL COMMENDATIONFLEUR ADCOCK POEMS 1960-2000 B150DAX6