￼NO MORE POEMS ABOUT PAINTINGS?EDNA LONGLEYIn 1955 Kingsley Amis famously declared that, among other taboo topics, 'nobody wants any more poems about paintings . . . or art galleries'.1That Amis was whistling in the wind is suggested by John Dixon Hunt's statement in 1980 at the start of a lecture 'On Poems on Paintings': The incidence of poems on paintings, especially in the twentieth century, is quite astonishing. And they form only one part of a group which, besides poems on actual historical art­ works, includes poems on imaginary paintings, poems on actual ar­ tists and on imaginary ones; poems on visual arts generally, and poems that employ the trope of 'painting' . . . as a metaphor for the poetic act'.2 In his lecture Hunt gives some bad poems over­ respectful attention. And I think Amis has a point: possibly more poems about paintings than about almost anything else are likely to end up in a Pseuds' Corner column. Also, addiction to the prac­ tice (e.g. Wallace Stevens) can be a form of imaginative auto­ eroticism. Certainly, quality is unevenly spread. In this paper I will be suggesting that Ireland comes off well. I will also be asking whether there is any broader significance for Irish poetry in the fact that Derek Mahon and Paul Durcan, for instance, have so notably defied the Amis fiat. Two of Mahon's collections take their names from paintings: Courtyards in Delft and The Hunt by Night; two others have Munch and Botticelli images on their covers. Two Dur­ can covers reproduce pictures by Edward Matguire; one reproduces Ortachala Belle with a Fan by the Russian Niko Pirosmani. Going Home to Russia backs up its cover by containing five poems intrigu- ingly said to be after various painters. Again, in Paul Muldoon's last two collections references to painting and painters have multiplied.Whenever the issue of 'poetry and painting' comes up, so do the90
￼No More Poems About Paintings 91Pre-Raphaelites. Does the fact that Yeats 'learned to think in the midst of the last phase of Pre-Raphaelitism'3 still influence the practice of his successors? Poetry's consciousness of painting inevitably highlights and measures its aesthetic self-consciousness, tilts the see­ saw away from history. As Bram Dijkstra says, in an essay on Wallace Stevens and William Carlos Williams: 'The study of the in­ fluence of painting on literature is primarily a study of motive and method . . . A poet's response to painting can tell us why he is a poet and why his poetry has taken its specific form'.4 (Stevens notoriously bought new paintings when he ran out of inspiration.) But his response can also tell us about aesthetic history and the history of poetry. Ernst Gombrich worries about the way in which both historians of ideas and philosophers of aesthetics downgrade 'mechanisms of tradition' i.e. the convention of particular art forms.5In my view some of the best contemporary Irish poetry still has an illuminating context in English post-Romanticism and in mechanisms which Yeats made central to that tradition. (I think there are more neutral and even positive ways to track the 'aestheticism' Yeats transplanted to Ireland than to construe it simply as the mark of the coloniser.) Ian Fletcher, writing about 'Leda and the Swan' as a Rossettian iconic sonnet, records as 'One of the curiosities of Yeats criticism . . . that the source-materials most accessible to the master, most likely to become a permanent part of his mental history, poems and paintings of the middle and late nineteenth century, have been generally ignored for more modish zones'.6 Likewise, more modish critical approaches may have neglected some of the specific aesthetic courses pursued by poets for whom Yeats is inescapably part of their mental history.The rest of this paper will first touch on the well-worn business of ut pictura. Then I will revert to Yeats and the shading of Pre- Raphaelitism into Symbolism. After that, I will refer briefly to Louis MacNeice and John Hewitt in the post-Yeatsian phase. My ultimate objective is to examine a few poems by Seamus Heaney, Paul Mul- doon, Derek Mahon and Paul Durcan in the light of previous theorising.The late American poet and art critic Frank O'Hara wrote a delightful poem called 'Why I am Not a Painter'.7In this poem the painter Mike Goldberg puts the word SARDINES into a painting. Some time later the poet-speaker starts off a poem by thinking about the colour 'orange'. But Goldberg's finished work contains ‘just/let­ ters' and O'Hara's poem ends:
￼92Irish Literature and CultureMy poem is finished and I haven't mentionedorange yet. It's twelve poems. I callit ORANGES. And one day in a gallery I see Mike's painting, called SARDINES.Sardines and Oranges. Chalk and Cheese. The image begins where the word vanishes. The word begins where the image vanishes. I agree with O'Hara's implied separation of artistic powers and processes except at the point of imaginative origin. SinceLessing's demolition of utpictura poesis many commentators have pressed further the distinction bet­ ween spatial and sequential art-forms. These tend to be specialist art and literary critics, e.g. Rudolph Arnheim's Visual Thinking on the one side, P. N. Furbank's Reflections on the Word 'Image'on the other. It is the philosophers, who in the words of W. J. T. Mitchell, 'crave unity, analogy, harmony and universality'.8 Hence the 'linguistic determinism' which Arnheim criticises,9Derrida cutting off the ear to universalise the text, and the tendency of new semiotics to sophisticate old ut pictura. M y own suggestion is that relationship-in-difference — sardines and oranges — is not the same thing as homogenisation. Mitchell, despite his critique of the search for a master-theory, attaches a homogenising title to his study: Iconology: Image, Test, Ideology. And by underprivileging the aesthetic in his argument, he is able to con­ tend tha t the politics of different critics and periods, rather than essen­ tial distinctions, govern discussion of 'the text-image difference'.10I shall shortly be suggesting that the literary politics of Modernism itself has obscured a primarily aesthetic issue.Not only theorists but practitioners can fall into the trap of homogenisation. Two contemporary English poets who, in my view, lose their balance are Charles Tomlinson and Craig Raine. Some of their poems make a useful contrast with those by the Irish poets. Even when not writing about paintings, Tomlinson tends to produce art- theory rather than poems, art-criticism rather than criticism of life. His poem 'Paring the Apple'11relates to Pieter de Hoogh's ‘Woman Peel­ ing Apples' (a genre painting also relevant to Seamus Heaney's sonnet about peeling potatoes in the sequence 'Clearances'):There are portraits and still-lifes. And there is paring the apple.And then? Paring it slowly, From under cool yellow Cold-white emerging . . .
￼No More Poems About Paintings 93Tomlinson's poem glosses the painting rather than discovers possibilities in its mode, colours and shapes. The punning punch­ line merely announces a fusion of form with emotion, of looking at the painting with reading the poem:The cool bladeSevers between coolness, apple-rind Compelling a recognition.In contrast with Tomlinson's effort to reproduce 'stillness' by repeating single words — cool, blade — Heaney's sonnet creates its own visual and moral relation between objects and people. And he exploits the resources of his sequential medium to 'break the silence' and thus emphasise it:When all the others were away at MassI was all hers as we peeled potatoes.They broke the silence, let fall one by one Like solder weeping off the soldering iron: Cold comforts set between us, things to share Gleaming in a bucket of clean water.And again let fall. Little pleasant splashesFrom each other's work would bring us to our senses.The pulse beating between 'solder . . . soldering' and 'let fall . . . And again let fall' amounts to more than repetition. It underscores a momentum which introduces life into the still shot of the icon- ically posed memory.Where Tomlinson abstracts, Craig Raine over-visualises, tries to beat visual representation at its own game. His sequence of poems, 'Pre-Raphaelite Paintings'12, gilds the Pre-Raphaelite lily:Suddenly there are little green vultures hatched from varnished petits foursThey perch like envious angels, plottingin groups of two and three, with cloak wings.I was expecting a more expansive gesture,a coup d'etat, not these little stings of greenthat will go through a pineapple stage . . . Things seem, well, frivolous —the wych elm buds and wafts its drying fingernails, careful to keep them apart.In the autumn martyrdoms, tonsured heads will fall.(Chestnut Trees)
￼94 Irish Literature and Culture'Chestnut Trees' invites us to visualise vultures, petits fours, angels, pineapples, fingernails and monks. (The phrase 'little stings of green' works better because it evokes the visual as sensation instead of sen­ sationalising the visual.) Neither as image-cluster nor as rhythm does the poem fully cohere: 'Things seem, well, frivolous . . .' seems a fairly frivolous primum mobile. Gilbert Adair, in his brilliant Myths and Memories, argues that 'the characteristic trait of Raine's metaphors (similies, rather) is, paradoxically, their pedantic, fun­ damentally tautological literalness. 'This looks like that' is what they say, over and over again; and, so in most instances, it does; and that, it would seem, is that.13Adair finds that words themselves fail to 'reverberate' in Raine's poetry because that 'would fatally com­ promise the analogy which is often [a word's] sole raison d'etre'.14 The poems by Tomlinson and Raine, I would suggest, are parasitic on another medium in proportion as they are deficient in their own. This indicates an impaired relation to the tradition which they im­ plicitly and explicity invoke.That tradition is the late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century interaction of English Pre-Raphaelitism with elements in French Sym­ bolism. I agree with those critics who increasingly stress the in­ digenous contribution, especially to Yeats's consummation of the movement. Frank Kermode's insistence on 'native Romantic roots'15 has been developed, for instance, by John Dixon Hunt in The Pre- Raphaelite Imagination 1848—1900 and Alan Robinson in Poetry, Painting and Ideas 1885—1914. Hunt argues that 'the symbolism which [their] discussions of Blake document and support is perhaps the central mode of the Pre-Raphaelite imagination'.16He describes Yeats as 'the first to appreciate how much the actual practice of the Pre-Raphaelite arts endorsed the more vocal and formulated pro­ gramme of French symbolism'.17 In 'Art and Ideas' (1913) Yeats conceived 'our reintegration of the mind, our more profound Pre- Raphaelitism'18specifically to counter the Modernist view of verbal- visual relations put forward by Pound, Wyndham Lewis and theVor- ticists. This project for 'reintegration', together with the Pre- Raphaelite doctrine of mutual support between the arts, culminates in what one critic has termed 'Yeats's masterpiece in the Rossettian mode'19i.e. 'Lapis Lazuli'.In New Poems and Last Poems the solidarity of the arts functions as a metaphor and rhetoric for the solidity of Yeats's 'old man's eagle' vision. The punning opening line of 'The Municipal Gallery Revisited'— 'Around me the images of thirty years' — unites image as life, image as painting, image as poetry. Painting constitutes the inter­
￼No More Poems About Paintings 95mediary stage, as the visual arts often did in Yeats's creative pro­ cess ('Leda and the Swan' is only a particularly rich instance). In 'Lapis Lazuli', as in 'The Municipal Gallery Revisited', Yeats lets us watch him transpose a visual art-object into a verbal one. Animating the stone, giving it movement, historical sequence and finally sound suggests how Yeats activated mechanisms of poetic tradition which eluded his Pre-Raphaelite predecessors. More profound pre- Raphaelitism betokened more profound symbolism: a symbolism which did not drain vitality from syntax and rhythm; a symbolism which reintegrated, not only intellect, but speech and drama into Yeats's nineties sister-arts aesthetic of 'sounds, colours and forms' (see the twin essays 'Symbolism in Painting'/'The Symbolism of Poetry'). I suggest that, as a result, poets who follow Yeats negotiate more adroitly with the visual arts than do those who follow Pound.Indeed, it's possible to see Symbolism as splitting into two, or as parting company with Modernism, over a different conception of such relations. The paths diverge at Imagism. It seems significant that the most important contemporary critics of Pound and Imagism, Robert Frost and Edward Thomas, based their critique on this poetry's aspiration to the condition of the visual arts, its demotion of speech and rhythm. 'Kiln-dried tabule poetry'20Frost called it, and he scorned 'eye readers' and eye writers.21Of course Modern­ ist verse-layout often tries to exploit spatiality instead of providing a notation which alerts the reader's ear and cues his voice (and perhaps alerts his intelligence: W. J. T. Mitchell plays down the con­ nection, traced by Kermode and others, between the spatial aesthetics of Modernism and the rise of Fascism). A recent off-shoot of this is the post-Modernist concept of 'radial reading' which collapses language and history into collage. Jerome McGann has said: 'every verse form is a spatialised form once it is committed to a written mode'22(would he say the same of a musical score?). Interestingly, Gombrich interprets Lessing's Laokdon primarily as resistance to the encroachment on literature of principles derived from the visual arts.Alan Robinson — the title of whose book revealingly contrasts with Mitchell's — reminds us how deeply discussions of art and literature interpenetrated at the turn of the century. His map, like Frost's, marks a crossroads at Imagism. He argues that Imagism repudiated the transcendental impulses, the Hegelian idealism, which had hitherto unified different branches of avant-garde aesthetics. Robinson terms Imagism 'a truncated Symbolist aesthetic'23 (con­ trast Yeats's 'great rooted blossomer'). And the theory of T. E.as well as the practice of Pound and others, underlines ther
￼96 Irish Literature and Culturedirect challenge presented by visual Imagism to Yeats's rhythmic Symbolism (even in the nineties rhythm, if 'wavering' rather than 'energetic', was intrinsic to the Yeatsian aesthetic). Hulme says: 'Regular metre to this impressionist poetry is cramping, jangling, meaningless, and out of place. Into the delicate pattern of images and colour it introduces the heavy, crude pattern of rhetorical verse' (my italics).24I would argue that the methods of Heaney, Muldoon, Mahon and Durcan — not only in poems about paintings — belong to the tradi­ tion of more profound Pre-Raphaelitism rather than to the M odern­ ist spatial aesthetics; and that the varied uses to which they put the visual arts illustrate the diversity of that tradition as well of their own aesthetics.Obviously since Yeats the small change of the sister-arts has con­ tinued — Irish painters supplying designs and images for pamphlets, poets eulogising painters in exhibition-catalogues, Louis Le Brocquy emblems all over the literary shop. Much of this collaboration descends, like the Cuala Press and the Dolmen Press, from William Morris and the decorative-craft aspect of Pre-Raphaelitism. An outstanding instance of cross-inspiration from the visual arts side is the portraiture of the late Edward M ^uire — though inspired by poetry rather than poems: a reaction against his commissioned paint­ ings of the likes of Charles Haughey. Maguire painted twenty-five portraits of poets and other writers: the best-known appears on the back-cover of Heaney's North. Three aspects of these portraits tie in with Pre-Raphaelite visual literariness: firstly, what Dorothy Walker terms their 'applied rather than inherent' colour25; second­ ly, their combination of meticulous detail with an aura of mystery; thirdly, their culturally interesting substitution of the male poet (eyes and hair to the fore) for the iconic female Muse.On the other side of the post-Yeatsian fence it's remarkable that two poets who mediate in contrasting ways between Yeats and the contemporary, namely Louis MacNeice and John Hewitt, should have had formative connections with the visual arts. These connec­ tions also exemplify two kinds of affiliation which need not be mutually exclusive: consciousness of the international avant-garde and closeness to local artists. It is not widely appreciated, outside MacNeice criticism, that MacNeice's first intellectual mentor was An­ thony Blunt, once chiefly celebrated as an art critic, and already such at school. In the early 1920s Blunt played truant from Marlborough to attend art-exhibitions in Paris. MacNeice's accounts of his own early attitudes to poetry are permeated by allusions to painting. He
￼No More Poems About Paintings 97read Eliot after becoming habituated to reproductions of Picasso and Matisse. Blunt's artistic credo at this time was Pure Form, a par­ ticularly severe brand of abstraction advocated by the young Le Cor­ busier among others. MacNeice's retrospects on Pure Form are in­ variably ironical. Thus his 'Eclogue for Christmas' (1933) attacks Pure Form and abstraction for selling humanity short:abstracting and dissecting meThey have made of me pure form, a symbol or a pastiche.Stylised profile, anything but soul and flesh.However, MacNeice distinguished between the degrees to which pain­ ting and literature could afford to ditch 'soul and flesh'. The following statement (1936) repudiates Modernist homogenisation, and is relevant to the issues of semiotics and radial reading: 'It is no doubt possible to use words merely for decoration, as the M oors used tags of the Koran to decorate their walls at heights where no one could read them[SARDINES again]. To do this in literature seems a perversion.'26 Yet MacNeice did not emulate Blunt's conversion from Pure Form to Marxism (indeed he saw it as plus ffl change). In 1936 they visited Spain together, less to sniff civil war than to frequent the Prado. In MacNeice's autobiography The Strings are False painting focuses his aesthetic-political disagreement with Blunt. MacNeice enthuses over Goya's creative vitality and ideological self- contradiction as against Blunt's dream of 'in every parish a Diego Rivera'.27 In Autumn Journal VI MacNeice uses Goya-images to imply the condition of contemporary Spain: 'in the Prado half-/wit princes looked from the canvas they had paid for/G oya had. thelaugh-/But can what is corrupt be cured by laughter?'Further, a conflict between poetry and painting contributes to MacNeice's most fundamental formal preoccupation: the right rela­ tion between flux and pattern. MacNeice also had a painterlyobsession with colours and with shifting prismatic light — initially, a response to Irish light: 'your water-shafted air/Of amethyst and moonstone' ('Valediction'). Thus he wished his poetry to follow 'the living curve' not turn it into a dead geometry. (This has im­ plications for his imaginative relation to politics as contrasted with Pound's.) So it's another case of resisting ut pictura-, indeed moving pictures* cinema, helped to resolve the problem. MacNeice's early sonnet 'Poussin' (Blunt was to write definitive works on Poussin) turns a classical painting into a post-impressionist painting by see­ ing it in a light not literally present, and by stressing the flow of perception over its surfaces. The poem shows the influence of Virginia Woolf on MacNeice: ,
￼98Irish Literature and CultureIn that Poussin the clouds are like golden tea,And underneath the limbs flow rhythmically,The cupids' blue feathers beat musically,And we dally and dip our spoon in the golden tea. The tea flows down the steps and up again,An old-world fountain, pouring from sculptured lips, And the chilly marble drop like sugar slipsAnd is lost in the dark gold depths, and the refrain Of tea-leaves floats about and in and out,And the motion is still as when one walks and the moon Walks parallel but relations remain the same.And thus we never reach the dregs of the cup,Though we drink it up and drink it up and drink it up. And thus we dally and dip our spoon.'Poussin' is another Rosettian sonnet: one which explicitly substitutes perpetual motion for the sculptural model of such a poem. And it does so by means of a rhythmic rhetoric which would have pained T. E. Hulme: refrain, internal rhyme, dynamic assonance. The poem indeed uses words like 'rhythmically', 'musically', 'refrain' in opposi­ tion to images within the picture of 'sculptured lips' and 'chilly marble’. So MacNeice animates 'cold pastoral', solves the problem of stillness and motion in a verbal medium — partly by suggesting that the poem will never quite end: 'And thus we drink it up and drink it up and drink it up'. This both makes the sequential run on the spot, and imitates the potential infinity of looking and of the painting's effect. Perhaps the difference between this and the Tomlinson poem is that 'Paring the Apple' simply looks at a pic­ ture; 'Poussin' dramatises looking.John Hewitt's poetry received no particular formal impulse from painting, and his taste in the visual arts always stopped short of Pure Form. Instead, his role as 'art gallery man' at the Ulster Museum in Belfast, from the 1930s to 1950s, consorted with his whole effort to generate cultural self-awareness in the North. This agenda owed something to Yeats and the utopian (William Morris) wing of Pre- Raphaelitism, as well as to contemporary Scottish and Welsh movements. Thus in his book Art in Ulster Hewitt defines the essence of the Ulster visual artist as 'not primarily a question of birth, of blood or accent; [but] the condition of being involved in Ulster life and Irish landscape, and finding therein the material for . . . art'.28In his purchases for the museum, then civically con­ trolled, Hewitt did his best with limited money and city councillors
￼No More Poems About Paintings 99who objected to nudes. Colin Middleton and John Luke were the local painters he particularly favoured. Hewitt's long poem 'Freehold' (1946) names the artists first in its fervent regional cultural 'Roll Call'.29 The revised version forty years later (in the collection Freehold) retains a central episode in which Hewitt and Luke, poet and painter, walk near Armagh sharing a landscape and its expres­ sion: The long five miles of road to Killylea/Held only half the things we had to say.' However, Middleton and Luke are far from being realist painters, and Hewitt always insisted on Ulster painters ac­ quainting themselves with international activity in the visual arts.Hewitt's curatorship at the Ulster Museum undoubtedly helped to give young writers and others 'loftier thought,/sweeter emotion'. Seamus Heaney, who most directly followed up the links Hewitt forged between landscape poetry and painting, says as much in his introduction to an exhibition he selected from the museum's holdings: '1 began to visit the Ulster Museum when I was an undergraduate at Queen's University in the late fifties . . . John Hewitt's career as a curator probably established that vital connection between pic­ tura and poesis.'30In fact it was Middleton rather than Hewitt who represented the older literary-artistic generation to young writers in the Belfast of the early sixties (Middleton and his wife Kate both wrote poetry). Hewitt was then running the Herbert Art Gallery in Coventry. The first collections of Heaney, Mahon and Longley all contain a poem dedicated to Colin Middleton. Heaney's 'In Small Townlands' sees Middleton as including and transcending those physically absorbed rural craftsman that his early poetry envies and mimics:In small townlands his hogshair wedge Will split the granite from the clayTill crystal in the rock is bared: Loaded brushes hone an edgeOn mountain blue and heather grey. Outcrops of stone contract, outstared.The spectrum bursts, a bright grenade, When he unlocks the safety catchOn morning dew, on cloud, on rain. The splintered lights slice like a spade That strips the land of fuzz and blotch, Pares clean as bone, cruel as the painThat strikes in a wild heart attack. His eyes, thick, greedy lenses, fire