￼154 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’Protestant Irish culture.15 In Church and State in Modern Ireland John Whyte observes: ‘deference to authority has been a feature not just of Irish ecclesiastical life, but of Irish life in general’.16De Valera as ‘the chief, national founding-father and custodian of the past, managed to fuse the auras of father as paterfamilias and father as priest. M uldoon’s poem ‘Cuba’ makes this link, together with an Irish-American political connection. A father telling off hisdaughter for ‘Running out to dances in next to nothing’ goes on:‘Those Yankees were touch and go as it was - If you’d heard Patton in Armagh -But this Kennedy’s nearly an IrishmanSo he’s not much better than ourselves.And him with only to say the word.If you’ve got anything on your mindMaybe you should make your peace with God.’17In the last stanza the girl confesses ‘Bless me, Father, for I have sinned’. But the poem in fact exposes the sins of fathers, men laying down the law} controlling women and taking up arms.Fathers in Northern Irish literature calibrate tradition and tran­ sition, small shifts in the land of ‘Not an Inch’. Muldoon calls it ‘writing about what is immediately in front of me, or immediately over my shoulder’.18 If I now concentrate chiefly upon poetic fathers, it is because poetry more radically transmutes the autobio­ graphical into the symbolic, looks further round the corner of the status quo. The actual fathers of poets include the following mixed bag: a Belfast shipyard worker, a South Derry cattle-dealer and small farmer, a Brooklyn exile, a market-gardener in Armagh orchard- country, a headmaster, and an English furniture salesman who fought in both world wars. The generation gaps span movements from country to city, from country to country, and in all but one case to a university education never achieved by the father.Brian Friel’s drama has close associations with poetry, and the fathers in his plays since 1969 represent one pole of perception. In Aristocrats and Translations they personify the inadequacy of what the past has transmitted. The ‘aristocratic’ O’Donnells of Ballybeg Hall are described, with Friel’s evident sanction, as:four generations of a great Irish Catholic legal dynasty...a family with­ out passion, without loyalty, without commitments; administering the law for anyone who happened to be in power; above all wars and famines and civil strife and political upheaval; ignored by its Protestant counter­ parts, isolated from the mere Irish...15Symbolically maimed by a stroke, the current head of the house focuses the play’s attack on collaborationist, Redmondite, West British
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:32 am Page‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 155traditions in Irish politics. (Oddly, Aristocrats is usually interpreted as an exercise in Chekhovian melancholia.) Hugh, the hedge-school­ master father in Translations, is more positively conceived. From the historical moment preceding the O’Donnells’ amoral deracination, he hands on authentic qualities and traditions of ‘the mere Irish’. Nevertheless, the play criticises his pandering to colonialist expecta­ tions about the drunken, verbalising Irishman, who speaks a ‘language ...full of the mythologies of fantasy and hope and self-deception’.20 Hugh’s son Owen, once a literal and metaphorical ‘collaborator’ in the Ordnance Survey of Ireland (begun in the 1820s), finally rejects his own compromises and his father’s ‘confusion’,21when the British soldiers threaten the community. In both these plays the sense of weak fathers having let down their children makes a political comment on the history of Northern Catholics since 1921. This may be why Friel misrepresents the Ordnance Survey as an imposed Anglicisation, rather than as an effort - supervised by the best Gaelic scholars - to standardise the orthography of Gaelic place-names. (j.H. Andrews, historian of the Ordnance Survey, has recently castigated ‘the credulity shown by serious scholars in swallowing Translations as a record of historical truth or at any rate historical probability’. 22)The work of three poets from Protestant backgrounds situates the father with reference to rejection, reinvention, dislocation. Derek Mahon’s poetry takes as its premi^ even its sine qua non, alienation from familial and tribal origins. In ‘Ecclesiastes’, which satirises the Protestant religious and political will to domination, the speaker resists blood-calls to ‘nourish a fierce zeal’ andlove the January rains when they darken the dark doors and sink hardinto the Antrim hills, the bog meadows, the heaped graves of your fathers.”‘Fathers’, with its biblical ring, is a common Protestant word for ancestry and history. John Hewitt’s best-known poem, ‘Once Alien Here’, begins ‘Once alien here my fathers built their house’, and Mahon’s ‘Canadian Pacific’ evokes Ulster-Scots and Scots noncon­ formist emigrants to the new world as ‘Those gaunt forefathers’. Mahon has written no poem based on his actual father; but his early poems about anarchic male relatives - ‘Grandfather’ and ‘Wicked Uncle’ - imply a son’s revolt by subverting ‘adult’ bourgeois Prot­ estant respectability.His patriarchal poles seem to be the wrathful father and the renegade.Tom Paulin’s Liberty Tree (1983) attacks Protestant culture in more narrowly political terms: Protestantism as Unionism. In ‘Father
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:32 am Page156 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ of History’ he seems to invent an ideal forebear, a schoolmasterwho buildsLisburn like a warmplain-spoken sermon on the rights of man. A sunned Antrim face, he maybe praysto the New Light in a relished dialect... z<Certainly a sunnier Antrim than Mahon’s. This prelapsarian vision of the Protestant United Irishmen who should have begotten history, names the specific Republican fathers of its attitudes: ‘Munro, Hope, Porter and McCracken.’In Michael Longley’s poetry the father focuses questions of belonging rather than longing: an Englishman who fought twice for his country. The poem ‘Second Sight’25imagines a disorienting visit to London during which the speaker asks: ‘Where is my father’s house, where my father?’, what of an English dimension in Ireland, an Irish dimension in England? There is a contrast between two poems about the father’s war-service written before and after 1969. The earlier, ‘In Memoriam’,26 sets out to ‘read’the father’s personal ‘history’ as a means of comprehending the‘death andnightmare’ of the Great War. The later poem, ‘Wounds’,27 uses the father’s witness of the war - ‘the Ulster Division at the Somme/Going over the top with “Fuck the Pope!”/ “No surrender!” ’ - as a perspective on civil war in Ulster, on the still more quintessential futility of deaths such as a bus-conductorshot through the head By a shivering boy who wandered inBefore they could turn the television down Or tidy away the supper dishes.To the children, to a bewildered wife,I think ‘Sorry Missus’ was what he said.Paul Fussell comments: ‘the irony always associated with the Somme attack remains to shade that conclusion. But at least the Somme attack had some swank and style: one could almost admire, if after­ ward one had to deplore.’28To digress briefly from fathers: the Somme occupies the imagin­ ations of Longley, Martin, Leitch (Barbour Brown reflects: ‘So many of his friends’ names in the Deaths column of The Ballymena Observer')TM McGuinness. The latter, who comes from Donegal, is unique in approaching the theme from a background supposedly alien. More commonly, the world wars divide imaginations, if more subtly than the way Remembrance Day every November divides Dublin. Denial of any Catholic Irish participation in the wars
￼‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 157resembles the cultural suppression that obliges Paulin’s Protestant United Irishmen to ‘endure posterity without a monument’. By a nice paradox, Stewart Parker’s play about McCracken, Northern Star (1984), attracted Belfast audiences as much as Observe the Sons o f Ulster drew Dublin. This may help to change something, if not any results. However, Seamus Heaney’s poem ‘In Memoriam Francis Ledwidge’30finds this Irish Catholic’s involvement in the war imagin­ atively unresolvable, although the theme clearly compels him. Where­ as for Longley the English ‘soldier-poets’ such as Isaac Rosenberg and Edward Thomas are declared literary-historical touchstones, Heaney’s ‘In Memoriam’ regrets: ‘In you, our dead enigma, all the strains/Criss-cross in useless equilibrium’ (‘strains’ puns on another genetic definition of history). Nevertheless, the poem’s own blood­ line includes one trope of First World War poetry, the haunting rural flashback, in the beautiful image: ‘Ghosting the trenches with a bloom of hawthorn’. Other elegies by Heaney recall Wilfred Owen.In telling Ledwidge, ‘You were not keyed or pitched like these true-blue ones’, which may impute undue patriotism to the British dead (‘True Blue’ figures on Orange banners), manifests a deep Northern assumption about tribal inheritance. John Montague’s The Rough Field is grounded on such assumptions. ‘The Cage’31 introduces the poet’s father as ‘My father, the least happy man I have known’ and also refers to ‘the lost years in Brooklyn’. ‘Molly Bawn’, in The Dead Kingdom (1984) still more explicitly places the father in the context of ‘the embittered diaspora of/dispossessed Northern Republicans’. The next poem, ‘A Muddy Cup’, explores the poet’s separation as a child, not only from his father, but from his mother who gave him to be fostered. This family ‘diaspora’, echoing in the repeated adjective ‘lost’, both underlies and under­ lines the historical losses mourned by The Rough Field: ‘shards of a lost tradition’; a dead Gaelic civilisation; the vanished, vanquished O’Neills; the Flight of the Earls; the ‘Loss’ column of the New Omagh Road balance sheet; ‘Our finally lost dream of man at home/ in a rural setting.’Montague’s Tyrone terrain shows how local as well as family history influences the shape of the past in a poet’s imagination. Local historical societies are much thicker on the ground in the North than in the South, perhaps for obvious territorial reasons: every Northerner is an amateur local historian. Barbour Brown’s obsessive researches into his ‘Valley’ parallel Leitch’s own curiosity. Brown progresses from church records to ‘lists of rocks and plants and buildings’ to a voyeuristic interest in ‘the forked animal again’, thus
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:33 am Page158 'WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’becoming ‘this spy creeping about the hedgerows’.32Similarly, Paul Muldoon’s poetry can be read as alternative, transgressive parish- history. Seamus Heaney presents South Derry as a lusher field than Montague’s Tyrone, and as the product of more complex geographical and historical co-ordinates. ‘Terminus’, from the pamphlet Hailstones (1984), ends on a vista of less than total loss:Baronies, parishes met where I was born. When I stood on the central stepping stoneI was the last earl on horseback in midstream Still parleying, in earshot of his kernes.33Heaney’s midpoint ‘parleying’ gives rise to more than one version of the past in his poetry, even different fathers. At theoutset (mid­ sixties) the figure based on his actual father sums up apositive in­ heritance of skills and values which the poet transmutes within his own medium. Several poems dwell on the responsibility of ‘following’, and being followed by, earlier generations. In ‘Follower’ qualities of the father define qualities of the poetry: technical ‘expertise’, weight: ‘His shoulders globed like a full sail.’ The sense of ancestral solidity, rich rural continuity, in Death of a Naturalist (1966) is disturbed by those literal ‘skeletons’ from the past who appear in two Famine poems. Later, Wintering Out (1972) leads Heaney ‘into [the] trail’ of more insubstantial forebears than his farming fathers. Flitting wraiths symbolise discontinuities rather than continuity: the deprivations and repressions both of Irish history in the long term, and Ulster history in the short term. Heaney’s gloss on ‘The Tollund Man’ initiates him into this tragic family: ‘[he] seemed to me like an ancestor almost, one of my old uncles, one of those moustached archaic faces you used to meet all over the Irish country­ side.’34 (‘Moustached archaic faces’ is, curiously, a quotation from Philip Larkin’s poem ‘MCMXIV’.) In contrast with the Tollund Man’s attenuated condition, the early poem ‘Ancestral Photograph’ begins: ‘Jaws puff round and solid as a turnip.’ Heaney’s most cel­ ebrated poem about his father, ‘The Harvest Bow’ in Field Work (1979), reverts to the more tanglible-of-his family-histowes. A re­ newed vision of poetry as calling on the father’s ‘gift’ and ‘mellowed silence’, rather than breaking silences of dispossession, poetry as peace-maker despite the changed ‘spirit’ of the times, attaches toa drawn snareSlipped lately by the spirit of the cornYet burnished by its passage, and still warm.o-e^states 6 '01 I*; ijreC\S. Jita fc Le"tijpe/
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:34 am Page‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 159 IIINorthern Irish poetry sometimes echoes, more often revises^philos­ ophies o f history articulated by historians and politicians. W hat might be termed ‘the aspirational approach’ tends to receive least modification - Nationalist history still proving its literary seductive­ ness. Exemplified by Paulin’s Liberty Tree this approach derives from the corporate Field Day position, including more complex manifestations in Friel’s drama. Seamus Deane’s introduction to Friel’s Selected Plays stresses how sundered Donegal haunts his imagination as ‘a powerful image of possibility’.35This image crys­ tallises Friel’s protest against what Deane calls ‘the sense of a whole history of failure concentrated into a crisis over a doomed community or group’.36Pointing to the sources of Friel’s themes in a community robbed by history, robbed of history, Deane repeats such words and phrases as ‘depressed and depressing atmosphere’, ‘apathy’, ‘desolation’, ‘failure’, ‘crisis’, ‘socially depressed and politically dislocated’. This language partly derives from psychology: the termin­ ology for depressive psychosis. Friel in Translations applies a kind of therapy to this psychosis by offering Northern Catholics an alternative history, cultural self-respect, however ‘doomed’ that Gaelic culture itself is shown to be. Translations can be read as an ‘image of possibility’ to redeem the more recent past in the North: an aisling. It fits Oliver MacDonagh’s phrase for the goal of Gaelic revivalists in the twenties: a ‘land...repeopled, in imagination, by a pre-colonial society, free of the stains and shames of anglicisation’.37The aisling is the cultural figure that exemplifies the paralysing contradiction between epochalism and essentialism in Irish Nationalism.Liberty Tree, too, sets out to ‘father history’, to sire the future on ‘images of the past’. Paulin’s ‘image of possibility’ for Ireland, for the Protestant people of the North, is a date - 1798. Another date, 1912, represents the contrasting nadir, and completes his vision of Ulster history as decline and fall from an ideal. ‘Desertmartin’ ‘[sees] a plain/Presbyterian grace sour, then harden,/As a free strenuous spirit changes/To a servile defiance’. Decline and fall, like failure and possibility, rules out merely developmental and evolutionary understandings of history. Even Paulin’s ‘critical position .. .is founded on an idea of identity which has as yet no formal or institutional existence. It assumes the existence of a non-sectarian, republican state which comprises the whole island of Ireland.’38The aisling as literary theory? Similarly, Paulin’s Field Day pamphlet, A New Look at the Language Qiiestion, proposes a more ‘institutional existence’ for
￼-e-Paulin aspires to redeem history, to start again from 1798 with‘a pure narrative before him’ (‘L’Envie de Commencement’). DerekMahon’s greater pessimism about the sin of being born into historybegets a recurrent imaginative hankering to abolish ‘daylong/twilightsof misery’, to cut short its universally disastrous course. If Paulinoften approaches history with Calvinist denunciation, Mahon moreradically transposes the evangelist alter ego he satirises in ‘Ecclesiastes’.‘Another Sunday Morning’ in The Hunt by Night (1982) calls poetry‘A sort of winged sandwich board/El-Grecoed to receive the Lord’. o This disposition to say ‘The End is Nigh’ makes him in one sensea son of his fathers. Mahon’s fundamentalist view of Ulster Prot­estants as ‘a lost tribe’, rather than the elect, extends to the wholehuman race, and its lack of truly human or spiritual qualities. Hispoetry’s grand prophetic sweep embraces ‘civilisations’, the beginningand the end, ‘the biblical span’; contracts history into a Beckettian‘instant’. ‘Another Sunday Morning’ casts the poet as ‘A chiliasticprig’, i.e. a millenarian. John Wilson Foster, discussing millenarianaspects of W.R. Rodgers’s vision, cites millenarianism as a traditionwhich looks for ‘sudden divine intervention to destroy the existingorder’.'10 M ahon’s less ‘enthusiastic’ version dispenses with divineagency and ecstatic revelation, but projects spiritual renewal throughdestruction (compare Women in Love). However, man may not beamong the worthy permitted to survive. In ‘The Antigone Riddle’41Shy minerals contract at the sound of his voice, Cod point in silence when his bombers pass, And the windfall waitsIn silence for his departureBefore it drops in Silence to the long grass.‘Matthew V. 29-30’42preaches an absurdist but logical sermon on the text ‘Lord, mine eye offended, so I plucked it out’. Here theoLongley 150-172 4/5/94 11:34 am Page160 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’the English language in Ireland, a dictionary to codify what he regards as linguistic and literary ‘anarchy’.wThis aspiration towards an ideal language sometimes distracts the actual language of Paulin’s poetry'. Words, on the whole, take an evolutionary view of themselves, ‘Worn new’ in Edward Thomas’s paradox. Paulin’s impatience to establish a new vocabulary, tartly hascd-on ‘a relished [Ulster] dialect’, gives words like the following little time to settle: ‘glooby’, ‘scuffy’, ‘claggy’, ‘choggy’. As well as adjectives which aspire to exist, Paulin also repeats adjectives of aspiration ‘green’, ‘sweet’, ‘equal’. And his poetry’s general dependence on adjectives seems to me over- insistent, willed, willing - an effort to institutionalise the future."ko ~bCconstitute
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:34 am Page‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 161poet intervenes to destroy the ‘offending’ world himself, including ‘evaporation of all seas,/the extinction of heavenly bodies’. Although the first line of ‘A Disused Shed in Co. Wexford’ gives history a last chance -Even now there are places where a thought might grow —Mahon’s historical consciousness, as guilty and punitive as Beckett’s, not only turns biblical Protestantism inside out, but contradicts Whig history and deplores Belfast’s industrial history. His poetry denies progress, views the rise of the bourgeoisie as a descent into ‘barbarism’, and cries woe to a houseproud ‘civilisation’:on stormy nights our strongdouble glazing groans with foreknowledge of death,the fridge with a great wound...(‘Gipsies’)45Michael Longley’s perception of history, lacking Paulin’s and Mahon’s religious and prophetic colouring, concentrates on the empirical issue of whether different histories can be accommodated, either imaginatively or communally, in a context symbolised by the last line of ‘Letter to Seamus Heaney’4as ‘A wind-encircled burial mound’- anothercemetery’.‘OnSlieveGullion’45specificallymusters such histories:On Slieve Gullion ‘men and mountain meet’, O ’Hanlon’s territory, the rapparee,Home of gods, backdrop for a cattle raid, The Lake of Cailleach Beara at the topThat slaked the severed head of Conor M or...One figure in the landscape is ‘A paratrooper on reconnaissance’ who ‘sweats up the slopes of Slieve Gullion/With forty pounds of history on his back’ - a sign of intertextual dialogue with Seamus Heaney’s ‘The Toome Road’,* in which a speaker who encounters camouflaged armoured cars opposes to their intrusive presence ‘The invisible, untoppled omphalos’. In ‘On Slieve Gullion’ Longley registers his own English connections in the phrase ‘Both strangers here’, and leaves the poem’s mythic and historical ingredients in a state of suspension on the mountain. This implies the contemporary scarcity of such balm as ‘slaked the severed head of Conor Mor’. As in ‘Wounds’, Longley’s version of decline and fall differs from Paulin’s.But if ‘On Slieve Gullion’ finds no answers to the weight of the past, to ‘forty pounds of history’, it does not embrace the deter-
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:35 am Page162 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’minism which characterises John Montague’s vision and which derives from the ‘integrity of [the] quarrel’ between the Ulster com­ munities, ‘two crazed peoples’47- an emphasis that contrasts with Friel’s concentration on the Catholic communal psyche. Montague favours the word ‘again’: ‘Again that note!’, ‘Once again, it happens’; ‘Again, the unwinding road’.48 A hazard of perceiving events as cyclical, is that style, too, can develop habits of repetition. ‘Pattern’ and ‘ritual’, also favourite words, sometimes apply to Montague’s own technique, stiffening poems into a species of heraldry which excludes or precludes the active verb, rhythmical dynamic. The main process attributed to history concerns what is ‘lost’ or ‘gone’ (another favourite word), with loss itself a pattern - familial in the poem called ‘Process’:50‘time’s gullet devouring/parents whose children/ are swallowed in turn’. After 1969 history repeats itself in Montague’s imagination, presents itself as pre-processed, or perhaps as an impasse between the perspectives of ‘mortality’ and ‘continuum’.However, Ulster novelists also find it difficult to evade determin­ istic structures. Martin’s The Ceremony ofInnocence and The Road to Ballyshannon, Mac Laverty’s Lamb and Cal, all centre on characters whose options narrow to a single historical necessity. The conclusion of Stamping Ground falls into a similar mould/ despite Leitch’s gesture towards the positive -f a girl raped by three young men implausibly feels ‘sorry for them now more than anything’.51Hetty essentially shares in the socio-sexual fatality, emanating from ‘closed places of the spirit’,52which has already engulfed the Valley’s older generation. H er post-coital joie de vivre does not outweigh the past, any more than does a wistful and wishful vision near the end of The Road to Ballyshannon-.‘I see it,’ the sergeant said. ‘I see it.’ Through the mist and the broken cloud a dolphin swam among the stars. ‘I see it. It’s a dolphin, isn’t it? And it’s free.’ It was then the sergeant realised that the boy’s right hand was held up by a tree root and the eyes that glistened to the night sky were dead.”Relentlessly deterministic, Martin’s fictional techniques shoot home, with loud clangs, the bolts which circumscribe existence. His epi­ graphs pre-condition the reader as well: from Marx in The Ceremony o f Innocence:Men make their own history, but they do not make it just as they please; they do not make it under circumstances chosen by themselves, but under circumstances directly encountered, given and transmitted from the past. The tradition of all the dead generations weighs like a night­ mare on the brain of the living.
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:35 am Page‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 163And from Nietzsche in The Road to Ballyshannon: ‘[Man] wonders ...about himself - that he cannot learn to forget, but hangs on the past: however far or fast he runs, that chain runs with him.’ The Ceremony o f Innocence incorporates quite a rich historical and social panorama of Belfast since the Second World War; but all this gives birth to a boy’s destiny as ‘a small black cross among the thousand and more crosses that line the lawns of the City Hall when the peace- marchers keep their silent, lonely vigil...’54A leaner, less rhetorical work, set in 1922, The Road to Ballyshannon follows two Republican fugitives and their RIC sergeant hostage to an inevitable rendezvous. Although only the latter escapes with his life, his son has earlierbeen killed by the Republicans. The sergeant is additionally doomed to remain ‘a hostage of the dead’,55 because during the enforced journey he has become a surrogate father to the younger of his captors - perhaps another touch of wistful transcendence.Mac Laverty’s Lamb also turns on surrogate fatherhood, but within one community. To make altruistic amends for the authoritarianism of a boys’ borstal run by the Christian Brothers, Brother Sebastian (Michael Lamb) takes rebellious Owen on an escape-journey. Its time, money, and spirit ‘inevitably’ run out:He had started with a pure loving simple ideal but it had gone foul on him, turned inevitably into something evil. It had been like this all his life, with the Brothers, with the very country he came from. The beautiful fly with the hook embedded...Owen was dead. He had killed him to save him, although he loved him more than anyone else in his life.5*The sentimental tinge here, a counterpart to the melodrama informing Martin’s doomed odysseys, also weakens the impact of Cal’s fate. And if sex is dodged in Lamb, it seems unlikely in Cat. Cal’s guilt- ridden love affair with the widow of an RUC reservist, to whose murder by the IRA he has been accessory, ends thus: ‘he stood in a dead man’s Y-fronts listening to the charge, grateful that at last someone was going to beat him to within an inch of his life’.57What in the case of poetry causes predictable cadences, in the case of fiction causes predictable plots, predictable emotional conformations: ideal glimpses belying a masochism under history’s iron crushers which the novelist’s sensibility shares with a passive victim-hero.But the (would-be realist) novelist must work with society as it is. Poetry has perhaps less excuse if it fails to maintain the tension between creative dynamic and historical stasis, to detect hairfine tremors or locate chinks in determinism’s defences. Perhaps Paulin’s idealism weighs too hard on the dynamic scale-pan, Montague’s determinism too hard on the static. Both also, unlike Mahon, writeJbdL-
￼164 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’very explicitly about Irish history, which given half a chance will write the poems itself, turn idealism or aspiration back into deter­ minism again, book the text in advance like Coulter’s graves.Seamus Heaney’s ‘Bogland’58 famously does its own digging, conceives the past as a dimension to be explored dynamically rather than received statically: ‘Our pioneers keep striking/inwards and downwards’, and so do the poem’s rhythms. This conflates historical enquiry with psychic investigation, and Heaney’s subsequent sound­ ings resemble Jungian therapy, rather than Friel’s implied prescrip­ tion of electro-convulsion. Heaney’s methods affirm the presence of depths and layers whereby the past imprints individual and community, a ‘script indelibly written into the nervous system’.59 Hence ‘Broagh,/its low tattoo/among the windy boortrees.’60Yet this begins to edge towards the mythic inevitabilities that take hold in North (1975) and give his forms, too, a more deterministic cast. Perhaps the concept of the ‘Bog People’, subsuming history in a single ‘icon’, ‘an archetypal pattern’, was bound to have such an effect.61Again, the two fathers of Heaney’s poetry merge into general­ ised ancestor-worship: ‘pinioned by ghosts/and affections’ (‘Viking Dublin’); ‘god of the waggon,/the hearth-feeder’ (‘Kinship’).The iconography and rituals of North (which I have discussed elsewhere)62also freeze the fluid religious element which has always permeated Heaney’s imaginative relation to the past. This - very different from Mahon’s and Paulin’s theologising - began with the animistic natural magic of Heaney’s childhood landscape (captured in Death ofa Naturalist) when the ‘pump marked an original descent into earth...centred and staked the imagination, made its foundation the foundation of the omphalos itself’.63In his lecture ‘The Sense of the Past’ (my italics), Heaney traces a progression from the child’s ‘intimate, almost animal response’ to ‘the mystery and claims of time past...the sense of belonging to a family and a place’, to ‘those images which widen this domestic past into a community or a national past’ and offer ‘a dream of the past’.64 In the latter connection he describes the enduring mystique within his imagination of a mass- rock picture with its ‘emotional drama’.65Yet, these two ways of apprehending the past, as the second accrues political meanings, cease to be progressive or concentric. Do the ripples widen evenly from the pump in the yard to the historical nation? Are the two fathers really one? How far does the ‘common emotional ground of memory and belonging’ extend? Is history-identical to - whose? - collective unconscious? (In ‘Bogland’ this analogy is a matter of subtler metaphorical suggestion.) Similar problems arise from
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:36 am Page‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 165Heaney’s landscaped female-frgw© representing ‘mother ground’, origins: the eternal mythic presence of the past, as opposed to the father who at least participates in generational cycles.Heaney’s omphalos or Mother Ireland in his own backyard at­ tempts a winning throw in the poetic, as well as political, game of naturalising religio-historical origins. Others, like Montague, have gambled on the dolmen as symbolic touchstone. Louis MacNeice reached back to the early Christian era when his aspiration to belong reached a qualified climax in ‘The Once-in-Passing’:6As though the window openedAnd the ancient cross on the hillside meant myself.But beyond all monuments, the land remains ‘the stable element’ in poetry too, whether inscribed with historical essences or with revisionist desires. In ‘Rocks’ (after Guillevic)67 Mahon uses geology, the durability of rocks (‘Their dream of holding fast/In the elemental flux’), to dwarf the human episode ‘Lying in their shadows/in the last traces of time’. More broadly, the (non-human) animal, vegetable and mineral harbour ‘The Banished Gods’,68whosit out the centuries In stone, waterAnd the hearts of trees,Lost in a reverie of their own natures...Longley partly integrates natural and human history; partly sees Nature as improving on man’s record of environmental accommo­ dation, ‘rinsing’ the burial-mound as does poetry itself:The spring tide circles and excavates A shrunken ramshackle pyramid Rinsing cleaner scapulae, tibias,Loose teeth, cowrie and nautilus shells Before seeping after sun and moonT o pour cupfuls into the larks’ nests, To break a mirror on the grazingAnd lift minnows over the low bridge.6’(‘Spring Tide’)The Southern Irish poet Paul Durcan, in ‘Before the Celtic Yoke’71,' gets rid of the past by conceiving a platonic landscape, innocent of history’s invasion. Pre-human, not post-human like Mahon’s millenarian dream, at once Genesis and Revelation, re-visionary rather than revisionist, this variant on the aisling once again suggests that Irish poetic imaginations are caught between trying to transfix history, to finish it, and to begin it. Durcan imagines the aisling’s object defying history-ridden poets and speaking for ‘herselP:&n ncXsDel phic.e-
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:36 am Page166 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’My vocabularies are boulders cast up on time’s beaches; Masses of sea-rolled stones reared up in mile-high ricks Along the shores and curving coasts of all my island...IVPaul Muldoon’s poetry does not assail the tyranny of the past by any such bold strokes as ‘Before the Celtic Yoke’. Instead, it suffers death by a thousand cuts. Most fundamentally, Muldoon enquires into the whole business of the writer, or anyone, looking to history at all.To begin with a digression: Muldoon’s points of departure are thrown into relief by the contrary methods of Heaney’s long poem ‘Station Island’, and Brian Moore’s fiction. The scenario of ‘Station Island’ not only builds in religio-historical pietas, but an appeal to (or for) higher authority. Heaney’s theme of following or ‘trailing’ returns on a larger scale as his pilgrim seeks spiritual and artistic guidance by conversing with ghosts: various male voices from and of the past, surrogate fathers or ‘fosterers’ - all from the Catholic tradition - in the guise of priests, schoolmasters, mentors, master- writers. A ‘hard’ macho Joyce is hailed as ‘Old father, mother’s son’.71 Although that last voice urges ‘swim/out on your own’ the poem itself enacts an entrapment, not least in its thraldom to literary history. ‘Exemplary’ is a favourite critical term of Heaney’s, and Seamus Deane salutes what seems more like dependency than freedom, when he says: ‘Heaney has begun to consider his literary heritage more carefully, to interrogate it in relation to his Northern and violent experience, to elicit from it a style of survival as a poet.’72Thus ‘Station Island’ may stage an incomplete liberation- struggle. Indeed, its Joycean denoument recycles, rather than revises, the patriarchal/artistic will to power: the schema is that of initiation into manhood, acceptance by elders of the tribe. Moore’s Fergus (1971), perhaps also seeking a style of literary survival, revisits the past within a secular scenario very like that o f ‘Station Island’. Fergus Fadden, serious novelist hoping to strike gold as a Hollywood script­ writer, is literally haunted in his Californian beach-house by ghosts from his Irish family past. He too holds ‘conversations with the dead’73(and younger versions of the living). His dead father, a socially and religiously conservative authority-figure, who resembles Gavin’s father in The Emperor of Ice-Cream, heads the haunters or hunters of a less securely liberated psyche than Gavin’s becomes. Moore’s resurrection of a ‘father’s world’ bears very explicitly onoar-b'ifi'ci# I3\a S ti
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:37 am Page ^5,7'WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 167the theme John Wilson Foster sees as first surfacing in An Answer from Limbo (1962): ‘primitivism and provincialism become virtues,bulwarks against the erosive hypocrisies of modern cosmopolitan life’.74Fergus articulates a crisis close to the novelist’s own sensibility:He stood...hardly able to believe that a few moments ago, far from fleeing his ghosts, he had pursued them with questions...Until now, he had thought that, like everyone else, he exorcised his past by living it. But he was not like everyone else. His past had risen up this morning, vivid and uncontrollable, shouldering into his present.”However, Moore’s externalisation of interior or unconsciousdialogue involves fairly stock characters and responses. The father’santiclimactic last words are: ‘If you have not found a meaning,then your life is meaningless.’76 Moore’s fiction after Fergus oscillateswithin the terms of this over-neat antithesis. His protagonists findor lose some kind of faith, with the supernatural underlining theissue in Catholics (1972), The Great Victorian Collection (1975), ColdHeaven (1983) and Black Rohe (1985). The Mangan Inheritance (1979)pursues, antithetically to Fergus, the question of faith in the pastitself. Keeping the faith, whether religiously or historically, drawson the same font of Irish feeling. James Mangan, a Canadian notan expatriate Irishman, becomes obsessed with proving his kinship e to the nineteenth-century poet James Clarence Mangan. His questfor genealogical ratification of his character and talents ends in tears, in ‘hated self-images’,77 in the shattering of a talismanic ancestral daguerrotype, in a return home to healthier emotion about his father’s death. Moore’s dialectic between Irish total recall and Californian amnesia derives - like excessive determinism or idealism - from Ulster experience, but may be too much of a swinging pendulum to extend it artistically. Foster calls Fergus ‘more of a re-hash than an advance’.78Despite his variations on a theme, Moore’s historical imagination seems arrested between a futureless Ireland (doubly so since it belongs to his past) and a pastless North America.Thirty years younger than Moore, Muldoon so far shows no signs of augmenting Foster’s ‘wry irony in the sight of yesterday’s apostates becoming today’s nostalgics’.79 His poetry questions its own authority along with origins, foundations, heritage, precedent, preceptor and pedigree. For instance, in Quoof (1983) the trans­ atlantic dimension of ‘The More a Man Has the More a Man Wants’80 is partly a way of suggesting the remoteness, the archaic distance, of Irish-American bloodlines:On the Staten Island Ferry two men are dickering
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:38 am Pagee-168‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’over the priceof a shipment of Armalites,as Henry Thoreau was wont to quibble with Ralph Waldo Emerson.The scene then moves to the Algonquin where, in a parody of Young Ireland’s heroic genealogies, the protagonist encounters ‘a flurry/of sprites,/the assorted shades/of Wolfe Tone, Napper Tandy ...Then, Thomas Meagher/darts up from the Missouri/on a ray/of the morning star/to fiercely ask/what has become of Irish hurling?’ (This poem is no respecter of ghosts.) ‘The Frog’81 attacks from a different angle the notion that ‘images of the past’ hold lessons, can be made ‘exemplary’. The speaker to whom the frog-image occurs seems poised between alternative politics of the poem: ‘I set aside hammer and chisel/and take him on the trowel’. ‘Hammer and chisel’ implies the egotistical (and patriarchal) sublime: coercion of the image to fit an agenda. ‘Take him on the trowel’, like the poem’s self-image as ‘another small upheaval/amongst the rubble’ (‘Troubles’), implies negative capability. ‘The Frog’ tries out the first approach, but stops short:The entire population of Irelandm springs from a pair left to stand 0-overnight in a pondin the gardens of Trinity College, two bottles of wine left there to chill after the Act of Union.There is, surely, in this storya moral. A moral for our times...This anti-Aesop, anti-Davisite fable plays down 1800 as much as Paulin plays up 1798. It also criticises Heaney’s ‘Act of Union’ as not only portentously futile, but radical chic, a frivolously aesthetic dabbling in violent waters: ‘What if I put him to my head/and squeezed it out of him,/like the juice of freshly squeezed limes,/or a lemon sorbet?’ A related Muldoonian moral queries the status of historical stories themselves. ‘History’82embarks on research: ‘Where and when exactly did we first have sex?’ and obliquely concludes that only imaginative truth can be trusted since a possible location is ‘the room where MacNeice wrote “Snow”,/Or the room where they say he wrote “Snow”.’ MacNeice’s poem emerges as the only sure thing in a world of shaky facts. (‘Exactly’ belongs to aesthetics in ‘The Frog’ too.) Similarly, the poet in ‘Lunch with Pancho Villa’83 undermines a whole industry of publication on Northern Ireland when he states: ‘there’s no such book, so far as I know,/As Horv it Happened Here,/Though there may be. There may.’-e-
￼‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 169Muldoon’s poetry, then, attempts to loosen the grip of the past on both life and literature, perhaps as epitomised by a habituated pump attendant: ‘grown so used/to hold-ups he calls after them,/Beannacht De ar pn ohair \ 84 He ‘interrogates history’ in a more genuine sense than do many who make such a claim. His techniques sabotage all kinds of certainty about how ‘far’ we ‘know’ into the past or future. Hence the subjunctives, conditionals, syntactical ambiguities, refusals of historic tenses. The locus of the poetry is an un-(easy present- continuous, at once an ironic echo of Ulster’s ‘eternal interim’ (‘Lull’), and ‘exactly’ where language tries to break into the future:How often have I carried our family word for the hot water bottleto a strange bed...’5(‘Quoof’)To defamiliarise is also to defamilialise. Throughout Muldoon’s poetry the father is a persistent metaphysical shadow. Behind, rather than both behind and in front like Heaney’s father-figure, he rep­ resents ‘what is...immediately over my shoulder’. Some of Muldoon’s early poems dramatise the son’s psycho-sexual maturation - presented in Freudian, rather than Jungian, terms. ‘The Waking Father’86 (from Neiv Weather, 1973) includes a disturbing infantile Oedipal fantasy:When my father stood out in the shallows It occurred to meThe spricklies might have been pirhanas, The river a red carpetrolling out from where he had just stood...In ‘Duffy’s Circus’ 87 (from Mules, 1977) the speaker-son’s drive towards individuation reaches adolescence. He ignores his father’s Polonius-like ‘nuts of wisdom’, ‘loses’ him, and ends up absorbing rawer facts of life, sex and violence: ‘From under a freighter/I watched a man sawing a woman in half. This Freudian drama shades into the father’s function as history-bearer. Sometimes (as part of Muldoon’s running demurral with Heaney) he becomes an amalgam of archetypes/stereotypes. ‘The Mixed Marriage’88, with its ‘school-mistress’ mother and rurally atavistic father, parodies Lawrentian oppositions between super-ego and id. The fatherfurther dimmed the lightT o get back to hunting with ferrets O r the factions of the faction-fights - The Ribbon Boys, the Caravats.
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:38 am Page170 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’Two poems in Why Brownlee Left, ‘October 1950’ and ‘ImmramaTM, more directly challenge blood-conscious imperatives. The former presents conception not as determined or (wholly) determining but as ‘chance’ which might lead to ‘Anything wild or wonderful’. The speaker of the latter at first seems eager to join the poetic paternity suite: ‘I, too, have trailed my father’s spirit’, but orthodox Irish biography or literary cliche (‘mud-walled cabin’, ‘farm where he was first hired out’, ‘building-site’) has an unorthodox South American finale: ‘That’s him on the verandah, drinking rum/W ith a man who might be a N azi...’ This impugns not only any mytholo­ gised purity of family stock, but doctrines of such purity. Earlier the father’s authority and factuality were revoked by the very ded­ ication of Muldoon’s New Weather: ‘For my Fathers and Mothers.’ His debutant historical pluralism prepared for other pluralities and mixtures in the poetry, subtler versions of those surrogacies or difficult mixed parentages in fiction: mongrels, mutations, doubles, androgyny and sexual ambivalence (‘The Bearded Woman, by Ribera’90 with her ‘Willowy, and clean-shaven’ consort), alter egos, alternative lives, promiscuity of cultural reference. Muldoon’s puns and rhymes endow words themselves with multiple identities, strange bedfellows, surprisingly extended families, and his poems unfold through associations that unsettle the reader.The title-poem of Mules presents a son witnessing a father wit­ nessing an awkward birth:We had loosed them into one field.I watched Sam Parsons and my quick father Tense for the punch below their belts,For what was neither one thing or the other.91Among other things, this problematic hybrid symbolises offspring of the so-called ‘two traditions’ in Ulster, including Muldoon’s poetry itself. But fathers’ breeding too, as Tmmrama’ suggests, can be suspect. The longer poem Tmmram’92 takes shape as a search for the father, for an explanation of some dirty business in the pastwhich forces the son to re-think autonomy and free association:1was fairly and squarely behind the eight That morning in Foster’s pool-hallWhen it came to me out of the blueIn the shape of a sixteen-ounce billiard cue That lent what he said some little weight. ‘Your old man was an ass-hole.That makes an ass-hole out of you.’My grandfather hailed from New York State. My grandmother was part Cree.This must be some new strain in my pedigree...
￼‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’ 171I suppose that I should have called the cops Or called it a day and gone homeAnd done myself, and you, a favour.But I wanted to know more about my father.But, shifty and shifting, the father eludes pursuit: ‘He would flee, to La Paz, then to Buenos Aires,/From alias to alias.’ The son does not set out to avenge an entirely innocent father, as he does in Immram Mael Duin, the medieval voyage tale on which Muldoon’s ‘Immram’ is loosely, if not licentiously, based. However, at the end of the poem he is released like Mael Duin from thraldom to the past, and ‘happily’ returns to ‘Foster’s pool-room’ (a genetic pun on the fostering of Mael Duin). As he moves to rejoin the ‘flow’ of the living, the poem seems to resolve the father-son conflict on both its Freudian and its historical levels. In ‘Gathering Mushrooms’” we glimpse the father once again as a familiarly solid rural figure: ‘He’ll glance back from under his peaked cap/without breaking rhythm’. Muldoon may partly allude to Heaney’s father-figure, and, as elsewhere, to Heaney as a literary father-figure (‘rhythm’ in Heaney’s poems fuses poetry and rural work). Such fathers are now perceived as sadly obsolescent: ‘one of those ancient warriors/before the rising tide’ - a helpless Canute or Cuchulain. Set ‘fifteen years on’, and thus straddling recent history, ‘Gathering Mushrooms’ presents the ‘tide’ of violence as psychedelic transformation. The substitution of magic mushrooms for the ordinary variety symbolises a grotesque mutation or regression of tradition. A reversed aisling, the poem is also a slow-motion reprise of ‘Easter 1916’ (‘changed utterly’) in which nothing - or a changeling - gets born. The speaker, his head ‘grown into the head of a horse’, finds in his mouth the words of a Republican dirty-protester instructing: ‘I f sing you must, let your song/tell of treading your own dung.'' The speaker implicitly resists imperatives delivered by the past (‘dung’) in the name of the future ("the day we leap/into our true domain'), history’s Davisite attempt to dictate to the poet.If Mahon demolishes Whig history, you might say that Muldoon deconstructs its opposite. He exorcises the hovering ‘ghost-life’ of mythic history, what Oliver MacDonagh rather euphemistically terms ‘an absence of a developmental or sequential view of past events’.94But his poetry does not simply or simplistically walk away from atavism into agnostic daylight. Nor does it weigh too heavily on either side of any antithesis, but resembles Brownlee’s abandoned horsesShifting their weight from foot to Foot, and gazing into the future*
￼Longley 150-172 4/5/94 11:39 am Page172 ‘WHEN DID YOU LAST SEE YOUR FATHER?’Muldoon negotiates that small space, that inch, between necessity and possibility, with an integrity faithful above all to the present. ‘Cherish the Ladies’,96 like other Muldoon poems, takes place in the present tense and is aware of itself as a tiny piece of historical process if not progress:In this, my last poem about my father, there may be time enoughfor him to fill their drinking-trough and run his eye overhis three mooley heifers.Such a well-worn path,I know, from here to the galvanized bath.The phrase ‘my last poem’ could mean either final or most recent, thus suggesting work-in-progress. ‘Cherish the Ladies’ (like ‘Immram’) braves the reader’s imagined boredom with father-poems: ‘Such a well-worn path/I know.’ And it restores for the space of the poem the rural archetype of the father by insisting on the actuality of his opening ‘the stand-pipe’ - an image for begetting. Like ‘Gathering Mushrooms’, ‘Cherish the Ladies’ incorporates an italicised alterna­ tive poem, alternative history, alternative future controlled by the past:I know, too, you would ratherI saw behind the hedge to where the pride o f the herd, though not an Irishbull, would cherishthe ladies with his electric cattle-prod.As it is, in my last poem about my father he opens the stand-pipeand the water scurries along the hosetill it’s curledin the bath - One heifermay look upand make a mental note, then put her nose back to the salt-lick of the world.What might be going on, or written up, behind the hedge smacks of an abusive heritage (there are parodic references to folk-song). As ever, Muldoon discriminates between dead and living tradition, between apparent and real breaks with the past, between the oppress­ ively, tribally progenitive ‘pride of the herd’ and the more admirable father who really ‘cherishes’ the future - even a female future - who makes available ‘the salt-lick of the world’.[1985]