￼Arrivals1The plane meetsits reflection on the wet runway, then crossesto where I waitbehind plate glass.I watchwith a mixtureof longing and despair as you re-enterthe real worldAll we have is each other.1 sometimes wonderif that is enough;whether being together enlarges or diminishes grief.2Remember arrivingfrom Thorame -the s c e n t _________________t^f honey,^of lavender clinging.^)On the Jonte, climbing goat-tracks to drink from a spring under an archof red sandstone.Or last year,a second honeymoonin Amsterdam, having exchanged gifts: a miniature war-horse, a silver ring.ues&A60
￼3Tonight your return from Ulsterrentiersmy fears unfounded. Yet neitherof us speaks. Instead we think of those living there, others who have died.Your brother-in-lawhas decided to emigrate: the one sure escape.As I draw upat the lights, you droop forward, hands on your lap.4The pubs are coming out. In Dumbarton Rdtwo drunks, having battered each other senseless, sitin their own vomit.No one interferes. It is not easyto accept there may be a certain mercy in living here.The lights turnto green. I imagineyou lying alonein a white room, surrounded by flimsy screens.../.C1v/61