￼(
￼YOU NEED A CIGGY TO•XSomeone would be sitting, his back to the screenWhich at the movies**usually 'doesn't happen.He'd be riding. His horse's hooveswould have shoes nailed on backwards.Don't look at him.He's saying something-, but don't listen.ttThe walls get dressed up, but by themselves. Sit down, says someone in the shape of a chair.♦x Topcoat extends a hand, I take it.A carton proffers, I take it.'A catchy jingle takes me muttering along."You need a-ciggy to stop goin' crazy."Sit down, says the chair —X*XHelp yourself, says a carton; and I accept the ciggylike a challenge.I ask a light, a girl's form flame-flare;her skirt's all strawI'm only just now noticing.LAJOS PINTER, "Kell egy cigi, hogy ..."
￼q* ) he\*' ( 2 " ) N b oft3K *P \ ^ vj r A d t u 5 c l < r^■7^) C^oWnU,UA B^A^Ici rW lL^HTlrslCrTW ^ .<p&&,.^prIQ4s> 3^ fOC\. Ist Se-u'VMA-^U o ) g,v_/XKiVd -L - P e ^ r y ^ > b - \ .^_, d \ d < ^r^c\ s^c'tw^(I'b'lA^^...>.fv,i^-sap "-fctac0 C %lb -3*\ Vd s^crK^-,ScAN^lC(C[i) bt'dr^K-l P'~^)( ° \ Z ) > 3 U \ K > < J ^ r P e i r c e s I jp° \ b ' ^ Sc h C*-*5*A
￼SOURCESThe Latin texts of the poems are taken from:CARMINA BURANA, eel. A. Hilka and 0. Schumann. Heidelbefg, 1930-19^1.DRONKE, Peter. Medieval Latin and the feise of European Love-Lyric. 2nd. ed., Oxford, 1968 GASELEE, Stephen, eel. The Oxford Book of Medieval Latin Verse. Oxford, 1928.MEYER, Wilhelm, eel. Die Arundel Sammlung m ittellatein- ischer Lieder. Berlin, 1908. (Arundel collection)RABY, P .J.E ., ed.TheOxfordBookofMedievalLatin Verse. Oxford, 1959«STRECKER, K arl., ed. Die Cambridger Lieder. Berlin, 1955. (Cambridge Songs)Wherever possible I have given references to Raby's Oxford book (1959)» as this is the most readily available anthology and includes further notes on some of the poems.Other important works on the subject, in additionC'Thew<>*> 1te ^ \ to Helen W addell's books, are:DRONKE, Peter. The medieval lyric. 2nd. ed. Hutchinson, 1978.RABY, F.J.E. A history of secular Latin poetry in the middle ages. Oxford, 193^.A note on the spelling of my Latin texts, in which some inconsistency will be detected: in his anthologyDr Raby chose to present most of the poems in 'the familiar spelling of classical Latin', and in those cases where I have taken my texts from that volume i have let his spelling stand. The other poems, however, are inthe original spelling of the medieval manuscripts; this differs from classical Latin in a number of details,the most obvious of which is that the diphthong 'ae'has disappeared and been replaced by 'e'. MedievalLatin also varies from author to author and accordingto the traditions of different periods.
￼"to -trim\vTHE VIP.GIN & THE NIGHTINGALEo
￼PLuASt-jy\VSfd UnivetoihjPress,Oxford Book of Contemporary New Zealand Poetry 1(0.U.P.j _____ 1 9 8 2 )Selected Poems (Oxford University Press, 1983)Ci I1\ HOE-MTSO*(The Eye of the Hurricane (A. I-I. fe A. ( f 9 6 4 ) j _________ -------------------- - =Also by Fleur AdcockHigh Tide in the Garden (Oxford University Press, 1971) The Scenic Route (Oxford University Press, 1974)The Inner Harbour (Oxford University Press, 1979) Below Loughrigg (Bloodaxe Books, 1979)- = Tigers (Oxford University Press, 1967)~ C MAR .983 Uk'WIN BROTHERS LIMIT[OLD WCKlNG, SURREYReed, New Zealand, A ^ ---------------- --------
￼BICJ0DAX6 BGDK5
￼H'VUWCopyright © Fleur Adcock 1983 All rights reservedISBN: 0 906427 55 X hardback 0 906427 56 8 paperback0 906427 57 6 limited signed editionFirst published 1983 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.Cover printing byTyneside Free Press Workshop Ltd, Newcastle upon Tyne.Printed in Great Britain byUnwin Brothers Ltd, Old Woking, Surrey.
￼*< /Y'iPs©
￼AIc k n o w l e d g e m e n t sThe author wishes to thank Peter Dronke for his encouragement and for permission to include the texts of three poems from his book Medieval Latin and the Rise of European Love-Lyric; acknowledgements are also due to Oxford University Press for the use of material from this work and from the Oxford Book of Medieval Latin Verse.In addition the author is grateful to Northern Arts for financial support (as Fellow in Literature at the Universities of Newcastle upon Tyne and Durham) during the time when these translations were made, and to those universities for the congenial environment they provided.A-to 'fcrirvv
￼|Iiv*m trirA ContentsB irdsI. The singing-contest 11II. The golden oriole at the monastery17III. The nightingale 19IV. The swan 21V. The thrush 25VI. The birds and the beeVII. Love's agent 29VIII. The anti-nightingale songIX. The roasted swan 37Songs by Peter of BloisX. Lucy 41XI. His not impossible sheXII. The conquest of CoronisXIII. A friendly warning 53XIV. Orpheus 57XV. Flora 61XVI. Peter's lament 67XVII. A new leaf 71Anonymous Love-songs273145 4779 81-•».XVIII. The lover in winter 75XIX. The lovesick girl in springXX. A touch of impatienceXXI. Cecily 83XXII. Farewell to the threshing-floorSources 91Notes on the poems Biographical notes 9687I
￼vSbifbj
￼t78 I.910 Sunt saecla praeclarissima,11 sunt prata vernantissima,12 formosa gaudent omnia,13 sunt grata nostri moenia.1415 Laetentur ergo somata16 et rideant praecordia,17 amor petens finitima18 sint cuncta vitulantia.1920 Phoebus rotat per tempora21 torquens polorum lumina;22 somnum susurrant flumina,23 aves canunt et dulcia.2425 Turtur prior dans oscina,26 rauce sonat post ardea;27 sistema miscens merula,28 olos implet croemata.2930 Myrto sedens lusciola,31 'vos cara,' dicens, 'pignora,32 audite matris famina,33 dum lustrat aether sidera.3435 Cantans mei similia,36 canora prolis germina,37 cantu Deo dignissima38 tractim refrange guttura.3940 Tu namque plebs laetissima,41 tantum Dei tu psaltria42 divina cantans cantica43 per blanda cordis viscera.4445 Materna iam nunc formula46 ut rostra vincas plumea,47 futura vocis organa5 contempera citissima.'6\pV"*
￼4I..4849 The singing-contest5051 We live in splendid times: the fields52 are rich and blossoming with spring;53 our city is a pleasant place;54 there's joy in every living thing.5556 So let our bodies take their ease,57 and hearts enjoy this happy state;58 with 'love thy neighbour' as the theme59 all creatures ought to celebrate.6061 The heavens wheel about the earth62 with sun by day and stars at night;63 the rivers whisper sleepily,64 and singing birds express delight.6566 The cooing turtle-dove is first;67 the heron follows with a squawk;68 the blackbird joins the chorus; next69 the swan contributes to their talk.7071 Then sitting on a myrtle branch72 the nightingale instructs her young:73 'Now while the stars are bright, my74 take lessons in your mother-tongue:7576 copy my song; I want to hear77 the younger generation's notes78 in seemly hymns of praise to God79 emerging from your little throats.8081 We are a joyful tribe of birds,82 the Lord's musicians and his choir.83 So let him hear your instruments:84 make every tiny chest a lyre.8586 Tune up your growing vocal chords87 for instant use; adopt my skills88 and we'll outdo what pass for songs3 from other birds' inferior bills.'dears,11Ir .Ii m\m 'tb -truw
￼vtge. *8990 Hoc dixit et mox iubila91 secuntur subtilissima;92 melum fit voce tinnula93 soporans mentis intima.9495 Densantur hinc spectacula,96 accurrit omnis bestia,97 leaena, lynx et dammula,98 caudata stans vulpecula.99100 Pisces relinquunt aequora101 et vada sunt retrograda;102 pulsando Codrus ilia103 praegnas adest invidia.104105 Auro sedet rex aquila,106 circum cohors per agmina,107 gemmata pavo tergora,108 cornix subest et garrula.109110 Corvina quin centuria,111 ardet phalans et milvea;112 de marte tractant omina,113 vincatur ut lusciola.114115 Palumbes at iuvencula116 praesumit e victoria;117 gallus prior cum merula118 disrumpta plangunt ilia.119120 Cicadis inflans iecora121 campo crepat misellula;122 palmam tenet lusciola123 versus trahens per sibila.124125 Turbata gens turn rostrea,126 exsanguis hinc et aquila;127 frigescit, in praecordia1 virtusque cedit ossea.(S >2^ # 12LtS(,f - —I ix>cr .. .^ -mgH O C > A o 'Wt -tVve VC.rse.-S> C*'V«L P<^Gp. "THe s»p*.c<bs> cbo g JI Iinrto dLcjooor\t. ' ^ r\d 2cre c o rre c t , )
￼^„,'tp'u'rA128 V129 The youngsters do as they are told;130 and soon their sweetly piping art131 is mingled with their mother's tune132 in melodies to stun the heart.133134 At this their audience expands,135 as all the creatures flock to hear:136 the little fox with bushy tail,137 the lioness, lynx, and fallow deer.138139 Even the fishes leave the sea,140 and rivers find their flow reversed;141 the poet Codrus tears his hair,142 so full of envy he could burst.143144 The eagle on a golden throne145 presides above his marshalled rows146 of peacocks dressed in jewelled gear,147 and companies of chatty crows,148149 squadrons of kites, battalions150 of ravens, all exchanging views151 about the contest and its odds,152 keen that the nightingale should lose.153154 But no: the ringdove has withdrawn,155 despairing of the victory;156 the cock and blackbird, ruptured both,157 can only squeak with misery.158159 The cricket-bird inflates her lungs160 and bursts with a pathetic pop.161 The nightingale, with staying-power162 to match her skill, comes out on top.163164 Dismay confounds the other birds;165 the eagle's face is almost pale:166 a ghastly chill invades his bones;3 his very heartbeat seems to fail.fwX13f,. 11-mw-fo "torvxI
￼167168 Praeco fugae fit ulula169 urgens gradi per abdita,170 pudore mens ne conscia171 poenas luat per saecula.172173 Tunc versa castra plumea174 sparsim legunt aumatia175 auraeque fissa flamina,1 petuntur tecta silvea.214V"tD 'trimI