￼BLPDDAX6 BQDK5P.O. BOX 1SN, NEWCASTLE UPON TYNE NE99 1SNtelephone: 091-2325988Chairman: Simon Thirsk Managing Director: Neil Astley Company Secretary: Nansi Thirsk l l b, ' » ( -Lmi With Compliments V4oboc5^AcLu vs. reaK't; fNcb3AzA&yJQw*v> v>, £>Iakc^) SO 'Ihzrc 3/<_ S Cs>rrec'-Kxw_Shire ~4o 'IKjl cj&rr«-crbv<<v\JL wrcsACiLA3r\<\ ^\f\c ^LP'fbO|7V\o'ho<q r2^wv> . "’Thi*: sX-cxj1c\%Editor: NEIL ASTLEY AdvisoryPanel: FLEUR ADCOCK, DAVID CONST NTINE, DOUGLAS DUNN, EDNA LONGLEY, CAROL RUMENS, ANNE STE ENSONBloodaxeBooksLtd: RegisteredNumber1656254England.VATNumber414406289 RegisteredOffice:ExchangeBuildings,Quayside,NewcastleuponTyneNE1 3BJ.be /'V\e. \vaf
￼a different decision.Martin Bell’s life can be seen all too easily as a cautionary tale ofthe price the poet pays for inspiration. Indeed, it is already being represented this way in some quarters. It is no secret that his later years were blighted by addiction to alcohol, and complicated by depression, lack of recognition, shortage of money and touches of paranoia. It is quite easy, of course, to accept this pattern and still go on to praise Bell as a poet - indeed, if one wants to achieve the full romantic apotheosis, the life’s agony is a necessary pre-condition of the ultimate vindication. That Bell deserves wholehearted vindi­ cation for a life almost religiously devoted to poetry is beyond doubt, yet such an approach to him and to his verse is both a simplification and a misrepresentation. All who knew him well will assert that he remained at all times, to use an appellation which Auden was fond of, ‘no wet-4*g.’.He was a man of great charm, enormous erudition and, despite his devotion to serious literature, someone who observed the world around him with extra-journalistic sharpness and wit. The hermetic poet in him shared a sensibility with the worldly moralist and social critic. He was the true inheritor of the Auden mantle (his only rival the slighdy older Gavin Ewart), and, even during his later concen­ tration on twentieth-century French poetry, he kept faith with the thirties’ creed of poetry as an agent of moral healing, a trackingdown of the spoor of history as it is imprinted on our world. He had a highly developed sense of the poet as magus, refiner of the tribal language and high priest of psychic understanding. Sometimes it seemed paradoxical, in his later years, to find him, broke and slightly bewildered, speaking of the poet’s power and pride which made him a dangerous adversary and forceful catalyst. Music andJungian con­ cepts were the only orders which came near to sharing the supremacy ofpoetry in his imagination once his disillusion with the Communist Party took him out of active politics.In one of his best poems, ‘Reasons for Refusal’, Bell invokes his friend Roger Frampton, ‘desert-killed in ’40’, as ‘a pattern of accomplishments...joiij^d the Party first, and left it first’. These words can be used of Bell himself if the accomplishments be taken further to include infallible taste in literature and moral generosity. Nor did he ever desert the idealism which possessed so many ofthe finer spirits of his generation: he was always a man of the Left, even if he loved to add a Gidean 'helas' after claiming to be so. He was prescient of the dreadful blight of right-wing reaction in which we find ourselves today, recording as early as 1961 the way things were
￼going in an England bored with the egalitarianism and libertarianism of the post-war Labour governmentsWe didn’t want to say the way things went Pissed on the hopes we entertained,Na'ive, of course, but vivid and still pissedon - (Christ, boy, they’re reading The Times now!)&\d >arr> ao3"~i i~vWhat he would have made of Thatcher’s Britain I cannot imagine. My feelings vary between relief that he is out of it and regret that the philippics it would have spurred him to will never be written. We have many pre-echoes, however, in his poetry of twenty years earlier - ‘But the terrifying thing/ Is houses/ A stake in the countrySomething to hand down.... Dismal boxes voting tory.’ Martin Bell was bom in Southampton in 1918 and lived there until he was twenty-one. His father worked for the Southern Rail­ way, and Bell always described his parents as lower middle-class. Certainly, there was not much money about during his childhood and manhood, and this prevented his profiting from his educationto enable him to set out on a literary career - at least until he was in his thirties. The war, of course, was a further obstruction to his progress. But it was not poverty which rankled with him so consis­ tently, but the fearful gentility which went with it. Poem after poem testifies to the warping influence of lower middle-class respectabil­ ity, most clearly felt in people’s sexual lives. Only D.J. Enright, in The Terrible Shears (‘Whatever sex was, it was another enemy’) has covered this ground as effectively: the novelist’s world of keeping up appearances, sexual timidity and class embarrassment has nevermuch appealed to poets, and only Bell and Enright have made it eloquent as verse.^s,<TfisTelationship with his mother was close and neurasthenic, as late memoirs, letters and a dream-diary indicate. One of his most sardonic poems is called ‘Ode to Psychoanalysis’ and it indicates clearly that this expensive therapy could not lift the weight of child­ hood neurosis from his mind. But Bell was always able to place them in a larger context where the personal becomes the general. His perfect command of rhetoric never deserted him. The ‘Ode to Psychoanalysis’ ends with him ‘suffering Hell because I’m al overdrawn/Atthebankwhosemanagerhovers/Clackingrevengeful shears/^Hey there! Nobfttatidy!/ That’s my flaming sword...’The Blake reference is not just a neat summing up, it ties in with all the invocations to penis, bowels and negative transference, and remindsNous that Freudianism is based in prophetic religion as strongly as in medical science.
￼Democracy(from Rimbaud)The colours on parade, dipping past the filthy bricks ofthis garrison town. Boots, newly issued, stutter on the cobbles; but we can keep step.We’ll be posted overseas, to the big Base Depots. White buildings in long straight lines, like the Big City itself, but with everything laid on, just for us. It’ll be the biggest, best-run brothel in the world.Ifthestudentsriot,it’llbeusreservistswho’recalledout.East of Suez or thereabouts - where the cold beer is grateful to the clay that gurgles it up, and the temper rises nicely after meals. We’ll make the black bastards work: leader-writers will talk about the Commonwealth.Anywhere, to get away from home. Glad to be back in the army, we’ll use our loaves, all right. We can’t pass exams, but we get our feet under the table. Everyone else can get fucked. Progress we call it.By- The- Right- Quick- MARCH71
￼Instruction for my Godson(for William Redgrave)God help me, I’m supposed to see you’re toldAll about God the Father. So my beard mutters: There are always two fathers, one Good and one Bad. You can’t miss the Bad One, he’s always around, Particularly first thing in the morning,Scruffy and screaming for a razor-blade,Wondering who to eat up for his breakfast -He won’t eat you however much he shouts.I’m not trying to sell you bad old Nob^daddy -Learn to shrug off his sessions on his throneFarting thunderbolts and belching clouds.The Good One has a different way with clouds; he watches. He knows fifty-seven ways at least of looking at them,He addresses them politely, and his lookingCan hold them still in the sky.72/
￼I didn’t get very far, acting it out With Doctor Hackenbush.I developed, he said,‘A massive negative transference,’ So the analysis was cut offAfter I hadn’t paid himFor over two months -He took two-fifths of my wages.(His name wasn’t Hackenbush anyway). I still wanted to kill StalinAfter that. But I felt I’d let Freud down. The cook would not run the State,And the State wouldn’t wither away, And psycho-analysisWas very expensive indeed:Postpone, for the time being,The New Jerusalem.IVSo here I am, in the middle of several paths, More or less where I’ve always beenHaving survived war and intensive masturbation Getting away with murder, maybeBut suffering Hell because I’m always overdrawn At the bank whose manager hoversClacking revengeful shears.Hey there! Nobjidaddy! That’s my flaming sword...
￼ManicureEach fingernail, ugly again,Must be clipped to a crisp moon.Ten homy wedges,A city’s dirt under the edges,Could sharpen to ten weapons,Razors, flick-knives - mustn’t happen.An urbane law,Not red in tooth and claw,Says what nails are for:Combing the eyebrows neady,Scratching the skin discreedy,Squeezing blackheads, scraping corns from toes, And picking one’s nose.82
￼PyromaniacSuddenly he was amazed byThis fresh packet of Swan Vestas - ToreThe sides out as instructed.Each scarlet bulbWill pay for a flameSafety matches are Drier and more discreet Hurrah forBryant and MaysWork out the average number of matches ForYourself. The^e might be a prize.But if you want a bombAnd don’t mind burning your hand Explode a fresh boxO f Swan.
￼177 178Dear PeterAs you are the worst Jonah I know I address this letter to you.(Remember the time at VictoriaWe boarded a train for DulwichAnd landed in the middle of Kent?They said it was a signalman’s mistake,But was it?And George arrived late in Leeds for a reading And the porter had put himOn the wrong train.At first I heard and believed ‘Porter put me on the wrong train.’Why does one always expect you to arrive Half an hour late? However -)We crept down the stairs from your flat,Walked along swinging QueenswayTo Bayswater Station very cold and earlyThen Victoria - pushed through the people, Collected luggage, pushed on with heavy luggage, Until Stass’s Gurdieff moustacheBristled among thie'crowds, smilingAnd nis children were jumping up and down, And Mary was smiling patiendyAnd we joined the party, then a hitch -A dark emissary from the Travel Agency Saying my cheque was made out incorrecdy- Actually the advance had been bouncedBy my former bank-manager (I dropped him) So I had to do a complicated businessO f changing cheques with Stass. I here insert a parenthesis -