￼THE LUNCHEON OF THE BOATING PARTYPoems bySTEWART CONN/Final typescript: November 1991
￼Also by Stewart Conn:Thunder in the Air The Chinese Tower Stoats in the Sunlight An Ear to the Ground Under the IceIn the Kibble Palace
￼
￼AcknowledgementsThe title sequence, with 'Renoir in Orkney', first comprised a 'Weekender' feature in The Glasgow Herald.Thanks are also due to the editors of Aquarius, The Best of Scottish Poetry (Chambers), Cencrastus, Chapman, The Edinburgh Review, Gairfish, The Living Poet (BBC Radio 3), The London Magazine, New Writing Scotland, The Observer, The Scotsman, Six poetes ecossais (EditionsTelo Martius), The Sunday Times and Verse where poems in this volume previously appeared, though not always in their present form.
￼10 11 12 13 14 15 16 1819 20 22 23 24 25 26 27 2830 31 32 33 3437ContentsIWILDFLOWERS BURIALMOUNDBOAT TRIP WHITENESS WHITE CLEUGH ARIATHE BOATHOUSE BIRD SONGSStarlingBittern RESIDENTBIRDOFPASSAGE FAMILYTREE CRAGGYCOUNTRY ILLUSIONISTS JANACEKQUARTET THEEYE-SHADE BUTTERFLYFARM 2POEMSProfileSuilven MANZUEXHIBITION PICTUREFRAMER INTIMATELETTERBREACH OF PRIVACY SKYEPOEMSOn arrival Dawn, Drinan Reminder SabbathThe islanders to the newly-wedsBog myrtle OCTOBERWEEKPresenceThe chair IntruderFrom the ridge Relic
￼40 WS GRAHAM41 RENEWAL NOTICE42 3 POEMSAccessories Storm damage Intricacies44 FORTH BRIDGE45 FROMARTHUR'SSEAT46 UNICORNTAPESTRIESSurvival Millefleurs1Signaller' AftermathII50 THE LUNCHEON OF THE BOATING PARTY AlphonseThe Baron Unknown man Madame Renoir Renoir56 ATLESCOLLETTES 58 RENOIRINORKNEY60 TRANSFORMATION61 FORT NAPOLEON62 MILITARY MUSEUM63 MONFLANQUIN64 LOT-ET-GARONNE*