￼132 I rebuilt the shed. I threw out what was splintered and rott­en and fetched myself some good. I built a strong and shapely shed. What have I ever built like that before or since? 1 thinkHis Highness driving home in a tank; and hitting it full throttle wouldn't demolish it. i bet it’s standing now. Think of that, gentlemen: somewhere very remote and south and west of here there's a shed of mine still standing, ny (jhrist, I worked.Mother, perhaps to try me, asked if I'd ever cleared a cess. I jumped for joy: a cess! Show me, missus, show me what wants do­ ing, give me a shovel, rods, a giant ponce, a prong- or nothing,with ray bare hands I'll be in there. Gome, she said, have it aonebefore mid-day, your tools: a thimble and a backscratcher. Tenminutes later I'd unplugged the place, the waters ran, the goodK ca- < /|u n •earth drankNit dumL. 1 tidied up a bit and planted some chamo­ mile before Old mother appeared. Oh ho, she said, pleased with ourselves, are we? I was cleaning my nails, you see, with astalk of last year's grass. There's a tree down, she says, been down a week, Father says bugger it, but we can't get the cattle througn. Show me, I said. It was a beech, athwart the sunken lane, last fling of the mad March gales, i'll send your dinner out, she said. Just as you like, 1 said. My tools: my teeth and nails, myAtlas back, my wrestler's arms and thigns. I— pressed that gi'anl- I slewed the monster round and let him drop, his tethering rootswaved on a sunny sky, his crown was in the mud. Then I sat in the crock of gold place, in the loamy smell, hugging myself for glee.uver the rim of that crater she appeared at noon and giggleddown at me- at me her clay and roots man leaning back at his ease on an upreared circle of tree footing. I've brought your dinner,she said. You'll have to jump, I said. She did, with lifting skirts, sure-footed, down into my earthy hold, my den, my rooty house.That was the first time she fed me the bread of heaven, there un­ der the gasping roots of a fallen beech, bread she had baked, good still warm white bread, and a bottle of beer from her basket towash it down.
￼133*2,Listen, Lilian, I'll tell you some. Don't want to hear yourdirty stories, fir Horn, save 'em for them as does. Too bad, I say, can't wait, I say, they're pressing for utterance this very minute, iou go on back now, i said to her, tell MotherI'll be through with this by tea-time, Loon as she'd gone I . JifSkJkj-ek-oe— 4r)^e— eartn— tetk -Lnt-o— the gsping root hole, 1-lee ou-r plac-e—i+t. Then lopped and faggoted the tree, humped-it^^uid two dozen trips, heart sounding like a giant's, my- e«Liju j.epeifcnire of—th-e-obd—rrnge.-I—oard I don't want (btohe r^your carryings on, says the Widow Clack, and I'm sure these gentlemen don't either. Nevertheless, I say, imagine me happy, imagine me humping wood like a cheery Caliban and skipping back for more. Never humped nothing for me, she says, dabbing an eye.Untrue, missus, I say, the bins every Sunday night, regular as clockwork, crates galore every delivery day. Humping? Day in, day out, I never stopped. And thought of her while you was doing it, she howls. Enough, enough, the Marquis says, whut1a done is dr»*a_, precious little happiness ever comes our way, let's not spoil what's been. Jfer curving nails can't reach my dim andtant past.By tea-time I had stacked two winters' worth of logs against the coal-house wall. Smell of the sappy wood, me hiding my bleeding hands, Mother nodding and dreaming up more tasks. Not interested, says Clack, these gentlemen isn't interested in all the poor women you've ruined. Cack asked me to ask you what yougot for tea, says Dougie. A cold meal, old boy, tell him a cold meal: best tongue and pickles, cheeses, gooo bread and butter and as much hot tea as you could drink. Apple pie afterwards, also cold, spiced with cinnamon. Mother left us occasionally to seeto the old man. He was in bed, roaring for attention.After tea the young Mrs Evans played the piano and I sat list­ ening in a rather c .Id parlour. Lord, how rny muscles ached. I looked at my hands, my fingers were stiffening up. Hers werewhite and light on the keys. My mother was a real Liberace in her day, says the Widow, and Father had a fine singing voice. You needn't go thinking there's only folks you know with any musical haspirations. Music hath charms, says the Marquis. Blurtings from Took. Patsy is in by the nearth, he spits, the coals gasp. I knew a tart in Wigan played the tooba, he says, fat little lass she was, sat wit?) it on her knees, on a cushion,
￼you couldn't see anything of her, just her legs and her feetin carpet slippers, and the old how's your fat ;er corning outthe top. This was different, I say. Imagine my physical fat­ igue, an immense wellbeing, no thought for the morrow and her playing tunes you never hear nowadays, the Raggle-Taggle Gypsies-0, Walk in the Paradise Garden, and more Preluues than you'd think existed. Had an aunt played everyone of 'em on Sundays after evensong, says Bov/1es, you made your own entertainmentin them days, of course. The little onions and the ungenerous cubes of cheese go round, the Widow eyeing me from behind the pumps.Well, Mr Horn, if that's what you're called, the mother said, I'm off to my bed now, such as it is, sty more like next to that swine, and you'll be off to yours. Our Florrie here has to beup early and so have you if you're to earn your keep. What's for me to do tomorrow, missus? I enquired. Ever ploughed, have you?Master would have ploughed the top field by now, but for his un­ fortunate accident. 3orn with the bit in my teeth, lady, ploughed everything in sight i have, from the word go. Show me the field, it won't know what's hit it. Hm, she says.You're remarkably good at things, Florence observed, once the beldame had exiiited. White Michael lurches in, face like a puff­ ball. You're barred, the Widow says, leave my premises and don't want telling twice. Speak to him, Joe. Am I to be flouted and you standing idly by? Michael totters out. You're barred, saysJoe. What did he do, missus? Pat asks, it's so long ago I've forgotten what he did. Kicked my Bertie, says the Y.;idow, and I'dhave been better pleased if you hadn't forgotten. Kicking my Bertie'.s one thing I'll not stand for. Sausage dog of her bosom.A marvellous power, I was saying, seems to have possessed me. Offhand I can't think of anything I couldn't do. Try me. Any marshes you want draining? Any hills in the wrong place? I don't think so, she said. Now's your chance, i said, now's your chance while the spirit's blowing through me. Who knows, how iong it'll last. She rises, gently at lap height closing the piano lid.1 don't like the evenings, she said. Yes, I said, let me do what I can for you, let me make things a. bit easier if I can. Yau'revery kind, she said, smiling. We should go to bed. She said that? the Widow says, her beehive of golden hair reverberating,134
￼zk*. She said what you just said? Aye, tnissus, and with­ out meaning anything to be ashamed of. Husband away, and ner conversing v/ith a strange man (Walter: you can say that again) in the parlour and Mother leaving 'em to it. 1 can tell you,Mr Horn, when my Dicky was away doing his bit no man ever hada friendly word from me. 1 wouldn't look at 'em. I had 'em hang­ ing round my knees but 1 wouldn't so much as look at 'em. Itwas stronger than her, Mrs Clack, she knew her duty as well asyou did, I daresay, only when these things happen you have to bow to 'em, man or woman, no use swimming against the tide likeUncle Jim. Sniff from the Widow.Took takes a pint. Like the drink, he says, no different, like the drink, hee, hee-^ his flat cap rising and falling v/ith hiswrinkling brows- I never fight it now, when I have to I have to, and that's that, and mostly I have to, only when I'm sick 1 don't have to and even then I force it dov/n or I'll/be rignt again, if you know what I mean. So I agree v/ith him here for once. Compul­ sions are a strange matter, says the Marquis, science has no ex­ planation for them, I believe. We're witnessing here a perfectly respectable young woman- the Widow: humpn!- happily married weassume, who-sc husband s? away risking his life in a good cause,and that woman, so Mr Horn is about to inform us, come late even­ ing when her loneliness is worse, after a bit of piano in the parlour and Mr horn having laboured like ten men all the day and asking for more on the morrow, that good woman, a jewel by all accounts, finds it impossible to leave the chilly room and ling­ ers in the -d-e-orway by the open door, her fingers turning and turn-wpher wedding ring.Thank you, yes. There was a wind that night. Standing in silen­ ce by the open parlour door we were both suddenly aware of thewind. Perhaps another tree will come down, I thought, the bigger the better, or a chimney pot. I've done some roofing in my time, I said, if y u need any tiles fixing, or if a chimney pot comes dov/n, after this wind, I mean. There's a door banging, she said, coalshed, I tnink, ausn't have fastened it properly. Let me go.No, I'll go. Neither went. The door slummed: each time, in each interval, our nerves were waiting for it. When she lookeu at meI looked away. Some faces, I was thinking, some C-aces of women's faces are so open, are so without any coverin. or mediation ex­ pressive, that you want to look at them through your fingers. 1135
￼must have raised :>y hands, i must nave been in the act of cover­ ing iny face like a child, for she noticed them am without hes­ itation touched my knuckles, which were, as a result of ourcollision and dp my day's labours, scraped and raw. And she took both my hands then, took them into hers and turned themover, and saw how stiff and sore they were and calloused fromone day's willing -iabo-ur work. And at that moment, heaven forgive f*tme, feeling at her touch how rough my hands were, I j^agined- no, I looked upon, i felt- all those places of her body that nobody, I sup rosed, but one, and him overseas, had ever seen and touched,and my hands- credit me v/ith that much- shied away from hers in a gesture of Tending off and my wicked eyes closed, but being closed they perceived more clearly still that young wife's lovely places, beginning with the secret of her throat and thus...We don't have to listen to this, says nilian. 1 say we've no need to listen to filth like this. Lave it for your d-irty raen- fricnds in the Institution, there's respectable mixed company here. Speak to him, doe, tell him to mind his language, he wants to wash his dirty mouth out with soapy water. Joe turns his cod­ ling eye on me, his mournful cow's arse face, his slick of bryl- creme hair. That'll do, Mr Horn, he says, falsetto. Don't tellme what'll do and what'll not do, little man, I bawl. I knowwhat's proper and what isn't proper as well as the next finger.I also know- this in an undertone- what Mrs Grundy here can standa bit of and a lot of on occasion. Hand on her bosom, rolling her eyes to God. God sniggrs. It’s in his mind, says Walter, nothing’s happened, perhaps you wasn't listening closely, mrs ulack, it'sall in the old feller's mind, he’s si nding there in the draught and the shithouse door's banging in the wind and,the tart in ques­ tion giving him^,the eye^he imagines the rest. It's all in tr.e poor old feller's mind, can't see no harm in that, I'd be the first to object if it was anyways real, these lads- a generous sweep­'ll back me up on that, I'm not a man for any effin and c-in where there's ladies present.I had reached ,her throat, tier cameo, the topmost buuton of her high white blouse, i was about to say, before little fish-face and his mistress interrupted me, that proceeding in the mind's eye to see what would be seen v/ere fingers gentler than mine in a kinder reality to have undone that button, I was taken with such a fio of trembling, such tremor cord i6, such weakness in the knees, starl­ ings of wate> behind the eyes, constriction in the gullet, tingling136
￼of the scale, -ingels passing twenty to the dozen over my grave and a frisson snooting from tie coccyx to the oine 1 gland (Mrs Clack: Well 1 neve- did!) tna t I ran from the room with a groan into the wi .iy yard to secure toe aforementioned door whichwns, as Florence had supposed, the coalshed door and not, as Falter misheard, the shithouse.So nothing happened? No, sniffing missus, nothing happen- d. And working us up like that, nil talk, says Took, always has been, rhe Marquis smiles, puts together his clean finger tips.My dear Took, my dear Mrs Clack, I should hardly say nothing happened, exc pt in the very grossest sense. She did not let fall there <=>nd then, it seems, nor have ripped off her by cal­ loused hands, her married clothing; but to say uhat nothing happened would be to inhabit a very coarse world indeed.imagine the feelings of our hero now, standing alone in the starlit andwind-crazy yar , rhe animals restless in their creaking sheds. It is certain innumerable proofs of a psychosomatic kind have been given him- that he loves this young woman. But who ishe? A bum, a lag, a wanderer, got into her o-ho-rity by the merest accident and some elbowing, and certain to be asked to leave ag­ ain within a very short time. And were he to stay, were the old man to continue bed-ridden and were his, our friend here's, services to continue to be required, still what prospect does hehave but torment? She is married, don't forget, and conscience forbids him to attempt any trespass. And yet, and yet... If I guess aright, if I have learned anything from what our poets tell us, his deepest sense, as he leaneu his knobbly forehead against the coalshed door, war not of anxiety but of appiness, of gratitude and plenitude. For love is an end in itself, ladies and gentlemen, when it comes it comes, and that is final. We breathe it in, we inhale it into our bloodstx'oain, it courses through us, fills us through with a generous happiness. What an expansion love is, coming as it were from nowhere, what a putt­ ing forth and creation out of nothing we are suddenly seen to be capable of. Love is of its es ence, I beiieve, quite direction­ less. Though Mr horn here was focussing a minute since on thecameoed throat of a lady in particular, alone in the yard his feelings will have filled out a universe, omitting nothing, leaving nothing, however mean or intractable, untouched. That is love at its purest, informing the world but craving nothing, ab-J37
￼138undantly giving and asking no return- mo i do not imagine that he will hold it thus for long. Jut there in the yard 1 think we can envy him, standing sure-footed at the mid-point of a uni­ verse of love. Rare equipoise, so full of happiness that nothing exists beyond it for a man to crave. Not to want is, I am sure, the answer to most of our problems: to be, to love, and somehownot to want. To want nothing in particular, to make no partic­ ular semand, and yet to love, to be in, to be a part of, to com­ prehend .Silence. The Widow's shining eyes. Above us, crossing t e via­ duct,a long slow train, a shudder through the glasses. How's the queer fellow? Bowles asks, him with the eyes. He's not been in the news for a week or so. Says he'll be through in a fortnight, says Pat. Then what? The open road. Fancy. Norman driving. The car's been ordered, Norman says, iM-irraJor, all mod cons: electricwindows, two cigar lighters, upholstery in maroon velvet, revol­ ving cocktail cabinet. Fancy. Norman's made. Lucky for some. His ex's'll see a bit no doubt. He's a gentleman, says the Widow, always nicely dressed, always respectful, unlike some. You heard McGrury's dead? Fell off a lorry. In that green overall? Carry­ ing his trade plates? They say so. Makes you wonder. Guess whowas in. In here? Right where you're sitting. Henry Hall? Bone. Tank fetched him in last week, says Joe. He never said, Tank never said. Sat down there, he did, lunch hour, not much trade, poor little bugger, the Missus had pity on him, gave him an on- ion and half a pint. Kind of you, Mrs Clack, he can't meet withmuch charity nowadays, he must be pretty far gone. Tank take him off again? Well, he did and he didn't: top of North Hoad he had one of his turns- frothing, eye-rolling, tongue up his nose-and Boney got dropped, near the drycleaner's, it was. The Lav/ came here for a wheel barrow just on closing-time. Where they took him I don't know, but they never brought the barrow back. Tank never said. Forgot perhaps. His turns make him forget. I'd han him up for a flypaper, says Walter. 1 mean, he's not human, ishe? I seen that little grub put cold rice pudoing in his pocket. I seen him eat chips from Sweaty Betty's dustbin. I mean, he's not a civilized being. Cack much better? Cack don't hoax’d, you'll not find Cack with oudding in his pockets, what Cack gets he eatsand that's more natural to ray way of thinking, Bone's a hoarder, that's why he stinks, stuff goes off in his pockets, stands to