￼eAttila 48-64 3/9/92 12:47 am PageATTILA THE STOCKBROKERI was born John Baine in 1957 and grew up near Shoreham Har-transmitted to me before he died in 1968, made me determined to get out there, say what I think and earn a living as a poet - some­ thing which all the critics tell you is impossible to do in this coun­ try. I’ve often wished I could tell you, Bill - I’ve managed it since 1982!But this is not so much a living as a vocation; I really did begin this thing believing I - we - could help to make this world a hap­ pier and more equal place, and the fact that Newspeak is now real­ ity, everything that my parents’ generation fought for is being des­ troyed and the atmosphere in this country is getting more squalid, selfish and unpleasant by the minute just makes me angrier and more determined not to throw in the towel! For all those on the Left throughout the world whose eyes are dulled and spirit shat­ tered by years of defeat I say: do not go gently! Scornflakes is for you.e64e
￼T An/cAOs£ T(t?i ch^ccclut R>£ qisGaes fc>(Z i\/&0 0proofs...corrections and alterationsPage 1 is fine.(!)Page 2 delete exclamation marks after '1982', 'throw in the towel' and 'do not go gently.'(Ideological advisor says overstated. I see her point.)Page 3 should have Eric Bloodaxe above your logo. He's my mate. Page 4: slight query about the legal notice. I often get requests for work to be included in fanzines and other non-profit publications. That’s not a problem for you, is it? Otherwise fine. CUe^^e ,Page 5. Dedication:For JoyPage 6. (Neil, you sarky bastard, you did it deliberately! Don't shoot until you can see the whites of their eggs!) Grandchildren of ALBION not ALBUMEN! (I know people say that Michael's poems are a bit insipid but really...)....and you slightly misread my copy;'....Hard Lines 2, Apples%&Snakes 1 and 2, Prism and many more and in magazines,...' Stick the Womble in between the first two paragraphs, ie+f/«j Cbabove 'The illustrations...'- it looks better.Last paragraph: 'If you want to write to me you can do so c/oBloodaxe Books, P.O. Box 1SN, Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN. I promise you'll get a reply.'Page 7. There are loads of changes here - I'm not quite sure what happened to my original list! Both letter case changes and text alterations. So here is Page 7 in full.Contents11 Repossessed by the Devil12 Language Barrier14 The Blank Generation (singular, Neil-how otherwise?)) 16 Slough19 Belgium20 Worthing21 Harlow1Basildon23 The Bible according to Rupert Murdoch24 Contributory Negligence26 Letter to Saddam28 Libyan Students from Hell! 30 A Cautionary Tale32 The Gulag Archipelago-go35 Vegetables36 To Slough and Sanity38 Canada39 Australia40 Xenophobia42 Four song lyrics:The Pen & the Sword This Is Free Europe Market Sector One Tyler Smiles48 Rain49 Tell Sid......50 The Iron Men of Rap!52 Boys in the Hood (Trainspotter Rap) 54 Rapping Mole!56 N-n-n-nine nil (Selhurst Park Mix),
￼57....And Smith Must Score! 58 Dustbin Poem59 Video Nazis60 Awayday 2Page 8it should say LPs/CDsI appreciate your additions....however, Donkeys' Years was a UK release last year so it should just read thus:Donkeys' Years (1991)and underneath it should say:For further information on any of these releases write to me c/o BloodaxePage 9 diekhead'ls the right size but it should be near tliu DuLLuw of the-page 1$ c^oTac^ R lo-e.Page 10 I should like the quote from 'Do not go gently' which is, I believe, from Dylan Thomas, written to his dying father - I'm sure you knowtheoneImean-aboutfourlinesorso ci'tL(aJLs^J^ t>(~Page 11 My ideological advisor has reacted to my punctuation in exactly the same way that you did so we're putting it right, all the way through the book.So you borrowed the earth in the eightiesYour repayments are lateTo our creditYou bought crap on a whim ' But again you believed what they told youDELETE Lamont! I think by publication he may be no more! and the Chancellor, neighbour of the beastPage 12 is finePage 13 full stop after British (line 9)Page 14 seem happier not are happierfinish intro with leader dots not full stop - Chris Rea LP.... Blank Generation singular as beforeBy the time they're eightthey like Blur and the Manic Street Preachers (add the)Page 15 is fine Page 16 is fine Page 17 is fine Page 18 And allPage 19 is fine Page 20 is fine page 21 is fine Page 22 is fineI ask (in Masefield quote)
￼Page 23 no quotes around Gotcha!Page 24 2nd verse - Told me cap both times Said he thoughtBloke was onlyGirls like that3rd verseAsked me cap both times Told meSaid he'Need a slash' When he did4th verseTook his keys Crashed the car Though he moaned? after Kevin, lose the commaPage 27 delete exclamation mark after shooting partners " after I'll do the rest.Page 28 delete exclamation mark after earliest poems (in intro) With scaly tailsWe undermine everythingAnd we don't care just'cos you sold usSo don't mess with....Page 29 is finePage 30And as he grewPage 31And then some Sheep Then he gased downPage 32Archipelago-go not go-Go (as per contents) Underground Sun should all be in italicsPage 25 -is-fi«c £fauS l«cPage 26 has headed notepaper so you can delete the second White House
￼
￼Page 33 'cos not cos ( lines 8 and 11 lettuce get it right)Page 34 let's call him BarryPage 352nd verseYour viewsYou go to bedfull stop at end of second verse3rd verseAnd so she took a lover And if you had some spirit Your brain stem4th verseYou're an eighteen carrot cretin Arid although this verse is cornyPage 36 is fine Page 37 is finePage 38 - Arransweaterhas2Rs n/0I'T-DO^kTI oblivious y&’w presencegentlemen or the wrist not gentlemanPage 39But on the way to MelbourneNow I've made my contribution (line 18)delete last two lines of poemaddAnd with a squelch, another hapless kanga rues the daythat the Government of Victoria built that new Hume Motorway.Pages 40-41THE DUTCH THE DANES THE SWISS THE FRENCH THE CZECHS THE FINNS THE KRAUTS THE SWEDES THE GREEKS THE POLES THE YANKSgiving us your bombs and tanksThe Sun in italics not capitalsPage 42Where the page is a flameWhere womanhood is crushed (line 20)
￼Page 43Where the pageWhere womanhood is crushed Here's to youPoet on the runMan of wordsumlaut on 0 of NiemollerPage 44 lias 3rd verse running into chorus: paragraph after listen to me now....one more CHORUS at bottom of page (the word, not the whole thing!)Page 45Umlaut on 0 of JorgNo colon at end of introduction2nd verse;carve-up is hyphen, not dash ~J%e vultu^j And now the old, rich foreigners'You're living in my house...Page 46(22nd November 1990) not (22/11/1990)Too much Chingford , But it's a taxing timeSix hundredNow historytake commashand-pickeduser-friendlyPerhaps he never really..yearsrolls backoff standing on their own two feetPage 47 is fine Page 48 is finePage 49hard-earned not hard ownedPage 50Delete 'like Louis Farrakhan' in intro - the point is made in the poem Delete next sentence.Insert If they were white, their misogynistic, homophobic, reactionary nonsense would be treated with the contempt it deserves.And there's violence....but some of you like it (both times)Page 51 is fine
￼Page 52Hey, don't walk awayYou know what they call us On Saturday morningsft/ilI*Page 53And here's what I say DeleteMe and rqy posse InsertThe anorak posse,And if you want informationPage 54 is fine Page 55 is fine Page 56 is finePage 57sight....The memory of that awful miss(fourth yerse)We lost the replay 4-0 rPage 58Full stop at end of poemPage 59The bloodlust rose Then naked humansi<^yThe cesspit of the huamn mind The vampire free....And now sick menAnd hipsterspage 60 deletecrypto fascistandby organising a fake army coup and looking ever so brave by standing on a tank surrounded by his cia backers (ray ideological advisor says it sounds ridiculous!)delete end section and insert
￼arid the millions of people thrown on the scrapheap all over eastern europe in the name of rationalisation and profitability and market forces said bollocks to that and the relatives of the victims of the nationalistic orgies in yugoslavia and the pogroms in east germany and the hopeless hunger in albania said bollocks to that and all the brave, hopeful, creative people totally unimpressed by the painted McDonalds smile and the crisp IMF banknote and the leer of the advertising hoarding and the soulless chatter of the world money market and the brainless yelling of the tabloid and the obscene illusion of 'freedom' in a starving, violence-racked, fascist-infested continent said bollocks to that and we're forming a mass revolutionary party with a brand new vision and we're going to wave the red flag again and we're going to take power again and next time we're not going to confuse perestroika with selling out to capitalism and our slogan manifesto andprogramme is going to be bread peace and land ....andbollocks to that...!/
￼SCORNFLAKES
￼ATTILA THE STOCKBROKERI was born John Baine in 1957 and grew up near Shoreham Har­ bour in Southwick, West Sussex, the only son of Muriel, a pianist, and Bill, a poet who left school at 14 and worked in the civil service for 46 years. My father’s limited opportunities and enthusiasm for words, transmitted to me before he died in 1968, made me deter­ mined to get out there, say what I think and earn a living as a poet - something which all the critics tell you is impossible to do in this country. I’ve often wished I could tell you, Bill - I’ve managed it- since 198$JBut this is not so much a living as a vocation; I really did beginthis thing believing I - we - could help to make this world a hap­ pier and more equal place, and the fact that Newspeak is now real­ ity, everything that my parents’ generation_fought f o r being des­ troyed and the atmosphere in this country^is getting more squalid, selfish and unpleasant by the minute just makes me angrier and/"more determined not to throw in the towel(f)For all those on the Left throughout the world whose eyes are dulled and spirit shat- V- tered by years of defeat I say: do not go gen11}(f)Scomflakes is foryou.
￼Attila 1-8 17/9/92 10:58 pm Page 3ATTILATHE STOCKBROKERillustrated byWOMBLEBlGODAXe BGDK5
￼ACtila 1-8 11/ 9/92 10:58 pin Page 4eCopyright © Attila the Stockbroker/John Baine 1992 Drawings © Womble 1992ISBN: 1 85224 231 0First published 1992 byBloodaxe Books Ltd,P.O. Box 1SN,Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN.Bloodaxe Books Ltd acknowledgesthe financial assistance of Northern Arts.LEGAL NOTICE>A11 rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, ortransmitted in any form, or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise,without prior written permission from Bloodaxe Books Ltd. o4 Requests to publish work from this bookmust be sent to Bloodaxe Books Ltd.Attila the Stockbroker has asserted his right underSection 77 of the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 198Sto be identified as the author of this work.Cover printing by J. Thomson Colour Printers Ltd, Glasgow.Printed in Great Britain byBell & Bain Limited, Glasgow, Scotland.
￼AtCila 1-8 17/9/92 10:58 pm Page 5 <>Dedicapop?here?J^e^igraph?Plate j ) f herrings?-e-frypfe? ^SCAjfr us [peA<>
￼Attila 1- 17/9/92 11:47 pm Page 6 <y Acknowledgements--Poems in this collections have appeared in various anthologies inc­ luding Grandchildren of[Ajbumm. Hard Lines 2, Apples & Snakes 1 and f Prising anti many moreAin magazines, fanzines and other publicationsMarrge and small all over the world. They’ve been read on radio and TV and performed in arts centres, rock venues, lib­ raries, pubs, comedy clubs, colleges, folk clubs, schools, at open- air festivals, on trains and football terraces and in a hotel basement in Albania. ‘Contributory Negligence’, ‘Vegetables’ and ‘Video Nazis’ were first published in my 1985 collection Cautionary Tales for Dead Commuters (Unwin Paperbacks).The illustrations were done by Womble, aka Dave T, who apartfrom being probably the world’s only rock ’n’ roll dentist is thepublisher of an excellent magazine called Wake Up, combining hard­hitting political satire, excellently informative and well-researchedarticles, band interviews and loads more cartoons like the ones inthis book! Issue 9 £2 inc p&p; issue 10 £3 inc p&p from Womble,H-3 Viotoi»in-Itead, Qulton Broad, LoweatoftySuffolk 9LU. 1 P.O.Box 34, QuitoloiMibft;SubfetUP.O. Box 1SN, Newcastle upon Tyne NE99 1SN. J prohima Row'll (\ef A ^ IIf you want to write to me you can do so c/o Bloodaxe Books,/NR|32 -
￼eAttila L-10 18/9/92 8:31 am Page 7 <> ContentsRepossessed by the tfJevil Language lsarrierThe l&ank Qcneratiorj/'’ SloughBelgiumWorthing9-April l992The Bible according to Rupert MurdochkContributory Negligence)ear Saddam..yibyan Studet/ts from Hell *A\ Cautionary TaleThe Gulag Archipelago^ Vegetables / „To Slougj/ andjaanity CanacAustralXenophobiaFour Song LyricsRain/Tell/SidTh/ Iron ofRap Boys in the H\odapping Mole’uesday September 12 1989.../...And Smith Mu9f Score! Dustbin PoemVideo Naziswoke up got up read ftae post..Ppr Paj* ^ M full Sit Check LcsT
￼eFor -furfkc/ o^ IviK took* U> cjo BloobUtf-e .Attila 1-8 17/9/92 11:47 pm PagePublications by Attila the Stockbroker BOOKSCautionary/ Talesfor Dead Commuters (Unwin, 1985: out of print) (ed.) In Praise of Slough (1988 - thankfully out of print!) Scornflakes (Bloodaxe Books, 1992: alive and kicking)LPs/CDSRanting at the Nation (1983: deleted) Sawdust and Empire (1984: deleted) Libyan Students from Hell! (1987: kaput) Scornflakes (1988)Live at the Rivoli (Canada, 1990) Donkeys’ Years (lc1cf1^)This Is Free Europe (©ertttattj/, 1992)668 - Neighbour of the Beast (Australia/New Zealand, 1992) plus various singles & tracks on compilation albums/