￼D'Aguiar part one 18/3/93 9:28 pin PaSonnets from Whitley BayTroubled but not distressed.FROM A WINDOW IN DURHAM CATHEDRAL1Stretches of this country smell so bad,I apologise. We laugh at your, ‘I’d think About my love for an Island that stinks.’ Those hours we took to find the North had Become a straight line: imperceptible curves Broken by an occasional roundabout,Until talk ran out and we banned ourselves From idle thoughts of the distant South.Wake up love. We’ve long passed the border. The South is irredeemable. The slanted light From the early summer sun is colder,Now it casts elongated shadows of you and I Ascending the stairs to our love-nestWhere we smell tired and unwilling to rest.2We always star in one another’s dreamsIn full technicolor and super sixteen.We fall asleep like spoons and only turn When one or the other decides to turn. Morning is a silence that won’t fracture.An elbow-room closeness and the odd gesture Confirms the other’s thoughts in sea-air thick With desire. We nod our approval at brickIn a city w'here I first said, I love you,Climbing the cathedral’s 325 steps to viewOne shire shouldering the next, like molars,As God would have it or Buddha, or some polar Icecap and then the warming of the globe, Exactly as the heat I feel when inside you.30
￼D'Aguiar part one 27/4/93 7:47 pm Pagg^l3These are the people I told you about,The ones with mostly goodness in their mouths. They treat us like old friends come back at last. The pints you and I lever to nought renew fast, Faster than we can toast the water of Tyneside. Late into the evening we find seats side by side. Our legs touch and when I shift it’s to feel your hip As I see it through this straight glass at my lip.I’ve brought you here to be undressed by allTheir kind and hungry eyes, only to takeYou to a Hi-Fi lit dark, Motown Soul,And enough spring water by the bed to slakeThe thirst of two flushed, open-mouthed lovers, Through locked-eyes, locked-arms, hip-locked hours.4My love you fill my head to distraction.I am pacing a room you hardly looked into, Furthest from the bedroom-cum-granaryWhere we lived and loved and woke in an aviary That quietened as the light intensifiedAnd objects muddled by the dark, clarified.All that night nothing could come between us,A sliver of light or dark couldn’t separate us.By morning the bed had split into half - Us in a dividing current on two rafts;Us in our deep dreams, private and sweet. How did we drift apart, even in sleep? One look from you of panic, loss, love, And I leapt from my raft to share yours.r31
￼. vy5I hold up your 501s against my waistTo get the measure of you: come back, now, From that big, big city that pulled you away,To this one main street, coastal town,With five minute jams and one of most things.I knew between us, me and Whidey Bay,We couldn’t make you stay. We tried everything: Flora and fauna, the sea’s light displays.Your long, elegant legs opened fluently.I eased into a wet, warm, silky placeThat made us gasp, quicken, then rock gently- Our eyes searching one another’s eyes and facfe;----- When not one of ninety nine cars registered Passing the house in the rush-hour was heard.6This kind of loving wrecks the body, Makes it impossible to function properly.You wake up mid-morning feeling like the night before, But to go back to bed would turn your head forever.You stay on your feet and sway like a ship Becalmed, waiting for anything to happen, to slip Your world back into orbit, but nothing does, Except the light slips and you register a dull pulse.The ship is hers and the sea is hers, the lightYou see the world by, hers; the loving that night Was all hers; the feeling that you’re wrecked, hers.The love you think is a blessing is a curse,A weakness, something not hers, but yours: stop, / Before you have no pulse, before you drop.32D'Aguiar part one 18/3/93 9:29 pm Pa
￼D'Aguiar part one 27/4/93 9:39 am Pa7Your touch, I’d nearly forgotton your tom __ And you’ve been gone less than a month, mufch- Less; yet here I am using poetry as hypeTo conjure you from a Daguerreotype;From a past neither of us could have known. The fine tremor in your hands is mine now, As is that chain of sweat on your upper lip. I offer my China silk hanky whose tipSticks out of my top left hand jacket pocketAnd a half-smile: take it, use it to mopThe sweat beaded on fur so delicateIt might be kissed away, not electrocuted.All I can do is call you up and hope you’ll come, And pray that in calling you, no harm’s done.8The miles between you and I open up.The days stretch out against all my wishes.I fight betrayal when a hand brushes mine, Preferring a bruise from an upper cutDelivered by one of Whitley Bay’s British Movement. A stranger’s eyes make four with mine, I hot up instantly like a four bar bluesLaunched by Muddy Waters or B.B. King.Not so long ago we watched a moon in a shoe Step from that shoe which changed to something We couldn’t name, as clouds do, then the moon Perched on a lake big like the sea; that moon Looked like it owned the lake and all around. But we watched it fall into that lake and drown.33
￼D'Aguiar pare one 27/4/93 9:40 am Pa>When I turn my back on this North of Norths And I kiss you goodbye, how come it hurts?When se^it winds loosen a stinging rainOn Whitley Bay, your tears drown out mine.This curved beach of seaweed and stones Shows from my wavy footprints I’m all alone.The waves form an orderly queue to see Who’s the miserable man bringing misery.When those waves wreck in despair on sandstone, It’s my back breaking with my need for home.I give up town and sea for glass and concrete, And a capital adding to itself,House by red brick house on the For Sale shelf, And new-post-code street by tarmacked street._-I34o-/e
￼D'Aguiar part one 27/4/93 9:41 am PaFrail Deposits(for Wilson Harris )1. The Trench RevisitedWe’re being driven past when you point to Where you’d pushed in a friend long, long ago, Into what was a trench, to test its depth.You say it taught you how a civilisation, Feeling a blow or tug may still not knowA hand’s involved, so can’t feel indebted.I was falling, horizontally, justTo keep up and lucky to win your trust.Push him again, he’ll fall on land that’s dryThis time and think nothing of it, and you’ll Bank all that knowledge lifted from the sight Your friend made clad in mud, convinced totally That he slipped and your hand on his ribcage Was your brave, unlucky, one-hand-clap save!2 A Jealous GodThe light on our first morning at breakfastIs such that three women as many hundredsOf yards away in pleated, cotton frocks asBlinding as if the green, yellow and redAre light sources and we’re in some studioWithin touching distance of them; we lookTheir way, quiet and still, more like studyThan look, they are grouped close, signing their talk.The sun is a jealous God are your words. Suddenly nothing means much anymore; Watching those three women, a timeless world Regards us as much as we regard her:We feed like enraged Ugolino fed,Though captive, on his captured jailer’s head.
￼D'Aguiar part one 27/4/93 9:41 am Pag(^~yl3 Bone Flute‘This your son?’ enquires the curatorAs we waltz in for our official tour.You finger the thousand year flute of bone As if about to burst out with a tune.You tell how the bone came from an enemy, Morsels of whose flesh is consumed by them.When air is blown into the fashioned bone,The enemy’s knowhow and plans are summoned.The flute I’m trying to blow a tune on Belongs to you, got by me over years fromStringing your thoughts sentence by sentence, Or what must stand for you in your absence:Having to check when I’ve said something To see if it’s yours since it has your ring.4 SeawallYou explain rudimentary quantum theory: The frailty of us jetting above weatherFrom one world touching down in another With a wheel-screech equalling our surprise.Ah, to leave marks in this life that survive! That outstrip the skids of a jet’s tyre!The stretch of seawall we walk looks breached. A man who seems too fit to beg wants change.The sea is muddy, loud and creased in the distance. We have to lean a little into a welcome breeze,Our heads bowed from the direct beat of sun.The soldiers in barracks reach us in waves Dictated by the wind’s direction and pace; Dear God, I think, don’t let this moment pass.36
￼D'Aguiar part one 27/4/93 9:41 am Pa102a1Rain on the slate roof and more rain collects in gutters then down drains.Where does the picture come from of it falling up? I hear a rhythm:drips, slips, taps, smatterings, rattles; out of this a pattern surfacesthat is thought itself. Then the thought purely to do with rain, turns righton itself, as if against all that water washing the world, reverses waterup drains to rise off the roofslatesto where it’s still, floats, and is weightless.2Cold in a room that won’t be driven out by heat, hangs solid like a gas lanternor mosquito net or drapes or a web dangling preciously in a strip of light.I look at why it has settled for here.The shape of the room is no longer room-shape but the form cold takes settling in a place;and I don’t belong; heat doesn’t belong.I am no longer simply feeling cold,I am being asked to leave, pushed outby it into another cold, into the openwhere size and blue puts the cold in capitals.37
￼-0-D'Aguiar pare one 27/4/93 9:41 am Pa-Early morning light weighs nothing. Lacking the conviction,it cuts through windows, but avoids corners; filling the room with live shadows.The roof over my headtakes on extra layers and new pressures.I am instructed not to move, even a mere flickercould demolish this delicate balance. The main beam is not the main beam I takeit for but the very weakness I see and criticise in light.I begin this apology,noiseless, urgent and scaredthat the roof might collapse and light fall flush on me, and I might end up crushed.38