￼\X2\1cj inheritedMr'So many without memento...( Lt>Vv«’1. i^fPrologue:The Children 'I bade them climb: they must have come to the very crest And it was beautiful to see them shineNot steadily but charged at a sudden momentAnd for only such duration as the light allowedThe light they caught upon their faces from the face Already we should have thought sunk out of sight.There are some dead we see and even see by; They glimmer for a generation, our looking Lends them more luminance. I saw the father, Whom no-one can rekindle, appear to shineOver the earth in the eyes of the gazing children/ They cast his face upon my white paper. ^2% #vrcJLo------ 2.tl] After how many Novembers ...i o j tf[cpu,In Memorjam ^57d-JPrivate J.W. G1eavewho was at Montauban, Trones Wood and GuillemontHow soon, I wonder, after how many Novembers 7 □ Did the years begin to seem not pacesInterminably around a pit nor steps deserting -■^QA place, but slow degrees by which she cameOver the curve of the world into that hemisphere Q His face rose in? Again we have given ground, The dark advances an hour into the afternoon,Q In the interlude between cloud and horizonA mild sun scythes the field— so by the last winter Q After an illness and before her deathWe saw a similar light dawn on the womanQ Who had been a widow more than fifty years.lMVUtrtv>IP * 10'
￼She lingered in the doorway of the living-room □ Impelled as people leaving are toSome word more than goodnight. I□ Bright as a young girl’s on that thresholdBright with tears. She found nothing to say. But having ClHer purse in hand— the purse she had kept house from For generations since the Queen died— she took outQ The new, neat, folded notes of her pensionAnd to the children and their children and their child Q Disposed of these. We do not like to watchA person look for words nor by whatever gestures Q Taking her leave of table, hearth and chair.She went to her own room where everything was ready □ To leave, the furniture of her married lifeThough in another house, one he had never seen.□ But in that mirror he had seen his face,They will have stood side by side and looked at themselves □ She will have stood by herself and remembered.And always she held the two or three photographsQWhich light had fallen on man and wife to makeIn an envelope with the notice of his death□ A s if to cross over with these in handThat she should know him again who had been effaced QAnd he should know her who had lived and aged. \ ;3.Q Notification,&m TIt was the painful duty of Lieutenant Thomas Dinsdale On Army Form B 104-82In an envelope the postwoman shrank from touching To notify my grandmother of her altered state.The women stood by, they followed the post like crows: To whom would such a communication comeThat morning, to what woman by the hand of a woman Whose job it was daily to visit that village of streets And lay the stigmata on certain doors? iu
￼So the news came from Guillemont to Salford 5After a lapse of weeks during which timeShe had known no better than to believe herself a wife.Not having seen him die and whenUpon their notification nothing followedNeither the body to her hearthNor any of the late soldier’s effectsA little whileAs though the outcome could be put in doubt She trimmed her mourning with a thread of hope She kept the Suitor from her husband’s chair Showed Death the doorNightly, until the evenings were long.He called then with a companion from France. The neighbours, who miss nothing, sawOnly the soldier leave.No messenger in the tragediesSo mean but coming to the wife, the motherOr any beloved woman waitingRecounts fittingly the dead man’s deathIn alexandrines or iambicsAnd honours him in the telling.But who the pal was is not rememberedNor what he said, nor what the questions were She had the heart to put nor whetherShe lamented there and then, praising the qualities O f the man lost and hiding her face as queens do In her apron. Not a word, not the place itself Reached me in his pronunciationBut as to how and where
￼She only shrugged her shouldersAnd perhaps she had that from the messengerWho did not tell her that the night was very short And began in a barrage of phosgene gasAnd ended in a thick fogAnd a barrage of high explosiveAs they moved around the southern edge of Trones Wood Across seven hundred yards of open groundGently sloping to the village of GuillemontIn an attack understood to be hopelessBut serving the French on their right Whose attack was also hopeless And that somewhere before the wire He was obliteratedIn gas and night and fog. 0 *1—- 6.But by November the congregation of widows Q Being told it was a reasonable sacrificeTheir men had made saw mutilated trees bedecked QWith bloody tatters and being nonethelessPromised a resurrection of the body□ They saw God making their men anew out ofThe very clay. These women having heard from soldiers Q However little from the battlefieldTowards All Saints gathered black gouts from the elderQAmong their children stared at the holy treeAnd envied Christ his hurts fit to appear in.PSome then insisted on a photographTaken before the harm was done— which face they caused Q To appear in the hideous crater of their livesUpon its slimy water. In time while she pursued U1With wrung hands her business as a widowThe water cleared. On the surface of a peaceful poolQDecentlyframedthefaceshonesteadily. rv4\
￼XA/tC±^>,7. JcK\kfiThere being no grave, there being not even one Ranked among millions somewhere in France, Her grief went without where to lay its head. She would have rested sooner had she hadOr had she even learned somewhere there was A well-kept place where he was lying dead.■4tShe could not even think him out of harm:He must be hurt somewhere by every shell, Somewhere his mouth could not get breath for gas. She would have scavenged all his body homeInto the shelter of if not her houseAt least the roofed and hidden well-walled grave.But of what comfort is the body homeWhich here or there cannot embrace or smile? And of what comfort is the body whole?Only the rich and saints do not corrupt.She almost thought there were degrees of death And he was more dead piecemeal and abroad.There being nowhere but the family graveShe went and called her grief out of the air And coaxed it to alight upon the stoneThat did not bear his name. Upon that absence She grieved as though it were the greater one And death was lured almost within her view.Sne set that feature on the featurelessVisibly everlasting plain of deathShe trod a path, she made some little inroadAnd placing three or four remembrance daysShe netted in their few intersticesGlimpses that she could bear out of the deep. fu4 \
￼*r8.Q Roll of Honour CM _She never saw his name at ThiepvalNor even in Manchester CathedralBut on Liverpool Street outside the Mission Hall There was a Roll of Honour on the wall4Affixed in nineteen-seventeenAnd this she will have seen Daily (until the BlitzBlew all the names to bits).he enlisted men— there were no officers— Were columned street by street and hers Was one of those already crossed. By rightse Vicar should have come at nights?And crossed the others one by one Until the toll was done.%9.Q Like shrapnelLike shrapnel in the lucky onesShe carried fragments in her speechRemarkable to grandchildrenBut to herself accustomedLike rise and shine and leftLeft... he had a good home and he left Andalong,longtraila-winding... * E?L- O