￼BalderschwangI often recall the wordshe spoke to me that nightduring our walk togetherround the castle ruins.The snow continued to fall,and his stories grew more fantastic,' and in the muffled darknessI weakenned and gave way. Ah,it was dawn,I remember,when first I kissed my master, using my tongue like a fisha woman might slide alluringly from its temporary resting-place inside her moisten^ing vagina. Yes,I often recallthe words he spoke that night during our walk together round the old castle.(Revised version of The Hunting-Lodge)rVi%: 3
￼The work goes on as usual. Only the men survive -only the men,who guard the wrought-ifon gatesthe red glass bowls of sweets, the satin sheets;who operate the fans that cool the womenand fill the night air with their giant wings.
￼Everything Is WonderfulEverything is wonderful up here - the flowers,the air -especially the air -how did- 3/ou find it?Wonderful - but weird,as if I'm in a curious hotelI don't remember anything about,where everybody's kind,and seems to know me. But I must admitit doesn't feel normal,and I sometimes wonderif there',s some mistake,or if my other life'sstill going on somewhere,and where my friends are,and the house I knew...It's perfectly alright to ask probably.I'll ask this person feeding the hydrangeas. Maybe he's my son.You never know.What I want to know isIs it serious?And do I live here? Normally,I mean.Or is it just a joke,an exercise?How boring of me if it is.I'm sorryiPerhaps there's someone I can talk to somewhere? Or do I just decide anyway?'Thanks-a-lot-I'11-take-it' type of thing? The nice hydrangea man says Feel freejIt sounds so easy,doesn't it -'feel free'?GM> ,
￼DogsI'm not as unprepared as you might think. Take a look outside my window.Dogs.All day they wait like soldiers for my voice, a voice so beautiful that everyone -no,not so beautiful,a voice so clear - t that everyone who hears it,dogs included,will leave the hospital,without a fuss,some with chocolate,some with fruit,or fish, and make their way into the distant mountains; and if they want to dress in dresses,let them.Let them wear the shiniest materialsthe nurses and the clergy can provide,so when they reach their final destination the rocks will sparkle with them^for one year; then men will come,attracted by the light, and,armed with flames ,-ir.cinerate them all; returning with the ash to the valley,where things have changed,and even dogs are burnt, and palmtrees' dessicated leaves go clacketty,in at the hospital windows,clacketty-clack.
￼JELLY - Selima Hill1Who made me?God made me. fWhy did God make me?God made me to know her, love her and serve her; to call her hy whatever gender seems appropriate, to peel her roads,to lay her tozverblocks down along the ground' like washing,to embrace her crows,to pacify her vivisectors, lick her sons;to train my mind, which is like jelly, y to be like rock,unshakable and well-grounded;to try and make sense of compassion,'to try and be calm,even though my mind trembles all over like afish, a panic-stricken fishthat has been cast up on a strange beachand thrashes about this way and thattrying to escape the hands itfeels grabbingf t it-to nurse sm all orifices;to temper steel;never to yield to total elation -or yield, and know that I'm yielding:she made me to know her, and think about her (but then no longer to think about her,the way a rock doesn't think,or a lover)and she made herselfto know me.