￼THE MIRROR WALL(1) 4 page insert. Produce col seps from five slides plus b & w artwork. Delete all black keylines. Your telephone quote for this was £320. Pictures could be brighter than on the transparency. All to width of 100mm, with height dictated by this enlargement.(2) Master set is the Bloodaxe paperback cover. Produce four colour set as per photocopied guide, using transparency (print also provided for guidance). Match turquoise front cover and spine type with turquoise headgear of cloud nymph. Dustflaps to be included, but will be trimmed off in printing.(3) Bloodaxe hardback dustjacket. Identical cyan, yellow and magenta. Produce replacement black film incorporating changes marked on photocopy: i.e. delete ISBN, blurb and price from back cover and replace bar code. Dustflap copy is correct as per paperback.(4) Wolfhound paperback cover. Identical cyan, yellow and magenta(Bloodaxe logos in yellow/magenta will be deleted from the plate during printing). Delete all bar codes, ISBNs, prices, etc, from black film, and replace Bloodaxe logos with WOLFHOUND PRESS + dog logo (back cover) and WOLFHOUND (spine) using lettering + dog provided; replace ISBN with Wolfhound paperback ISBN; keep price as £4.95 as on Bloodaxe cover.(5) Wolfhound hardback dustjacket. Identical cyan, yellow and magenta (Bloodaxe logos in yellow/magenta will be deleted from the plate during printing). Delete ISBN, blurb and price from back cover; replace Bloodaxe logos with WOLFHOUND PRESS + dog logo (back cover) and WOLFHOUND (spine) using lettering + dog provided, same as on paperback; replace Bloodaxe hardback ISBN with Wolfhound hardback ISBN; keep price as £10.95 as on Bloodaxe dustflap.(6) Wake Forest paperback cover & hardback dustjacket. Identical cyan, yellow and magenta (Bloodaxe logos in yellow/magenta will be deleted from the plate during printing). Delete all bar codes, ISBNs, prices, etc, from black film, and replace Bloodaxe logos with WAKE FOREST UNIVERSITY PRESS (back cover) and WAKE FOREST (spine) using lettering provided. Don't delete blurb from the back cover.