￼X{&rC<ai*Ct feLM&'H0fTDAT~LN THkH'^ UF ^VITTDEnTs^O'VITCHCanvey Island Zen Stalinist Theme Gulag 12th June 2018Dear Darren,Been here nearly three months now, ever since the United Communist bastards stopped my car at the Hertfordshire border checkpoint and found that old Madonna tape and the copies of the Underground Sun I was trying to smuggle through. I reckon I'd have made it if it wasn't for that bastard sunstrip - no-one told me they had been made illegal under that poxy new Articulacy Act and I hadn't bothered to take it off, which was a dead giveaway. I was shitting myself when I got here, what with all the rumours about those Red bastards torturing people with books and chess sets and copies of the Guardian and so on, but, believe it or not, I'm having a great time! Yeah, straight up!Didn't look good to begin with though. When they checked us through the perimeter gates things were really grim. The whole of the camp is surrounded by this huge moat full of what looks like soya milk, and it's guarded by loads of pit bull terriers with really fierce lesbians on long leads - even if you get through them, there are two huge barbed wire perimeter fences thatW^ really rip your clothes, with an illuminated strip in the middle covered in that really thick motor oil that absolutely ruins your trainers. Anyone who did manage to get out would be looking at well over a grand for a completely new set of gear, at least. And the illuminated oil strip is kept under constant surveillance by hundreds of teachers and social /Workers who watch your every movement from massive ivory towers. It was well scary, I can tell you!But when we got inside...wow! First of all, we were met by these really nice birds who gave us all 'Canvey Island Zen Stalinist Theme Gulag' baseball caps, and then the camp commander - an old geezer called Billy something who seems alright, as it goes - gave us a welcoming speech in which he told us not to worry, the external security system was not at all representative of life inside, and astry to escape we'd all have a whale of a time since particular gulag was Saturday Night in August on the hours a day, 365 days a year! And then the welcominglong as we didn't the theme of this Costa del Sol, 24 party started....At first wesupposed to be the Reds' most notorious prison camp, the one no-one had ever escaped from - but when they turned on the lager fountain and brought out the paella and the disco began I thought hey, why would anyone WANT to escape? If you lot in the Tory Resistance knew what was giong on here you'd tear up your membership cards and start lighting the pit bulls and lesbians to try and get IN!It's officially called a work camp, but there's hardly any work to do 'cos everything we need is flown in from your side - volunteerscouldn't believe it at all. After all, this was
￼go down to the airstrip once a week to unload the food and videos and lager off the supply planes, and yours truly always volunteers of course, 'cos it means I get to 'lose' some of the stuff on the way back, if you get my drift, though there isn't much point actually since everything's free anyway. Old habits die hard, eh? But the rest of the time - party! Unlimited free condoms! Unlimited booze! We've got cable TV with 215 channels, and we've even got our own camp newspaper, run by the bloke who owned that Sunday Sport before the revolution - so you guessed it. PHWOAR! None of that boring news stuff at all! Though I hear rumours that things are pretty bad outside - apparently the Reds have renationalised the air industry now. Bloody Commie bastards! You know what we used to say in the good old days - there's no such thing as a free breath!All in all, what with their bloody Articulacy Act and the raising of the school leaving age to 20 and all that socialism and nationalisation and health service nonsense (whoever thought we'd be hearing that rubbish again, I thought the 1990s killed it off for good!) I reckon I'm better off in here!Although I must tell you that there's one tiling here that really worries me. Some of the people here, most of them actually, believe it or not, started to get bored with all the non-stop partying and discos and boose and sex and videos after a couple of months and they're going quite voluntarily into this big building marked'rehabilitation' where all they do is sit around reading books and talking! Every day loads of teachers and social workers come down from their ivory towers on the camp boundary to take part in discussion groups and sometimes people don't come out of there for days - there's plenty of sleeping accommodation, and it's tucked away in a comer of the camp, and they just stay there!And when they do come out....well, I can tell you, sometimes it's horrible. One of my best mates from the Resistance, an old bloke called Garry who used to be quite a famous Sun journalist before the Reds rounded them up after the Battle of Wapping and stuck them in here, spent two whole weeks in rehabilitation and when he came out he started talking about Zen Stalinism arid the United Communists' education programme and the bloody Articulacy Act and - get this - how the global AIDS plague wasn't the homosexuals' fault at all! He called me a neanderthal - I had to ask one of the teachers to tell me what it meant - and he even tried to get me to go to rehabilitation! I mean, what a traitor! I was going to get a few of the old gang together (though most of them are in rehabilitation too now, I'm sad to say) and give him a right old kicking, but the next thing I knew - he'd gone!'I've gone over to the other side', the note read, 'to help supervise the returning of the United Kingdom's air supply to its proper place in the public domain!' Wanker!Wey-hey! I've just seen the latest issue of the Gulag Grope,our paper! Talk about jugs! And I've got to go 'cos the curries are
￼>here, and there's another party starting in a couple of minutes . PARTYYYYY!! Hope you manage to destroy those new hospitals and schools the Reds are building - SMASH THE ARTICULACY ACT and GOD SAVE THE KING!! My so called mates might be going soft tut me - never! I reckon I might just pop down to rehabilitation tomorrow, though; just to check out the birds, like, not cos Zen Stalinism means anything to ms.fcO iSZu.