￼It Was a Violent Time.. literary history; it is savage with gang-warfare.'__________ K — A. ALVAREZ1Who scarred the editor and smashed his snitch? Which X-bard flashed a chiv, and which one wailed?Who snapped whose umbrella, then Tore down urinals, roaring?Who told whose mistress, in waltz-time He was out to get him?Which megalomaniac said, aggrieved,‘You’rr the pushingest mon in poetrry today’?Who needled whomInto hurling a glass of water?Who bashed up Pakistanis in the street?2Learn skills. Either the skill of a boxer And afford to be firm and forgivingOr deploy your sharp remarksFrom a barricade of horn-rimmed spectacles -That way you win your action for assault: And when you stab, stab always in the back.And pray for an unfailing hunchTo know which pundit to take out to lunch.
￼Ultimate AnthologyJacket it winsomely in primrose yellow!Here A, B, C are drained of words they said - Decendy wild now, each a handsome fellow, With X, and Y, and charming little Z.120t
￼Footnote to Enright’s ‘Apocalypse’Cultivated Signals types During the campaign in ItalyUsed to tune sets in To German stations:‘The Nazis do Beethoven beautifully.’ And one American boastedH e’d caught Freischtjitz complete - Thus diminishing his boredom.(Our chief culture-martyr Was Glenn Miller.)The Tedeschi certainly bought Their magic bullets.What have we bought? What have we paid for?
￼121122CouplesThree couples in this bar, at different tables,Two old, one young: the partners are like each other. One has vegetable faces, chunky respectableCarrot or parsnip faces: they look fed up,Keep still, have company manners on:In private this breaks down, one hopes, suspects,In rootish laughter, wrinkled grins.The second is restless and furtive and tatty,Two mangey carnivores pacing one cage grey-pelted, He fidgets pipe, taps chin, her fingers flutterRound the gin she isn’t drinking:They talk and talk, unsatisfied.The third couple is young, unworried, in good health -Skin, hair, teeth gleam like advertisements - They carry off their clothes as elegance -Speak in a lively manner, gesture like film-stars - For a few years now are privileged, boss-class.The girl, a bit plain beneath the glitter, Glances round at the others,Is troubled, briefly troubled,Intelligent under her hair-do.
￼AnecdoteNovember afternoon, misty at half-past three, Chrysanthemums still bright in slant of sun,And two small girls chattering along the pavement.The smaller said ‘It was shepherds.’ The larger, ‘I know,’ ‘Praise him, praise him.’ The other said ‘No,IIt was shepherds.’ At last it came to themAnd they sang through a verse in wobbling unison:‘The king o f love my shepherd is And he that doth mefeed... ’Having accomplished this they shook off their Sunday School smugness,And trotted away like little animals.There was the mist getting close, getting closer. There was the sun, an acid slant of yellow.It had been warm and now was chill.Most uncomfortable weather.
￼DialoguecorbiEre:The song of self-praise goes on, too long, too long. You’ll have to sober up soon, old comrade,And live an ordinary boring day through.I died of TB at a foolishly early age -Why do you have to act so finicking hypochondriac?BELL:You never had to live with so much praise In pounds and shillings and pence.They riddle my vitals, painfully.It is not true that I am not in pain -You damned unlucky maudit poet, you And writing so well, blast you.124t