￼e loved the rain, it bathed our minds to tnink of The replenishing rain. On a morning thenThe cloud had lifted and we saw the whiterSplash of the stream at the cwm mouth and the wallThroujh which the bracken trickled, behind tiiat dyke Ownerless herds of fire cropoed, unhousingLittle birds but leaving springs in hoofmarks and On a craterous level above two valleysThe lake where once in a cotton grass summer 3o®s-Vhite gulls lifted quietly from the surface And we undressed to bathe. I showed you afterwards Blood on a stone, feathers and a bridge of bone.Love of the dark, love of the falling silentOf everything but the stream... We left the road At nights, we trespassed over the propertiesBy the white clue of the climbing stream, by redLanterns of rowan. Above the stepping falls Under the lintel of the lion-gate foldAnd tnrough a hogg hole in the cyclopean wallWe entered our sleep like children. Hand in hand we Ran some distance to the last skyline. The lakeHVS’HeMStill lay in a sun^jand moonlight at a time Of the soft drifting of cotton grass or when Ice clouded over our full crater of rain.GO --- ec\ k 3>'Orw^ ---1?s-
￼-------b«=>vAUnder oompulsion when the moon turned murderous Coldly we walked out during the white hoursWho should have kept ourselves indoors for warmth Asking of one another only mercy.+Sweetheart, I pleaded, under this hag moonWe must say nothing and look upon nothing. Come in and sleep now or we shall convert Our universe to ash and ice and stone.Her hung and hitter face setting against me, Look everywhere, she said, once and for all And speak of everything and show me if you can Some love still living under my truthful moon.Turning to look I gave our fields to ash,I creased the brows of hills with lines of stone, I struck the wincing surface of our lake,I wrinkled every stream. In silence thenStanding triumphant by the sobbing iceI cupped my hands in trickling dust for herWhom fever shook. Moon love, she said, This being done how will you warm me now?------------------ — ------------ -t
￼Black where he is now who drew them, lightless QMy love, and where they are and all thoseLike them, the youth and the girl, and where we □Shall be, over the curve no sun,No star ever rising. Black. See how they shine, Diheir fired bodies. Smiling she curves Ascendant daylight over him to quench□With her cone his standing torch. That done* Were they living they would sleep as we do □Sightless, enfolded warm, on black.
￼llfcrviS \ ^\HytCAfc cca VERSIONS FROM THE GREEK
￼S £ ----- S 5to\, ,,—^S.°me 8ay.n.°thiiig on earthyj —»Some say nothing on earth excels in beauty Fighting men, and call incomparable the lines Of horse or foot or ships. Let us say rather Best is what one loves.This among any who have ever loved Never wanted proof. Consider Helen: she Whom in beauty no other woman came near Left the finest manIn Greece and followed a much worse to Troy Across the sea and in that city forgot Father, mother and her baby girl. For where Cypris led her there41She followed as women will who are allMalleable under love and easily turned. My absent Anactoria do not likewisePut me from your thoughts.&For one glimpse of your lovely walk, to see The radiance of your face again I'd give The chariots of all Lydia and all their Armoured fighting men.*3h/tlCAt 1*TM>1.-r,„