￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:42 pm PageFROM PENN (I 986)
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:42 pm Pages
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm Page0^' &>■Everything greenSeems like this day is winding on and on shedding things as it goesdown towards night.Everything greenis pouring out of crevices.When I go out the heavy boughs bunch their blossom into tight fists hailing down the mouth of earth.I am asking green to heal meor in some gesturemutely to acknowledge me,but the wind is changing coloursback and forth, somehow preserving purity of green, on the top, and on the underside, green closing her throatto my tentative desires.Am I not worth that one sign?ef13
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm PageCurious GeorgeIt’s a long day, Thursday, and Curious George looks at it sideways. The sun is hot but the wind blows it all over Crazy Daisy’s field when winter comes and the sky is bitterly blue.Then flocks of hungry waxwings come back to Cirrus Bay. Curious hungry George is watching cloudbanks happening.In a lonely windfilled sky there are no questions;in winter skies the rain comes when the clouds are hard and smooth.Then Curious raindrenched George is quietly glad.All along the ridge on Otis Mountainwind-filled reeds are whistling and bristling flattened, to the east shy Otis Mountain barebacked in the wind,Curious George’s mountain, and he smiles when he hears its name. Trees that are quiet in the sunshinesquare off a field that belongs to a widowed maid.The rest of the world is wild but the field is sleepyand Curious sleepy George is still, watching the sky. The long day Thursday is nearly endingand all over Pennypies Island a thousand island pines are dressed in many splendid nightblue shadowsbut Curious shadowswept George is afraid of their trembling boughs, rain will be long days washing the summersoaked mountains,and later on when ice is dry on the windfed reedsOtis Mountain will darkly slumber through sleep in the face of winterand Curious winterwarm George will be smiling again.I would father this pogiv\ /ewiaiV) c*u lowe/cciSeas i/i tl/te o/igidaL TGe idea was for tUelack of- typographical cowple/if-Lj fo Mattn theSiiMpliCito. of tup poeM's title daa/act-ef. "~-l would a\sQ have a Sfro/ijpreference fo/1Me po&V\ Sfayloy id cue block— imiC-evety £>urtM line Md&ibed if possible, as id the osfgiAaI.TPie.poe*A is Meaof fv be Je aAd compacted-50.L would like (Me po&Mto repaid exac/iy as14/please punctuate- as little asfOSSible '•fot -CXU/nplO— 1.it’saIqmday _z*C/azy daisy's f/ejd3.and k/isrlika, fi^tte/ted «t-OtiS tAOOAtaiiAy ba/ebackzd 5.curious yeotge's mouataiV\^p/n/ifed id ?&m .If Mis viol ales tMeMouse Style too badlyBlTIcv\ce Qqaiv\j rwyIS Me poem as it" appea/s fiAPo m v r i t d t l A e t o M M aoA |iiA6 lb, except-fb{ the (Mm ^lx v e c3ppc<A/e4-
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm PageoV--$*■PennI woke this morning and Penn was there. With him I walk barefoot on broken glass and swing sideways from the breeze spreading the summer dust.Breakfast with Penn is a shady corner of the day he watches the floating orange peel, I tell him lie Like children do.Penn gets in his car and drivesand when the dust has settledit is clear and noon and I am drinking cold liquid by the pool. Can wecross the world by Tuesday?I say it’s hot today. Penn thinks so too. Together, apart, we swallowtastings of the day. They slip down easily.And down the strand on Saturdays the grasses stripe young lovers(we are not watchingbut our eyes burn anyway)and beach-long waves sift round stories of heartbreak and of calm.It is evening. Penn sleeps.And I become much olderwith this late shaking of the leaves. I have promised I’ll die easily. Penn says I never miss my cue.Through the gratings of the eveninghe gets on his bike and rides,and in the small, receding shadows of the day the wheels turn in a loose metal kind of grin.15
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm PageSS>-Out in the stormThis storm explodes while it is still dark.I have no flight to watch my flightfrom here on up - riding, riding my storm. She blows the sky aside for me to passand from her back the ground looks faraway. Rainswept. Black.A coiled coastline writhes in a swirl of sea, lightning spills yellow road across the fields. She swoops. Riding storms is fun -she bucks and rears like real horses.Who is old in her timeless gale?She blows a tunnel through the years. Winded words from the doubling treesas she gallops past. Riding storms is easy! Gliding on a tide of rain -oaks are not afraid of rain.Time to bring her home, my stormbut reining her is hard.And long after she has bolted to another sky, below me waits the road, yellow in the silence and the oaks are never afraid.Driving storms is fun until they crash.\/V“Tfte R oasts *{b/ittvs poe/v\? OfUI (XfA i'V £ 'fdll-QP
￼eBrainburstSad, tremulous lightstands shyly before intrepid shadow,the integrity of darkness hides not but washes me -I am too bright. It is making me cry out. Walls topple towards me but never fall,and red cars smash green carsagain and again, though I scream a warning always slow smashing through the pinholeof a pupil, which will not look away. Rivets do not swivel. So I rhymeto comfort: an odd wish for confidence in metre. I tick, and soonit is no longer I who am bright, who cries out.Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm Page X,aAd soo/ut "is no Icrngef t vMo aw\ who CAj (XSY( "Cft'es" CeAaiCnly SOufldS be(t3T, k x i? fS if" /lOf "Cf\j" because " 1 atA lo/iglnf... t Cfy ood..." ? S b ) ("Also, if “cn&s* is gramAOttncaiiy correct Mere,ShO o|d/vtr "aiA" bQ " is*? SinoUld/iT t)wjmmJAl)
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm PageLRevival nightHard and hot in her room, way down in the brittle heat, where no birdsong reaches her, her wordless criesshock the sleeping night,(names and numbers draw backand she sees nothing in the paper gloom. [C oiled grief curling her limbs,she cries out, making the mirrors crackcand water spout, waking the walls,^but still the stubborn earth will not move Tor open wide enough for her to fall. /'Outside the blowing sand bleeds,v staining the shallows red.| Long after the last ocean drains J she lets a nightdress make herpure again. Warm and tender(in the healing light, she loseshours in a rippling sleep,waking with washed eyes. Searching /•behind the crusted lids, she hugsthe morning, her fingers working funny shadows in the silver light like small impatient flickingsof a silver knife.new' hyie breads biirwouid prefer tfoe poej/i topa/Vs of iMevefl \e/\apA.It is toe Shifts l7l MOOd tMaV Make ttAeje breaks logical - TV& -Pti^f secfi5v\ otAdtke seoo/id xectio/\ Have swvtilar Moods <5f aiAjer,btft toe tou/d is caltw-er. SB>.18I likef
￼- Q -ChrysalisI find you washed up on your own shoreamong the small stones dragged up in reluctant shoalswith the pull and swing of the water still in your veins,and the brittle shells whispering secrets bright in your inner ear. It must be close to four by the way the shadows fall and setde.cShould I tap the glass web that shrouds your limbsto plumb the silence of your comingor wait by the chrysalis for your soul to emergewith wet and crumpled wings - a flickering, frightened thing shedding the hours like loose skinswhile you slip dreamlessly through the layers of day and the wide earth stretches in unbroken song, yawns a sigh to touch your folded limbs,keeping the clouds idly at your sleeping fingertips.At evening when the rain glances off the hours and the shy friends gather in the dark,duty bends me smiling to the earth -your trail blazes nakedly in the open sky, casting your shadow to drag the deepwhere minnows tremble in their quick flight,yet such a thin slip of life scarcely parts the air and letting me put my two hands into your side you still ask across the aching silence:Now are you full of pride? ^v** <>•Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm Page19
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:43 pm Page 2.In St Etheldreda’sYou do that small thing.Know nothing, think nothing,where the unlit stonesupports dead prayer of seven centuries massed in drifts against muted glass.The slow beat of awakening consciousnessis the one you move toand climbing, memory on memory,remain unsure of the presence, three-personed, whole, which moves to your side after so long,and doubt, and climb back down.In St Etheldreda’sthe echoes are prolongedand purple is wornbrushing up against the candle flameand you have been close as you will ever be to an admission that the flame,that same flame, burning,is causing you pain.Although you know nothingand may soon stop wantingthe reassurance of feeling again,for now, you do that small thing - understanding nothing, believe all,and the certainty is awful, reverential, calm.
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2.UnseenThe only blind man in the galleryis missing Whistler, Braque, Matisse; tells me not to try the colours outon such forced memory, but asks instead that I be part of his absurd joyon the street, the open street,because down his mindhe sees the tiny soldiers charging -it’s the Light Brigade -and somehowthe colours in Still Life on a Man{lfj>iece begin to fade.I have no words for such things anyway.He says the cityis forcing her skull through the flesh of streets,lays a finger on the pulse of coming trains(that rumble is the dark grind of suture upon suture) and long before warm air stirs the jointed stickhe has heard them cry their sweet whistlealong the veins, under his feetthe white bone shiversinto fissures as he steps quicklyin the train to take him home.et21
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,Coming toI wake from some distant place of dread(is everything spinning sadly out of gear?)but you lie sleeping and I’m sure you dream (how fine to build a house without foundations and coolly scar a treeline with the roof)coiled shyly about the bed. You area brute, lunging, wondering does he bruise. Sleep drags this admissionfrom your defenceless form,calling me cousin, sister, wife.Over at the easelcolours have wrapped themselves on canvas, fierce in the patterns of our dreams,a picture two lives deep.
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,fThe Judas ^1owerWhen the sun purples the low end of the day he obediendy lights the room.Here is my chanceto stroke his hairand touch the soft, round collar-ends. But tonight he is staying very stillto separate the restlessness of limbs from the fearful, early stirringsof a sense within; his clear skinso easily fingerprintedby the blundering of my hands, and though I want to ask him for another chanceI say instead it is time to end his play.His eyes obliquely roam familiar walls, burning the air in a delicate, suffuse way.My son already knows the cord is cut and tied the liquids of birth long dried.He tries in a childish gameto take narrow breaths, restrictthe rise and falling of his chest. Without looking, I know thatit will stir again, hold out until thelastandthenpeachupandout and backjrn the ceaseless draw o f life it’s a suffocating, impotent, leaden-legged flightjand he lights up the eleventh hourjm y son,my Judas flower.ehoufj"HaQ[asfa/id tUeA(man up <xs\d oof a/\din tue ceaseless dmw 5f life—teaden-legged flicjUt-jand in& light's up H/iewy sqM) Judas -flower:23
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2He drew back alwaysWhen he dived in water, the ripplesspread out, out to the ground we stood,and I suppose we thought how heavilyhe breathed when night was down,how he was the perfect son, and then something in him was shot far wideand they said sometimes you can read the sign in the pattern of dropped sticks;tried to make out the fault laynot in the way he was shapedbut in the way a star warped its orblong before we thought of love.<yid f suppose we thoughthow heavily ne bfeatl/\Pd hhen night was dow/u hoodbewiasthe perfectsa/\d Uneh£6And his eyes would saythat air mustn’t torture us the same way when I asked why he hid his face walking the North Strand on Saturdays. W hether the fault lay in air or soundor in the way dropped stickshit the ground he drew back always showing the screaming bonesand I had to lead him home.tkfbetuw Me -fduir lay w-in aiVorsou/i6or in th? waydipped sticks hit th£ Q(ou/i4 be d/aw back always ShOOJi/10...SBAll thisbecause a pair of swallows crossed the sun as he was bornor on the day he was begun.24-e-
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,SongYesterday I heard your song of being no longer deadyou sang to earth three timesand hearing no answeryou sang to me instead,opening a silent drawer full of good things.The sharp painwas folded there among the scarvesand fluttered lightly to the bedroom floor,let fall unseenas I became many childish thingsbefore the mirror - Empress, Princess, Queen - the perfect image came of wanting it,of course you would allow me vanityand a little pride.I was thirteen and three-quarters when you died.You, in a crisis,always threw a wide expansebetween you and the nightmare visionscrossing the horizon,a camel train in a constant desert:there the narrow tunnels,there the great heights.But though you allowed me vanityand that little prideyou also threw me from my refuge at your side.Yesterday I sang your song of beingno longer dead.I sang,and sang again most loudly in my distress they were three cries to eartheach without answerthe answer comes from wanting it and I have never stopped wanting so I sang to you instead.25
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,Death in a stranger’s headFour years since youlaid your hand on the wicker gate coming with a half-child’s faceas close as you dared,looking to me for reasonhaving died in a lover’s head somewhere.And I -I saw a running light and describing it, said it is love without beginning or end,it is the tightest circle round the sun,and you will thrive in the memory of no one.But having died in a stranger’s head you were looking for the moist earth, the silence of burial,and it was not reasonsaying here was a man, coming unbound to a nub of painfrom a lover’s unopened door nor was it reasondictating that you should come to me for more of this troubled shame.Four years since the nightI slept, while you were torn apart questioning whether the elements really were air, fire, water, love, earth.And when you came wearily to my bed I felt that you were hot to the bare soles and later I heard you in your sleep.You said no, no.26/
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,Cycling backA sense of your name fills the place.He has left his bicycle quietly weeping in the halland climbs the stairs: a dead umbrella, dead cigarettes litter the room where he thinks you are.A sense of the recent pastspreads its stain on a blank pagewhere the four white letters of your name throw stiff shadows across the day.Your absence sends out feelers along the walls.He is standing, picture-bright, framed in the door. You had filled up every space with so much self that the empty air rusts down in flakes.Your skin smelt of honey and saltand he searched for some meaning to your dreams, sure he could rest in their familiar arms,but they had the aimlessness of wild things,and when he reached out to stillthe restless, yearning movement of your neck you recoiled in a tight spring; a showerof vibrant, blue triangles sent across the room.He is cycling back to any age, pedalling blindly, dimly awarehe cycles away from an empty room where he thought you were.
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,OrangesThe orange colour fills the veins,the orange threads the bones.She glides into the driest of my dreams,that boat with oranges on the canalcleaving the water with her orange laden bows through great June nights. She does not come in little pieces, she is tidal,unified and smooth. You lay your handson them then - like two round, firm breasts, the orange glowing in the veins.No miracle emerges, onlythe prickling of skin leaving the fleshof oranges that slip quietly by the banksfrom Fairways where the meadows boband the opiate afternoons drip like ice.Someone has found a church,someone else has thrown away a stoneas easily cast as chosen, like orangeswith their clamorous colour, with their voice - wrung from a supermarket trolley -or picked from the boat where the others bubble to fill the gaps; and the ear is ripefor the water-throb of the enginessensing the barge loom,hideous in night’s gaslight, staidwhen morning’s feathers settle placidlyto noon, and white milk curdleswith each of the orange drops.28/
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 2,HejiraHave you left the silent bedor is a shadow hoveringtrapped within a life of girdersand the grey pools reflecting sins "I and dimpled with the sleet J on iron, snow-dressed days?0t/\d tkY6 Q/ty pools f€f-lectiflg S/VlSdi(V\ple.d Ultt* U/\&steetW hen the sheet is drawnand you hide, naked, from a bitter reproach,I am rocked, petals blown.The world begins by swallowing me whole and spitting out the yellow aftertaste of grief. Ghosts already crowd the corners of the room.They have shorn the fields since then rising like stubbled jawsgrey-massed, grimacing, and no birds alighting for the grain.v -li I • i You will never let warm air playon your bare arm again.f29
￼Berkeley 11-30 19/8/94 4:46 pm Page 3.The partingYou lower my emotions, sealed in their casket, to the sea bed, knowing I have nothing to say, paring down to presence and absencethe sad abstractions of our last day.My throat grows heavy between your hands, my heart gets tossed away.2A shadow is working hard against the night, working furiously on a morning wallthe shadow cast by fifteen beams of light.I am a child’s bright stonelonging to be the weapon of your figh^j jI am the fifteen beams coming straight down. A3In brief moments when a nerve winks outit seems as though you will always be there. The heart kicks —and then you are removed. You are climbing down the angry white stairs, you are the shadow resting on my skin,and we, a double splash of oars into the still air.e30t
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:51 pm Page 3,FROM HOME MOVIE NIGHTS (I 989)ef
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:51 pm Page 3
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3.ILittle riverWhen harm is doneyour sorrowcreaks along like an ice-floe,and then it is no man’s remorsebut a hunted animal(tangling in briars and tearing free,on and wantonly on from the small wrong -but I can be a river where the scent will drown. j/I~am the river where you come to fish,lean and fleet where the line drops lazily in,trembling with the slight fish just below my skin, Land where the threaded fly brushes\winnowing riverweedmy warm current carries the light twig and the small wrongdownstream, and above me on the wooden bridge you swill water in the pail,ready for all I have to give.OM \A[WeCe the m/eaded flubrushes uii/ii/iowWj MyvjamajaeAi-carn&stheliW fwi< a/vdtki-eSMallwfew)f37SB.
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,Just don’t walk out in front of my bikeDon’t walk out in front of mewhen I’m pedalling so hard,quite likely to cycle over some edge, because I could take you tooor you might unhinge the symmetry of my beautiful, clear-eyed bike.You ran me over with your passion for fast cars. You know, you areonly one of the men I knowand in my own, shy way,I like them all; you scorched me slightly with your fire-fascination, but I was right to be an empty, earthen crusewhen you tried so hardto fill me up with every liquid that I like, and when you want to be a wavecome up from the bed all crest and plumage I’ve got to do my bestto tip my weight - beaches burst a seam when you froth shorewards,and is it for fun you tilt beneath me?On September mornings there is usually a slight ice to be broken between usand in the face of all thisI must requestthat you do not walk out in front of my bike.
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,Scarecrow(for John)I danced with a man of straw.the music blew through his prickly arms,his heart was a reed -it went with the wind -his smile was wry, tinderish to the touctyf) j■There were seeds for teeth,I could hear the pods crackingas he lit a song.We danced for a week, I was danced drjg) jI heard the changes being rung in meand had I been a birdI, too, would have risen with a shrill, vowel sound.e41
￼0Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,Death of a red flowerI am not dear today, there’s a bloom on me - you’ve got gentle hands and I may cry again for you replenished that unhappy reservoir, that lake we found, hugging in on itself.Even our silent awe sent ripples to the other shore.You discard things as you understand them. After ten years you know wellhow a whole parcel of your lifemay be bound tight and put up on a shelf. Memory is a red flower,the best bloom,chosen by you from a drenching of colour on a March street-corner.Today I put it in dying water,it has lasted these ten years,only now is it bruising.34
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,Do you?You came for Sunday afternoon,you stayed for teaand look what you left behind -every memory, sheafed carelessly on my window seat, of you and someone who looks sadly,sadly, sadly like me.I sometimes think I see youloitering in the shrubberywithout intent, idling nonchalantlyunder the weeping beech; I sentthose memories, lovingly enveloped, to that memorable attic flat,someday I may evenstand at your door,hopeful andcompletely uncalled for;but distance is proving such a very thick wall I can hardly hear you any more.Do you feel this at all? Do you?e35
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,Sfc.I don’t want his name in hereAt his death they cried that way —the sun howled, rain came.I loved the grief, it had so many parts, I hugged it to me on cold dayswhen the air was fulland love took longerto recall.His image is burned on my retina.I get dry-throated whenever I look,I whistle in the dark(^) ^I haven’t a hope.But light flocks, circling, and dawn brings soft shapes pacing in an upper room; maybe it will snowbig, forgetful flakes blunting the grassand the edge of hurt.I don’t want his name in herebut I don’t regret.I turn the death over on my palm -it is a small, soulful thing,it could blow away.42e/
￼- Q -Maker of rainI hear the muffled voice of my heart, the fretted moan,when the day sinks to its kneesall full of cries and heavy skied,and I knowyou still have the power you had when we slept in the dim room.When we came in latefull of the labour of sundownand dropping dark,drawn close by the doors creaking under our skin, and the cats brushing, saucer-eyed, against the dark, how you wove the threads of meinto slumbering cloth.I answer the voice of coming rainwith words of the sunlogged roomwhere we lay until late in the afternoon.You still have that steady hand -opening my sorrowwide as it will go.Maker of rain,I ghost the intimate roomwhere you wove the sheen of my most precious moods and I knowyou still have the power you hadwhen we slept in that dim room.Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,0^36
￼the- AThe harbour town is washed with dirty greens.I hum an old lullaby until it hurts, >and the dim lines of poplar trees•breathe in time to the breaking and^healing of the sea.(I find the slatted comfort of the wooden seats,sit facing the machines,watching them digest their wet, cotton meals, and through the tumbling heatBerkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,/Laundrette( his shirts grasp feebly at the glass door, dancing for me, pleading with me -(so I concentrate untilthe helpless linen tells how heavily his life lies, how he wakes late to feel the dark come down, obliterateso t cowteAtvabe'H A 2 - h/\€A...the comfort of old things, childhood things, long put away, dust-mantled;and I try to fold something moreinto the warm damp of clean clothes -something he will come upon, ^•intent in that unguarded momentleaning back to catch the second sleeve, something blue-green, orall the colours of a child’s wish.SB>.som^tkuvvtj Hue-gwefyor an tke lo\ogi$ of a child's wiih.45-e-
￼A study o f us together(for Niamh)This is how I go with her:you can study us together,we listen to the water notesthat tremble down the ear’s tunnel; we hearthe spring’s first impulse to tears checked by the wind’s sigh;we’re both washed awayon the wild silk, moonroll of spring tide, my sister and I.The same anvil beaten and beatenuntil the shape is white-hot beaten.You can carry away this fashioned thing and it is not lovebut stuff o f the marrow and nervesand of the blood.Sometimes we are two notesa breathspan apart - the breath of a tiny bird with the hint of a minor tone beneath his heart, sometimes one is shorter,we are sometimes both the same,and how easy to citizenthis world of two noteswith the faintly minor beat of wingsand a brave face put on things.Sometimes we listento ghost notes making the memory tremble and the room is washed through,washed free of all trouble, and weare two small girls again, eating ice crean"£) ^could be any age, seven, eight, nine.
￼Berkeley 3L-54 19/8/94 4:56 pm Page 5,&TenHer tenth birthdaysends an ache from eye to eye.Across my brow she strings the decadeshe has made; down my spineher lovely fingers let the years course through. A pool forms at the base.Double-figured, she unwraps her gifts, turning up her tiger-lily face, freckled, sure of a rich capacity to pleaseand if a sudden impulse should arrestmy empty lanoto gather her in,my shoulders ftfrving her weep at them again, I wonder could I keep her in the darkwhere she would lean only to my sun;but when she sleeps she seems #6 briefly5 fohav®to join the dead, taking ontheir ice-edged white, not to be touched in case a flawshould shoot across the skin.Even taking her leave for school she takes too much; I wish her well,she swallows the wish,a slim match, eating her flame,archly blackening,so I offer her the gift of choice;she chooses lightly with her delicate hands; an hour of silence, poppy seeds,the tale of Ruth, such things.Allowed out on her own, she comes in, wind-blown, arms fullof contradictions, laughter aboutthe eyes with their mute agreementof grey and green; she should have been named for a queen, for she lovesto presume, she does itwith a simple calm, countingmountain peaks among her natural heights.Allowed oub oa berowA, she coM.es i/\j tdihd-blow/y, afMS -fOl! 8[ SovUVadichb/v^laugkt-e/ about tW? eg&5with their Mdte agfeeM<?rtt of grev/ QAd QfiBAShe should kave bee/irtawed fob a quess\, for she. loves to p/esuMSyshe does'it wiftA a siw\p;e caiM, couAtii/ia MouAfaik peaks a^o/ig her v\ato(a\ heights-she seeMS bnefly fo joi'o fMP dead,taku/iq on tiAeir ‘tce-adged vfhife,nof to be ftxicmed [V\case a flaw ^ should snoot across the sjaVt.
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:56 pm Page 5/These rumours reach me by a side-wind: I never gave her leave to growso leggy-geranium tall.Once she raised the lid on a box of light; her face dazzled, and I thought I sawa child of light - but in a waking dream she let it close again. Has no one seen how a little light stillplays about her when she smiles?54e/
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,Homefmovie nightsRatcheted, in stills,how thin and brown the smooth-limbed brothers, throwing off their casts of sand (bury me! I am a dead man!)framed in loose rolls of celluloid,and I, smaller even than the buried ones, up there on our sitting room wall.I was once caught under a giant wave - they brought me out alive(they did not save my lifefor I was saved on celluloid)but through the wave I saw them dive for me.All my life they brought me, pearl-like, from the waves, and now, well usedto handling the names of menlong gone from me, and unfamiliar grown, and opening the letters homeI do most of my wringing of hands alone.38e
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,Pole-boundPole-flown, jittering in the sun,you can see me for miles:I am the jubilant one,highflown; my spirits soar and whip, knuckles white, I grip the wind.We are bound. We are all thoroughly bound.1 have all this wasted passionand how do I sleep?The restless breezes paw me awake;my tongue is minced, it ripples uselessly. I am the one who always sees the dawn. I sleep fitfully.Rain moulds me, abject,to the bitter pole;I brush my eye-lashes wearily against its cheek yes, this is reluctant love,everything’s under lock and keyin my heart. Everything’s shut down.I can see for a hundred miles aroundbut I am bound. We are all closely bound.44
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4.3rA time of droughtI am with you on the long road,I keep timewith your pale and winded giving in,A I don’t let go.Today I shared a day-long lifting of the weight.t Qwi with you 6V\ the lov\q (Dad>1 keep tii/v\& w ih your pale aj\& winded/•We water-skiied at a warm place,'we pitched in, learning the feel.I saw your shoulders straighten with the load removed, you held tightto your nerve, riding the surf, Jaughing your ropeworn laugh -thought you’d rise above the mounting dread,.your child’s shrinking from the end of things, .but you were sinking, anchored at the wrists, “head bent to those depthsplumbed from an early age.I watched the water rise against your dry sides, I saw it suited you to drown,my heart kicked up enough sand to hide itself and lie back still, for you scorn placeswhere the rock-falls make a shallow pool;you held tight to your fraying nerve, you took hold of my words, they came by the roots, as in a time of drought.giving ih- I doA't let go-I saw yoor snooldefswith the h avjtxjheldtigUttopus i\et\Ajyi'duAcj Iaughfng your fcpewovn laugw—h£ad kenf 10 those1 wafcked thewater rf;e agai/utyou/d<ys[d^ ' 1 Sawif Jc/itredyou to otfowAj47pIuMked -fto/A aA ea/\yac
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,W interingO f course I feel you gathering up to leave.In our tightest, briefest argumentsI crush nettles with my blind left hand -the child in me peers through a grid of fingers, my eyes are an open wound.Your lies have piranha teeth, freshwater white;the stones of the river grieve until they are worn smooth,and pain has its way with me - a great fish, nosing at my spine.Because I will not try to blunt this helpless, piercing sight, you push me to one side.The cold air salts my face. Perhaps this, too, is a cure, for you are slightand leave no trace.My hand digests the slowest nettle juice, I have no scars to showbut I have heardthe muttered refrain of wintering tremble up from a flurry of dried leaves at your heel; it goesbury me, I shall grow in spring.e49
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 5,ConvalescentThere’s smoke in the air although it’s spring; people are shedding muddy boots and things,slamming their private doors on rooms with sofas and TVs.I fall into the wind - it rights me, mildly,and I walk like a convalescent down a tree-lined path,wood-soothed, thinking of bough and bark and all that will comeof the nutshell, the circlesin the circles the lathe handleslovingly with its gaze,the hacked limb a lumberman healswith his dab of bright paint. Somewhere friends are waiting,lies in their hands, hands by their sides.50e
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 5,The swingThe afternoon’s awry, it slivers off in curves. My dress makes a crimson pendantat the garden’s throat; I swingcausing a frivolous shiver of green across the lawn; I am cradled there printing this crescent I wearacross the brilliant, livid-sided air. All this swinging stirs the blood, makes whole the filled-up heart,until the garden, stiff in its joints, begins to make fluid the swing to good and the return to wrong —and when I fall, just let me liefor the more I try to be featherlight the heavier I becomeand the more I try to be wingedand sleepless, the heavier grow my eyes; my senses list to the warp of the earth.Whose voice is this, singing the swing to rest, shrouding it in loveliness?/51
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4Closed outI saw you close me out with that one look, the flick of a smile-edge emptied ashin a sad flutter downand I am only some dull creature thudding softly round, not pretty, though gendeand so unwitting, treading white snow brown,bewildered by youburning through the trees like a whipping wind silver-witted, while I am slow iron -and when you opened my handand found the first bloomwincing from a late frost, on the palm,winter fled through the air in a fine dust, making me feel I end soon toonow you have closed me out with no word.aAd l qm o/ilu] somq doll cfeatuie tkuddiVtg softly found, nobpfefty, fkaugUf43S£>-
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 4Less than a hundred hoursI have put on a warm skir^j ^I have come infrom the garden, where a pallor is caught on every thorn.You know it’s you I see at eveningbefore the light goes.The secret alters with the hour^)sleep slows the colours,but in the morning, wakingfrom some warm place, it flowerstimidly against the covers, pale onthe pillow where six hours of sleepdamp down easily to a drawing of breath. You know it’s you I see at eveningwhen the light goes.It is less than a hundred hoursand the secret fits so closeI have almost grown to it,something I have touched a lotg)I know its shape by every lightits colours deepen as the day arches towards noon, dragging its heavy form by nighy it has become hot and damp in the palm, and now it is lessthan a hundred hours until you come. You know it is you I see at evening before the light goes.but ih tueKiakiVu}40-fV©M SOM? wcwm platgjHr flowefs h/v\'id[\j against the Cof>al&onthepillowS\t Mou/sof-s\e&pby /ugWr rt has W/omChot" and damp in\ the palM, and i/\ow it is less tlnan a t\ofidt?d incutsuotil yoo eowe.I\s i
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 4,The figures in the rainOver all the flowers I holdyou have sometime bent your head, inhaled my peony’s bluff soulmy violent rose.And every time your train goesmy life lies fallow about the tracks;like bramble whips, the small blind winds blow dark without you, I tryopening colours to wander throughbut you so briefly visit everything I own, sing to me of the meek figuresin the rain, then leave with the scentof my scarlet blooms still colouring you.Sing me the song againof the meek figuresfor there is often rain.Tell me the story of the figures of doubt then bend your head and depart,leaving me to wring from my heart how if I had come from the dark,if I had only looked upfrom the dark crook of my arm,life could have been so warm and I could have seen so much.Please leave ttAisfexactly asft appear f</\ Howe-MGMg MaV\t\$;ftpa/t -ffOM USiVU} [OvOS/CCUfi, at foe sta/t ofI p/efe/i1'lAZbfeatcS0/ld \jtio(oY£A -fo/AA Of the SKi^iiAal.O48o
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:52 pm Page 3,The hung manI have hung, spider-kickingbetween laughter and fine sorrowwhen this happens I drink coffee and I don’t know what to do.From the top o f the worldevery slope runs down.I’d hate to die right now —I have this scent between skin and bone, it smells of a nightmare townthat knows no primary colour.You have no idea what it’s liketo hang with hope and a fear of falling, it is strange and stronghow the thoughts runwhere limbs won’t go;I am taking the winter sunon the backs of my hands,pleased I am not of the dead ones,I am safer now than I have ever been but sometimes you just feelunclean./33
￼Berkeley 31-54 19/8/94 4:55 pm Page 5,The courage gathererWith the sun too closea loose wind catches me off guard, dreams flock to my skirtsand cling there like a litterI’d steal sleep to feed.Asked exactly how I feel I answer from the fields and summer laneswhere I have come gathering courage.A wing shadow strobes the lane; from time to time the future sinks with the black doubt of people leaving me - but hope comes out in her lovely shimmer,her hair behind, untied, freshon the morning, never fully woken, never still. I follow with my arms full of the songs she leaves,all of the same brave tune.ivA V&( lovely sIaimmV; be/ hair bewd,untied, •jYesi'i sv\ tu e Mo/mUq, rteve/fulfy woice/i, i s u n . 1 follow witU\ r^A\j afMSf/U lUf> so/i^s sue lea\j&Sjall isj- eU<? sa/v\e yasjo. tune . _5b-52&■