￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:06 pm Page 76*1^rfiA) 1 .. ,Graveside(for myfather)A graveyard crammed with Protestants & you all overlooking the knackered cement worksover at Magheramourne. I ride there, borrow Derm’s bike about twice a year & in some awkward phase Pm usually inI stand & talk to your headstone, not entirely convincedthat you can hear me or that you ever do follow me around;watch me in my city high-rise stoned, articulate then giggling when Jo comes over & the sunset looms at Spital Tongues,or the nights when I chat up pretty English studentsin The Strawberry or when I just float about Eldon Squaretrying to explain just why the city has taught me endless fear, & let’s say I’ve had the odd fling, the odd transgressionfrom the way you wanted me to be. I’m not half as gentleas you were, nor as caring, but you can appreciate the world’s changed!So I can’t keep harking back to that night in 1975 when I sat in with you Cos Peg had to go to Bingo.You asked for tea & toast coated in Lyons Golden Syrup & it was almost as if you knew the score & felt likea last small indulgence, a taste of what was perfect.They came & took you to the coronary unit but I wasn’t wakened& the cardiograph they did was clear but you had them outwitted. I was sent for in Geography & in the office Nurse Curry looked grave.I could replay the whole scene at random & have done& the last words I’d written in the classroom were ‘broken marriages’& Peg told me that my future plans should stay exacdy the same & I thought that was justice, I’ve never regretted it.76A
￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:06 pm Page 77I’ll never be completely English, I hope you must know that & I do strive to be as gentle & as considerate -at least when I blow it, get tainted by Black Bush & urges at least I agonise over it. So if you can hear meI’d like it if you were always nearby watching.I’ve never forgotten my brother’s face when Peg went to tell him.He drew up in his Post van & she reached out to hug him. & how I saw how his face twisted, from up in the top room.That’s imprinted oi^me wherever I go, this year Europe, next year The State, today the graveside at Islandmagee.1k 57*7CS .I’/m a few steps behind you, but I’m catching up...77
￼£ JCleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:07 pm Page 78SurrenderSinging ‘yigh yigh yippie the Pope’s a fuckin Hippie’ the loyal sons of Ulster used to gather in the shelteror hog the wall near the Chinkie knee-deep in Harp tins. They’d conspire as against my will I’d be drawn to them,to try & get to know what makes men in bomber jackets tick, how they see the whole shooting galllery, descendants of Planterswith names like Billy or Crawford, never Seamus or Sean. I reckon the occupied are paranoid but so are these boys,long after Stormont & the B-Specials they all still see it I suppose as one long slow betrayal to London & Rome.The ‘Free State’ is far from free but they’re indifferent.It’s a dream they never wake from, a worse threat than Russians& remember that boycott agaisjntouying Guinness & Fig Rolls because they came from Dublin? It seems every 10 minutesanother reverend appears & pounds away at platforms & there’s never any faulting rhetoric if you’re Orange.Sure, what about the Clyde Valley, Carson’s old gunship? - they hauled it in glory to Carrick Harbour, then it rotted& it’s all a bit primeviJ, I reckon, the uniforms & flutes, fasgow Rangers & hangovers, Red Hands & Ulster friesbefore the long march led by men with drums & fat bellies off to ‘the field’ & whatever te fuck happens there?How should I know? It’s not a football match where neutrals go, & come to think of it I wasn’t much interested in ‘Our Holy Father’when he kissed the ground at Knock. I could live without uproar & though Westminster doesn’t give a tuppenny fuck78e-
￼Cleary 53-80 13/7/93 7:07 pm Page 79they continue, it’s their culture, well fair enough!But I can remember a flute band stopping outside our gate,they taunted Catholics by calling with their collection boxes & my mother said ‘don’t answer’ & I said I wouldn’t darebut I felt powerless & angry & bitter & frightened. Just say one of those jokers saw me with their mates in some bar?They might call me a Fenian Bastard, week me down by the hair, boots gettin stuck in, it happens on both sides I know,so when I get there, I’ll stay, any place but here...0f79