￼O'Siadhail 9-46 5/7/95 4:24 pm Page & AbelI seem to follow the lure and flow of a story. Then glimpses of a garden or a school dormitory Shift and interchange. The frames begin to slip Quicker than I understand. I’m losing my grip. Why this crowd? And why are they hunting me? Faster and faster. Suddenly I’m on a promontory, The frenzy of chase closing its faceless threat. Over the edge. I’ve woken in a snow of sweat.Frenchie, let’s get Frenchie. Again a tableauO f schoolboy persecution sways in some undertow O f memory. I hear the swishing wavelike noiseOf a mob in hot pursuit. Our ritual sacrifice.A sallow and dapper stranger weaves and dodges Down a corridor with a swarm of blurred visages Close on his heels, whipping boy and scapegoat, A swoon of oneness singling his difference out.This evening in a country that I’d first comeTo half a life ago, some blond youths loomUp the platform, beer-cans glinting in the dark.My suspicious swarthness. A Greek or even a Turk? ‘Is it here we trounce foreigners?’ sneers a voice, Partly his show for the gang, partly his menace.An ugly moment. I hurry on trying to pretendI didn’t understand, scanning exits for my friend.a -H4—Unbroken line of pogroms, this blindman’s Muff.A planet now at stake, perhaps we know enoughTo reveal even the slants and bias of our lens?A stark figure transverses our shed millennia,That first victim forever crying his innocence.Stay the knife. Children of a jealous violence, Fugitives on the earth, may we still ask his pardon? Say to me, brother Abel, that I’m your guardian.46
￼0'Siadhail 47-5/7/95 4:27 pm Pag&BOUNDARIESSpringbrunn ar du, vars solig it glittrande strale skon i sin jamvikt, skon i sin formstranga bage, skon i sin styrka, agermakten att alska granser och adla matt.A fountain you are, whose sunnily glittering beam, beautiful in its equilibrium, beautiful in itsform-strict arc, beautiful in its strength, possessesthe power to love limits and noble dimensions.KARIN BOYE/ Translated by David MeDuff
￼O'Siadhail 47-80 5/7/95 4:27 pm Page'-48HopscotchOur chalkedfigure of boxes squared offand interlocked. Overlappings ofsides, t-shapes, half-shareddivides. A groundwork for high jinks.'Your go!’And everyone hunkers to watch if I toe the line. Footfall vigil.Is this why the Germans call hopscotch‘playing a game of heaven and hell’?Such passion for limits and thresholds. Johnston's shop in Pettigo, its entrancesin both counties. A foot in two worlds. Abutment and frontier. Old ambivalences.Or the way sometimes exact same sounds seemed to slide and play with words;a child is riddling out how ‘bounds' means 'confines’and ‘bouncesforwards’.Then, the pivot homewards. Our swift about-face. Thrill and crisis of turning; one ankle clasped, one hand aloft,frail balance ofgravity and yearning.A skittish jump. Again our spreadeagle heavy-footed landings astride a border. Stop-go momentum of hop and straddle.That need of lines. That leap's desire.48
￼O'Siadhail 47-80 5/7/95 4:27 pm Pag?--^9NoonI’ve fallen in love again with gazing.A lake is absorbing shimmered transfers of grey alders and ripplings of leaves.A hollow twig hesitates, then steers outward, canoeing this ice-age maw.M ountain eye. Basin of contemplation.A skimmed stone tumbles and disappears. Minutiae of an aeon. Noon is fillingthe air with its riddles. Who am I?Archaeologies of thought define me:the words I use, phrases, gestures.Is everything seen with an encoded eye?Piecemeal layers of address and response. Process of encounters: fall-out, settlings, accruals, a womb of residues and ores.Silent undertows. Still-living sediment.A mountain lake swallows and endures these slow, deep accumulations of sludge.In the dark and light of every about-facesome beckoning aim, a hovering remembrance. My spirit is watching over the waters./49
￼O'Siadhail 47-80 5/7/95 4:27 pm PagStoryA man turns hostage for his friend’s release: It is a far, far better pfofe that I go to... Abandon without return. Gratuity of sacrifice.Itisafar,farbetterthingthatI do...that cadenza of Dkjrfms’ Tale of Two Cities and a child bursts in tears. Must it be so?One story will haunt him all his living days. The wartime girl with her German soldier flees over the frontiers. Or tell him, now as he greys,of an African spirit between one world and another who stays around as a child just to make happythe bruised face of a woman who’d become his mother.M y name is made illustrious in the light o f his.To break and enter another’s brokenness and glory.This is the story I’ll touch in every caress.50
￼SunlightTwo children swimming out to the low tide rocks and a woman watching. Breaststrokes. Headlong aspirations of dips and bobs across the water.Her lovely givenness a vigilance of substitution, hostage to every breath and splash. Stange paradox: the further they swim away, the nearer they are.‘That’s my place in the sun’ is how the usurpation ^oFthe whole world begaiQAnd I fill with wonderwatching a woman watching. What is this reflex?An abandon and weightlessness of concern. Pure undergoing. Almost as if they float in the matrix of her being, drifting in passivities of creation.Some overflow of boundaries weaves its intriguesof motherhood. A debt being payed before the loan, as though she usurps herself in watching overthe whirl of their busy limbs oaring back water in sunlight, the whole gown of her life turned inside out. Her face glories in this reversal.Some obsessive patience hears an ungiven order. Does an echo somehow anticipate its sound? She’s so full of answers before they ever call.
￼- Q -Slowly I wipe her brow with a sponge. It’s as though \STwo women are merging into one. I swab her hairline, Breathing and undergoing all she’ll have to undergo.A sudden exhaustion seizes me. Now I watch for a sign. Maybe she’s begun to doze. I leave. Sneaking. Tiptoe.I wanted to be the Samaritan pouring my oils and wine. But was I some skulking Levite abandoning her pillow?I know to serve you better I need to hold the line, Yet where that line should go, how can I ever know?Here nursing your fever will I be forever nine?You gaze a gaze that seems to say: ‘To think it’s so,To think for someone else even this face of mineIs the face of a certain man going down to Jericho.’—O'Siadhail 47-80 5/7/95 4:27 pm PagMergingNursing your cold’s fever I’m forever nine Worrying there by my mother’s bedside years ago.A blind is drawn low to guard her eyes from sunshine,52&y.a/