￼Sun ValleyIt was the first time they had seen the light,and gazing, they were too dazed by the sun’s radiance to murmur when their legs were caughtfrom under them: with a clean snap of bonesas they were lifted out, reminding meof Yule feasts, or the faint click of a stone’s/Fall down a chasm. One, that had dropped free,was frightened by a ground so fathomless;its wings flapped and its legs flopped uselessly.More fathomless to my vision was the placewhere they were hung up on the hooks that bare them swiftly onwards, upside-down in space;the cause I know not, but all as they hung there let fall a rain of excrement, whence came the gross miasma everyone must bear.How weak are words, and how unfit to framemy concept - which lags after what was shown so far, it flatters it to call it lame!And it might be ten thousand fowl or one went smoothly past the imperceptible electric impulse where they had beguntheir afterlife, wings fluttering the while;and even after they had been thrust through the cutter, headless they were fluttering still.But swiftly after that their power to move compassion vanished - as when, journeying far down through Inferno, one’s own power to loveVanishes like the sun and the other stars.
￼MenottiMenotti is sad because the World Cup has begun, sad because already they have fallen behind. Crouched round a wireless in their naked huts, hearing the frenzy mixed with mountain static, peasants believe in him, their terriblefaith hunches his shoulders deeper than Atlas’. Christ of the Andes knows he has no powerto feed the hungry, or to make life bearable.A mountain as it moves behind the sunis not more motionless than Menotti.His face is the mountain looming out of mistalmost touching the wing; and is the night-windmixed with moaning in the fuselage;the steel that finds a home in a girl’s breast.Blood pinks the snow nearby, but otherwisethey’re cupped in snowy white on white. Those yet alive cut into their friend’s flesh with slivers of glassbecause of the body of Christ, who has ordainedsome to die that others stay alive.The wings! The wings! They’re so quick on the break. Torocsik must be taken out.A cigarette smokes Menotti to the root.He’s turning into ash.He’s been living for this hour.Here, in the mountains, stars are moved by love. On the roof of the Andes, you can see it occur. You can see God using up his own bodyto move the stars. Menotti does not movea crevice of his stone face, for every timeyou move you use up a part of your own body. Though somehow they’ve drawn level, he is still the death-mask. Buried in immeasurable snow, red nails peep out. They are cutting into heras they die, praying Our Lady for a miracle. And they crave stronger tastes, for man is bad. Send on Bertoni for one last assault.A centre dies to let a wing survive.
￼Thomas 107-154 10/11/92 3:24 pm PageQ £Resting, talking, in the hour before sunset, watching the peaks crimson, they are almost happy. You can almost touch God up here. Life is love. Menotti is sad because his team has drawn ahead. Above, two condors wheel.They are the first sign of spring.Descending on the last of their friends,and suddenly, round a gorge’s bend, more beautifulthan Mary, a patch of greenjKeep us on this height. Wanting to lose, moving the bright starsover the Andes, as men moved stones to Macchu Picchu. The ball’s passed back again,possession football. Menotti’s face is a tragicmask at the whistle, but moves like lightning,sending a smoke-cloud out, a sigh,embracing his weary and triumphant men.Cesar Menotti was manager o f the winning Argentine side in the 1978 World Cup. Other references are to a plane crash in the Andes in 1972, involving aUruguayan rugby team and supporters./141
￼Thomas 107-154 10/11/92 3:25 pm PageElegy for John Walter(Family-tomb, St Catherine’s Church, near Wokingham)JOHN WALTER 1776-1847ELIZABETH ANNEwife o fJohn Walter1793-1815 (Dec. 29)MARYwife ofJohn Walter1793-1875JOHN WALTER 1818-#94ft*CATHERINE MARYelder daughter of John & Mary Walter1%1- 1>142Why, Jack! How goes it, my old chum? This wedding’s got me down; I’m glad To steal into your shade awhileOut of the flashy kodachrome.Steve’s cheerful; and the girl’s not bad. Off to Ibiza - not your style.Oh, your young wife, Elizabeth!Shrouded in her wedding-sheet.Child on the way, was there? Poor lamb. The Magi brought her torments, death, The cold churchyard. Sun-flushed Birgit’s Been fitted with a diaphragm,Finding the pill had side-effects.O shit, you might have waited longer. And yet I’m sure you put it right: With Mary ageing, loathing sex, Elizabeth grew ever younger;I’ll bet you screwed her every night.You’re a tough nut, young John in green! Came kicking through the broken water! The burden Liza died to bear;Then, all the joy and half the painShe left to Mary, like a daughter.Old lad, you’re your own son and heir.Talking of daughters - Catherine Died just before your father, Jack. That did for him. She could not face The hoops of rectitude and sin (Sickening with a ramrod back),The hourglass narrowing of space.&
￼Thomas 107-154 10/11/92 3:25 pm Page19 /John & E.F. Walter1845-70Also your third bride, so to speak, Perished at her Whitsuntide,Leaving you, precious Jack, aged nine. Yet she might say, if she could speak, That she was happy to have died Before the ape-man’s age began.Some say you died a hero’s death,Saving your brother; others writeThat, stealing jewels from Sheba’s Breasts, You fell in love, she took your breath- The sombre bride, the Shulamite,And in your heart her arrow rests.Here, we’ve a dazed look, slightly grey, From listening to our Zulu spell- Cranmer’s ritual, that nourishedYour Flora through her long, rich day Until the twilight she timed well, When all the holy ikons perished.You scoffed the lot, Jack. What of that? But Hubert, lucky sod, tight-roped Between Hiroshima and Mons,Living discreedy off your fat.Had Freudian hang-ups, but he coped. What happened to your other sons?And what - especially - of John?What did the lad do with his life? Mortgaged the manor, took the loot?We only know the bird has flown;And Phyllis, your beloved wife, Distressed, sailed off in search, old fruit.We’ve swathed into your peace, like rally-drivers, Clutching our road-maps, burning up your rides; Fearful that we shouldfind LeviathanWe’ve goggled round the murky wreck, like divers. Sleep well, John Walter, with your ivory brides. We shall not look upon your like again.143EMILY FRANCESwife ofJohn Walter1824-54JOHN BALSTON13/wife o f John Waltereldest son o fFLORA 1836-1917HUBERTfourth son ofJohn (S> Flora Walter1870-1933PHYLLISbeloved wife of John Walter1876-1937
￼Thomas 107-154 10/11/92 3:25 pm PageFor Doll Pentreath(The last native speaker o f Cornish; d.1777)With the doll she had mothered, with mother and father,with boys and maids,beasts and birds, curses and songs,in her crazy old head,herbs and flowers conferred day and night-longaround her bed.All that she lovedin their own tongue came home and stayed,and quiedy moved around, as a crone muttered and prayedin her simple words, dying alone.Cornish obeyedher, slowly, like the herds she had driven home.But the sea bledback to the whispered moor-grass and moorstone of her stone head.Nothing was heard.It was home,where nothing is said.144r