￼1Glory be to God for dapjLino too:an ocean of strange scuffed lands; mountain-smudges on a white chart,shoals and coral-reef sands.I can see Victorian explorerstracing it with their hands:their amazed inner conjectureswhere nervous calligraphic coastlines show continents petering away.My*childhood rekindleson this public-building floor:cosy evenings in a bedroom den, encyclopaedia, star-map, bird guide,'The Picture Book of World Knowledge^ adventure stories about lagoons(adventure stories favoured lagoons). That far country is hidden nowbehind gradual high-rise blocks:exam on exam, narrowing degrees, concrete roads marked 'Career1and no road going back.Only sudden transits: for now this floor is gaseous infinity where stiletto heels have stamped slow suns in their thousands.I
￼WashingStrange that in our discreet suburb where houses are bastions of privacy gardens should burst into weekly bloom with rows of most intimate garments. Sexual histories strewn on the wind: not-quite-washed-out stains and blood, frilly incitements in scarlet and black, tiny triangles embroidered with hearts speak sensational night manoeuvres.But the lacrimae rerum of laundry!Here, the brave underpants of youth, tight yet elastic for times of expansion; there, hoisted in shapeless surrender, the vast flapping whites of old age.i/fc