￼Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:34 pm Page 457. When the door began to crack ’Tivas like a stick across my backIt seemed an important dream: wounded, he came to me for help and safety; I kept him in the innermost room and barred the series of doors that led to him, but laterI could not find the way back myself, the locks too many. I sit up in bed in the dark and think about it:door barrier or door opening, and how to keep the balance between its dual uses in a life growing too private, too enclosed - a nunnery walks about the littered streets in full daylighton a weekday, not once creaking wide its disguising grilleor guiding a route through complicated cloisters to my cell.<9 And the wounded hero? Ah, here’s where I’ve made the rod for my own back. Come clean. I love the falconerwho gave up even shipping’s sociability as a boy.He has the locks and shutters to match mine,the drawbridges, portcullises, iron bolts and chains,the dark barn with its moat of field surrounding.I sit up in bed in the night and consider strategy:when I break through the barriers that have held mejust obsessed, watching him from afar, I’ll have to tell him.When in the morning the letter comes through the door -‘You were Wendy’s friend. Please think back to what she was doing, to where she used to go, who and what she talked about’ -I lay it aside for the moment, completely immersedin my larger project, of laying siege to Joe’s defencesin some believably natural manner, not courting humiliationor telling lies. It’s easy to feel no more than fifteen or so,ritually inscribing ‘I love him’ in a diary last thing at night, writing ‘Jonas Hinds’ on the inside covers of all my school exercise books, or carving it on a branch - that stick again./45e
￼Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:34 pm Page 46L8. When my back began to smart ’Twas like a penknife in my heartHands and face hotter than the weather justifies,I walk over the endless openness of the fieldto Jonas’s barn in its disguise of ivy. I’ve found no pretext for my presence there, but have come anyway,the dream a goad behind me. Now or never, says my head, take up your bravery at once and use, or lose, it.It’s not, after all, as though he’s an absolute stranger;there are things we can talk about - old times, new countries. But the shock-headed youth who comes to the dooris someone I don’t know, and I am speechless.I am leaving a note - ‘I must speak to you about something.’ He is rolling^wadded newspaper laid under perchesto absorb the droppings, replacing it with fresh sheets. Friendly enough, he, one at a time, unhoods the hawks for me. I move in to stare into their unrelenting agate eyesout of another morality entirely. ‘Don’t touch them,’ he says - the tip of each beak is a needle, each separate talonhas a stranglehold upon its pole. A worm of fearof Jonas enters me. When we drink tea quite silentlytogether, the birds behind us shift and lightly murmur.There was that battleground that Joe walked intoin my vision. I think of it, of the otherness of his creatures, retracing my journey with my courage leashed -though not the loving. And find a pretext waiting.The letter says, in Letraset capitals and newspaper cut-outs, ‘If you’re looking for Wendy Christopher, ask Jonas Hinds.’ As much a weapon as a claw, a knife, a beak, a needle,it makes little slashes in herringbone pattern on my heart,so sharp it’s shock I feel, a stop of breath before the bleeding.46o/
￼. K.JHe talked about the pain it gave him to see her name written, having tried to omit-tfe* memory from his life but failed completely. He had grown used to her fleeting ghost in the barn - the flag of bright hair always caught for a moment in the sunlight before she went outof his door into the day. She was ever going away. At first he had pursued her presence, then he learnt she stayed seconds longer if he could just sit quietand receive the tawny gold and energy that was Wendy, passing through his life again and not gone, thank God.Though she had left him - ‘nothing more about me to find out’ he said. Two months before her disappearanceshe had said goodbye and really stood for the last timein his doorway, before following her curiosity elsewhere.‘But it didn’t stop me loving her. I’ll always do that.’ The bleeding starts from that arsenal of one weapon.I sit beside him and begin to leak my heart awayon his dry ground - though going inside the nunneryof my head to properly spurt and puddle and lie down, drawing the grille tight shut behind me with a final clang.^ v.)Austin 35-64 10/2/93 4:35 pm Page 479. When my heart began to bleed’Twas death and death and death indeedA falcon, its jesses trailing, swoops in circles over usbefore it settles on the barn’s ridgepole. The ivy’s thickness makes a shade wide enough to sit in. Jonas holds the paper with its anonymous lettering in both hands. Linesfrom the sides of his hawk nose draw his mouth downat the corners. He looks at the message again,then as before he looks through the message to the ground that’s arid and dusty under the ivy with only a woodlouse going about its grey business into the deeper shadow.her fG--e-/47