￼CASUALTYI got up on the wrong side. All day I wondered where I was in a house I part-owned; fell into a trap tryingto fit a small cupboard in­to a large one, succeeded, though it ate up all my time. However hard I tried tomake it pretty, it was stillone cupboard forced by a one- track mind into another.Morning slid into midday.I guessed by the way light dulledin cornerless shadows ascloud massed stewing up something. If there was a sun to tellthe time by I wouldn’t knowhow. Was it there at the start?Had she returned in one piece, though confined to our hard bed, I’d have found a way round things; left those two cupboards alone.The ambulance will bring her back to me and our settee sure to resume its function, no longer resembling acoffin she’d straighten moments before her collapse in frontof me when the look on herface, directed at those two cupboards, cut right through me and beyond. I took it to meanI should do something about them to cement her return, when you came in, remember?
￼EVERYTHINGThey know where our pipes run below the city;narrow bores abandoned to silt;plans to huge, polished, sunnedcockroaches, pretty permanent and in love with silk.We’re back to level steps- the spill of bucketsmapping our journeys from standpipes; to coffins dumped on tips.We hear how dawn breaks; how cathedrals shrink with frostbite:under an even frostnot just thrown but spreadworldwide as if with a trowel. Taxis with headlights offknock people down dead stopping to clear their paths, towelblood from a cracked windscreen, straighten a bumper,or castigate a live victim. They pull away with screamsand leave burnt rubber, hitting the road hard for custom.
￼SEA CHANTEYThis ship on this sea like my sweetheart and me: Left and right, up and down, round and round. Be still, I told her, when lying on mined ground; More still or you’ll trigger the detonator; Absolutely still before I fall off the world;Please steady your breathing or I am history.All the while I’m begging, she’s answering,Man, something sweet, some thing bigger than us Combined, pulls and pushes me so I can’t hold on; I’m harnessed to two stallions poweringLeft and right, up and down, round and round. This ship on this sea like my sweetheart and me.So she moved. So slow, moving without moving, You couldn’t see her hips’ sway; a slowness Gathering itself; picking up, picking up quick. Then she bucked and I bucked and we exploded: This ship on this sea like my sweetheart and me, Left and right, up and down, round and round.
￼ARRIVAL-1-I left my villageand my village girl, for a town my age which is no age at all.I am stirring pepperin a Pepperpot:her promises for Casrep; her promises for stock.-2-You see me gripping my felt hat, The cold squeezed me so,My head no longer filled it.Customs rattled me to my bones, My teeth opened fire with blanks From my sea-soured breath.Just when I thought saltHad seized me up I started belching.I belched at everyone who came up to me.I belched through my apologies,And apologised through my belches,Thinking, this must be Belchertown, not England./
￼A RIVALFour men in darkness Check if I conceal a tail- I am swinging low.
￼A Dream of FatherhoodMy sons float into and out of an airless room I keep books in or I’m kept in by books. They’re covered in powder or flour or chalk,I can’t tell since all textures are the sameand everything smells of nothing or I can’t smell. Cameron and Elliott, I say in my stern voice,Don’t be in and out; either you stay and sit with me or play in another part of the house. They appear to listen but drift in and out again.
￼CAMERONYour arms and legs squeeze mewhen I pick you up, resting your head on my left shoulder, then on my right. You eye me over with searching nods, as if to confirm it’s really me,while you change your head-rest.When I put you down at last,all the places where you wereache with removal, like the limbpatently not there, that an amputee feels when a cold spell’s about to come on and then miraculously does come on.
￼ELLIOTTBones as small and thin as yours need a protective case round them.You run the length of a corridor on a matchstick frame to greet us.You fall forward with pidgeon steps, I scoop you up in time, my griploose as if I’d cupped a wasp and firm against any notionthat you’d be dropped by me: my son while hospital machinerycircled a lump in your bladder you cried at us and peed on us.