￼I^l AtJVC c * yr\v€r^— —-j*Pfc
￼performance of today’s dandies, the Martians, and he would be disappointed at the re-emergence of Oxbridge fashion as the dominating tone of English poetry. A programme on Radio Three which I compiled of his verse in 1983 merely earned censure from the network’s cultural officers. But I trust that such neglect is a thing of the past.I have already outlined the principles on which this collection has been made. All that remains to be done in this introduction is to offer some notes on the poems printed - an editor’s justification. Everything up to ‘Pets’ (page 129) comes from Bell’s own Collected. I do not feel that any notes are needed. Bell offered none when he first gathered these poems together. The music which Anthony Burgess wrote for ‘Senilio’s Broadcast Script’ has been retained. It presents a challenge to any amateur pianist, with its florid Lisztian bravura. All poems after ‘Pets’ come from the mass of material in Bell’s possession at his death. He had some major enterprises on hand, as well as others which he had abandoned in various states of completioru-—1. FrornfJHe City ofDreadful SomethingThis was to"be a sort of mini-W aste^and, castigating Leeds and all its works. At various stages, poems were added and deleted. There are other poems, which he did not include in this sequence, which also apostrophise Leeds. I have included them here, after the specific sequence under the above title. The text I have chose^ for the sequence appears to be the closest to a definitive one among the many recensions he preserved. The title is parodied from James Thomson’s City ofDreadful Night.2. Letters from CyprusI have given this sequence its title, since Bell’s definitive text, clearly gathered from among the many pieces he had intended for the book of that name art*-, in his final fair copy, unheaded. The sequence is his own, though he obviously intended the book to contain much in the way ofprose letters, as Auden’s and MacNeice’s did, into which these poems would have been leafed. Clearly, he regarded the project as a sort of gallimaufry where many different sorts of poem could be accommodated, even if they had little bearing on Cyprus itself. Thus the sequence includes poems about cats, London life, French poets, Leeds, his old friends, Stass Paraskos’s pictures etc. At the end, I have added five further poems which may not be specifically for this undertaking but are connected by subject matter.JL-72T
￼3. Operatics and IntrusionsI have described this previously, and have taken only two short poems from the text in my possession, the others being works included in Collected Poems and here used in a different context.4. Translations from FrenchThough I have excluded everything in this great mass of material, I shall list what is included under this heading to demonstrate Bell’s application to projects which fired his imagination:MAX JACOB: Le Comet a des, 226 pages o f prose poems.ANDRf. BRETON and PHILIPPE SOUPAULT: Les Champs magnetiques,117 pages.ROBERT DESNOS: A la mysterieuse, 24 pages; Les Tenebres, 46 pages. BENJAMIN P&RET: Le Grandfeu, A selection.PIERRE REVERDY: Poemes en prose,11 pages; Ltoiles peintes, 20 pages;La balle au bond, 40 pages.Selections from ARTAUD, BECKER, f.I.UARD, HUBERT, MESENS andQUENEAU, 70 pages.There are also versions of Rimbaud, which Bell seems to have thought of as lying outside this specifically twentieth century file.5. DiariesThese are in prose. One is a dream-diary he kept in the last years, in which he interprets his dreams according to Jungian lights. An extensive autobiographical diary also exists. Many letters from him to Peter Redgrove and Christine McCausland have also been pre­ served.In deciding which order to put the post-1967 poetry, I have been, of necessity, somewhat arbitrary. First come his resumptions of the mask character of Don Senilio. Then Leeds is celebrated and execrated, and poems dedicated to Leeds friends are added. Some of the larger shapes among his later works are the next in line, including his addresses to Patricia Highsmith and Bing Crosby. After this, I have placed Letters from Cyprus and further poems inspired by the island and the Mediterranean. Now come poems addressed to father-figures and the Frenchmen he translated, together with ruminations on translation. Then some engaging squibs for friends and colleagues in Leeds and elsewhere.W here Bell did not provide a title, I have, in general, not invented one, so that several poems are listed in the Contents merely by their opening line or lines. This section of the book contains much of the light verse and lampooning which he wrote, including some more savage satires on literary people. Some are fragments. The tone
￼darkens towards the end of the book. Social poems, not satires but denunciations of a crass and materialist society, follow, interspersed with mysterious, almost cryptic laments. Bell’s increasing sense of his own mortality emerges in this part.As far as I have been able to date them, I have kept his final poems to the end. His parents come back in these short verses, as they do in his accounts of his dreams. His love for the lady who was his Muse is faced up to once more. Poem after poem is ‘For C’ or C’s name is worked into its pattern. Their being what he calls defiantly ‘love poems’ does not prevent his weaving much self- reproach and well-observed pain into them. A lm ost^ the end, dated the year before he died, is his ‘A Vocation Possibly’which he sent to Anthony Burgess. It is a quiet poem, but a desolate one.The great majority of Martin Bell’s manuscripts, in long-hand or typed, insist on capitals at the beginning of lines, and I have kept to this preference strictly. His punctuation is a much more open-ended matter. He tended to punctuate in a lordly way, as Byron did. Perhaps both poets expected their editors to put the punctuation in for them. I have done so very gently indeed, so that there are many poems in which punctuation is sparse or non-existent. Meaning, however, is seldom in jeopardy. Lastly, there may be further poems I have not seen. This book reproduces all the original poetry that Martin Bell and his circle kept intact, except for some clearly incomplete and uncompletable pieces.Amongst the prose Bell left is a brief manifesto which is worth reproducing since its various maxims help a reader not well acquainted with his verse and the thought behind it to understand his procedures, and the strange combination in his nature ofsardonic doubt and idealist enthusiasm. He entitled itAgainst the Gram: Con­ tradictory Theses.Poetry is too popular. What occurred in the Albert Hall was disaster. Poems should be detested, but irresistible.‘Doing one’s own thing’ is as obscene a pun as ‘doing one’s bit’. Crowds are for contracting out of.It is necessaiy to postulate the existence of absolute standards, and to endeavour to approximate to them. These standards are ratios.There must be formal etiquette to disinfect applause.We are not elitists, but nevertheless have chosen ourselves. Enemies: the Don, the Administrator, the Impresario, the Journalist,the Anarchist, and Old Charlie in the corner with the squeeze-box. Conspiracy is necessary to Democracy.Ancestor-worship is essential. Pope, Baudelaire, pray for us!atirise popular art: this function it performs
￼Some people have not yet heard that Dada is dead!The Unconscious should be treated with courtesy, not raped. Again and yet again: to purify the dialect of the tribe.We are on the Left, helas!These admonitions could be taken for reactionary only in a debased age, though they were written at the end of a simple-minded one. Their authorknew more aboutpoetry than anywriter Ihave known.I should like to thank especially the following people for helping t o b r i n g t h i s e d i t i o n o f M a r t i n B e l l ’s p o e m s t o a s u c c e s s f u l c o n c l u s i o n -John Milne, Philip Hobsbaum, Alan Brownjohn, George Szirtes, Peter Redgrove, Joan Russell, and, the most essential person of all, without whose devotion to M artin’s memory and his legacy ofpoetry, nothing could have been done - Christine McCausland.PETER PORTER