￼rroowry drrs.si thr lakerfforinr reeds t<-*+hc shallow.v.;Hui rioue, -rnrl-r.pi t.r:pirf,;»r out fr*or' ihp shoT .4Week "by work the hroar]'inter shrinks from the hanks .'nd the palnoto {set of coot fc^ave longer tracks.4Asecret fissure is IrakinrThe whole lake away,A t.reachcnv nohody knows ofRut the '1repeat of the slurrhsh tench.4Tf this roes on those slow Bronze fish w ill find themselves desperately flattering dowr'Into the last wet■ inches. •'Vdheir small rapes will round /s if howlinr out hurt.*nd accusation at the thinHidden wound killinr all of them."ft. will hr no use. Comothinr has, struckWay hcneath where any hoalinr Q?n possihly rca ch . rhei r triis tours will shrivel and then choke.u\%^ 2C1
￼PRECAutionSmile at everyone as ifMost of them are moderately Benign.,______i-.Move into crowdsOn quiet feet. Keep your eyesMobile, your ears alert.Know that there is always one Silent and behind you, whoStands where you are neverLooking, in some alcove of your life And, choosing a runnel in the ribs, Slides in the knife./'
￼NOCTURNEDismal as a toad's domed eye, a cloud Across the sundown's duck-egg blank Yellows at the edges; its massLeans on itself, clambers, swells Over itself, layering up and up. Sleep threatens like a suffocation.Think of freedoms; feel wind, Smell bracken, listen to leaves. Lie under rattling aspensOr a clumped oak. But there, Stuck close to the trunk,An undiagnosed lump, secretFrom the light, hugs itself ready, Ready to lift open the stareOf a killing eye, and clack Rehearsing billhook mandiblesFor the inevitable sweet sunfall.It will launch out moth-like, shrieking.^Jdfi^eSW idy* 31
￼''VMINOTAURV>^-------^It is there in the darka blacker piece of the blackI can see nothing no silhouetteof horns no nostril no roll of eye-whiteI can hear the shift of weight the heavy rhythms.of breathI fancy the dull beat of a pulse I can hear the malevolence•4 -in the net of passagesI have contrived for itsecure as a lattice of thick bars secure as a pitthe deeper shadow lurks and stirsyouth is crunched there it swallows maidens and I Paed^aiusof my craftsmanship have madeits home, deep, central, aseven its begetting I engineeredPmy skill it lives in, my life is equal to it, should it appearthe shape would be unrecognisableas monstrous being too familiar----------------(Oj .
￼/4SCENARIO tOE I DREAMYou are leading the raid.Among the neglected treesSurrounding the target houseYour colleagues are posted, with dogs. Car tracks scar the shallow mudOn the path to the path to the door Which opens without a key. YouClimb the stairs, quietly, seeing The door at the top that you know is The door.|------ - Movement behind itStops your climb. You listen,Thumb on the safety-catch. And shout.Come out with your hands in the air, Slowly, one at a time.Now. Now you will know, really. " Know. And you simultaneouslyKnow that the gun is defective, probably 'Jammed, perhaps, paralysingly,A piece of wood.The squad in the shrubs was neverThere. You shout for the dogsAnd there comes no galloping bark. There is only you.Always there has only been youThe one to come out of the doorThe one you have come here forThe one who will walk out aloneThe one who has turned you to stone
￼Is going to be, you know it, he too Ts going to beYou.4The door handle dips and the gapAppears, widens and widens. 4^si