￼Bensley Back & Front 9-64 20/4/90 4:30 pm Pag*& Faint HopesDriving him to the station for the last traiiy^ she resolved that next time she would bemore entertaining, sexier, choose a better wine.On the platform he didn’t even offer his usual playful insults - merely eyed the dull graffiti, stifling a yawn.The silence was awkward. Outsidea car set up a wail, clamouring for relief in a glissando of outrage and distress.41
￼What Went WrongHe did his best to love her, it is true,although his hopes were tenuous and slender. He summoned up politeness, kindness too.But lust? Bad luck. She wasn’t the right gender.House DetectiveMy heartbeat imitates a castanet.The sofa wears its dustsheet like a pall. The house is manifestly empty. Yetthe floorboards creak across the empty hall.The telephone is ringing by the bed.The door’s alarmed; the desk is quite distressed. The empty car is singing by the kerb.I think you’ve gone. I think it’s for the best.