￼r\\/<>JS°4+&*Q 5 D^<A fe K^Ass%f |"AOr^-s^ ^^\CoV\C/'SCREWED S0H1ETS, THE* MOUNTAIBSAndrew Greig*"TV\tM (YlOvjO'Ut VS* I OScS.cmnc^S ^~+ ^ Sc>
￼THEM MDUHTAIIS----------"^fckcEm ARRIVAL, LHOTSE SHARIITTERLUDE OR MUSTAGH TOWER SARDY, TOPPIRG OUT ERTERIRG ASKOLEAFTER EVERESTC n_>x /\\)^2ncVifc2lO
￼ARRIVAL, LHOTSE SHARWe're back again,with our tents, our trash and more. Be arrogant:we animate this wilderness.Mai flicked his lighter, an avalanche roared - we have come to assert everything fits;the entire mountainhangs mirrored in our shades.All day snow sank in the billy,was boiled, drunk, peed, replenished as we passed the mountain through us night unfoldedin the presence of witnesses; unblinking stars and lightning - the darkness is litfrom a depth we can rely on.
￼THREE ABOVE IAMCHE BAZAARSandy, feeling somewhat queasy, squatted above lamche,shat a foot-long worm. My life's like that, he said as welaughed and took our photographs, a thread of consistencythrough unpredictable shit- all things passas expeditions through the Bazaar,joking & jiving & ripping each other off. Got a bad feeling about this trip, boss.Some days you scoff and scoffbut just get thinner,Mai grinned. Had a friend,now dead, wha'd swallow a lil' tape-warm before he came out here - never got ill. Believe it,just to be here, we musta been promoted.We rounded the corner^ ______there — big Mothers: Ruptse, Lhatse, Everest. My heart batteredin my chestlike a man beatingon the wallsof the cage         surrounding himand I thought( huhClimbingthis bad bug kills off all the rest.
￼SAJTDY, TOPPIIG OUT (Mustagh Tower, 23,860 ft)So began to lead the last of the TowerQuite hard more bold than difficulttough ice loose snow but soon brainbegan to play the game My paints investigated stabbed good placements to be hadamong the choss Crucified by altitude Ibridgedasteepishrockwall Goodvalue that I remember everythinglike ice-slivers in my windsuit's creases Camp 4 a thousand feet beneath my heels climbinginto my shadow the sunflashed off my axeJon he was somewheregiving good rope and no advice the ideal secondbutme IwasgoneMice work when you can get itj_the hardest the best hours passedgvvi^ill I wanted a think and a restso thumped in an ice-screw and hung out awhile -Like I cannot spell, speak porter-talk but who does not who's lived like me with oil roughnecks and a French girl?diOne look in her eyes, I know. .^tone straight hit, I find good ice.Climbing's not so much, my life's more in the way I eat my food, the man I rise above, the roads I drive to friends,these suit -Re-engaged myself and winkled on |r>with patient pickers unlocked the cruxHWrc / iRlvChfcjAv3^..341 '— and the grass is yellow at the centre of the path.to£set my axes well and at full stretch pulled over the top and saw into Chinahe Ao \jMAv£>m<oTEL %|felt ok felt well(h cheval across the summit)K2 in the distance looking good (suspicion of moisture behind my shades)4'£tv\ Made a belay and took in the ropes as Jon came up. Hey wasted youth so how's it going?-‘From Base Camp to the stream there is a path now
￼EITEEIJTG ASKOLE(for Malcolm Duff)On the eighth evening we entered Askole. How can I tell you? We had seenno habitation in two months. Brown dogs twitched in the shade, a chicken screamed, we smelled dung, dall, smoke, lentils. Many voices, the bronze fields shone.Lean as schoolmasters, tall wheat rapped our knuckles as we limped into the square.Say there are miracles betweenwhere babies twitch and sleep and old folk sleep and totter. Water-mills spun,yaks plunked circles round the threshing floor. Evening prayers, a sleeping miller, tawny goats stole husks of wheat. Goitres hunglike apples on the children's necks.Hadji lightly touched our backs, Salaam ...We had been above ourselves, hooked to pure worlds of black & white & blue, the narrow world of sleeping bags.We sat till dawn, smoking, waitingon something; rose and crossed the river, found our porters, jeep did the rest.We broke down, sang 'It will come hardto sleep on beds as soft and wide as ours.'
￼AFTER EVERESTBetween one expedition and the next we buried the tiny Buddha's bones upright, with respect,at the bottom of the garden. Then we were drivenback to the mountain.Between the highway and the ditch the restless Westverges at its limit -no one said we are too oldto die young, too young to retire as we left Lhasa in dust.
￼CRUXDelicate, hell-cat, at the crux on Hoy, last ward in day-long conversewith rock above deep blue, climbing into pale blue, aiming for grace.A hard way to be normal. Mental technics took him far, 800 feet, soloingand high on that mug's game.low our chancer's fingers stutterbelow the bulge - he's run out of waysto speak to sandstone. Gripped? Mummified. The rock is smooth as political tongues.Hung from a hand-jam,rock crystals enquire of his skin*.How much you wanna live, \Some questions draw blood and prideequally, he answers, smears his right foot, gets his left edged high. Chalk-bag,pinch-grip ... He's kiltered out,all trussed up and nowhere to go.The world waits with casual interest. Gooseflesh. sonnythis draught blowing through from the next world - going there soon?Adhesion's mostly faith for intricate movers but he's shivering agnostic nowslipping the hand-jamstretchinghis right boot slipsright hand upfast as a prayer grabs his Grail o lovely jugcranks like a maniac over the bulge ... Thugged it to the top, sat and was blank, was gone, was everywhere in Orkney longlight.We met him in Stromness, it was etched in his eyes he'd dipped deep into more than his chalk-bag that day.White as cocaine his fingersdrummed the bar, awaiting tequila; -Been pushing the envelope, matey?His eyes were schist as he consideredour question, glinting and flakey his smile:Yeah, licked the stamp too. Revving kite on taut string, could plummet or soar - delicate hell-cat, you'll do.
￼AVALAICHEHe's at it again;first time in yearsa woman's hips hands eyes, wherever the categorical resides, have issued the imperativeScrew our lights out.Hot bulb! (Cooling in the dark.)He dreams of an avalanche casual as breathing ...Swathed in white sheetshe regards her where she lies face down.The terror liesin the tenderness derivedbetween the slope and shiftings of her ribs.
￼GULFABOUT TESSTESS, IB TUNISIA STILLMAGGIE SAYS'NOCH ANNIE, VISITINGANNIE, IN SPRINGK^x yx.x« *** xx^xvx,wwx, FISHINGD., IN A CHECKED SHIRT D.,RIDINGTREATY AVALANCHESCREWED SORBETS & OTHERS
￼GULFSothing is missing, said sheon White Wisp, the world turns and we turn with it, not losing touch.I'll always love you and butIn the Gulfa destroyer lowered its defensive screen for a chat - men were blown away.Sorry pal, we didn't mean ... The plane flew back to base in some confusion;soon she did too.Men yearn, metal gapes, verses implode memory and daily news. Between I & I the holy wars elide; between us flewlovely, misguided, direct, words like love, like Exacet.f
￼ABOUT TESSYou draw smoke down your throat;the rasp which says you're not dead yet is the trigger of seductions.'Do you ever', she asks, 'act on irresolution?'The bar is melting at the edges. You colonize each other asthe folkies sing of Nicaragua - in such moments you may find incandescence in amnesia.'Alright,' one hand on hers, the other round your car keys,'Why not?' There are reasons but they melt. You'll find them in the morning by the bedin pools of stiffened candlewax.Relax. Tonight you will not cross the border. You cast huge shadows as you get into the car./