￼And if he still felt a compelling needFor something on the sideThere were always first or second or third year students (Girls, of course. He wasn’t like that),Who needed extra encouragement.
￼Wordsworthian / Ovidian Episde to Patricia HighsmithMiss Highsmith, O Miss Highsmith, Dear Patricia - No blush would mantle our good Laureate’s cheek For this effrontery, but James’s would -Henry I mean, not the footman. That odious Strether Is utterly more wretched than poor Ripley!Poor Tom’s a-cold, we’d shelter him, Make him a retrospective Harvard man, W arranted Ivy League, the nicest type, With an instinctive nice discrimination. Psychopathic, yes, but not psychotic - Scapegoat for the massive psychic malaise Of all the (just how many?) vast United/ a /_.' £States of half^Americ’s north half.How good a President he would have made With all of Carter’s toothy dishiness,And Shadow/Nixon, shaved a' five o’clock -You know of course the work of Doctor Jung, And hypostasis of the Animus.(I’ve trouble with the Anima myself).Think of Tom Sawyer, somehow self-educated, And there you’d have him in a^Boeks- Bros, suit, But he’d know better than a Brooks Bros. suit.k(I only ran to Moss Bros, suits myself).If I parade some Limey prejudicesYour lady-writers give me ammunition, Mesdemoiselles McCarthy and McCullers, Dorothy Parker, and yourself not least.So right, his palazzo, Venetian,For me, at least. Not Corvo’s. Not Visconti’s. How witty is his choice of lumpish victims!(The passage in your work that most makes wince Is when they dub drab Mongibello, ‘Mongy’.I know that coast. Christ halted near there.)How justified the death ofJonathanIn being awarded an heroic end!I didn’t know that photographs could haunt On coloured book-jackets. Yours does.152iVooyles
￼Dark, handsome, noble, Sybilline, compulsive Your witch’s eyes demand obedience.I rest my case. Give me the daggers. With fondest
￼Lament for Bing CrosbyDead, Mister Crosby, deadThis unbelieving generationWould smother you in soft white christmasesMolasses of gossamer indulgenceYour greatness, sharp legato greatness0 Mister Crosby, Mister Crosby, Mister Crosby(I trust that I can make the matter clear)You were greater far before all thatThat going other people’s ways down various roadsWhen you would take it up and keep it going keep it going With Mercer, Mister Mercer... also deadNo ‘entertainer’, but an actor, a true histrionDid you not act with Fields and not upstaged?Fields, W.C., dead also, long ago in gloryDidn’t you ramble with Armstrong, also deadWe’ve got to accentuate the positiveEliminate the negative of smooth Sinatra1got a message from the Mocking-bird That Sinatra was dead on his feetSinatra made of plaster like our Joanie Biederbecke taughtyou, in mummer’s digs, Music, disced Debussy and Stravinsky, And it stuck. You got rhythm but also Style, like you said styleThere are a few enthusiasts leftWho can tell the differenceBetween the first and second versions of That Old Black Magic Old Black Magic Got me in its spell Gone FishingBob WhiteMister CWe’re gonna break it up tonight