￼Sestina: Maria MaddalenaIn his Memoirs, Casanova describes amorous encounters with two nuns, Maria Maddalena and Caterina, at the private casino of AbbS de Bemis. The scene is the Convent of Murano, Venice.iDo my eyes' gazing, Murano master, Jesus,And my meek up-offered breasts make you too lovesick, Dim, high on Cross? I'll swear your prick rose!I, Maria Maddalena, loveliest of petitioning sisters. 0 let night come, the pictures, the entwiningPoses, let my breasts swing from nun's blacks free!iiTime drags. This wearisome chanting!...My ecstatic sisters Assault you with aves. Giacomo never guessed, entwining His lips with ours. I'll tell him tonight, each roseIs a prick, is a round window, gives a free View of us; see how he takes it. Jesus, The very thought makes me stretch lovesick!iiiAll night, spying! My flesh sweats like a rose.Seraphic, Caterina kneels amidst the sisters,Her mouth stuffed full with that word Jesus.Dear, green child! Though, God b6 thanked, no more lovesick Of Giacomo: last night's trio made her mind free.Her limbs with girlish limbs with limbs entwining.ivShy to begin — albums, frescos worried her— lovesick Movice; till 'Which of our breasts please you?' I ask him,and free Mine; Caterina follows; soon, with blushes, entwiningHappily. All night till dawn we moaned 'Jesus!'
￼In turn, unselfish, weeping for joy, rose,Gave place to other, exhorted, were loving sisters!vCruel, your crucified eyes lust, for I am free,As though you crouched behind the pattern of the rose. Tomorrow, Giacomo must watch, must crouch lovesick, Unseen, beholding our rearranged, entwiningTrinity. And last, breathless brothers and sisters, Do you watch our quartet of joys, I pray you, Jesus!viCaterina smiles secretly... Would my lips were entwining Hers under your horned cuckoldry, Jesus!One day you will shut our soulful eyes, sisters.Dust will close up the vulva of each rose.Giacomo will forget me. Empty will be the lovesick Casino. Our skulls will lie alone and free.viiLet nights pass stormy as a crimson rose!Gad rot that we should rot here with these sisters! Send my beauty from God's Leads go free!
￼Christ on PalomarI have come out of the cave, gulped the thin air, entered the whitedomewhich is more silent, more laden with awe thanthe great templeof theprophets.My brain reels under spectrographs and maps of galacticclusters. I wasa simplecarpenter.Pulsars, quasars and neutron stars. All such is beyondme. Ithoughtonly oflove,creatingthem. Inolonger pretend to understand my progeny, why this particular, chancedesign.Plough, neversetting as the cells of generation, why did you sowso prodigally,
￼demoniacally?Andromeda's wheel, you are bland as a pharisee, luminous, doublemeaninged, as oneof myparables.I know that, if the faintest star fell or were added, the whole wouldcollapselike a card-house, but I no longer remember why. I bear aheavier crossnow,the culpability, the burden of itall. Iamblinded by theweight ofstars.They stream towards me across ' fields of space-time, poorbut confident: toomany prodigalsons.
￼PersephoneI have seen you wiping tables in the chilly silent cafeteria of the almost-desertedrailway terminus; and I have seen you in the dim city street waiting for stranded revellers;and I have seen you in a nurse's capwriting letters under a night-lightwaiting for disturbed men to cry out for tablets.And sometimes, when I have lain awake in the dead of night, it has been enough to imagine youin these places, knowing that a light still burns somewhere and that you are awake,however tired, however slowly you move, however alone; and that, through you, day runs into day without a break, the light uninterrupted.So I am glad you opened your legs to Hadesand agreed to go with him into his dark kingdom, solid and beautiful amidst the shadows,our representative presence, childishly fretful, demanding pomegranate seeds because you are pregnant, your thoughts rooted in the living,a white aspen among the black poplars./
￼HymenCatullus, 0 he licks honey,cool tar you ran, ay, a genius,why, rapid, tender and virile,you decay, then bone, ah, come bone,0 but alight we go.Singe the evening with roses, with suave olives and dancing, Suneum's cape, light us, seek seek her venial nipples, lurking,let no impediments, come,now is the vine at ready,now are the grapes for treading full as the flesh of Venuswhen to her judge's caressfrigid she flushed clove open,as a clam, as a flower opens,as split wood, mortal and tender. Cleave to the soft axe, cleave altogether, till the night ends.Harbour, us, implicit, errant.Take, timid, cup in hand, novice, this petal, dust, amen to that, star, floss, hyacinth in us,divide us, dominate, you're too low,prod her ass, nova, erupter.Courage against what ferries us over purging Lethe,aeons of our species bring you to bed, nymph, an irrigation,
￼nutrient, human.Vows in time similar, intactvirgins, you'll quiver but take,brought home from home, your mothers weeping and smiling. 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.And love enters the audience, the cither and the drum, conjugations of mortal,body venerates body,harbour, then, implicit, errant.This day that's magicest, amazing is ending, a man to be­come possessed of the magicof lightning? 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.Your sweet tremulous parents can't look at, to be virginalso long it's, but they resignyou timid, you're picked, a novicerapt in a glory of marriage.You're far off, already, in manners, flowers at your lips, I pull you them, dead is your dream, you a live matrix, 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.Ho protest, sign all to Venus, famished, good, bone, ah, come probe it, comeliest, capacious, breast,and violently, who is to know,
￼come per air or air or shit.Ho law courts will doom us lips, here, us, dare, no parents extirpate, tonight, nor protest, and violently, who is to know,come per air or air or shit.White you are, care for it, sacral, no disquiet dare presidein our territory, but quiet, splendour, potency, coma,an ardent ingenuous pudor.Not in tune no need we fear nature's tenderest, violet malice, the adulterer,nor persecuting incubuswill suckle you, bare, the paps.Lean till, why, feel it, adds to it, fitted implicit, a harbour, an implicit arbiter's your plum complexion, its scarlet dyes,prod her ass, novel, nuptial.0 you will whatever is human, uscandid our predilections.Two alight, our pure faces,flame me then, wider, between here, run a cool eye, very cool, breast, I you, 0 hymn of hymnals,
￼0 home in home are we.How from the trees cascadingthe nuts will lie where they've fallen, new juices, the purest, nougats desserts, at home in me, that audienceof concubines, scatter them.And whatever is our petition, bride, cave, never negate us, nor let us, in everything, eat. I you, 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.For you're his home-nest and potence, and his beata virgin,quiet in the eye of the storm,I you, 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.Loose, mist, set in, at bone, ay, conjugate, beneath, vivid it, blueberry, dates, manna,hungers grow hungers: dying,wider it won't be rending.Your honey's spread on us, very, excite us, we, hilarious, die, feminine, fuel all I am,I you, 0 hymn of hymnals,0 home in home are we.So, soon, 0 smiling partners, manly, 0 eat vaseline, she is, flame me then, wide, oven, here,I you, 0 hymn of hymnals,
￼0 home in home are we.Mixed, eyes, bracelets of tears,you sore, in that lamb, 0 your breast, all red, florid, the long night ends, ah but, such parting's nice, velvet,float, then, we, together, we're.Am I right, it's all me you want silences, where nothing ominouswill, cherish, neck where the vein is, knee, leg, we'll habituate,forget to remove your arm.Ho dying, commemorate usa son, vain is the bone to finish our young desire, when I have passed concupiscence, love and its offspringwill cap the bone with fire.Pull over us the chill sky, cither, drum and the dance subjugate, numerous prayersfor us to the numberless stars,melted and mingled together.Loaded and livid as berries,the old men collapse, can't take it, where they've drunken, dream liberal young men, easy, slid, undid them,simple in again her hairy.Talking of us, solo, my lonely mother and her grumbling sleepy husband tenders us a sonto ride their patrimony on, yet
￼semi-resentful her belly.Sit soon, smiling, in his father’s lap, his face will inscribeus in the after, humorousnose, where's that impudence from,his mother's, eyes', joy.Tall as, and strong as ebony, genius, his mother lauds, approves, sleeps, quite soon I'll abrupt her, may try, to let me go, again,into her, pineapple, tang.Frostier, before your sun, virgins: loose mist set in at bone, ay,can you guess, beneath, the writhing moon's your assiduous valentineexercising the young men.(after Catullus LXI)