￼orFive Parts in An AdventureAct I The Quest, The CompanyPrologue - Crossing Rannoch - Who reigns here? - Questions in the Clachaig Inn - A word of Explanation - A letter from theHospital - A Cure for Loneliness - Meet the Axe-Man - A Third and Final Introduction - A 'blue butterfly'Actll The Up & Down DiscoIn praise of Desire - Into the voodoo - A Reunion and a Fight- The Buddha receives a Proposition - Morning on a flying carpet - Cambridge to Dublin - Come TogetherAct111 In the High AtlasA Dedication - Four and a Mule in the Drylands - Tourists and Terrorists - Kenny Dalgleish - Meeting in the Mountains - Comparing notes on Black Houses - An honest trade, a pointy ball - Sweat and Succour - Clearing the well - One star awakeActIV Some Time in MarrakechTrade in the Djemma el Fna - Buddha hard pressed for an Answer - Axe-man's Band - Poet and the Monkey Man - Roast chestnuts - A last bus to the CoastAct V Bringing It All Back HomeReturn of the Native - A Self-appointed Coronation - End of the Company - Heading home - A meeting of two hats - Settling in - The Return of the Heretical Buddha - A wee push - The Court of Dusty Feet - The Good News?
￼Programme notesSome of these characters appeared in mvthic roles in a previous cult production Men On Ice (Canongate Publishing 1977), which was~mostly staged imaginatively in the Himalaya. Biographical notes from that performance are reproduced at the end of this Programme, and may helpfully be referred to now or during the two Intervals. (The insomniacs' bar remains open throughout.)Dramatis personaeThe part of Grimpeur is played by Ken, as in 'you ken' or the philosopher Anthony Kenny: a knowing man, the doubt-filledintellect. The head.Poet is now played by Stella, and much improved for it. The scene-setter, the heart.The role of Axe-Man is taken by Brock - a surly badger or Pictish stronghold. The body, and its music.The Zen Climber/ The Bear is now the Heretical Buddha, a.k.a. Bud, H.B. Who's he?Put it this way: if the three principal characters were threelegs of a stool, the Heretical Buddha would be the seat.Also featuring 'I':W» Narrator, speaker and listener, the Company as collective, the Holding Company for Heretical Buddha Productions, a.k.a. Ananda (see end notes), Drew-baby. I is the one who sits upon that stool.But already the lights are going down, the background fades. Please find a comfortable place, a stool for instance, a seat, or a bed.Darkness. The sound of the sea. As eyes adjust we become aware of a reading' lamp, a solitary reader, a bed, and a few cues. Such as:
￼THE HERETICAL BUDDHA orTHE DEBATABLE LANDSThree Parts in An AdventurePart I: The Up & Down Disco (the Company) Part II: Some Time in Morocco (the Sheath) Part III: The Debatable Lands (the Knife)Yes we'11 catch the wisdom trainbut why arrivetoo early at the station?- Bud
￼F>/=tCrL. C t& U £Part I: The Up & Down Disco (The Company)7Roll that log, old pro!a new voice whispers, soft and delible. Call him heretical, H.B.jHe speak in ital and he say— ?make your contribution then fade ...& SCfL.XT&ftY SF*£&/<SI am afraidThere is much to be afraid ofBad enough on good dayswhen jolly fishermen strip legs from living crabsand you wince how that mustWorse: waking alonein a large bed in a foreignwith a pain in your chest and the sea going on and on like the haivering old fool if you're spared(uni ikely)(*)ndent ?I am afraid of many things I could make a listbut it would go on a bitfeelcountryyou'll beThat list would exhaust an entire rainforestLet us consider now sleep's and you might as well admitmake tea and sit up in bed with this sapling's worth onand roll a cigarette because you refuse to be intimidated and it's some sort of friend touching your lips now -*O a pal at the cricket club in the shower after the gameout the question ityour kneethough you're afraid
￼found a small lump on his shinBone cancertook off the legwaitedHe came to watch us play-leant on a crutch on the boundaryTook off the otherThen from a wheelchair with his wifewatched the last match of the seasonsaid we'd have won but for a terrible decisionbut then again the umpire's always right even when he's a wall-eyed gitwith a blunt scythe and an altitude problemAfter the funeralwe had a whip-round for family and kids What can you dc0but stare out the window of the 4.32 like the man who told me thisas we glimpsed the cricketersresolvingtheir lunar-solargame *Well might you forgetthe meaning of fearand speed straight to terror quaking in your bootsespecially when you have no boots but are standing in the shower with the soap slowing overa small lump in your legand your world is a rocking chair gone off its rock*If the human heartwere a high and mighty bluffset above a smashing seawith a nearby rail link into the cityand excellent local facilitiessuch as opportunities for education and shopping
￼and a really nice cricket ground next to the churchyardwouldn't you call its potential for development - unlimited?And haven't we seen it wasted on yet another grotty scheme?Utterly unmortgageable at four in the morning you lean on the windowsillpain in the chest but stillcalling the bluffand hear at last the sea make sense the sense you began to makewhen you owned up and said 'I am afraid'.This is as good a place to start as any.
￼LIGHTS LJF> DIMScotland. January. Snow. A mean old day gloomily shutting up shop. We seea rusting questing 2CV shoogle over Cairn '0 Mountwith two last-minute customers ...'This salted road's a thin black tawse whacked down on Rannoch Moor.'Crack! The wiper blade breaks off. That'll learn ya, son,the Buddha spat then with a sigh leant out and clearedthe windscreen with his brolly,anthropocentrism makes you blind, a kindof beating your own trumpet.He huddled deeper in his cloak and warmed as was his wayto his subject(which was as wellfor with the window open to permit the passage of his brollyit was bloody freezing as I steered into another changeof tense and personnelthat lies across our way like ice)Night as well call the punitive tawse ^ O’h-y'in -ham nff -t-Tna 483, yOUr palmI hold out my hand and wait.At length the Buddha shakes his head, gently placesmy fingers back upon the wheel:I read: a violent culture, great wilderness in the heart.Above the whirring shoe-boxa hoodie craw veered North.I scanned for something dead or dying,thought of my friend Donald,HIV positive, two tendons cutby a Stanley knife when he came inon my account when I was jumped
￼by Casuals In Queensferrybetween chip-shop and Chinese takeaway'Sure thing,’ I said, 'but mine own.'The white palm dipped beneath the blow and we declined towards Glencoe,hands tight and careful on the wheel.It's narration of a sortwhen someone salts the road for usa long black line across the white-out below the Buchaille Etive Morand lets us wind down like a clockto stopoutside the Clachaig Inn. 'Let's enter. I have friends here.'
￼ItItWho reigns here?is not Concrete (that way lies fascism and no fun)is not Scale (easyto be depressedby the size of your wee selfstanding shivering at the creasebelow the advancing moonamid an ever-expanding slip field of stars, waiting for History's next blink-and-you've-missed-it de1ivery.Na, don't be too impressed by Scale!)Nor Force of Arms (here,if a desperate characterpops in with a gunwhat shoots out is lettered:BANG!)And you'll be noticing the tendencyto change name, sex and destinynot to mention subject, season and location, and if this History runs on iron railsit is only those of sound and rhythm while the sweaty driver whistles©samples' from all erasas he whacks new vocalsdown on those gleaming tracks -Who reigns here? I say the door of the Clachaig opens on a street in Katmundu; sayand we are walking with the Heretical Buddhaat dusk, past Hindu shrines;you'll note the fruit bats like inverted priests hung in dusty eucalyptus trees,incense, spice and sweet-sour piss churned by passing bicycles;the wind stirs in merely mentioned trees and we -Slam that door shut! Later ...You take the point.This is not the concrete world and everything herebends (when you incline your ear)faster than plastic when you credit it.
￼Got all that? Good. Knew you would.(End Short Asi de>Now back at the Clachaig,the customers wait upon their Quest for better beer and synthesis, and we can dispense with leaden formalities such as Othe real world'.Let's simply sayINSIDE THE CLACHAIG
￼'"thi 1,1So,incommunicado?'’Nah, she left the theatre years ag6.'no visitors?1and we are.'Hey, Drew! Whit ye wantin here besides the company of friends and the hope of good ice action tomorrow on the Ben?''That part of meI left back in the French Quarter.Also: a Poet with a white guitar, who knows perhaps the whereabouts of a Dual Blade - our Quest.''Oh, that.She went doo-lally,not so much a breakdown as a halt for reconditioning, committed hersel to the Royal Ed Infirmary.But at that time she'd often mutter how a knife had got her number' - Think that's a quote -''It isno state secret. Well you knowhow lyric poets exaggerate,when they discover themselvesone sip short of the loving spoonful.''Yup, I mindthings got kinda tense at meal-times. Is she'Not yet. I suggestyou pass a week in bleak Glencoe where days are short & time is sweet. Above 2,000 feetthe ice is in good nick and yer baldy-heided friend seemshe'd front-point with the best.His saffron parka's cool. Sherpa, is he?''Not exactly. But - her?''I suggest: write her a letter.' CviT ?
￼The Buddha made himself at home, had the table soon in roaring mood.Meanwhile this empty I,mere gutted vertical with flat cap and feet, scribbled a few lines, and wehung out awhile, just marking placelike markers in a book, waiting to openon her reply.
￼car J( acvclOA®SOME WORDS OF EXPLANATIONSo what's I doingin Glencoe with a Buddhawho seems heretical? What's the Quest, pal?Let's ba ckt ra ckLet's say you once woke alone, bereft, scunnered as a sheath whose blade is gone.And those constituent parts, body, head and heart,have split up, scattered, gone to seedNaturally, you are afraid.But there's a sea inside your ear and waves break upon that shore and you heara secret sharer.Call it heaven-sent, call it Buddha,call it your soleguide in the Debatable Lands. And it saysyou are forfochen and forsaken you are emptyyou must find the Dual Blade you must round up the Company.Now that's kinda crypticand you well might spierwhere to start on this Adventure and what's this Jewel Bladewhen it's at home?When you're at home the voice insists.Some help, but all you're going to get So you sigh and rise and pack a bag with toothbrush, slippers, penknife, condom, passport, change of clothes and sling it in the deux chevauxand GO."W-VeO \Where?
￼Start with the heart,last heard of climbing in Glencoe.So here we are, still waiting^ * /-rtf*? -•
￼/7//r t — /] Shflt )/J< ^S^/f/to/J 1^4fh t/#*/< L*L</L, *jf L+sLw* Hi/ tiki SI//J /}/iA/ /j # iji*1 J* KfUi^A SHORT ASIDESo what's I doingin Glencoe with a Buddhawho seems heretical? What's the Quest, pal?Let1s ba ckt ra ckLet's say you once woke alone, bereft, scunnered as a sheath whose blade is gone.And those constituent parts, body, head and heart,have split up, scattered, gone to seed.Naturally, you are afraid.But there's a sea inside your earand waves break upon that shore and you heara secret sharer.Call it heaven-sent, call it Buddha,call it your soleguide in the Debatable Lands. And it saysyou are forfochen and forsaken you are emptyyou must find the Dual Blade you must round up the Company.Now that's kinda crypticand you well might spierwhere to start on this Adventureand what's this Jewel Bladewhen it's at home?When you're at home the voice insists.Some help, but all you're going to get. So you sigh and rise and pack a bag with toothbrush, slippers, penknife, condom, passport, change of clothesand sling it in the deux chevaux and GO.
￼Brock on the mattressin the smouldering dumpunder a grey and relentlessly predestinated sky1aughsand lightsthe first of the day.'Ach, Daith - ower blate tae dance wi me?'Man of Earth,son of the Earth-shaker,bleeding bull and rolling thunder, all too mortal rock 'n’roller,rocking round Earth's diurnal course, rolling the stones and trees,needle-tormented Orpheus torn in clan leather -'FAUGGHHH!Je me lance vers la gloire, pal! ' He rolls to his feet and Up and Out.' ...and the mighty earth thundered with a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand voices, declaring 'I bear you witness! '. And the demon fled. '(Bud say:There are other ways than purity. Our power's in the flowbetween the light side and the dark.Excise it with prayer and discipline? You might as well fillet the fish then ask it to swim ...)
￼STELLA ESCAPING WITH BUDDHA *■ I -As I left the hospital with youearly under dripping trees,optics, sonics, motion in full flow -I didn't knowthere'd be so many bits of me to find.I must make a waythrough a world that may never conspire again, nor sing?its praises.
￼CUT TOBrock's pushing his luckas you or I might push a punto the limit. Ach,that's what it's for,says he, stroking the gleaming dropped cadence of the handlebars.A chancy man! Loosen the clench and the fist vanishes: that's him. He's shorn his locks wi flint, close to the skull and dangerous.I knew him onceyears back when he was mega but this world's no longer fit for guitar heroesany more than dinosaurs(whom they curiously res^embledin brain power and leathery skin as they thundered 'cross the stage through steam and primal grandeur)and I grieve to see one arm awry, one leg shorter than the other and I guess he's trying to adapt or find some spot to die.He shivers, coughs. Either way:Mad Max he ain't.But he's on the move,his emblematic transportBritish made, a burnt-out Norton.He pushed it till he'd made his point, now ditches it, limps on alonewith his sole instrumentthe fret less bass Raw Power -I hear him whistle as he leans into the wind, forcing the way open like a stubborn door.His destination?Oh, very well -Nepal. Through the monsoonhe runs a voodoo ravein down-town Katmundu: hard-core groove.
￼Crag-rats & Goths hang out therewith Sherpas, cops and double-dealers -if you want to blend,the colour's black and silver.And the address?You can find him directly on page 33.Maybeyou'll miss somethingin the interveningYour choiceIs that not cheating?voice.I hae ma doots.
￼A THIRD AND FINAL I NTRODUCT I OIMWhether you woke to find yourself an empty sheathor merely an insomniacin dire need of information -now you're being filled inand one or two thingsare pressing whereyou might suppose your heart to beNow meet another of the company We call him Grimpeuror sometimes Kenbecause he knows so muchor used to till he deconstructed and now he finds it hard to say just what it is he's sayingas he assembles in his roomand wonders why he had his breakfast among a crowd of Cambridge swansor maybe dons oh what's the they all take off so slowOut on the grapevine curling round his mullioneddark grapes murmurit's time to drink the winedifferwindowsRumours of a final expeditionwith his old travelling companions ... but he has no faith in their existence'It's fin de siecle - no Quests left’He paces in his room untilhe's ready to transmitand as he clasps androgynous fingers breathes deep and starts his lastdesperate solipsistic ariathe orchestra's re-tunedand you've had time to shift and cough and the fax is primed with his librettolet's see what's coming through -
￼note-fr> r>>j»>,// hAt$'I am the passionate clinician, drawnto snakes and sources, the tiniestblue butterfly of a stranger's thought. That is. I've not concluded yetmy notes on the ecology of Mind -sorry, but singing down below. Can't come.My passion's my career these days. Philosophy, it's rough. Pay's terrible. Fame's itchy as these bites.The dark interior when we close our eyes! Excuse this scrawl - it comes tonight.No rendezvous but drums insidesay we'll rush from first touchto highest ground. For Iam waiting by the watering holewhere all the passions go to die.'-Well I think we can safely put this one on hold,(said Stella as she put up her hairand accentuated the Gothicnegative around her eyesin preparation for our journey East) though I did like that 'blue butterfly'. It's all a bit beyond our Ken.Leave on the fax machine,the Buddha murmured.We'll catch him later.To find the second of the Companylet's save on time and money and just turn softlythe next pageand beTHE l_JF> & DOWN DISCO, KATMUNDUKENNY'S FAX