￼^* 1 1 * 1 ^*o *A sculptor works less openly,releasing stone in secret,scraping through caves to find a captive, hands like drills. The binds of stone-&Hpr\shrivel to his touch: a plying flame as fumbles out of smoke. He makeshis fist a phoenix; hands he turns are wings that clench a fire,ON FIREWhen, on withering into life, smoke chances on opacity, there& IOy^seems a kind of rockcut from the sharpest energiesA.*in fire: a compliancy, a pliant stoneof smoke, a .broken formturned blunt-end to the ground... Stoking-up, you flesh that sparseA l^p^Scontracted source. The flame-points swellwith wings and cobbled smoke. 10|)^Masking a fist, you weave-in half-burnt wood - tuff of lichens to fissure in fire -Aand stand away, watching howthe falling-up of heat A/ quarries air of flakes and finity.) Dr-A b°lont.
￼DAVID MORLEYra beak that bitesis chisel in this stone...The warm wings lifta trembling limb from rock;a dfist, like smoke, veers into air.
￼Errand2^FI came to a place where buildings were going up; biscuits of slate sat wrapped in twine.Earth moved like sugar, boilingagainst the metal of a dumper.A*machine dropped, dropped its yellow snout, nuzzling at joistsit hammered-in.When I got to my father I would learnthe heat of that impact, how you might light paper from it two hours on...The air meanwhile would shiver with fire, a fineless dust, the shouts of impact.He was with the welders -short-term hire - cutting thin plate to microns. Not visored, he-Stood out from that covenof kneeled and sparking menlike something they were makingor melting to start over.We went out to sandpiles, pounded stone, his eyes spindling, his mouthasking and asking why I was there.../cont