￼i & T ^ r 'ON FIRE .2- ~2-When, on withering into life, smoke chances on opacity, therezkseems a kind of rockcut from the sharpest energiesin fire: a compliancy, a pliant stone of smoke, a broken formturned blunt-end to the ground... Stoking-up, you flesh that sparse-4-contracted source. The flame-points swell with wings and cobbled smoke.4-Masking a fist, you weave-in half-burnt wood tuff of lichens to fissure in fire -4and stand away, watching how vtlje falling-up of heatquarries air of flakes and finity.A sculptor works less openly, releasing stone in secret,scraping through caves to find a captive, hands like drills. The binds of stone^ vishrivel to his touch: a plying flame as fumbles out of smoke. He makes4-vhis fist a phoenix; hands he turns are wings that clench a fire,4"a beak that bitesis chisel in this stone...The warm wings lifta trembling limb from rock:a dust, like smoke, veers into air.
￼72- - 6 ^I came to a place where buildings were going up; biscuits of slate sat wrapped in twine.Earth moved like sugar, boilingagainst the metal of a dumper.A machine dropped, dropped its yellow snout, nuzzling at joistsit hammered-in.When I got to my father I would learnthe heat of that impact, how you might light paper from it two hours on...The air meanwhile would shiver with fire, a^jjineless dust, the shouts of impact.He was with the welders -short-term hire - cutting thin plateto microns. Not visored, hestood out from that coven_________________ of kneeled and sparking menlike something they were makingor melting to start over.We went out to sandpiles, pounded stone, his eyes spindling, his mouthasking and asking why I was there.(■Errand10
￼Metal-workThe lathe we were at kept cutting-outin little deaths;our anger slid.Under a blade sheet-metal split.I stood wheremy father stood me:this side of a lathe. Weathers of dust fell to a hushat my feet.I did what he asked: watched calipers twitch legs skinny,an avocet's;4?but looked beyond:to drill-heads primed, fluted like wandsof steel..=fcHe halved the work: held mandrels, clamp. Drills spoke for him, talked themselves out.
￼JlAVTTL-MSSI^Jf-—v _ 5 E R i r r sf t e T I ^ E AIR STREETDeer-tracks - I followed them: madea forest slide through a deer's eye; feltTpVMVfor myself the trodden dints of hoof, shorthand codes cut on the frost...~7-|7Tt '4Pitch of night: insurgent shrews ♦scatter* in dissidence between owls.My torch-beam welds them to the ground; I could gather them like moss.The air as well, corrupt with movement, walks with me like gravityand, step-by-step, it flenses sound to whispers of a deer-cut.Where the tracks street together - passes of a scalpel -with torch-light off, eyes wide for catlight; I read their musks like creosote-lyivVand saw the deer - a herd of ten - scent me there, and go.1Morning took me southwards; levelled on fat curving rails, restive station platforms,ticks of rain. As if trespassing I cut the close-wire of people.frw ~73>
￼DAVID MORLEYFERRY HOUSEAMBLESIDE LA22 OLP-7^ o<~\Gundogs grabbed me at traffic-lights. Gamekeepers in Downing Street77^4met my stare.It was night delivered me this:a street lit by nothing - near where I could sleep -with a name like nothing: AIR.And I walked it without torch-lightsensitive for the wear of previous creatures,(YUr
￼MARDALE HEADA reservoir, filling, cutout a village in a flag of grey, halo-ing folds, indulging walls their done-with labour. Thud&-at the damstone, a door slammed shut. Then they grieved for sheep still out:wily beggars slipping collie-dog nets. Compensation came like drizzle on waterand wouldn't add... A stop-go tracklopes up to nothing: the dam,its forehead half-blown-off. Winds relevel what water-blades cancel:■&-stove, trellis, the twines of washday. Now, as this osprey confuses surface and fishlight, skylines narrow, a tightening wire,precarious with fresh weather.
￼EXACT £ ARESEven now, angle-poised over a deskhe takes his cue from the barbiturateof what was seen. Remembering rain:how a single droplet breaks its backon the hurrying window of a No. 3 bus.Or the fly: simmering on vibrated glass, intellectual, in that spiderless prison...A man in corduroys unscrews a flaskand shares warm tea with a woman he hated. He does not see a fly browse on the brimof their plastic mug, or the way raindrops garrotte the nerves of his rheumatic wife. We are sickwith fear the drunk will miss his stop,lolling over the seatback, leaving it our decision.37
￼JERUSALEMBallymurphy painted white, inside and out; road-blocked suburbs, then the accomplishment of a bounding wall to stop the desert’sabstract itch. This achieved, we grew fluent4-in our dialogues: the limit on sensewas vox pop, as was ambivalenceabout a noun for boredom. Came the day a master of lexicographymotorbike-jumped the lower wall-sectorsand made off for the border. He was taken alive, displayed in the central archives( r‘ r public vasectomy and grammar -confiscation), writing, rewritingin blackened sand, Lift up vour hearts and sing.
￼7bDE%M3&MiQrley^z3QiTHE POLITICISATION 0 F T H E NORTH WIND—3\A/(=>ramemitc^fo IInHorthoaonono•uontarl We came out safe, under the aspens; wantedthe road south, but winds deflectedour point of reference to the motorway.A Police Rover winks on its orbit roundan arterial lane. Cobs of leaf-litter give wayto a blackbird’s enquiry. Ivy dripfeedsan oak, as if accidentally. We needthe road south, but accidents are happening.A rescue party sifts the rubble of fallingleaves; a hand of the law harries us down turn-offs- its flickered blue flame; a kestrel makes its one-offbid in a plunging market We circle a bendwith a sign saying Motorway Regulations Terminate Here.Aspens. Wind. Regulations terminate here.ENNISKILLENThere was a speedboat ploughing up Lough Erne, an activity Ithought the local RCJCwould take no shine to.Iwatched three little grebes make with the rhythm.Imagine my discomfiture when the boatman waved then a four-eyed warden told me to push off.I plucked up my fag-ends, enough, never enough; followed laqer cans to the centre of Enniskillen,iba place, now, infamous as Walsingham, and shrine to all discomfiture. I felt a lot for a heavenwhose latest queuestill wore their Remembrance poppiesas though they’d just left the navewhere the priest held back, half-listening for - rain.
￼-y&Qi-As if the snow ixise.Lt were a countryQwit.h p1easure garaens, nate1s„ re.!.igion, CDbabyware, and the word yes and the word no.4i-You enter its capital along paths of slush.QSigns direct you to the Citv EIaer. Nothing w:i.11 growCD under her rule,, as Signs will tel .1, vou at every corner4But when she invites you to her Ice FestivalQyou will learn to love Slowfresse and Nightflake, CQier daughters toy sun1ess adaptian W i11 th(5y dance,4-dance with you? Only so slowly unless they melt Qat the heart from a neat of ecstagy,, The parquet rO:i.s white, white. You are falling out of life.4-Iheir images are 1ocked in you forever□You will carry them, bright on your lips, COeven over oceans, to your own easy gardens.4-One night you may wake before dawn,Qwalk naked to where the river thaws□Qin its grave,, Beneath a bridge of smoothest limestoneput your ear against the ear of winter □listening a yes, a no. Or touchTT|where the words enter the water,D a none of these things., Ca11 at the office,. QWhen someone says yes the answer is no.rT\Pi1e your dackets in toin bags for burning4-at the moment when a stranger rides up in the elevator. DMeanwhi1e,t.a1k of weather or the t.errito1e starm damage □DAvoid words 11ke informer, auditpr, po1ice.There are things in the wall very like ears. 0Their microphones are wonderfu.1. as knots in wood„CDListen, someone can sell you at the slightest, notice4with a single yes. So they will come for you Qin the small hours., To snout through your pastQirabid for evidence. To ask you to repeat after them,4-no, no, noTM Through it all they will help with heat □to the arms, chest, your white lips. Then, peace, t3ZJa dream of snow, co1d hands ha1ding yau,&which you love; that lift you to where water Qrushes over your face. Will you dance, dance? Ct)0nly so s1ow1y„lvle11ing,melting.5#”h.. ^S'!
￼Who forked me like compost from my country? Who spat 0:i.n my water, .1e-ft me diphtheriaI, haIf aIive?Who shovelled me in a bucket., lobbed me in the shitwith heads of schoolchildren,, kulaks, priests? □Who hooted up the ground in Red Square? Whopotted corpses? Who was the angel of earthworms.,of 11")e mass grave , the ba ne fie1d? Qwho hacked the breasts off the widow?Who blurted acid across her mouth? Who forced'IfM fher head back and cheesewired her throat? 0 Who smashed the na:L1s from my fingers?Who hauled me out, wrestled me under wateruntil I spewed the answer? Who chewed it ail over — □the ribcage,sku11,the spine?Who spattered my guts over a Collective?iprMfc-Wha p1oughed in brain mu1ch? Who broke the earth? □Who found the stench ever so exciting?Who fe11 my death essen11a1 to their 1ives?/