￼The Hymn to AphroditeThese things are told by the Muse of goldenAphrodite, the Cyprian, who excites desire even among The gods, and men who are under death’s dominion Are under hers too as are the winged birdsAnd all creatures the land rears and the sea.Garlanded Cytherea troubles them all.Against three of her own kind it is true she is powerless: Against clear-eyed Athene for one, the daughter of Black Zeus. She is indifferent to loveAnd delights in discord and warfare, the works o f Ares; But also in the manufacturing of fine things.She first taught earth’s craftsmen the makingO f war-q^iriots in intricate bronzeAnd young girls the management of the house—all Beautiful works of their hands come from her teaching.Nor can the huntress Artemis, armed with golden Arrows, ever be subjugated by Aphrodite,The lover of laughter. For she loves archery,The hounding to death of animals on mountains, The clamour of pursuit in dark forests; but also They lyre, dance and the rule of civil law.Finally the virgin Hestia cares nothing forThe works of Aphrodite. Strangely bornThe first and youngest child of cunning KronosShe steadfastly refujsed Apollo and PoseidonWho wanted her in marriage. On the head of Zeus She swore to live her immortal life a virgin:She had great honour from Zeus instead of marriage. She has her place in the middle of the house,The best portions are hers. In all the templesShe is reverenced. None of the immortalsIs more highly thought of by mortal men.These Aphrodite cannot sway. Otherwise not one Among the blessed gods nor any manHas ever eluded her. She distracts the mind
￼/Even of Zeus to whom the thunder isA plaything and whose maj^ty is greatest.She overcomes his wisdom whenever she likesAnd easily brings him to bed with mortal women Deceiving Hera his sister and his wifeThe first in beauty among the immortal goddesses, Born of Rhea and Kronos, the trustworthy Consort of Zeus whose wisdom is endless.And he caused Aphrodite herself to wantUnion with a mortal man, for so longAs she remained innocent of human loveAmong the immortals she could always point the finger At their having been joined in love by her,The laughter-loving Aphrodite, godsWith mortal women who bore them sons of death And goddesses in love with mortal men.He made her love Anchises, at that timeA herdsman on the steep slopes of ida,The mountain of innumerable streams, and likeA god in looks. She loved him immediately. Desire took hold of smiling AphroditeAs soon as she saw the man. She went to Cyprus, To Paphos where her precinct and altar are,Into her fragrant house. The shining doorsBeing closed, she was bathed by the CharitiesAnd anointed with an oil she had that the gods Perfume themselves with. She clothed her body In beautiful clothes and put on gold for ornament And laughing she left fragrant CyprusAnd flew to Troy through the high clouds Quickly making her way. So she cameTo Ida of the innumerable streamsand mother of wild beasts and went at once;T To the shying across the mountain. After her, Fawning upon her, came grey wolves and fierce lions,/ Bears and the fast deer-hunting le/pards.It pleased her to see them and she'madeThem lust, so that they coupled in the shadowy combes.But she herself came to the hill farm 88
￼And found him alone there, his companions being out, Anchises whose beauty was from the gods.His companions were following the herds over the pastures_and he was quite alone in the houseWandering here and there and strumming on a lyre.Aphrodite, daughter of Zeus, she stoodBefore him, like a virgin girl in appearance,So that when he saw her he should not be afraid:But still he was amazed, for she was tall and imposing.He stared at her shining clothes. She woreA peplos brighter than the brightness of fire,Golden, beautifully worked, that shimmeredLike moonlight over her soft breasts, and thisAstounded him, and the twisted brooches, ear-ringsLike calyxes and, lovelier than anything he had ever seen, Necklaces on her white throat. Then loveTook Anchises hold. He said: ‘Welcome,Lady, to my house, whichever one you areO f the immortals, whether Artemis or Leto orGolden Aphrodite or Themis or bright-eyedAthene, or perhaps you are one of the GracesWho are companions to the gods and are called immortal, Or one of the Nymphs who inhabit the pleasant woods Or one whose places are this lovely mountainAnd where the rivers start and these grasy meadows.I will make you an altar on a high peakWhere it may be seen for miles around and in allSeasons offer sacrifices. YouBe kindly disposed and grant me eminenceAmong the Trojans and strong sons for the futureAnd let me live long in the daylightProsperous among my people as I age.’/Aphrodite, the child of Zeus, replied:‘jmchises, second to none in fame among mortal men, I am not a goddess, why did you think me one?A mortal mother bore me to die as you will.My father is Otreus, you will have heard of him,He rules Phrygia with its many fortresses.But I know your language as well as my ownFor my nurse was a Trojan. She raised me
￼From infancy, in lieu of my dear mother.Now Hermes, Killer of Argus, Bearer ofThe Golden Wand, has snatched me from the dance O f Artemis the Huntress with the golden arrows Where we were playing together, nymphsAnd marriageable girls and a crowd surrounding us. Then Hermes snatched me from among themAnd carried me over many tilled fieldsAnd over much land owned by no-one and untilled Where savage beasts stalk in the shadowy combes Until I thought I should never again set footOn the good earth. And he said I should beThe wife o f Anchises and bear you beautiful children, And having said so he, Hermes, withdrewAmong the deathless gods and I have comeTo you, bound by necessity. By ZeusI beg you now and by your noble parents -For noble they must be to have a son like you -Take me, a virgin and ignorant of love,And show me to your father and mother.and to your brothers, that they may judge what sort Of wife I shall make you, and send quicklyTo the Phrygians, whose horses go like the wind, To tell my father and my grieving mother,And they will send you quantities of gold And woven clothes. Accept these many gifts As my dowry. Then let us be married since We wish it and heaven and earth approve.’Concluding, the goddess touched him to the heart With love and desire for her. Anchises said:‘If you are mortal and born of a mortal woman And Otreus, whom I have heard of, is your father As you say, and you have come here by the will Of Hermes, the Wayfarer, to be my wifeLifelong, nobody human or divineShall keep me from lying with you here and now, No, not if Apollo the Archer himselfLet fly arrows at me from his silver bow,0 Lady beautiful as a goddess, from your bed1 would not mind going down to Hades’ house. He took her hand. Then smiling Aphrodite/
￼Averting her face and with her eyes cast down Went slowly to the bed that was already laidFor the royal man with soft coverings, withThe skins of bears and o f loud-roaring lions Killed by him on the high mountains. And when They were together on the bed he firstRemoved the jewellery from her body, Unfastened her dress at the shoulders, undidThe twisted broches, the ear-rings, the necklaces, Loosed her belt and so one by oneTook off her shining clothes and laid themDown on a silver-studded chair. Thus ignorant Of what he did, by the will of the gods and fated, He lay, a mortal man, with a deathless goddess.But at the hour when the herdsmen drive the cattleAnd sheep home into the fold from the flowery pastures Aphrodite caused Anchises to sleep sweetlyBut she dressed in her fine clothes againAnd fully clo(h)jied stood by the bed tallAs the roof now and her face radiant with the beauty Only the immortals have, and among them only Cytherea.Then she woke him saying: ‘Dardanus’ sonI wonder what you are dreaming, look now Whether I am as you first saw me.’He heard her and woke at once, but whenHe saw the throat and lovely eyes of Aphrodite Then he was afraid and averted his eyes and hid His face—that she found beautiful—in his cloak Entreating her so: ‘when I first saw you, goddess,I knew you for what you are, though you denied it. But now by implacable Zeus I beg youDo not leave me like one of the dead amongThe living. H^fe mercy. I know the very lifeLeaves a mortal man who has slept with a goddess.’Aphrodite, daughter of Zeus, replied: ‘Anchises, best of men, be reassuredAnd on that score not too fearful. Nothing Harmful will happen to you either from me Or from the other gods. You will be loved.91
￼You will have a son who will be dear to you and me. He will be king among the Trojans, and children Upon children will continue your family for ever. He will be called Aeneas, on account of the griefIt gives me to have slept with a mortal man Though among such your family has always Approached nearest the immortal gods in looks.Did not Zeus, despite his wisdom, carry off Golden-haired Ganymedes for his beauty To be among the immortals and pour them Their drink, drawing the red nectarFrom a golden bowl? They held him in honour And wonder. Tros however was inconsolableNot knowing where the whirlwind from heaven Had carried his dear son whom day in, day out, He mourned. Then Zeus took pity, and paid him Compensation for the boy in the form of high- Stepping horses—such as carry the immortals. And with this gift Hermes, obeying Zeus, Explained all and said the boy would neitherDie nor age but be like the gods. At this Tros left off weeping and turned to rejoicing And rode his stormy horses with a glad heart.And Eos too, thro^ned in gold, tookj^. upAnother of your race, Tithonus, alsoIn appearance like the deathless gods and askedThe cloudly son of Kronos that he shouldLive for ever. Zeus assented. She had her wish,Poor fool, who never thought to get him besides Eternal life eternal youth and totalRemission of old age. Thus in the flowerOf his life he lived like one of the blessedWith the young and golden Eos by Ocean’sStreams at the world’s end—until grey showedIn his hair and beard, marring their beauty. ThenEos the Queen never came to his bedBut still kept him in her house and sawTo him with food and ambrosia and fine clothes until Foul old age overwhelmed him and heWas helpless to raise or move his limbs.
￼Then she thought best to lay him in a room And to close the bright doors on him and there He babbles on for ever and cannot liftA finger, who was formerly lithe and strong.I would not like you to be, after his fashion,Not able to die among the deathless gods.I should not like you for a husband in heaven when Old age, common to all men, ruthless age,The curse, the burden, that the gods shudder at,Has enshrouded you. And even were you to live Unaging and as you are now in looksStill I should be ashamed eternallyAmong the immortals because of you. For theyWere afraid of me who mated them allBy cunning with mortal men and women and laughed At them and they were all subject to me.But now who am I to speak having erred Outrageously and taken leave of my sensesAnd got myself with child by a mortal man?When he first sees the light of the sun let himBe given into the care of the nymphs who inhabitThis great and holy mountain, for in natureThey are between mortals and gods. Thelive longAnd eat heavenly food and dance the lovelyDance with the gods and goddesses and with themSileni and Hermes himself, the sharp-eyedKiller of Argus, go into the dark placesO f pleasant caves to lie down together in love.And at their birth pines or high oaks spring upWith them on the nurturing earth, beautiful, tallAnd flourishing trees on the high mountains. They______ Would ever lop them with an axe. But whenThe nymphs are fated to die and death is closeThen first those beautiful trees wither where they stand, The bark dies on them, the twigs fall and the soulsO f the trees and o f the nymphs leave the sunlight Together. These nymphs will have the custody of my son During his infancy, but when he begins his boyhood Then, once, they will show him to you here. Later,
￼About the fifth year, I shall bring him to you again And what I intend will be made clear.He will be lovely then, he will be likeA god, and a joy to you. Bring him immediately To windy Troy and remember if any askWho bore you such a son say this: that heWas born of one of the flowerlike nymphs who inhabit This wooded hill. But if, like a fool,You boast of loving and lying with Cypris,The crowned queen, Zeus in rage will blast youWith fire. Now I have said all I shall say.Be warned. Never name me. Fear the gods.’She rose then on the winds of heaven. Farewell Goddess, Queen of well-built Cyprus,With you I began, with you I shall continue.