￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 46 & T ransylvania(for Kathryn)1 TransylvaniaI’ve been hanging out down at the station again since you left for Paris. Grim! Christopher Lee!That’s how bad it is. People can all see my sickness, women run quickly into shops when they see my face.I’m Dracula again looking for victims on platform 3, eyeing the beauties in the busde, in the tannoy haze.Look! here they come now with their tube bags. Watch me suck them dry! Listen to my invitation!‘Roll with me beauties off the edge of your lives’ Nightmare. That’s the only word for a date with me& that buffet girl’s not interested, it’s plain to see,‘it’s the Spook,’ she thinks, ‘the Vampire of platform 3’‘it’s the man with the pencilled-in hairline! quick! it’s Christopher Lee! he’s creepy & hairy, garlic!’So there you have it, grim isn’t it, Christopher Lee, that’s me, hanging out at the station since you leftlooking for blood, blood to forget you for a while, blood to be back home since we’ve been apart,home in a box in Transylvania with the stakes beside my heart...46
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 472 RevolutionIt’s turn of the century Russia, ok? you’re a Countess & I’m a serf.a 00°) • Get the picture, a bo/ man with a scythe,out chopping fields with scythe for your heartknowing it’s hopeless as the winter stings. Up in Petrograd you’ll be getting restlessin the snow, beside your bourgeois fire & maids who heat up all your muffs, help keep your feelingsburied, subdued by the palace, majestic food, the grandeur of a thousand dinner partiesto obscure me, to obscure you from my face that night in the lonely carriage, a samovaron the low light later in my shack, my bogland. So Peter will be telling me soon of revolutionitSj& then we’ll have to fight, my dear, on different sides. Your world will be turned upside-down, my darling& my voice will ache calling out to the hinterland before the begining of the end, the dust of our lovetrampled as the citizens storm the barricades. You won’t ever escape me in exile either,on the meadow beside the Finnish lake so still...47
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 483 RotThere’s dry rot in the attic, sweetest, & we never speak, how are we supposed to sort out this rot then?There’s dust everywhere & now in the attic this rot, we need treatment, sweetest, we need to see an expert.If only we could see the village handyman even, but he’s out of town, poor simpleton, riding awayover the hills on his bike with a lucky sixpence was the last heard of that fella, no handyman!No expert! So we’ve got big problems here, my sweet, & I’m no good with rot, I can grow things no problem,look at the hyacinths I planted sure, their radiance!but DIY? you may as well whistle something backwards!Who can lend us the readies, sweet, the dosh, the LSD? surely not the bank manager, my sweet, a lost cause.He’s out on the green right now with his new putter & dry rot’s the last thing he ever thinks about,not ours, not his, not anybody tnkman can save us. No money from the moneyman can save our dry rot.Have you even been up to the attic of late, my sweet? remember love beneath the candles, giggling at the beams?no, I don’t suppose you’ve been up there of late, my sweet, it’s a wreck, devastation! not the dream home we seek.our attic is caving in, my sweet, & we never speak...48
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 494 Bye bye loveI’m packing my heart off to boarding school, it just has to be done, I can’t control it.Perhaps the stern brothers & nuns can help knock some degree of discipline into my heart.A cold shower at 5 in the morning, a 6 mile run through the mud & the mire, some meditation.Let my heart learn prayers for being so crazy! Let my heart scrub floors for penance!Discipline! Bed with no malted milk! No sugar! Not a spoonful of sugar will my heart be given,& I won’t even send my heart a care package.No care packages, I’m running my heart out of town.You big softie, heart, you snivelling wee weasel! Save all your tears & snotters for the nuns.Now I’ll get to invite the neighbour in for champagne. I’ll seduce the neighbour’s wife effortlessly.I’ll seduce the neighbour’s mistress heartlessly while the neighbour groans & drinks my poison tea& my heart by then will have forgotten me...49
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 50:ftCAP •5 Black iceIt’s like there’s been this massive car crash & our love has wrapped itself round a tree,or we’ve toppled over completely on the hard shoulder, the tyres of strangers squirting us as they speed by.Mud & slime from puddles in our hearts on the M6, let’s make it the M6, our love in heavy fog.So we should have gone by the B roads, my love, should have travelled by all the scenic routes,stopped for pints, stopped for plenty of bacon buns, smoked over tea & breakfasts in all the wild domains.But how we rush, we always rush & now we’re comotose & the ambulance won’t come, we’ve had our 15 minutes,& that AA man is surely kind but what can we do? the dents on the bodywork like an earthquake’s hit,the steering wheel all bent & petrol leaking.So we lie half-dead with our half-remembered prayers& that kind AA man can do nought, my love & no doctors either will just be happening along on their way to conventions.It won’t be like the movies now, my dearest, not now, because ouraove is wrapped around the steel barrier& our blood is running thin, we’re slipping away, my love, to some burnt out scrapyard, it’s a migration upwards,up to Jesus with his roadmap & his pencil poised to sea*our fate- a place, Jesus,’ he thought;‘Where can I find the place to take back their souls?’ Aye, we’re in deep water now, my dear, banjacksed,50-e
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 51up shit river with no paddle, up the grim M6,& that home in the hills we promised ourselves, my dear,is just over the rise if we could only make it, if fuel could be found or the ambulance did come miraculously.‘Look! here comes the ambulance men with their gleaming faces’ I’ll utter, our hands stretching out to each otherin the mess & in the fractured air...6 MonaI’m living in this attic now with my new girlfriend,does that make you jealous? do you envy her?, my Mona.Her name’s Mona, the bright elusive butterfly of love,& I’ve packed in whiskey, the breath of Satan, since we met.At night when I’m sad it’s good to hear her fluttering& she hangs out on my windowledge in the slow afternoon.She preens herself endlessly & although she flaps in panic I wouldn’t harm her, Mona’s safe with me, I swear it!You mustn’t think I wouldn’t let her float away either,I let you float away, remember, the streets beyond our nest.A friendly neighbour is keeping our nest spick & span & look, I realise if we go back there it’s without her.But you’d like her, she’s an orange shade I warm to, Mona’s looking after me in her own wild mystical way.Together we look through your photos & she soothes me, beautiful Mona’s my latest but you’ll never be my ex.51
￼Cleary 23-52 13/7/93 6:57 pm Page 52One day we’ll be back in that nest together, I know it! you can kick over as many cups of tea as you like,you can watch TV & ask dumb questions endlessly all night, you can get me to fetch hot pitta breads & peanut butter,I’ll fetch the croissants too & the durex bill is mine,& all the days just lying about in our nest will be precious.Mona understands all this, don’t fret, it’s just a phase, anothe^phase we’re going through, Mona & myself agreeshe’ll fly one day beyond the factories, set us both free...52