￼Hill Trembling 124-160 3/2/94 2:00 pm ge 131CarnationsAnd when he died,/»"reign of brutality and abuse that had gone on undetected for nearly twenty years suddenly came to an end;and we fell asleep among our fathers’ horses,and that’s how it all began -with the sound of their breathing.They waited by our sides, like aeroplanes,or graves, enclosed in silk,dusty and sweet like sponge cakesor carnations;we must have lain exhausted at their feetfor many days and nights;we saw the moonunroll ten thousand miles of sufferingalong their backs, as if the mane of one alonewere Upper Burma,as if each fetlock were Mongolia,where there’s only fifteen^ miles of tarmac-ed road, the rest’s small flowers...What happened next, my friend,you already know -something it’s hard for the people here to believe, after the reign of abusewe’ve been subjected to,timid as we are,for so long now.G131
￼EvelynAll I do's admire the distant sky-lineand run my fingers through the rustly dand while Evelyn,ever patient and resourceful, trundles off in search of tasty ants.And every night,at peace beneath the stars, we think about the zoo-raan in his bedroom battling with his large electric fan.We S^Stta&ise him getting out of bed and switching off,not only his supoly, but everyone's.The whole population's..nd everything goes ominously quiet.Then gradually,as dawn begins to break,he sees to his astonishment strange animals shuffling up his drive with their families;and as the days go by he gets to like them- in fact he can't imagine ever not.They fill his house and gardens with their normalness.Just the way they seem so down-to-earth.