￼‘Welcome, Lady. I wish you nothing but good. I think you are not of ordinary parentage. Your face is delightful to look at andLike that of a queen and law-giverInclines us to reverence. We who are not godsMust submit to what they send although it beA yoke of sorrow. Since you have come to usI will give you what I can. Will you nurse my sonWhom the gods have given me now late in my lifeAfter much prayer and when I had stopped hoping?If you will bring him to the start of manhoodWhen your work is done I will reward you with such gifts That you will be envied among the women.’Demeter,Haloed with shining hair, said ‘LadyBlessings upon you likewise, and may the gods Endow you with good. I will be, as you ask,Your baby’s nurse and bring him up, nor shall, Through carelessness of mine, any ill come near him Nor will he suffer pains, for against ill-wishingAnd to ward off pain I have a wealth of knowledge.’Then Metaneira was happy and handed her son toThe goddess, who hugged him close. So he,Demophoon, child of Celeus, a good man,And Metaneira, the loving, was nursed in the palaceA mother’s milk, for by day shining DemeterSmeared his body with ambrosia as though he wereHer own son and a god and breathed upon himSweetly as she hugged him close. But at nights unbeknown to His loving parents she would lay him like a coal inThe secret heart of the fire. They saw with wonder Their child growing beyond his years and becoming For them, mortal, like a god to look at. She would Have given him eternal youth and eternal lifeHad not Metaneira, the careful mother, wrongly One night, anxious to see, come down. She saw And clutched her two hands upon her heartAnd screamed in fear for her beloved son and cried Beside herself: ‘My child, Demophoon, the stranger78And cjreyo like a.r\ lonmortjil nest ed tAjdhbod nor
￼0Is burying you in the heart of the fire, alasShe has done us a terrible harm.’ Demeter,Brighter to look at than a white fire, heardThe ashen woman moaning and that dear child,The late-comer, the mother’s no longer hoped for,She snatched with her unconsuming hands from the / And threw him from her down on the ground in terrible Anger, crying: ‘Humanity, what fools you areWithout foreknowledge of the good or the evilComing your way. O human mother, the follyYou have done will never be undone. I swearBy Styx, by the pitiless waters, and give you my wordI should have made him deathless, your dear son,Nor would he have aged and the honour I gave him Would have been everlasting. But now he will not elude By any means Death and the Fates. Only this, that he Once lay upon my knees and slept in my armsWill be his glory and cannot be undone. In time However, in his beautiful manhood, the sonsOf Eleusis will go to war with one anotherDelete) e / And there will always be discord. I am Denver Honoured by gods and men as bringer to bothd.rmyOf help and joy. But now let all your peopleBuild me a great temple and an altar below it Below the city and its sheer wall, above Callichorus Upon a rising hill. I will teach you my worshipSo that afterwards piously doing as I sayYou may incline me to kindness.’Then Demeter - Changed her stature and her appearance, put offOld age, the air about her shoneWith beauty, streamed with the scent of her clothes, Her body was a bright light and her hairTumbled down shining upon her shoulders. The house Filled with a brightness like that of lightning.So she left them.Metaneira could barely stand. She remained for a long time dumb, forgettingEven to take up her baby, her lastborn,Who lay on the floor. He cried and cried untilHe woke his sleeping sisters. They came runningAnd one took him up in her aifyijs and hugged him close,
￼Another mended the fire, another hastened Quietly to bring the mother away. Then all Crowding together they bathed.the kicking child And cuddled him. But he would not be comforted Because these nurses and maids holding him now Were not the goddess. All night they never left off Praying to be back in her good graces again,All night shaking with fear. But when the morning came They told the whole story to the ruler CeleusAs Demeter, haloed with a blinding beauty,Had said they must. Their father assembled the people And said they must build a temple to DemeterAnd an altar, on the hillock. And they obeyedAnd built it, for the goddess. And when they had done Labouring and building the men went home again Each to his family.But Demeter, the corn-golden, Sat alone in the home they had built herStill shunning the company of all the blessed godsThin in the face for grief over PersephoneHer child. And on the earth that nurtures us allShe inflicted such a year as we shall never forget,A hungry year. The seed would not sprout in the ground For grieving Demeter shut it. The oxen ploughedThe fields for nothing and the white barley in handfuls Fell on the land like pebbles. She would have starved The human race to death and the OlympiansWould have gone short of the tithes and sacrifices Which they exact from men, had not Zeus, the canny, Turning the matter over, sent Iris, wingedWith golden light, to fetch Demeter, whose beauty They were missing.Iris obeyed black ZeusAnd flew quicker than rainshafts through the airAnd coming to the fragrant city of EleusisFound Demeter alone in her temple wrapped in black And said:‘Lord God Almighty Zeus, absoluteIn wisdom, wants you back, Demeter, where you, Goddess, belong, among the immortals, so come Do as he wishes.’80
￼Iris begged her. But she, Grief-stricken, would not obey. Then Zeus,The eternal happiness in Heaven being troubled,Sent down to her one after the otherAll the gods, and they came in turn, calling her name And bringing beautiful gifts and offering whatever Favours in Heaven she cared to choose. But northing Moved her, and nobody, so deep-rooted nowWas her bitterness. She closed her ears to their bribes And swore she would never set foot again on Olympus, Their scented heaven, and never release the seedFrom prison in the ground, until she saw her child Pt;dsephone, the bright-eyed. Zeus, big noise, Know-all, when he heard this despatchedThe Killer of Argus and Bearer of the Golden RodTo Hell, with suitable blarney there to softsoap Brother Death and lead the chaste PersephoneOut of the dark, through the mists, into the light,Into the company of the gods again, that Demeter, Seeing her, would relent.Hermes obliged, and leavingThe House of Heaven betook himself rapidly to the placesThat are below the earth. He found King DeathAt home in his halls, seated on a couch and by him The girl, ashamed, hating his company and pining To be with her mother (who, far off, was Spoiling The quiet lives of the gods). The Killer of Argus, The unafraid Hermes, stood very close to Death And said:‘Hades, Black Lord of the Dead,I am ordey(by Zeus to bring PersephoneFrom Erebus, back among the gods so thatHer mother, seeing her, may cease being angryAnd cease injuring us. She intends nothing lessThan the destruction of earth’s humanity by imprisoning The seed in the soil, and when they die, and thatWill not be long, where shall we unhappy godsGet worship from? Her anger is terrible, she will not Come near us but sits alone in in her templeIn Eleusis among the rocks.’Thus Hermes. Unsmiling Hades, King of Ghosts, smiled blackly
￼' r-s.'jv'iAnd bowed to Zeus, the stronger, and said:‘Persephone, go at once now home to your mother,The goddess in mourning, and towards myself, if you can, Be kinder, please, and do not think what has happened The worst possible thing. You could do plenty worseFor a husband among the gods than me, brotherAs I am of His Majesty. Down hereYd will be queen of everything that hasIts being after the fashion of the dead and amongThe gods none’s status will be greater and whoeverGives you less than your due and does not with offerings Strive officiously for your favour and performsLess than satisfactorily in your worship orFalls behind in the payment of contributions heOr she will writhe in Hell for ever.’Persephone, The toting, leapt to her feet full of joyTo be leaving Death but he, kissing her Goodbye, slipped slyly from mouth to mouth The juicy seed of a pomegranate so thatShe swallowed it and was thwarted in her wish Always to stay with her mother, revered Demeter Cloafked in midnight blue.Aidoneus,Ruler of Many, Receiver of More and More, Made a great show of harnessing his horses,Undying among the dead, to the golden chariot and handed his captive in. The Killer of A^gus Took up the reins and the whip and left the halls O f Hell at a gallop. The enormous distances Were put behind them in no time and over salt And rivers of freshwater and lowland grassAnd high crags they passed like a parting spear Through the deep air.Hermes, the coachman, Reined the horses in, outside the scented temple, The hiding-place of Queen Demeter. Like one ofThe mad women of Dionysos when the/career Down mountainsides so Demeter when she saw Persephone ran to her and she, the child,Seeing her mother’s face, the lovely, the beloved,trosboQ) (U(S’J(82
￼Jumped from the chriot, left the standing horses, And ran and fell upon her mother’s neck Tight-hugging her. Demeter though, whilst yet Holding her child again, felt suddenly coldIn the heart and her hands ceased caressing Persephone. She cried: ‘Oh, child, you did not, did you,Tell me, taste any food underground? Say notOr tell me the worst. For if you tasted nothingThen you have seen the last of ugly HadesThen you will live in the house of God your father, Storm-brewer Zeus, the Castrator’s son,And me, honoured among the gods, but ifDown there you swallowed something you mustGo back into the lifeless places for oneThird part of every year’s seasonsAnd stay with me for two. When with flowersIn spring, with the innumerable sweet flowers,The earth revives, then you will surface againOut of the dark, out of the mists, your coming will be Wonderful to the gods in Heaven who seeOf springtimes an eternity and to men on earthWho see a handful. But tell me, child,How he took you into the dark who is the strong Receiver of More and More, by what crooked means Did he add you?’The girl Persephone,The radiant child, answered her mother thus:‘When lucky Hermes, the hurrying messenger, cameOn the part of my father, the Son of Kronos, and the others In Heaven, to fetch me from Erebus, that youMight have me back again and relent in your angerAnd hard grudge against the gods, I jumpedFor joy. But Death, with a kiss, slylyPlanted in me the seed of a pomegranate,Sweet to taste, and this I had to swallowThough I did not want to.And as to howHe took me in the first place with the connivanceO f my own father, the Usurper Zeus, and carried me to That world below the roots, I will tell you exactly:We were playing together in a lovely meadow, IAnd the daughters of Ocean—these: Leucippe,
￼Phaeno, Electra, Ianthe, Melita,Iache, Rhodea and Callirhoe,Melobosis, Tyche and Ocyrhoe who is Herself flowerlike, and Chryseis and Ianeira, Acaste, Admete, Rhodope and Pluto,Sweet Calypso, Urania and beautiful Galaxaura. We were playing and picking Armfuls of lovely flowers, such asIrises and hyacinths, roses and/^reLilies than I have ever seen, but ILoved most of all a certain narcissus, Crocus-yellow at the centre, and whenI reached for this the earth, the broad earth Full of flowers, gave and from that hole The Lord who has Dominion over Millions, Gold-chariot-driving, rose and took me Under the earth into the dark, resistant, Vanishing, screaming.Mother, he sleeps and wakes Where the dead are, their only lightIs like the pallor of tubers, he never smiles, They never see the sun, and the worst is That I have eaten what he gave me.’But all day then Mother and daughter had an equal gladness.They lessened for one another with embracesThe grief in their hearts, the loathing in their minds. It was an equal giving and receivingO f presents of happiness. Then Hecate,Coiffed with the sickle moon, came near. She also Hugged close the precious daughter of Demeter And was her attendant and companion thereafter.Thunderous God sent another messenger,His mother Rhea of the Lovely Hair, to begHer daughter Demeter, cloaked in black, to join The happy family of the gods again. This doing, He promised, she would be given such honours In Heaven as she thought fit. Her child, alas, Must spend a third part of the revolving year BeloW, in blackness, but the rest with her84