￼ContentsI COAST TO COASTThunder in MissouriAll night a drum-roll of thunder had parallelled sleep.Even at daybreak green swathes of light flickered incessantlyagainst the sky and into our dull room.Headlamps along the highway beamed into walls of rainfalland across the Missouri river billows of smoky downpourwandered away over Iowa.It was a day like other days,a Tuesday morning and workspreading its routines and rumbling on: every driver behind the darkhol^s the wipers evenly madein the windshield’s skin of wet was stuck there in his Tuesdaymorning seat and going all out wherever Tuesday took him.The spray was yards high for miles.The sky was bigger than ever going on over all horizonsbeyond the penetration of the eye; its thumping mallet blowsflattening the whole land outmaking everything metal-coloured river road buildings grassand the leaning-over trees:the brave shines of the chains of traffica ridiculous minute defiance.10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 1920 21 22 23 24New York Harbour ManhattanFarm in PennsylvaniaAt a House of Robert Frost Walking in Chicago Thunder in MissouriNew Orleans Oklahoma City Noon in Santa Fe StoreThe Landscape Speaks, Near Flagstaff Dry River Bed, ArizonaBoulder CityjSea Lions off Monterey Waiting for the Cable CarII WALKING ON FROGS26272829303132333436384041424344454647484950EquipoiseTensionsOne Long Blue NoteThe FlawPrecautionNocturneMinotaurScenario for a DreamT acticOn the BridgeKafka’s FuneralCall-box, MidnightBraceletA Photograph of Your Friends Graveyard with Orange-Tree At an Outdoor CafeMeeting an Old Man in the Hills LockA Presence 1Harbour Lights < Looking Down from the Temple Crossings
￼WALKING ON FROGS
￼my familyVi(LorA I ^
￼AcknowledgementsAcknowledgements are due to the editors of the following publications in which some of these poems first appeared: Acumen, Critical Quarterly, The Honest Ulsterman, Outposts, Poetry Review, Poetry Voice, Poetry Jrffith an Edge (Bloodaxe Books, Ijc 1988), Smoke, Stand and 051. ‘Crossings’, ‘Boulder City’, ‘TheWasp Trap’and ‘Well-Heads’were broadcast on PoetryNow (BBC Radio 3); ‘Crossings’ was also broadcast on Poems from Abroad (BBC Radio 4).\-T 7 v U C S
￼ContentsICOASTTOCOAST __ _, .AI—-----------------iiwL<_vn^v£ t o 10 New York Harbour^yt^rrII Manhattan12 Farm in Pennsylvania13 At a House of Robert Frost14 W alking in Chicago15 Thunder in Missouri16 New Orleans17 Oklahoma City18 Noon in Santa Fe19 Store20 The Landscape Speaks, Near Flagstaff21 Dry River Bed, Arizona22 Boulder City23 Sea Lions off Monterey24 Waiting for the Cable Car11 WALKING ON FROGS26 Equipoise27 Tensions28 One Long Blue Note29 Zflaw30 Precaution 'Tts €>31 Nocturne32 Minotaur33 Scenario for a Dream34 Tactic36 On the Bridge38 Kafka’s Funeral i40 Calljbox, Midnight41 Bracelet42 A Photograph of Your Friends43 Graveyard with Orange-Tree44 At an Outdoor Cafe45 Meeting an Old Man in the Hills46 Lock47 A Presence48 Harbour Lights49 Looking Down from the Temple50 Crossings52 On the Shore ~1/ The.
￼S2L oa SWore.53 Landlocked54 House-Wall55 The Wasp Trap56 Stray57 Windfalls58 Still Life59 Well-Heads61 Marching to Breakfast62 Walking on Frogs63 All the Small Adventurest
￼I. COAST TO COAST1*V\ MviW WoWtf~R A G M E N T gOF AMERICA</♦/
￼At a House of Robert FrostIn Dearborn at the Henry Ford Museum they’ve built a village humouring the old America, shipping the houses herefrom everywhere across the continent.Clean lettering on a painted board sets out that Robert Frosthad this pine home way backand way up North of Boston^The tourist buggies rubber-wheel along behind calm horses; beds of herbs perplex the air in the noon sun.The grass is laundered, the trees tamed.This couldn’t be New Hampshire, nor one of the five farms in Vermont. The woods are empty of promises,no one swings on the birches. Still,put your hand here. I’d guess the stoop vibrates, right where his bootsclumped down in the pale daybreak,when he went out to clean the pasture spring.
￼Thunder in MissouriAll night a drum-roll of thunder had parallelled sleep.Even at daybreak green swathes of light flickered incessantlyagainst the sky and into our dull room.Headlamps along the highway beamed into walls of rainfalland across the Missouri river billows of smoky downpourwandered away over Iowa.It was a day like other days,a Tuesday morning and workspreading its routines and rumbling on: ever}7driver behind the darkholes the wipers evenly madein the windshield’s skin of wet was stuck there in his Tuesdaymorning seat and going all out wher^Tuesday took him.The spray was yards high for milesThe sky was bigger than ever going on over all horizons,beyond the penetration of the eye;its thumping mallet blows]flattening the whole land outmaking everything metal-coloured river ( road buildings ( grassand the leaning-over trees:the brave shines of the chains of traffica ridiculous minute defiance.LESS5-fh Uoe 'posckrv^ned15
￼New OrleansThe moon hangs like the last cantaloupe on the market, in its net of cloud.Even at this small hour there will be some slung yet over quiet traders downthat end of town. Musicsplutters out of the bars and fallsinto the streets, where tangles of people mooch and spread, their faces agleam like the potter}' carnival maskshilarious in the stores; they are glazedit seems armoured in joy.Out further, in the wide reaches of darkness,police-cars howl like sad catsand forage among shadows.There is a blood-scent on the grid. No night can be different.Later, the moon slips from its netand lifts, brightens into a white dominance, and pulls what could be hope, what feels like hope, necessary neutral illumination,along the glittering and enormous river.16/
￼Oklahoma CityOutside the CapitolIs the cowboy statue under the tree, With small shades dancingOn the flanks of the once wildPony gripped between his thighs.Over the road in open sun The derrick atop the oil-well Is a pyramid of glitter.It will have you frowning, Lowering your eyes.The cool museum’s statueThe End ofthe TrailIs white and gigantic. The ghostIndian slumps astraddle,The horse is collapsing like a snowbank. In the high-ceilinged roomYou can almost hearTheir harsh, last breathings.
￼Noon in Santa FcHigh-nosed truckswith snorting upright pipesget between us and the Indians. They sit beyond the trafficwith their spread jewellery, their bread big as pillows, their prune-pie,shaded under the colonnade.And about the plaza pale^splay-brimmed hatsmove pools of shadow slowly from awning to awninground the fawn adobe buildings, banks, offices, hotels,and girls are rollerskating silently, with elastic limbsand lifting, sun-bleached hair.Close, hard, knife-edged,the mountains jag into the sky,where a few blinding clouds, white as imagination, balanceand stretch. It is as if something is waiting, someutterly undomestic possibility hangs in the blue.The air shimmers over the trucks’ shaking engines.The heat is volcanic.18